<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.2" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Education and Skills</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.3" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 16:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Thomas Byrne, Senator Maria Byrne. Deputy Kathleen Funchion, Deputy Catherine Martin, Deputy Tony McLoughlin, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan,</p><p>DEPUTY FIONA O'LOUGHLIN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.4" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 4.34 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.5" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#B00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#B00200"><p>I call the meeting to order and remind members to turn off their mobile phones.  Apologies have been received from Senators Gallagher and Ruane.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.7" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 4.11 p.m. and resumed in public session at 4.40 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.8" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#E00100">State Examinations: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#E00200"><p>I remind members and delegates to turn off their mobile phones or switch them to flight mode, as they interfere with the sound system and make it difficult for the parliamentary reporters to report the proceedings of the meeting.  Television coverage and web streaming are also adversely affected.</p><p>The purpose in this part of the meeting is to engage with a number of stakeholders on the topic of continuous assessment for State examinations.  On behalf of the joint committee, I welcome Ms Moira Leydon, assistant general secretary of the ASTI; Ms Joanne Irwin, president of the TUI; Mr Ois&iacute;n Hassan, vice president for academic affairs, USI; Mr. Geoff Browne, president of the national parents' council post-primary, and Mr. Lewis Purser, director of academic affairs, Irish Universities Association.</p><p>I communicate the apologies of Deputies Thomas Byrne and Catherine Martin who had to leave the meeting to participate in the work being done in the Chamber.  The Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Josepha Madigan, and Senators Robbie Gallagher and Lynn Ruane also send their apologies. </p><p>I will invite the delegates to make brief opening statements that should be no longer than three minutes and which will be followed by engagement with members.  I thank the delegates for their submissions which will be published on the committee's website after the meeting.</p><p>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the Chairman to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Any opening statement submitted to the committee will be published on its website after the meeting, together with the submissions forwarded to the committee secretariat.</p><p>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>I call on Ms Leydon to make her opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.10" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Moira Leydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#E00300"><p>Go raibh maith agat a chomhghleaca&iacute;.  I fully understand members are busy; after all, this is their workplace.  </p> <p>  The ASTI appreciates the opportunity to be present.  It welcomes the space the meeting affords the teaching profession to communicate its views to legislators.  That is something we value and we would like to think it will be sustained into the future.  It is not something every other organisation enjoys.  It is very important that we communicate that message.  I know that the committee has received our submission, but members may not have had an opportunity to read it in detail.  The two core messages are that there must be more richness in our assessment and that there must be a greater spread of the assessment load across the school year, but we must also ensure the State examinations are assessed by the State Examinations Commission.  That is the only way we can have the quality assurance and control the system has enjoyed to date.  They are the two key message in our submission.</p> <p>  In the time available to me I wish to make two or three points.  This discussion is actually timely because 2018 marks the 20th anniversary of the establishment of the commission on the points system which, as members know, was a seminal event in looking at assessment and examinations in our system.  The commission made a number of recommendations, two of which are germane to our discussion.  First, it strongly argued for the retention of external assessment for the leaving certificate examinations but equally strongly recommended that more diverse modes of assessment be introduced to supplement the written examinations.  Since the publication of the report in 2001, all of the reviews of the subject and programmes that have taken place have heeded that recommendation.  For example, in the case of Irish and modern foreign languages, there are oral and aural examinations which form part of the overall mark in the junior and leaving certificate examinations.  There is project work in the case of history and geography.  In the case of home economics, students get to demonstrate that they can cook as part of the examination.  In the practical subjects of music, art, technology and science there are practical and performance tasks to be performed.  The practical assessment for leaving certificate science subjects will come on stream.  Therefore, in the case of practical work which is spread over time, there is continuous assessment under the examination system.  When the assessment is for the purposes of the State examinations, it is not conducted by the teacher but by the State Examinations Commission.  That system has merit and stability, but more to the point and most important from the point of view of education, there is quality control.  It is objective, fair and transparent.  </p> <p>  State examinations are meant to tell society a number of things, core among which is that they tell the student and his or her family how he or she has progressed in his or her learning, but they are also tell society how individuals and the system as a whole are progressing.  The view of the ASTI has always been, since time immemorial, that because of the role played by the State examinations, the assessment must remain located in the State Examinations Commission.</p> <p>  By international standards, we have a high performing education system.  The last PISA, programme for international student assessment, report found that of the 37 OECD countries, Ireland was third in literacy levels, which is really amazing when we are being compared with countries that have hundreds of times the population of Ireland.  Ireland was 13th in the case of science and mathematics.  By international evidence, we have a high performing education system with good quality control.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#E00400"><p>I call Ms Irwin, president of the Teachers' Union of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.12" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Joanne Irwin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#E00500"><p>The TUI welcomes the opportunity to address the joint committee on the issue of continuous assessment for State examinations.  Assessment in schools takes three forms: formative, which takes place in schools every day, for example, in the marking of homework, copies, etc; the summative assessment, which is used to measure the breadth and depth of knowledge acquired, for example, in the State examinations at the end of the year; and diagnostic testing to measure the capacity of a student to carry out tasks, for example, aptitude or special needs testing.  Each of these forms of assessment takes place frequently in schools.  By its nature, formative assessment is continuous.</p> <p>  It should be noted that in the State examinations additional forms of assessment, as Ms Leydon said, take place in many subjects in the leaving certificate examinations.  They are embedded in the new revised junior cycle programme.  For example, oral and practical tests take place in many language and practical subjects.  Of the 32 curricular subjects in the leaving certificate programme, 17 have a mixture of assessment components, between the terminal examination and the practicals, the orals, the aurals and course work.  All of the recently revised junior cycle subject specifications have a second assessment component which is assessed by the State Examinations Commission.  They enable students to demonstrate wider abilities than could be shown in a written examination alone.</p><p>We are not fully through that procedure yet and all the subjects are not on stream but as that happens, parents and students will see that a lot more.</p><p> The suggestion is sometimes made that continuous assessment reduces student stress.  However, the Teachers Union of Ireland, TUI, believes that there is a real risk that continuous assessment would simply lead to students experiencing continuous stress with no breaks between assessments.  Furthermore, it should be noted that an excess of assessments can infringe on time to learn and explore topics of interest.</p><p> There are potentially significant risks arising from the use of continuous assessment in the State examinations.  These include the reputational risk to the existing, widely respected system, to which Ms Leydon has referred, risk to student contact time and the risk of over-assessment.</p><p> It is also worth noting that the Department for Education in England has recently moved away from continuous assessment for the purposes of the lower secondary education, the general certificate of secondary education, GCSE.  This move was largely motivated by fears about a lack of rigour in the assessments and also because continuous assessment can cause difficulties if students move school during the junior cycle and it also causes difficulty for adult learners who return to do the junior cycle or the leaving certificate on a part-time basis.</p><p> Teachers already operate a system that is superior, we believe, than continuous assessment and that is formative assessment.  Formative assessment is where students are given feedback on a daily basis so they can learn from that as opposed to continuous assessment where they hand up a piece of work and they do not get feedback on that piece of work.  It is also embedded in the new junior cycle, as I have said.</p><p> The structure and the content of courses designed by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, NCCA, typically take full account of the variety of assessment modes that are available and of the need to equip students for a world that is ever-changing.</p><p> The TUI asks the committee to note that any ill-advised introduction of a continuous assessment could undermine public trust in both the junior cycle, which we are currently just halfway through and the leaving certificate.  This would have adverse implications on the approximately.</p><p> In conclusion, TUI believes that any move towards continuous assessment system could negatively affect the quality and the reputation of the Irish public education system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#F00400"><p>I call Mr. Ois&iacute;n Hassan, vice president for academic affairs in the Union of Students Ireland, USI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ois&iacute;n Hassan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#F00500"><p>On behalf of the Union of Students in Ireland, USI, I thank the committee and the Chair for inviting us today.  The USI welcomes the joint committee's investigation of the potential use of the continuous assessment model in State examinations.  USI has worked for many years on issues of quality and enhancement of education, primarily at third level, but has often taken a view of the need for wider educational reform.  USI is broadly supportive of the efforts at third level and especially at higher education in regard to continuous assessment, recognising and championing the need to develop a model of student partnership and we are eager to see efforts expand beyond the post-secondary sector.</p> <p>  The committee should be aware that USI has largely approached this submission from the view of third level and specifically higher education, and throughout the submission we have attempted to highlight the significant need for a more joined up approach to educational reform in Ireland.  Each phase - primary, lower and upper secondary and tertiary - cannot continue to be reformed in silos.  Further, consultation and input from students, staff and relevant organisations, and the public, should be facilitated in a more informative and collaborative way if we are to truly understand continuous assessment and the need for it.</p> <p>  The topic of continuous assessment across State examination presents an opportunity to do that.  I draw the committee's attention to the three key priorities that we listed in the overview, namely, that the committee should formulate a clear view of the value of continuous assessment, rather than view it as an international pressure; that the committee should embrace the opportunity to consult on this issue in a way that is inclusive of students, parents, and practitioners; and that the committee should utilise this opportunity to focus on transition from one phase of education to another, with continuous assessment as a key enabler to a successful transition, retention and student success.</p> <p>  In conclusion, I want to reiterate something in the submission, namely, that the senior cycle review currently being undertaken by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment and its relationship to this work needs to be carefully considered.  I also want to encourage the committee to involve the Irish Second Level Students&rsquo; Union, ISSU, in this work.  USI and ISSU enjoy a strong partnership and that represents a key opportunity to look at how that holistic and joined up approach to educational reform can be undertaken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#F00600"><p>We invited representatives from the secondary school students' union but they declined to come in.  They did not respond but we asked them.  I call Mr. Browne, president of the National Parent's Council post primary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.17" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Geoff Browne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#F00700"><p>On behalf of the National Parent's Council, we are grateful to the joint committee for the opportunity to make this submission on behalf of students attending post-primary schools in Ireland and also their parents.</p> <p>  I will refer to the National Parents Council post primary, as the NPCpp.  NPCpp has previously engaged with this joint committee on related matters and while we acknowledge that the leaving certificate examinations have served our young people well to date, we advocate review and reform of the leaving certificate and the examination process currently in place for same.  We welcome efforts to evaluate and adjust current practices and examination methods within the education system to better reflect the talents and achievements of students and to better prepare them for further education and their future lives and careers.</p> <p>  While fully accepting that some method is required to assess the knowledge that students gain through their post primary education, the current system is primarily based on one-off testing, namely, the junior and leaving certificate examinations.  This reflects more as a memory test mostly suited to rote learning rather than genuinely assessing a student&rsquo;s learning, knowledge, ability or acumen for a subject.</p> <p>  Indeed, many studies and informed discussions suggest that ongoing assessment has very significant value towards students learning and engagement while also being a better tool to establish the true depth of a student&rsquo;s knowledge.</p> <p>  Through nurturing a student&rsquo;s strengths and interests our education system can create self-motivated thinkers who learn and understand the benefits of discovery through research and evaluation.  Assessment methods should enable and examine a student&rsquo;s true depth of knowledge, overall ability and critical thinking on an ongoing basis.</p> <p>  NPCpp is also concerned that the current system of evaluation maximises stress on students who often memorise to regurgitate in a moment and then forget.  It does little for many towards assisting their learning or retained knowledge.  Once off examination can be brutal instruments undertaken at a particularly stressful time in most children&rsquo;s lives and does not sufficiently assess a student&rsquo;s overall performance and learning during their time at school.</p> <p>  Indeed, from the calls received from parents and sometimes students themselves, it would appear that exam anxiety is a very common reality in teenagers and to some students and their parents can be quite devastating.  This was also highlighted to us in calls to the helpline we had in place last summer.</p> <p>  Significant stress in teenage students definitely occurs as a result of the anxiety caused by the current method of assessment and the pressurised study regime that derives from it.  Educational or work opportunities associated with the outcome of the exam, the students' self-esteem with regards to their grades, judgments from friends, family and teachers in relation to their performance are among the main causes of stress in teenagers reported to us.  Comparisons to friends and siblings based on once off exam results are also feared.  Let us not forget that the stress the students are under can and does reflect on their families as well.</p> <p>  NPCpp acknowledge that some changes have already been made and that some subjects already utilise forms of continuous assessment and project works and believe that, where this is the case, there is wide acceptance of the benefits towards fairness and better evaluation.</p> <p>  NPCpp affirms that our curriculum and method of assessment should be evaluated on an ongoing basis to ensure that our education system is fit for purpose and delivering fairly.  Changes, when made in subjects, curriculum and assessment methods, etc., need to be regularly reviewed to ensure that they actually deliver the benefits as envisaged and will require constant updating to retain relevance in today&rsquo;s rapidly changing world and to ensure that Ireland remains to the fore in quality education.</p> <p>  In summary, NPCpp believes that the current examination method is not fully serving our children to their maximum potential and our education system, curriculum and methods of assessment particularly, must be reviewed and changed to incorporate increased levels of continuous assessment, to ensure that it is delivering what every child in our country deserves - a quality education that prepares him or her for his or her future life.  We also acknowledge the changes cannot happen overnight and that significant investment will have to be injected by government in developing continuous assessment methods and further teacher training will ensure continuous assessments completed by students are free from plagiarism and are carried out in modern and fully equipped school environments.  We owe it to our young people to ensure that best practice is employed in our assessment methods of their learning and ultimately benefits all the people of Ireland and our nation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#F01000"><p>I call Mr. Perser, director of academic affairs for the Irish Universities' Association.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Lewis Purser" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#F01100"><p>We have been asked to represent the universities in this important discussion with the Chair and the committee.  Our opening statement and contributions to the discussion are based and are heavily informed by the written submissions we understand the committee has already received from our colleagues in UCC, UCD, NUI Galway and the University of Limerick.</p><p>This opening statement and our contributions to the discussion are based on and heavily informed by the written submissions we understand the joint committee has already received from our colleagues in UCC, UCD, the National University of Ireland, Galway, and the University of Limerick.  Our aim today is simply to highlight some of the main potential benefits and risks for the State examinations system that may be associated with continuous assessment and to list some of the most important enabling measures and conditions that we see as being needed for continuous assessment to be used in State exams in pursuit of the overall goals of the State's education and skills strategies and policies.</p><p> Continuous assessment is, very simply, a way to ensure that all learners have opportunities to succeed.  This is what teachers do every day in their classrooms and good teachers do it very well.  By continually observing learners, monitoring what they know and can do, teachers can ensure all learners are making progress in a holistic way, irrespective of the type of examination system in place.  With the high stakes terminal leaving certificate examinations currently in place in Ireland, it means much of this good practice is often sacrificed in order to prepare for the exam.</p><p> Regular, ongoing assessment also means that teachers can use a range of assessment tools and methods to assess learners in a variety of different ways, developing confidence in their knowledge of what the learners know and can do.  Research indicates that this allows for much greater flexibility in teaching and learning and provides a more accurate and robust overview of student progress and performance than methods that provide a single "snapshot" through formal examination.</p><p> There are particular benefits that continuous assessment can bring to the well-being of students.  It is likely to reduce the pressure associated with preparing for final exams, for example, and continuous assessment gives a better rounded and nuanced profile of the student over time.  If correctly designed, it can play to a student's interests and strengths.  Continuous assessment activities focus on student understanding rather than their ability to memorise.  Assessment should require learners to think, express their thoughts and demonstrate their skills.  This enables learners to display a much deeper understanding than if they were simply memorising information for a test.  This greater emphasis on skills related to critical thinking, reflection, teamwork and creativity are appropriately assessed over a continuum in time and through multiple methods.  A consistent critique of high stakes one-off examinations is the narrowing impact on what and how students learn.</p><p> With respect to risks, there is certainly a risk to the integrity of the exam system and a number of measures would need to be put in place to counter that potential risk.  There is a serious risk around validity, reliability and consistency in examinations across the many thousands of teachers who would need to be involved and the different assessment measures.  A rigorous and comprehensive external monitoring and moderation process organised by the Department and the State Examinations Commission would be needed if we move to this sort of system.  There would need to be much initial training, continuing professional development, ongoing support and resources, including the necessary time to allow teachers to engage with this successfully. </p><p> There has been much recent positive change to the junior certificate and there is an impetus for change at the senior cycle.  However, the junior cycle reform is still a work in progress and there is no data, as of yet, on the effectiveness or experiences arising from these classroom-based assessments.  We need some rigorous investigation and research into international best practice, including the various forms of assessment that could be best used in the leaving certificate context.  This would involve consulting with a wide range of stakeholders and bringing them on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#G00200"><p>You should make a final point now, if you do not mind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.22" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Lewis Purser" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#G00300"><p>We have highlighted in our submission a number of enabling measures, critically around staff development.  Continuous assessment, <i>per se</i>, will not be a panacea or a one-size-fits-all solution.  Much appropriate training and development will be needed but there are very good models in further and higher education about how this can be managed over time very successfully, with good external quality assurance and monitoring mechanisms.  We would be delighted to engage with the committee further in these matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#G00400"><p>I thank all the witnesses for their observations and opening submissions.  We will have questions from members before coming back to the witnesses.  If questions arise and the witnesses feel they would like to come back over the next few weeks with written submissions, they should feel free to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1266" speakername="Kathleen Funchion" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#G00500"><p>I thank everybody, including those in the Gallery, for attending.  I have a great interest in the area, and not necessarily in the context of the current debate on some of the proposed reforms of the leaving certificate.  It relates to students' anxiety, stress and mental health.  It even starts as young as primary school, as we see children worrying about spelling tests on Fridays.  Children tend to compare themselves with other children from a very young age and feel they are not good enough or cannot do something as well as another student.  That can stay with a person and it is a constant battle to try to build children's confidence.</p> <p>  I am not questioning the quality of teaching or the curriculum of the leaving certificate but I question the way we currently assess students.  It is not a fair system and it is weighted in favour of students who might come from a more affluent background and may be able to afford grinds or extra support.  If students are in any way panicked or stressed, or if they suffer from anxiety at all, it will be exacerbated during exams.  Most of us would know many people who say the leaving certificate was one of the worst if not the worst experience of their life.  I include myself in that.  If we have a system like that, it is clearly failing.</p> <p>  Continuous assessment does not necessarily need to be from fourth year onwards but we could look at the model in some colleges, where 60% of marks are awarded for exams and 40% comes from continuous assessment.  A student must pass the exam in order to pass a particular subject.  I do not see the difficulty with it being run by the State Examinations Commission.  Some teachers take issue with being the person who must assess a student constantly and the fairness in it.  It is a reasonable point.  We need to move from the model of having just one exam.  Depending on subject choice and day on which the exam takes place, a student might study for two years but have everything examined in four or five days.  If exams start on a Wednesday, all the exams might be completed by the following Wednesday.  With other subject choices, there might be a gap of a week in which a student can study.  It is completely unfair as it currently stands.</p> <p>  Would a level of continuous assessment be a fairer way of examining students?  If not, what would the witnesses suggest as a change to the current leaving certificate?  There are many stories and everybody knows the level of stress and anxiety in students.  People cannot say it does not have an impact on students when it does.  Mr. Browne made the point that there is an effect on families as well.  It is becoming clearer every year.  It does not help that when the leaving certificate examinations start, there is hype in the media about the number of students doing it and what they thought of the first English paper.  We should not have any of that as we are constantly drawing attention to it.  On the day of the results, there are one or two people with six or seven A grades, which is great for them, but that does not reflect the majority of people.  Students who may already doubt themselves and have issues of confidence and anxiety will look at them and see somebody else who is again better than them.  We know there are major mental health issues with young people.  I am not saying this is the only reason for it but it is a major and increasing factor.</p> <p>  If the witnesses could change one element of the current leaving certificate structure, what would it be?  What should be done differently from a mental health perspective?  For example, I know some schools practise mindfulness, doing it for maybe five or ten minutes every day.  I know we must consider resources and what can be done but there are practical ways to try to address the mental health issues of students.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1343" speakername="Tony McLoughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#G00600"><p>The witnesses are very welcome and I thank them for their very detailed submissions and presence today.  They have been very informative so far.  What evidence suggests that continuous assessment alleviates student stress?</p><p>Mr. Browne referred to the stress experienced by students.  Is there evidence to support the contrary view?  Given their already burdensome schedule, will teachers be able to appropriately grade or correct additional assignments?  Do students tend to receive better or worse grades under the continuous assessment model?  How will it be possible for the State to standardise continuous assessment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1325" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#H00200"><p>I thank the witnesses for their presentations and the useful written submissions made by the organisations represented today and several other organisations.  It is important that the committee feeds into the work being done on the leaving certificate examination by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, NCCA.  I share the concerns expressed by previous speakers about the stress experienced by young people.  The leaving certificate places great emphasis on the final written examination.  As Ms Leydon and Ms Irwin stated, there is also an element of assessment in the oral examinations and so forth but it is primarily based on the final written examination.  This approach places severe pressure on young people, especially those who are not particularly strong in written examinations.  The system should be modified to make it fairer to young people with different skills, for example, co-operative and critical thinking skills.  How can we advance this objective?</p> <p>  I have history in this area as I have sat across a table from some of the witnesses.  I know the teaching unions must negotiate on behalf of their members.  I had a particularly interesting experience working with the higher education sector on modifying grading systems and so forth.  I am interested in hearing the views of the teaching unions on the new grading systems for the leaving certificate. </p> <p>  The recently introduced junior cycle reforms were negotiated.  I am interested in how teachers, students and parents are responding to these changes.  I remember attending a meeting in Kilkenny facilitated by the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment in the 2000s while serving as an opposition spokesperson on education.  Representatives of the Irish Second-Level Students Union to which Mr. Hassan referred attended and provided feedback from second level school students.  We have not made much progress in the intervening years.  How do we move forward and reduce the severe pressure on school pupils?  I do not know what the witnesses' views are but I find league tables appalling.  We need to move away from measuring schools' success on the basis of the percentage of students who progress to higher education because there are many other pathways available to school leavers.</p> <p>  In its written submission, the Irish Universities Association refers to mitigating risks and ensuring continuous assessment has robust criteria defined in sets of standardised but flexible rubrics.  It also refers to making learning and teaching outcomes visible for students, staff and parents and making teaching and learning accountable.  It notes that a terminal examination system can be shrouded in secrecy and normative assessment.  I presume this is the point Deputy Funchion was making when she argued that people from certain backgrounds have an advantage in written examinations. </p> <p>  All of us, from all backgrounds, agree that we need to modify the system in some way to reduce pressure on students and achieve formative results of assessment and focus on engaging with students in the learning process.  This may not be primarily the examination function of assessment, if one likes, but we need to be able to offer feedback to students.  The NCCA's written submission refers to processes and outcomes of learning.  Rather than judging young people, education is supposed to be about the process of learning and facilitating young people to become lifelong learners.  These may be somewhat abstract points.  How can we move forward to achieve something better for all students, not only those who are good at written examinations or can afford to pay for grinds or repeat the leaving certificate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#H00300"><p>I thank Deputy O'Sullivan for her contribution.  No one here is more experienced than she is in the area of education.  All speakers made valid points.  I note that 50% of students now take grinds, which surely mitigates against those who come from a disadvantaged or vulnerable background.  This must be borne in mind.</p> <p>  It is interesting to note in the written submissions and the views expressed by those representing teachers and students a divergence of opinion on this matter.  We all want students to have a positive, holistic experience of education.  We want them to be educated for life and helped to learn the skills and resilience they will need to find employment and live their lives.</p> <p>  Ms Leydon referred to benchmarking the Irish system against the systems of other European countries and noted that we are doing well in the PISA rankings.  While it is important to benchmark, would transitioning to continuous assessment facilitate effective benchmarking against other European countries?  Would such a transition and enabling greater student engagement have a significant impact on early school leaving?  I expect it would.  It is very important that we should not focus only on students who will do well in the points system but also support those who are at the bottom of the class, so to speak, in terms of achievement and attainment.  Does the current educational model impact on the use and take-up of new technology?  I expect that it probably does.  Does the system have the capacity to make the transition to continuous assessment?  What needs to be done in this regard, both in the system and in terms of teacher training?  I acknowledge that this will cause great upheaval for students and teachers.</p> <p>  I propose to open the discussion again to stakeholders.  I will take speakers in the order in which they indicate.  We will then have a second round of questions from members. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Joanne Irwin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#H00400"><p>I will make a few brief points.  Like Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, I know exactly what it was like to get the junior cycle to where it is now and it is not yet fully on stream.  As my colleague pointed out, it will be a number of years before we see the effect of classroom based assessments.  Every subject will have two classroom based assessments taken during the year.  Students will have an assessment task that is marked by the State Examinations Commission.  In a way, they will have experienced a form of continuous assessment.  It will take a long time to embed this in the system, which will be necessary before we make changes to the senior cycle.</p> <p>  On the issue of anxiety and stress, from my experience of teaching in further education where all courses are taught through continuous assessment - I have taught students aged from 16 to 83 years - certain students experienced stress more frequently in the continuous assessment model because they were anxious in any case.  Rather than only experiencing it at the end of the year, these students felt anxious every time they were given an assessment.  This meant they felt more anxious throughout the year.  I acknowledge, however, that some students did not experience anxiety.  The main issue is the CAO points race because it causes most of the stress students experience.</p><p>We need to change the whole focus on the leaving certificate result or when the leaving certificate starts.  I have never yet seen a student featured on television who got their leaving certificate applied or PLC results or who completed an apprenticeship - all these areas that those of us in the education sector are told to promote but which are not promoted.  So much pressure from the media and the third level sector is on going on to third level and that should not be the case.</p><p> I am totally against league tables.  They measure one form of assessment and do not take the holistic learning of a student into consideration.  The day of the leaving certificate results, we do not hear about the student who struggled every day to go into school, who got a D and who passed.  I have had students like that and it meant more to me, and to them, than the students who got an A1 because these students were always going to get an A1.  It was the student one encouraged to come in every single day who should be out there to show people what they can achieve.</p><p> Workload will be a major issue.  We have a teacher supply crisis, pay discrimination and very low morale in the profession.  However, they are engaging in the CPD for junior cycle, which is an extensive programme.  To try to put this on top of changing the junior cycle will be the straw that breaks the camel's back for teachers.  They just do not have the capacity to do it.</p><p> I welcome what Deputy Funchion said, which is that it will be assessed by the State Examinations Commission.  We have huge faith in the commission.  I do not know if it has the capacity or whether it would be funded to have the capacity to extend the work it does.  We do not have any objection to a second assessment component if it is externally assessed by the State Examinations Commission so that it is an objective analysis of the students' work.  I am not speaking on behalf of the State Examinations Commission but I would have fears about whether it would have the capacity to do it.  It would certainly have the ability but the question is whether or not it has the capacity.</p><p> Regarding the Chairman's question about whether it would impact on early school leaving, a recent study by the OECD entitled, Education at a Glance, showed that Ireland has a 91% completion of upper secondary education where the EU average is 67% so we are very successful at present.  I accept that if there are more second assessment components, we do not have an issue with it but it should be independently assessed by the State Examinations Commission.  In fairness to the NCCA, in respect of the work it does in devising the programmes, it takes on board the views of the development groups and has more practical elements.  Music for the new junior cycle is worth 30% practical while home economics is worth 50% practical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Geoff Browne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#J00200"><p>I will make a few observations.  Deputy McLoughlin asked whether we had any evidence that continuous assessment alleviates stress, etc., in students.  We have only anecdotal evidence in terms of phone calls received by the National Parents Council.  We would often ask the students what model works best for them.  An example given to us involves construction studies.  My figures may not be exactly correct but a day practical covers 20% of the marks while a project covers 25% so straightaway, they have attained almost half of the marks before the actual terminal examination.  Students have told us that this works for them but, as I say, there is no empirical evidence of that.</p> <p>  With regard to the final examination, I would like to add that it often does not suit our most academically bright children.  They can also suffer from nerves on the day of the examination and underperform due to the stress it causes them.  I concur with what Ms Irwin said.  Deputy O'Sullivan asked about league tables.  I have described them here previously as laudable at best.  They make no allowance for students who go on to do apprenticeships.  I think a stigma has developed around the leaving certificate applied and those who complete it.  I have children myself.  Some children are academically gifted while others are practically gifted and will go on and do apprenticeships so the area of apprenticeships and the leaving certificate applied should be given more focus.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.32" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ois&iacute;n Hassan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#J00300"><p>I will try to cover as much of that as I can.  The CAO race is probably the bigger factor but a high-stakes examination is still one of the root causes.  We are focused on rote learning.  To return to Deputy Funchion's question about whether there is one thing we could look at and start to do, it is gradual reform.  Certainly the experience from higher education is that the move towards continuous assessment needs to be done gradually for the benefit of an underfunded system, the staff who are involved in the CPD that is required and the students and their ability to adapt to a changing environment.  We need to realise that everyone has to adapt to the move to continuous assessment because we have focused on a high-stakes examination and rote learning in the past.</p> <p>  To return to the point about transition, the evidence to say that a move to continuous assessment will have a positive impact on well-being is not necessarily there because we have not gone out to find that evidence.  We have not done the research and we have not started to make the necessary moves towards what I would view as continuous assessment to start to see the benefit of that.  I draw members' attention to the transition report from the National Forum for the Enhancement of Teaching and Learning in Higher Education which concluded that there was no link between academic performance in the CAO and the ability of the student to successfully transition and not struggle.  Students struggled across the board with the transition, particularly in that first academic semester and the first year.  We know that drop out at that level is around one in six.  The majority of students will drop out in first year so transition is a big issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Moira Leydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#J00400"><p>I am glad Mr. Hassan used the word "transition" because we have certain solutions to the problem we identified.  I am picking on three themes that have come across very strongly.  At the risk of being teacherly, I think we are talking about two different things.  We are talking about assessment and how it is spread over the year, etc., but we are also talking about the role of the leaving certificate, to be very blunt, as a selection mechanism for third level education.  I prefaced my remarks by saying this is the 20th anniversary of the establishment of the commission on the points system.  This was the very issue it sought to address.  Continuous assessment is exactly what it is.  It is spread over the two or three year cycle.  Actually, it is pretty well embedded in our system.  For example, in Gaeilge, 40% of the marks for the examination at junior and senior cycle are for oral communication skills.  This is exactly what it should be for a language because if someone cannot communicate orally, their communication capacity is diminished.  The same is true for the practicals for music and the sciences.  As the junior cycle rolls out, that facility is there.  Continuous assessment is not really the challenge for our system.</p> <p>  The perennial challenge for our system is the fact that the leaving certificate is a very high-stakes examination and will remain so as long as it continues in that selection role for third level.  As legislators, members of this committee are in the business of finding solutions.  I was doing some reading around this matter this morning.  I think we should all revisit the transitions project of 2011 when Professor &Aacute;ine Hyland prepared a very well-researched and thoughtful paper in which she set out three potential solutions to this high-stakes selection function and how we can reduce stress and what has been called the backwash effect on teaching and learning.  I would certainly suggest that members revisit that report to see how far the three core recommendations in it have been implemented.  At the risk of being shot down by my third level colleagues, the one area where the least progress has been made has been entry to third level.  We have changed the grading structure and conducted very reputable research on predictability in the leaving certificate examination.  The conclusion was that leaving certificate examinations do, by and large, test the higher cognitive skills so it is not all about rote learning, etc., so we need to revisit that.</p> <p>  I think we have taken our eye off the ball over the past decade.</p><p>The Deputy referred to what I would describe as significant socioeconomic patterns in student achievement.  That is still with us.  It has not gone away.  Every system struggles with this.  We should look very carefully at how we can, as a system, put more resources and supports into our schools in order to break these cycles of disadvantage and lower achievement.  I cannot quote the most recent but there have been evaluations of DEIS and ESRI research on the subject.  One recent study showed that more than 64% of students deemed disadvantaged are outside the DEIS system.  Those students are in schools where they are not getting the extra supports.  They are not necessarily in schools which have a dedicated focus on dealing with disadvantage.  The research on disadvantage shows that it is not so much the model of assessment that is critical to students' achievement levels.  Rather it is whole school policies for school attendance and retention, high expectations of students by teachers and, more critically, a feeling of student engagement and being part of the school.  That is what teachers often talk about - the school as a community.  As Ms Irwin has said, our retention rate is up there at the top because schools make a huge effort in this regard.  If 64% of our students who are not achieving because of background are not in DEIS schools, we need to think very seriously about supplementary models.</p><p> Coming back to the issues of well-being and stress, it is really to the credit of our legislators and our education community that student well-being has been at the heart of our debates on curriculum at the junior cycle through health promotion in schools, youth mental health guidelines and our new child protection policies.  It is absolutely critical that we follow up on these good intentions and build the capacity of schools to realise them.  </p><p> To be teacherly, I will say there are issues with continuous assessment in respect of how to do it better.  We have a balance.  We can always get a better balance, but we must address the selection function of the leaving certificate.  Some 67% of our students transfer to higher education, which is defined as the institute of technology sector and third level sector.  The iar-Aire was very much part of this policy development.  We are really in a very good space at the moment with regard to further education and training, the amount of apprenticeships coming on board, the sense of enthusiasm out there and the promotion of these alternative post-school pathways.  Ms Irwin referred to the junior cycle bedding down and that over time we might see conclusions.  I believe that over time - over five years or so - we will see the impact of that further education policy and the opening up of apprenticeships.  It will loosen the nexus between the leaving certificate and the selection function.  I ask the committee to revisit the transitions project.  That would be a good step.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#K00200"><p>I thank Ms Leydon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.36" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Moira Leydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#K00300"><p>I am sorry.  I have gone on a little bit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#K00400"><p>Not at all.  It was all interesting.  I am sure Ms Leydon is aware that the committee held hearings on positive mental health and education and on the area of apprenticeships and that we have issued recommendations to the Minister in respect of both of those areas.  We sing from the same hymn sheet without a shadow of a doubt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.38" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Lewis Purser" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#K00500"><p>I thank the Chair.  I will make a few general remarks and then try to respond to some of the more precise questions which the committee has raised.  When we discuss the topic of assessment we have to remind ourselves of the purpose of assessment.  What are we trying to do?  We are trying to establish how well students have achieved the level of knowledge, skills and competences which the programme was designed to equip them with.  Obviously there are multiple ways to undertake such assessment.  Any form of assessment will involve some form of stress, but there are well established ways of spreading that stress over multiple methods and over periods of time.  In most cases students will learn to deal with that stress and that is a quite a useful life skill to develop.</p> <p>  The purpose of assessment is important because if we are looking at what we want the students to have achieved as part of their programme of learning - in higher education we refer to this as the learning outcomes - and if we are explicit about what those learning outcomes should be and what outcomes are desirable, then the assessment methods need to be aligned to ensure that those learning outcomes are being achieved and to ascertain the extent of that achievement.  Different methods will be useful for measuring different types of outcomes.  </p> <p>  In Ireland we have a very robust national framework of qualifications which is very highly regarded internationally.  The further education sector and higher education sector engage extensively with this and structure their programmes around it.  QQI, Quality and Qualifications Ireland, conducts all its quality assurance on the basis of the national framework.  I would contend that the State Examinations Commission, and the State examinations system in general, has engaged to a lesser extent with the national framework of qualifications and has been less explicit about the learning outcomes which should be achieved; about how the knowledge, skills and competences which we would like learners to have achieved at key stages in their learning careers are tested; and about the optimal way to do that.  There is quite a lot of literature on that topic.  There is a lot of experience in other countries and, as I have referred to, there is very good experience in the further education sector.  There has also been some quite good experience in the higher education sector over the last ten years. </p> <p>  There was a particular query about addressing student stress and diverse types of learners.  There is a considerable body of research which shows that a broader assessment base, as opposed to a very narrow assessment base at a fixed point in time, is eminently more suitable for meeting the diverse range of learning strengths and needs that we find in our high-participation system.  Ireland has a very inclusive system but I am not sure that the assessment part of that system meets the needs of this very broad range of learners.  The current examination model restricts the opportunities for those students, for example, who have special education needs to demonstrate their learning in the way that is best suited to their own requirements.  Students who experience difficulties with aspects of literacy, memory, concentration, mobility or anxiety are immediately disadvantaged by aspects of our State examinations system.  That is currently the situation.</p> <p>  There was also a query on how we should step towards implementation.  I mentioned earlier, and I believe this is supported by a number of my colleagues on the witness bench, that some very positive change is taking place in the junior certificate but that we would be wise initially to carry through the full set of reforms involving continuous assessment at junior cycle.  We need to help teachers manage the change.  The junior cycle culminates in a State examination with lower stakes - the junior certificate.  This will help address teachers' attitudes towards risk taking, because we are talking about moving outside comfort zones, taking a little bit more risk and being more comfortable with a broader range of assessment practices.  </p> <p>  There is quite a limited culture of continuous assessment in our post-primary schools, at least on a formal basis.  Not all subjects allow continuous assessment to count towards State certification.  Some subjects use it very well, particularly some of the languages and some of the laboratory based subjects, but if compared with the way in which state examinations take place in a number of other European countries - and I do not think the United Kingdom is necessarily a good benchmark - we are certainly behind the times.  If we are looking to assess the 21st century generic competences that employers increasingly call for and the need for which is recognised in society for all our learners, including those who are academically brilliant and those who are more vocationally oriented, we need to do something about the assessment method which we use.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#K00600"><p>I thank Mr. Purser.  Do any members have any further comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1325" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#K00700"><p>I would like to respond briefly.  I tend to agree with the point made by both Ms Irwin and Mr. Purser about the need to see how the junior cycle changes bed in.  Although I asked how this process could be moved forward and expressed frustration at how long we had been talking about this, I understand that we have to take it step by step.  There will be a learning process in changing the junior cycle which will feed into any changes to the senior cycle.  I take that point.  Ms Leydon referred to &Aacute;ine Hyland's report.  I suggest that we circulate that to the members of the committee.  We all need to be reminded of it even if we did originally read it.  It would be useful in terms of how we proceed.  I am not sure that I have further questions except a very specific question about how each of the organisations is actually engaging with the process which the NCCA has undertaken.  Obviously we are engaging with the process.</p><p>Are there related issues of which the committee should be aware?  I assume that all the witnesses are directly involved in the ongoing discussions.</p><p> We need to learn from the junior cycle outcomes, the work that is being done at the higher education level, as well as apprenticeships and all the other alternatives such as further education and so on.  At the same time, we must start thinking about and certainly adapting our mindsets as to how we might proactively and positively engage with the reform process for the leaving certificate examination in order to address the real problems we all acknowledge exist.  Despite having very good educational outcomes in Ireland generally, many people still find the leaving certificate examination to be problematic. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1266" speakername="Kathleen Funchion" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#L00200"><p>I agree with Ms Leydon that students may not attend a DEIS school yet qualify for DEIS status.  While funding is an issue, one way to solve the problem is to expand the school completion programme because it does a lot of good work.  Many schools that do not have a DEIS status participate in the school completion programme.  The programme makes a great difference to the lives of many students.  For example, one of my constituents contacted me recently about a child being very stressed about the leaving certificate examination.  Luckily, the student attends a school that participates in the school completion programme and, therefore, had the opportunity to access counselling nearly straight away.  If a school is not part of the programme then a parent or guardian must source and pay for counselling privately because the waiting lists are so long in the public system.  The school completion programme is good but is often overlooked.  Unfortunately, the scheme is no longer operated by the Department of Education and Skills and is now provided by the Department of Children and Youth Affairs, which I do not consider to be a good idea.  The committee should consider the programme and call for its expansion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1343" speakername="Tony McLoughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#L00300"><p>I thank the witnesses for their contributions.  Would continuous assessment create a better environment for students?  Would it reduce the amount of academic stress currently experienced by students by distributing the stress over a period where several assessments take place?</p> <p>  The committee has discussed the CAO race on several occasions.  Today, the witnesses have made the interesting remark that emphasis is placed on third level education rather than apprenticeships.  In the past while, the committee has met many groups that called for a greater emphasis to be placed on apprenticeships, as there is a shortage of apprentices in various sectors.  At present, all of the emphasis is placed on securing enough points to enter third level institutions or universities.  I ask the witnesses to comment on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#L00400"><p>If witnesses wish to add anything else to this debate then please submit a written submission to the clerk to the committee and we will ensure that their comments are included in the final report.  I call Mr. Hassan as he was the first to indicate a wish to comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ois&iacute;n Hassan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#L00500"><p>In terms of the National Council for Curriculum Assessment, NCCA, a colleague and I have been involved since the launch of the review.  The general feeling in the room at the launch event was there were many lessons to be learned from international perspectives on how to consult with stakeholders, students, staff and teachers.  However, when the review process was outlined at the end of the day, there was also a feeling that it was not as inclusive as it should have been, especially considering the speakers who spoke earlier.</p> <p>  As for what steps to take, the review provides an opportunity to consider issues such as the length of time it takes to get the results of final examinations.  While the junior cycle review must takes its course, steps can be considered immediately.  Many final examinations amount to between 70% and 80% of the total marks that can be awarded.  The review is welcome but it needs to be more inclusive.</p> <p>  On spreading academic stress over a longer period, the USI has defended the value of continuous assessment in our submission.  We first must define continuous assessment.  As far as I am concerned, continuous assessment in its purest form simply relates to the timing of assessments and is not related to whether it is an examination or course work.  We need to be mindful of that aspect. There is a risk that continuous assessment might spread academic stress.  Assessment should follow the curriculum rather than the other way around.  Continuous assessment requires resources in all sectors and that comes back to the transitions.  It is key that continuous assessment be defined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Joanne Irwin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#L00600"><p>I also attended the launch of the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment review of the senior cycle examination and wish to disclose a conflict of interest by declaring that I am a member of that council.</p> <p>  In respect of any review by the NCCA of the senior cycle examination, the TUI is concerned that there be teacher buy-in from the start because teachers will operate any reform.  In May, a sample of either 40 or 50 schools will be selected by management to conduct research on the current senior cycle and the existing programmes.  The TUI has clearly told the NCCA that teachers in those schools must be consulted about whether they want to be part of the scheme.  There are schools that want to participate but management has not selected them.  Also, the schools selected must include disadvantaged schools, mixed education schools, girls' schools and must include schools in regions as far away as north Donegal and as close as city centre Dublin.  The research must include all aspects otherwise the findings will not truly reflect the current situation.  </p> <p>  On the issue of continuous assessment, the TUI is concerned that breaking up assessment points would not reduce stress for students.  When I hear the term "continuous assessment" I think, from the perspective of further education, that it is a lot of assessment.  For example, I deliver a level 4 module on the Qualifications and Quality Assurance, QQI, framework that has 14 assessments.  Therefore, when we hear the term, "continuous assessment", we think that will mean 14 pieces of work for one subject.  If one practical element takes place at one time of the year, as mentioned by Deputy McLoughlin, then that is very different.  I agree with Mr. Hassan that we need to define what is meant by continuous assessment.  Again, I repeat that it must be externally assessed by the State Examinations Commission.</p> <p>  It also is important to consider the current assessment timetable in schools, which is extremely busy at present.  One will not get an holistic picture of what students experience by analysing the timetable for one subject because most students study ten subjects at junior cycle.  I agree that we need examinations to take place on a phased basis.  One should not schedule the assessments for home economics and materials technology or woodwork at the same time, as that would increase stress.  Recently, we analysed the timetable for assessments as part of the new junior cycle when the programme was fully embedded and included all of the subjects.  We discovered that assessment takes place nearly every month.  One must be mindful of the increased workload generated by classroom-based assessment from the point of view of school management, teachers and students.  If one is teaching two or three subjects and if there is classroom-based assessment, that will increase both teacher workload and stress for students.  All of those aspects must be taken into consideration.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Moira Leydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#L00700"><p>Deputy Jan O'Sullivan asked about the engagement with reform.  The ASTI is on the council and we will engage with any public consultation.  It would be misleading of me to not state explicitly that the ASTI is not in the business of countenancing any proposal that links teachers assessing students for the State examination.  That would be the red line we would not cross.  Yes, one can supplement and balance written examinations with all sorts of practical examinations, oral examination, aural examinations etc.  If a proposal emerges, however, that teachers would assess and award marks that would go towards the final State examination, then we would be back where we started, unfortunately.  Such a proposal is not in anyone's interest.  While we will engage, that will be the point from which we will start.</p> <p>  Deputy Tony McLoughlin suggested that examination stress could be reduced by continual assessments.  Young people face challenges that we have no idea about and it is quite terrifying.  Examination stress is not the only stress experienced by young people.  We have had another fantastic debate on this matter.  I must compliment the legislators for spearheading a debate on social media and its impact on young people's well-being.  Achievement stress and academic stress is one dimension in one dimension of that.  Perhaps continuous assessment can alleviate such stress.  As Ms Irwin has said, however, a cursory analysis of the timetable for a child studying ten subjects will reveal there are tests at the end of each week, end of term tests and classroom-based assessments, CBAs, or one could be in third year or could have practical work to be undertaken.  The one lesson we have all learned from the junior cycle is that assessment should not drive the curriculum.  Instead, the curriculum should drive the assessment.  </p> <p>  I get the feeling that there is a nuanced understanding of assessment and what role it should play.</p><p>Spreading it out can alleviate stress, but there is much more that legislators can do for student well-being.  Bringing some of the social media giants to heel and making them deliver on their corporate social responsibilities is a good way of dealing with this societal issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Geoff Browne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#M00200"><p>Regarding Deputy O'Sullivan's question about engaging with the NCCA, the National Parents Council has a representative on it and we are invited to participate in all the working groups.  I have had the good fortune to be a part of the computer science working group over the past 12 months.  We are content with how that will be assessed, in that it is a 70:30 split.  The 70% will be for the terminal exam, but there will also be a project worth 30%.  It is heading in the right direction.  We have representation on the NCCA's senior and junior cycle working groups.</p> <p>  I agree with my colleagues that, from a parental point of view on continuous assessment, we are not advocating monthly or weekly assignments.  The word "continuous" should probably be dropped and replaced with something else.  I will repeat the example I gave earlier.  I did construction studies and that model worked well, in that there was the day practical, a project and the terminal exam.  The continuous assessment has to be defined and resourced and training must be provided.</p> <p>  I cannot concur with Deputy McLoughlin enough on apprenticeships.  Try getting a plumber or electrician.  It cannot be done.  Those trades people probably earn more than all of us put together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#M00300"><p>They are worth their weight in gold this week anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.51" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.52" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Geoff Browne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#M00500"><p>Us computer science guys do not earn much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#M00600"><p>Does Mr. Purser wish to make a final comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.54" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Lewis Purser" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#M00700"><p>Yes.  Questions were raised about the recently launched NCCA reform process.  The universities are supportive of it.  Obviously, it is still in its infancy, but we understand it to be moving forward cautiously and trying to develop evidence and a coherent approach in order to bring stakeholders with it.  Rushing anything in the current environment would be a mistake, but there is already a great deal of good practice in the system that we need to bring to the surface, make people more aware of, and with the concept of which we need to make them more comfortable.</p> <p>  Interesting and important work will come out of the NCCA's detailed consultation with the 40 schools, which I understand should be representative of the second level system across the country.  The NCCA will take those findings, put together a series of proposals and hold a second broad public consultation, which will point the way forward.</p> <p>  The universities contribute to all the NCCA's senior cycle subject development groups and are pleased to do so but, as Mr. Browne mentioned, new subjects are coming on stream and are presenting exciting developments, for example, computer science, new languages, and politics and society, which are moving away from some of our older understandings of what the leaving certificate looks like.  There are models in the new subjects that could be adapted into some of the more traditional subjects.</p> <p>  A number of committee members mentioned the transitions reform process.  A part of the rationale for reforming the leaving certificate grading system was to provide a little extra space at each grade band to allow scope for innovation in the system and a broader set of assessment options when the time comes.  Under the previous grading system, the transparency of the leaving certificate required students to be exactly aware of what they needed or could have got, so the pressure was ratcheted up even further when they were close to a different grade.  With broader grade bands, there is scope within them to innovate, for teachers to use their best professional competences and judgment and for the State Examinations Commission to build on that.  We have put in place the parameters for many exciting things to happen over the next five years.  I agree with Deputy O'Sullivan that it would be a pity to lose that opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1257" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ESJ2018030600002#M00800"><p>I thank Mr. Purser.  This has been an interesting debate and I thank our witnesses for their valuable contribution to it.  We look forward to debating the matter further, issuing a report and making recommendations to the Minister.</p> <p>  I remind Deputies that the select committee will meet the Minister at 9.30 a.m. on 29 March in committee room 4 to consider the Revised Estimates for public services of the Department of Education and Skills - Vote 26.  As there is no other business, this meeting of the joint committee is adjourned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.56" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The committee adjourned at 5.55 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 17 April 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.57" nospeaker="true" time="15:15:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.58" nospeaker="true" time="15:15:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 15:15</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Peter Burke, Senator Paddy Burke, Deputy Joan Burton, Senator Rose Conway-Walsh, Deputy Pearse Doherty, Senator Kieran O'Donnell. Deputy Michael McGrath, Deputy Paul Murphy,</p><p>In attendance: Deputies Dara Calleary, Lisa Chambers, Martin Heydon and Eamon Ryan and Senators John Dolan and Neale Richmond.</p><p>DEPUTY JOHN MCGUINNESS IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.59" nospeaker="true" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#A00100">EU Finances Post-2020: European Commissioner for Budget and Human Resources</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#C00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Senator Gerry Horkan.</p><p>I welcome Commissioner Oettinger and his colleagues and look forward to a good exchange of views on the various topics to be discussed.</p><p>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the joint committee.  However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  </p><p>I invite the Commissioner to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#C00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for inviting me and offering me and my colleagues the opportunity to have an exchange of views on the European Union's finances post-2020.  We are preparing the next financial framework which will accompany the European Commission's proposals in May in respect of the financial outlook and financial framework for the period 2021 to the end of 2027.</p> <p>  The reason I am travelling to the capitals of all member states to meet the governments and the parliaments is to understand the expectations of our national colleagues in respect of responsibilities which we all see as European responsibilities.  Related to and compared with the existing method, we see that there are new responsibilities in dealing with issues such as migration, the provision of development aid in Africa and the refugee crisis in the Middle East such that border protection and control and defence and defence research could be as important as the fight against terrorism.  </p> <p>  In parallel, we have the ongoing traditional responsibilities arising from the treaty covering areas such as cohesion policies and the Common Agricultural Policy.  We have two problems in that regard.  We have a problem on the revenue side because the United Kingdom is leaving the European Union.  After the transition phase, we will be at the loss of its input of between &euro;12 billion and &euro;14 billion.</p><p>On the expenditure side, it is up to the European Council and the European Parliament to decide.  If we see added value in investing or moderating and working together at European level to fight against terrorism or resolve migration issues and so, we will need the money to finance the investment via our European programmes in the next decade.  </p><p> We are undertaking spending reviews, with a view to modernising existing programmes and the way to simplify the rules.  We have to examine which cuts would be acceptable.  The halving of the gap created by Brexit, in addition to our new responsibilities, means that we will have to accept some cuts, but we will have to avoid damaging traditional programmes.  However, member states do not always have the same interests.  Some countries suggest that, in the interests of cohesion, we should invest more in agricultural policies, whereas others say a reduction of 30% in this area could be acceptable.</p><p> We have a budget ceiling or dimension which, in general, under the existing framework, year by year, is approximately 1% of gross national income.  It is crystal clear that if this ceiling is prolonged and remains at the same level, we will have no chance of closing the gap due to Brexit and financing the meeting of new responsibilities.  In my view, the ceiling should be a little higher and the formula should be set at 1/x%.  This is necessary.  Investing at European level means that we realise added value.  We have to bring clear arguments and proof that we will create added value by investing at European level.  If there is to be added value, we will need the money.  This is about the national budget and new resources and we have a window for negotiations.  </p><p> The Commission's document will come out in May and the European elections will be held by the end of May 2019.  Therefore, the earlier we negotiate the better for farmers, researchers, regions and all of our partners.  We would then have clarity and certainty about the available funding and the programmes and rules that would apply to the financial framework post-2020.  </p><p> The question I address to members of the committee is what do they expect from the European Union because at the end of the day it is about unanimity?  We need 27 Finance Ministers, 27 Ministers at the General Affairs Council, 27 Heads of State and Government and 27 national parliaments to agree.  It is not the Commission's annual financial framework but our common framework.  It is a framework for 440 million citizens, 27 member states and the future of the European Union.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00200"><p>I thank the Commissioner.  I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00300"><p>I thank the Commissioner.  The multi-annual financial framework, MFF, is the EU's seven year budget but with Britain being one of the major contributors, Brexit has left a hole in all of the budgets, as the Commissioner said.  Again, as he said, the choice is between cutting and adding more revenue.  Any cut that is likely to be made includes the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, because that is the biggest budget line and in order to raise more revenue the Commission is looking at extending the EU's resources.  Can the Commissioner tell us about the rebates of some of the wealthier countries and the amount that equates to?  If these rebates were removed, how less important would the withdrawal of Britain's contributions be?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00400"><p>The main rebate is the British rebate.  It was an agreement between the then Prime Minister Thatcher and the Council and the European Parliament and we have a system of rebates related to the British rebate.  Our position is that with the UK leaving, these rebates cannot survive.  We are bringing our next MFF without rebates, only with resources coming from member states related to gross national income, GNI, and with some new and other resources without rebate.  Nobody knows what the outcome will be afterwards because it is about unanimity.  I cannot exclude at the end of the day ending up with no rebate.  In general, maybe we need some of them.  Member states which are quite critical net payers include the Netherlands, Sweden or Denmark.  It is a question of the negotiations but our starting point is that there will be no rebate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00500"><p>Is the Commissioner aware that the distorted nature of the economic statistics, namely, the use of GNI, means that Ireland is in effect overpaying its share?  The revision of the GDP and therefore the GNI figures last year cost Ireland &euro;280 million extra in contributions.  Has this issue ever been raised by the Irish Government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00600"><p>It has.  Now we are analysing the situation and the basis on which we are developing revenues, the amount of money, the systems, the methodology and this is one point on a technical level but on a political level as well, to see if the methodology is future-proofed in an ongoing way or has anything to be changed?  Should it be just related to GNI, and in which years, or to labour market demography migration?  Are there other relevant points which should play a role in coming to the levels to be paid member state by member state?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00700"><p>Does the Commissioner believe the current situation is unjust that Ireland would end up paying such a huge extra contribution?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#E00800"><p>It depends on the negotiation.  It should not be too bureaucratic.  If it is too complicated, it will not be convincing.  GNI ongoing is a fair system with maybe some additional instruments to help to come to a complete figure that member states have to pay.  One has to compare revenues and expenditures - payments to member states.</p><p>For example, if there were to be a hard Brexit, although I hope there is not, I am sure in a new multi-annual financial framework, MFF, we could do a lot via a new instrument against asymmetric shocks, via, indirectly, the Juncker plan, or via connecting to an EU facility.  Nobody knows how much money a member state from 2021 up to 2027 will receive.  To compare payments or revenues and to compare payments to members states and their projects is quite an open picture.  Cohesion is clear, more or less.  CAP is clear but all other programmes - take Horizon 2020 - depend on important projects, convincing projects and priorities or problematic developments in which we have to assist and to help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00200"><p>One can understand that it is very difficult for Irish citizens to understand that they have to pay &euro;280 million extra when they have such a huge homeless problem and they have such a huge deficit in investment in infrastructure, particularly in the regions.  I want to refer to CAP.  This is hugely important.  If we accept that there is going to be a hole in the budget, CAP is in the firing line, as the Commissioner said.  I was concerned because last month the Commissioner told German farmers that cuts to direct subsidy are coming.  Who made that decision and when was it made, that there would be cuts to CAP?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.72" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00300"><p>There has been no decision.  Our proposal will be brought forward in May, as I have said.  We are engaged in ongoing preparation work.  I have been in 18 other parliaments and some colleagues of the member, not of mine, are demanding minus 30%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00400"><p>Minus 30% in CAP.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.74" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00500"><p>Yes, of course.  Just in CAP.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00600"><p>What countries are advocating this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.76" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00700"><p>Please fly to Den Haag.  The Senator should ask her colleagues in the Netherlands or Malta.  I have to fight to get a decision by unanimity, it is not so easy.  One needs maturity here; I need unanimity.  To think that with the UK leaving that there will be no cut anywhere is a mission impossible.  I do not want to reduce the amount of money for Erasmus+ or for Horizon.  I want to speak about acceptable cuts, meaning from minus 5% up to minus 10% in cohesion and maybe in CAP.  It is an open debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00800"><p>From our perspective, that would not be acceptable because Brexit is already impacting significantly on Irish agriculture.  We hear a lot about solidarity and a lot of words around that.  I acknowledge that the EU has stood with Ireland but I really cannot impress on the Commissioner how much a double whammy of Brexit and a cut to CAP would hurt Irish agriculture.  Over the last week Irish agriculture has suffered because of the extreme weather.</p> <p>  When we talk about the rebates to the wealthier countries, we could talk about money that the EU wastes in terms of the arms industry and military development.  Having CAP on the chopping board is not acceptable and I would say it is a matter of choices.  Our own MEP, Mr. Matt Carthy, has fought strongly on this point.</p> <p>  My message to the Commissioner today is that it would absolutely ruin Irish agriculture, particularly in the region where I come from, if there were cuts to CAP on top of Brexit.  That needs to be seriously considered from the Commissioner's point of view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F00900"><p>I call Deputy Michael McGrath.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#F01000"><p>I would like to welcome the Commissioner and his colleagues.  Could the Commissioner clarify the extent of the Brexit gap?  He mentioned a range of &euro;12 billion to 14 billion.  If we park the issue of outstanding commitments to existing programmes and when all of that washes itself through, what is the annual structural gap in terms of the Brexit bill, the shortfall as a result of the UK no longer making a recurring annual contribution?  What is the figure?</p><p>We have to compare the EU 28, what would happen beyond 2020 if the UK were a member with annual growth of 2% of its gross domestic product, GDP, and the EU 27 without the UK after a transition phase.  As an average of these years in the next decade, it is at least &euro;12 billion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00300"><p>What percentage of the annual EU budget would that amount to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.82" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00400"><p>The Commission's existing budget is about &euro;150 billion.  It is 7% to 8%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00500"><p>The Commission's initial proposal is that that gap would be met in two ways; split 50-50 between increased contributions from member states and cuts to EU spending on an equal proportion.  Is that the position?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.84" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00600"><p>Yes.  I propose to close the Brexit gap 50% by cuts and 50% by additional money coming from the 27 member states and the expenditure gap, seeing new programmes and responsibilities, here I will propose 80% fresh money and 20% cuts, seeing the existing budgetary structure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00700"><p>If that were to materialise, and if we take the figure of &euro;12 billion, member states would pay an extra &euro;6 billion in proportion to their contributions and there would be expenditure cuts in the region of &euro;6 billion out of an annual budget of approximately &euro;150 billion.  That is a 4% expenditure cut, there or thereabouts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.86" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00800"><p>The cuts needed to realise the new responsibilities must also be added to those calculations.  I mentioned 80% fresh money but 20% by cuts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G00900"><p>Is the overall timeline for the new MFF going to be a seven year period or is it going to be a ten year period?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.88" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01000"><p>Seven years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01100"><p>Is that decision made?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.90" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01200"><p>Internally, the Commission's proposal at the moment is for a seven year framework.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01300"><p>When must it be agreed by?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.92" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01400"><p>There is no time limit.  It has to come out in May, as I mentioned.  It would be in the interest of our citizens, our farmers, our researchers, our mayors and our regions to have a decision as soon as possible in order to get clarity and certainty.  There is a problem in that the European Parliament election is at the end of May next year.  We have two windows, before or afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01500"><p>The absolute deadline is some point in 2020.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01600"><p>By 1 December 2020 but if there is no decision or no agreement then we have a special procedure which is related to the existing MFF.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#G01700"><p>In relation to possible additional sources of revenue that the EU is examining, I note that there is mention of common consolidated corporate tax base, including the digital sector.  These are proposals that are not agreed, either the common consolidated corporate tax base, CCCTB, or the new proposed method of taxing the very large digital companies based on where their users are as opposed to where these companies are tax resident.  To what extent is the Commission factoring in income from proposals that are not yet decided on or agreed or are they not being factored in at all?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.96" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#H00100"><p>No the Commission is preparing the MFF on the basis of existing rules.  Maybe we are proposing some new own resources.  Take the emission trading scheme, ETS, scheme, which is agreed and which is an existing system.  Climate change policies are European policies.  The ETS is European legislation.  CO2 emission reduction targets for 2020, 2030, 2050 are European targets but the money is not going to the European budget, so this could be one idea, to take this existing ETS scheme and ask member states to provide the money to diversify the revenue side of our next MFF.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#H00200"><p>On that question of climate change and emission reduction targets, what role will that play in the new MFF in terms of meeting the UN's sustainable development goals, the Paris climate agreement, and the responsibilities of individual member states to meet their targets and their obligations?  How central will that issue be in the negotiation and in the final shape of the new MFF?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.98" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#H00300"><p>The whole system is an existing one.  We agreed, and via Paris we are obliged, to reduce greenhouse gas emissions up to 2020, 2030 and 2050.  It is a clear system.  The volume of emissions and the number of licences is limited, being reduced year by year by 3% to 4% to reach the goal.  Industries, steel users or coal to power plants have to pay licences.  This is the European market but the money is not going to the budget.  One only has to get agreement with member states to get this money to reduce the money we need from national budgets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1223" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#H00400"><p>It seems that the period ahead in seeking to reach an agreement will be extremely challenging.  Trying to reach agreement on any expenditure cuts is incredibly difficult.  We know all about that in this country given the crisis we have come through in the past ten years and the fiscal consolidation that was necessary.  How great a challenge will it be for the European Union to agree a new MFF, a new annual budget, in a post-Brexit environment where we are facing the type of shortfall in the budget that the Commissioner has spoken about, whether it be &euro;12 billion or more than that, and the challenges that poses by way of member states paying more money in, and cuts to expenditure programmes like CAP which Senator Conway-Walsh spoke about?  How difficult and how challenging will that be over the period ahead to reach agreement on those very difficult issues?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#H00500"><p>My obligation is to develop a reliable and balanced proposal.  In the end, it is not the Commission's budget, it is our citizens' budget.  The worst case scenario would be to have no budget.  Our farmers and our researchers would never accept and understand that we are not ready to come to a conclusion.  The winner would be an autocrat in Ankara, an autocrat in Moscow, and autocrats tweeting in Washington DC.  It is about good governance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#H00600"><p>There is obviously a lot of discussion around how big the MFF will be, but just as important a question is the balance of spending within the MFF.  From the Commission communication to the Parliament and the Council, the Commission reflection paper on the future of EU finances causes me to fear that the direction of spending points to the type of Europe that unfortunately we have.  It points to a Europe which is a fortress Europe, a racist Europe, an increasingly militarised Europe and a Europe which uses taxpayers' money to finance private development and private profits.</p><p>To go through each of those areas, the first relates to military expenditure within the EU.  In the previous MFF, not the current one, there was &euro;1.4 billion allocated for security research.  In the current MFF that we are in until 2020, there is &euro;3.8 billion allocated.  Am I right to take from the Commission's communication that the amount of money allocated to what is euphemistically called "defence research" will likely be increased, or the Commission would advocate an increase, in the next MFF?  The Commission's communication refers to how best to support a true European defence Union.  It reads: "Given the scale of existing national defence research budgets .... the research window of the Fund would need an estimated budget of at least EUR 3.5 billion over the period to make a substantial difference".  It also reads that at least around &euro;7 billion would be needed to co-finance part of the cost of defence industrial development, assisting the military industrial complex and that a separate funding mechanism of around &euro;10 billion for that period would increase the EU's ability to financially support operations with defence implications.  Is the Commission in favour of substantially increasing the amount of money allocated to defence in the next MFF?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#J00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#J00300"><p>By how much?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.105" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#J00400"><p>The Deputy mentioned the number of the investments.  Most of our member states are NATO members and NATO members agreed to invest 2% of their GDP in defence.  It is an agreement of all our Ministers of defence and foreign affairs, not my agreement.  The average Europe is investing is about 1.4%, so we have a gap.  We can bring clear arguments that to standardise on a European level, to prepare tenders on a European level and to co-finance on a European level is much more efficient than to standardise and invest 28 times in parallel because the US is much more successful in investing and in getting back services, products and weapons systems.  Why should Europe develop ten drone systems in parallel?  It is better to have a European joint undertaking, a European team, and the defence union is the network therefore, agreed by 25 member states.  It is in the taxpayer's interest to invest on a European level and to get more back than just to invest 25, 27 or 28 times in parallel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#J00500"><p>If the budget spent on defence tripled from the previous MFF to this time, would the Commission advocate something like a tripling again because that is what the figures seem to add up to, a substantial further increase in defence spending at an EU level?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.107" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#J00600"><p>The Commission's proposal will give the basis for making experiences.  A first tender, a first year, then we will see what is the outcome, what is the direction of the market for our industries and then let us come back to the Deputy's question.  In the end we need more Europe, even in defence, because America first can mean that Europe has to do more for its own external and internal security, of which I am sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#J00700"><p>Can the Commissioner justify to citizens of Europe, including citizens in Ireland who contribute to this EU budget, why their money should be spent on weapons that are designed to kill people as opposed to being invested in health, education and infrastructure?  Can the Commissioner justify that as a moral and political choice by the Commission to advocate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#K00100"><p>It is a political question.  I am convinced that if Europe does not invest more, it will come into a dangerous position, seeing terrorists, seeing Islamists and even seeing what Russia and others are investing in.  It is about our own security and the security of our children and the next generation.  I am totally convinced and I am sure I can convince Irish citizens as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#K00200"><p>I am not so sure but I appreciate the Commissioner's honesty which is often lacking from the Irish Government in this respect about the direction in which Europe is going.  </p> <p>  The Commissioner is aware that in the past MFF, in this MFF, hundreds of millions of euros through defence security research spending has ended up with Israeli corporations such as Elbit and other Israeli armament companies, the same companies that are involved in, for example, the construction of the apartheid wall around the West Bank and are involved in the creation of drones used against the Palestinian people.  Does the Commissioner agree that no European citizen's money, even if it is under the guise of dual-use, which is how this money ends up with Israeli armaments companies - I am against this direction the Commission is going in any case - should end up with Israeli armaments companies?  Surely that is a bottom line, given their flouting of international law and given their oppression of Palestinians.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.111" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#K00300"><p>Let us come to concrete projects.  Please come to Brussels, let us speak about these arguments and let us see which projects are not acceptable to the Deputy.  The Commission has Horizon 2020.  The Commission has about &euro;11 billion a year.  That is not nothing but it is not so much and it is really related to civil projects, to innovation, to digital projects.  For example, sometimes these partners are from outside of Europe, but mainly they are European partners.  I invite the Deputy to come to me and to come together with the Commission's people from Directorate-General RTD.  Then the Deputy can see how convincing European innovation and research projects are because against Silicon Valley and the Pentagon and against Beijing and Made in China 2025, no member state, not Ireland, not Germany, and no company, not Siemens, not Phillips, standing alone is strong enough to compete.  Together we have a chance and Europe needs its own innovative and digital sovereignty.  Europe does not have this at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#K00400"><p>I have been to Brussels.  I was a member of the European Parliament.  I made these arguments and I will be concrete.  Elbit received an EU contribution of over &euro;400,000 for its participation in the FLYSEC project which integrates new technologies on video surveillance, intelligent remote image processing and biometrics combined with big data analysis, open source intelligence and crowd sourcing.  It is an Israeli armaments company.  It is used against the Palestinians, people who have their land occupied.  The same applies in different systems, for Israeli aerospace systems, for Technion.  This is a very simple question.  Does the Commissioner agree that no EU money, money that comes from European citizens, should end up with Israeli armaments companies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.113" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#K00500"><p>Please accept that, as a German, I am defensive.  Because of what Germany did to Jewish people, we have to defend this as Germans, or at least be neutral and not accuse Israel, whatever it is doing.  Please ask my president and others but here I am in a national conflict.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1433" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#K00600"><p>But a national conflict the EU is funding one side of in terms of armaments companies.  It seems again that the direction that this is going goes further in the direction of the so-called "Juncker investment plan", the European Fund for Strategic Investment.  The Commission envisages more money would be allocated to that in the coming MFF.  Could the Commissioner confirm that?</p><p>The language around it is about mobilising private investment.  The mathematics for the Juncker plan were ridiculous.  It started with &euro;8 billion and ended up with &euro;350 billion magicked out of nothing.  However, it illustrated the fact that it was predicated on private investment.  Is this not about the public taking the risk of investment in infrastructure and the private sector ending up with profit gains in schools, hospitals or whatever?  It is like a public private partnership model that always results in the public taking the risk and the private sector taking the profit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.116" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00200"><p>First, the Deputy's colleagues in the European Parliament agreed.  The Junker plan is a plan of the European Parliament and of the Council.  We do not take all of the risks; we are taking some risk.  We are reducing the level of risk via the EIB and the Juncker plan.  These so-called new financial instruments are not just European instruments.  It is a usual instrument used by many member states and by countries inside and outside Europe for funding to reduce the risk and to give some guarantees to attract projects and to activate private investors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Commissioner go dt&iacute; an coiste.  The Commissioner made a number of comments to Deputy Paul Murphy about the direction of military spend and defence.  He said that if Europe did not increase that type of spending, it would be in a dangerous position.  What percentage of the budget is currently spent on that and, in his view, what increase is required to avoid what he terms a dangerous position?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.118" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00400"><p>In the draft of the next MFF we are developing a cohesion pillar with at least 30% of our entire annual budget and a CAP of least 30% as well.  Our heading 5 means staff and buildings, which it is about 6%, so we have 32% or 33% for the rest - for research, Connecting Europe Facility, ERASMUS+, migration, development aid and, perhaps, for defence research and defence industries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00500"><p>What is the current proportion of the MFF spend on the latter category?  The Commissioner argued passionately that this must increase, and his forthright honesty on this issue has been acknowledged.  I am trying to get an understanding of where the Commission or the Commissioner is coming from on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00600"><p>It is not my own ambition.  It is the expectation of our member states.  The defence union is a decision of the Council.  Some 25 member states are expecting us to realise added value via European standards, European tenders, European investments coming from the European budget plus additional money coming from member states.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00700"><p>Is the Commissioner familiar with the percentage of the budget under the current MFF that is currently allocated to the defence and defence research area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.122" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00800"><p>Starting with &euro;1 billion for defence industries and &euro;0.5 billion for defence research would mean more or less 1% of the whole annual budget beyond 2020.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#L00900"><p>The Commissioner believes that is insufficient to meet the demands of 25 member states and points to the dangerous position he believes Europe would be in if it was left at that.</p><p>What is the percentage he believes would be necessary to avoid the dangerous position he articulated to the committee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.125" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00200"><p>Take the 2% goal agreed to by NATO members, not by me.  The figure of 2% of GDP was agreed to by Defence and Foreign Affairs Ministers, NATO members and governments.  If all of the EU 28 were NATO members and had a GDP of &euro;15,000 billion per year, it would mean a figure of &euro;300 billion.  At the moment we are investing &euro;10 billion; therefore, there is a gap of &euro;90 billion which could be closed by having a figure of 1% or 1.5% on a European level.  If these European programmes succeed, activate and realise added value, figures of &euro;1 billion and &euro;500 million should be a starting point, not the whole story.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00300"><p>Are we expecting to see a reduction in programmes?  The CAP presents a major issue for Ireland.  One of main beneficiaries of the EU budget is the CAP.  The Commissioner has mentioned that we are likely to see a 5% to 10% reduction in that type of programme, yet, on the other hand, there will be an increase in military or defence spending in Europe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00400"><p>Perhaps the Deputy might remember that I referred to new responsibilities, new programmes, at least 80% fresh money and, at a maximum, cuts of 20%.  Let us wait and see.  If I were to propose a cut of up to 10% in the CAP, I am sure at least 15 or 20 member states would accuse me and ask why I was reducing the money for the CAP, not increasing it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00500"><p>I understand that.  However, the Commissioner has made speeches in the last month in which he has indicated that the MFF could see a cut of between 5% and 10% for the CAP and the Cohesion Fund.  Is that not a statement of fact?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.129" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00600"><p>Not yet.  It will be a fact on 2 May, but for the moment our ongoing preparatory work sees a cut of up to 10% for the Cohesion Fund and, in parallel, the CAP.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00700"><p>Yes, that is the point.  I appreciate that it has to be decided and agreed to, but the preparatory work sees a cut of between 5% and 10% for the CAP.  How do we square that with an increase in military spending at the same time?  Why is the military budget not being cut?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00800"><p>Perhaps European security presents an increasing challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M00900"><p>We appreciate that there are NATO member states, but this is a neutral state, or at least it should be.  It will be hard to swallow for Irish citizens.  This is where the European Union sometimes loses touch with its citizens.  On the one hand, preparations are being made to cut core programmes that support smaller farmers, in particular, on average and sometimes very low incomes, while, on the other, resources from national taxpayers are going towards increased military spending.  What does the Commissioner say to the farmer in west Donegal on an average income of &euro;6,000?  Will he say his or her support payments will be cut but that he or she is not to worry because the European Union will defend him or her because it is ramping up spending on military programmes and using Irish taxpayers' money to do so?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M01000"><p>I would like the Deputy to accompany me and fly to Amsterdam, Copenhagen or Stockholm.  All of these member states are stating we need cuts of up to 30%.  I am a moderator.  At the end I am the Deputy's partner.  There are sure to be cuts of 5% and up to 10%, but let us wait and see.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#M01100"><p>I appreciate the Commissioner's role and understand there are bigger demands being made by other European countries.</p><p>It is also the responsibility of the Commission to communicate with individuals who will see support payments reduced as a result of decisions or proposals tabled, at the end of the day, by it.  It must take ownership of these proposals.  Saying the Netherlands wants to cut more does not cut it.  That is what leads to people turning away from the European project.  They will argue, legitimately in certain cases, that the priorities are wrong.  There is a guaranteed increase in military spending, but everything else is on the chopping table.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.136" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00200"><p>It is about a figure of &euro;1 billion or &euro;1.5 billion, or approximately 1%.  The Deputy is using up ten minutes of the time available on 1% of the budget.  Is that balanced?  I do not think so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00300"><p>I represent farmers and people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.138" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00400"><p>The Deputy is a lobbyist.  I am a moderator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00500"><p>That is okay.  I say to the Commissioner that he has the opportunity to communicate through this committee to farmers who will potentially see their programme payments cut.  I am giving him that opportunity, but he is obviously not going to take it in the way I thought he would.</p> <p>  There is a second point.  The proposal from the Commission is to increase the figure from 1% to 1.1% or 1.2% of gross national income, GNI.  The European Parliament favours an increase of 1.3%.  In response to Deputy Michael McGrath the Commissioner spoke about a 50:50 split between cuts and increases in contributions.  What would be required in terms of the increase in the percentage of GNI to avoid cuts to the multi-annual financial framework?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.140" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00600"><p>It depends on responsibilities.  If we are just to close the Brexit gap with fresh money, a figure of 1.1x% would be enough.  In completing European Monetary Union to develop some new instruments and investments against asymmetric shocks or reform delivery tools, or to integrate the European development aid fund we would have, within a complete picture, a ceiling of up to 1.3%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00700"><p>Has the Commission settled on a figure of 1.1% or is it still considering a figure of 1.2%?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.142" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00800"><p>We are working with the formula of 1.1x% as there are several open points.  In the next eight weeks I will travel to eight more member states to meet representatives of eight more national parliaments.  For the moment I am being quite open and sensitive.  There is the question of whether we should integrate the European development aid fund, as the Parliament is demanding.  It represents a figure of about 0.03% of the whole dimension.  Outside x would be different, as inside x should be.  As I mentioned, there is a package coming on 6 December which will deepen European Monetary Union.  It is developing three new financial instruments and we need a clear order or expectation from the eurozone Council as to which amount of money it would prefer for the reform delivery tool.  It is to assist and invest when there is an asymmetric shock and so on.  That will bring me to a concrete x which may be 1.11%, 1.17% or 1.19%</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#N00900"><p>I will finish on how the impacts of Brexit could be offset by new programmes.  Does the Commissioner have ideas in that regard?  I can provide a Sinn F&eacute;in document that contains a number of proposals that we believe would be helpful.  Among them is that North-South co-operation would be treated as a qualifying combination for inter-regional programmes.  Is that something Mr. Oettinger believes is possible?</p><p>We have also argued for the establishment of a task force, based on the Barroso task force established to support the Good Friday Agreement, with an all-Ireland mandate to work with all the different national actors to support the maximum level of funding.  It was unique to Ireland and recognition from Europe of the importance of the Good Friday Agreement.  A Brexit initiative would be important there.  There are a number of other matters and the third I will mention is the securing of a PEACE programme beyond the 2020 horizon.  With those or any other element suggested by the witness, where does he see the multi-annual financial framework, MFF, as a support?  The only question is the scale of that impact of Brexit at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.145" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#O00200"><p>The European Commission, my colleagues and I are preparing negotiations in the best manner.  It is not really credible to answer those questions today.  If there is a hard Brexit, we will need additional and different instruments for the European Union and Ireland.  That is in contrast to there being a customs union, for example.  It will depend on such things.  The 2 May date is just a starting point for negotiations.  I am sure that before the end of this year we will know the detail of what will face the EU 27, the UK and Ireland.  That will inform what MFF we will need in the interests of Ireland and the whole EU 27.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#O00300"><p>Regardless of whether there is a hard or soft Brexit, the PEACE programme beyond 2020 is a requirement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.147" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#O00400"><p>In the regional programmes, the ongoing PEACE programme is future-proofed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1288" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#O00500"><p>I thank the witness.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1237" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#O00600"><p>I thank the witnesses for coming before us today.  I will take up the last point.  It is important there should be an understanding across Europe that Brexit will ultimately be a negative-sum game, probably for all of Europe and particularly for Ireland.  Whether it is a hard or soft Brexit will determine how negatively it will have an impact on our economy.  Either way, it will not be a positive for us in any way, shape or form.  Throughout the budgetary negotiations for 2020 and beyond, there must be a focus not just on the money that will be lost from losing Britain as a contributor but also on the impact that economies like ours will suffer because we are such a close trading partner with Britain.  There is a need for some budgetary steps to counteract that, whether that is in terms of the peace process or in trade in general.  Our proximity to Britain will be a key consideration.</p> <p>  The Commissioner made a point in his opening statement, saying that losing Britain as a contributor and not having cuts is impossible.  That is not the case.  We have proposed that countries which contribute may contribute more.  In Ireland our Taoiseach has said we are open to doing that if other countries do the same.  What is the Commissioner's sense from the other countries he has visited?  Is there an openness to increasing contributions in some ways?  At the heart of my points today is the fact that new measures are fine but they require new money.  With the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, and the Irish agricultural sector, which will suffer some of the worst impacts of Brexit, there would be a double-whammy if there was an impact on trade along with a reduction in the CAP budget.  Security is absolutely important for the EU but food security is also very important.  Ensuring there is a good carbon footprint for the food we produce is very important.</p><p>The positive environment impacts of sustainable farming are also very important to us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.151" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#P00200"><p>We are analysing the starting position of all member state governments and parliaments.  At the moment, a majority of member states are ready to accept the higher ceiling and invest a little more money in the European Union's multi-annual financial framework.  A figure of 1.1% seems to be acceptable to most of them and a figure of 1.2% seems to be acceptable to some of them.  However, and this is not a secret, the Prime Minister of the Netherlands, Mark Rutte, made crystal clear last week that for him the figure should be 1.0%.  The new Chancellor of Austria made a similar strong and clear announcement.  It is up to me, not us, to convince them and perhaps Sweden, Denmark, Finland and Italy - let us wait and see what happens in Italy after the elections - to invest a little more.  To be in the driver's seat, I must be ambitious but realistic.  Being overambitious would result in my proposal being rejected and we would then have nothing.  Looking back to 2005, perhaps the Commission was too ambitious then because the European Council rejected its proposal, leaving the Commission totally out of the game.  I need a balanced proposal that is ambitious but realistic.  I have to ensure we have enough tools in the framework to be relevant, important and acceptable to all of our 27 governments and national parliaments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1237" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#P00300"><p>I thank the Commissioner for his response.  Just as he was frank in informing us what the Netherlands and Denmark want in various areas, I hope he will, in the other eight countries he must still visit and throughout the negotiations, reiterate the points he hears in Ireland.  New measures require new money and the Common Agricultural Policy is extremely important.  Food security and sustainability are a key element of the CAP and that must not be lost in the discussions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.153" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#P00400"><p>I am aware that the same applies in respect of France and some new member states.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#P00500"><p>I welcome Commissioner Oettinger to Ireland and hope his travels have a good outcome.  I have a particular interest in the 80 million people with disabilities in Europe.  The European Union is in the unique position of being the only non-state party to ratify the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  It follows that the EU must not only comply with the convention, but also advance the inclusion of people with disabilities across its competencies.  This should guide and incentivise the greatest possible degree of compliance in terms of mainstreaming in the multi-annual financial framework and the EU's semester process.  Similarly, compliance with the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities is intrinsic to achieving the European pillar of social rights and the sustainable development goals.  The multi-annual financial framework and semester process are key mechanisms for achieving and implementing these and other objectives.  How does Commissioner Oettinger envisage the semester process and MFF being able to advance these objectives at European level?</p><p> Over the past decade, the European Union has demonstrated that it can act with determination, strength and resolve when dealing with crises.  However, as everyone will agree, poverty, exclusion and inequality have increased to unacceptable levels across the EU and the people worst affected are those who are already marginalised and disadvantaged.  In that respect, I speak for people with disabilities.  The EU must urgently take strong, determined and resolute action to improve the lives of people with disabilities in line with commitments in the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  As I stated, there are 80 million people in the EU with disabilities.  I will make three simple points about disability.  First, disability results in increased poverty for those affected.  Second, it increases their exclusion and that of their families in a range of ways.  Third, when the first two factors are combined, there is a loss of hope.</p><p> A number of speakers referred to defence.  The European Union is a precious and unique regional entity and no other entity in the world comes close to it as a model.  Notwithstanding that, the Union has problems and it strikes me that disintegration and the breaking down from within is as great a threat as are external threats.  I am not disputing that the EU faces external threats but sometimes threats are imported or develop from within.  One of the greatest defence mechanisms for entities such as the EU and its member states is to strengthen social cohesion.  This requires a specific focus on people and families on the margins, even if the instinct may be to argue that doing this would be unaffordable.  There is no doubt this is necessary when one considers how people with disabilities are affected across a range of indicators, including employment, poverty and education status.</p><p> Commissioner Oettinger set the scene, with which we in Ireland are familiar from the past decade.  The European Union's revenue is declining while expenditure is increasing and it is acquiring new responsibilities.  The Commissioner referred, for example, to migration, development aid, refugees, border controls and terrorism but did not mention Europeans with disabilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.156" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#Q00200"><p>Disability is not a new responsibility.  I was asked to discuss new responsibilities.  We must be clear about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#Q00300"><p>That is correct.  However, while the issues I listed were new responsibilities, Commissioner Oettinger also referred to existing responsibilities.  The European Union has ratified the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  It is important to remember that both the EU and UN were born out of the Second World War.  The Universal Declaration of Human Rights dates back to 1948, yet 60 years later, the UN was forced to point out that its members, which include all EU member states, had not viewed people with disabilities as among the human beings who should have their rights advanced.  The Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities is a statement, 60 years after the universal declaration, that is necessary to insert a "how to do" mechanism, as it were, to ensure people with disabilities can board trains, go to school and find jobs.  This is a serious international issue.</p> <p>  Commissioner Oettinger referred to the Holocaust.  We remember the awful fate of 6 million Jews.  Some 300,000 people with disabilities were murdered by the Nazi regime, many of whom were German.  No laws were introduced at Nuremberg to make that possible.  The point I am making is that the humanity of people with disabilities is not viewed as being as strong as that of others.</p><p>There needs to be a commitment through the protection of - the holding of the line - and improving supports for people with disabilities in the period ahead if ratification of the UN convention is to mean anything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.159" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#R00200"><p>In meeting our treaty obligations ensuring there is no discrimination and ensuring equality and inclusion are clear European Union priorities.  They are obligations for us as an employer inside the Commission and in terms of European Union citizenship.  We want to see them practised in member states and as part of the complete picture in the European Union and beyond in development aid and neighbourhood policies and so on.  Inside the Commission we are doing a lot in the interests of all of our staff via inclusion programmes to have fair, attractive and flexible working places, as well as via a clear order to ensure there is no discrimination and have a policy whereby people can let us know if anything goes wrong.  We are an engaged employer and sometimes pioneering.  </p> <p>   The European Semester, including the process and recommendations, was born at a time of financial and economic crisis.  It is an ongoing process primarily related to economic analysis and recommendations.  With the two pillars generated by our communication last autumn and the Gothenburg Summit conclusions, increasingly European Monetary Union and the Single Market in the European Union must be completed by clear societal rules.  With limited room to manoeuvre in the next multi-annual financial framework, MFF, perhaps we might invest more in the direction demanded by Ireland, but for the moment the majority of member states are quite defensive.  They do not accept that the European Union is doing too much in societal fields.  They have stated it is up to us, that it is a national and regional competence and that we can act and react in our own dimension, as we are closer to people and, therefore, know better what has to be done.  It should and will be a European dimension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#R00300"><p>I welcome the Commissioner to Dublin and Ireland.  I understand a hard Brexit would leave a &euro;200 million per week gap in the European Union's budget.  Essentially, it would make a major hole in the Commission's budget.  On the options being examined, can the Commissioner tell us how it is proposed to fill the hole in the budget?  He has talked about increasing the contributions made by member states from 1% to 1.1% or 1.2%.  Will he clarify where his thoughts are focused at this time?</p> <p>  Another option is creating an entirely new income flow from new forms of taxation or changes to rates or by achieving efficiencies in the case of existing taxes.</p><p>For example, we know that a group of member states are now having very advanced conversations about digital taxation.  I do not know how the Commissioner views the matter.  If there is such a development, how does he anticipate it would impact on the Commission's budget?  Increasing the existing VAT contributions is another possibility.  Ireland is now in an economic recovery period but we still have major financial obstacles to overcome in order to get us back to where we were ten years ago.</p><p> I have a few questions on specific programmes.  One of the greatest threats to the European Union, as a political entity, is the spectre of youth unemployment right across the European Union.  The youth unemployment rate is appallingly high in Greece and, to be honest, it is quite shocking in Italy.  When I was the Minister for Social Protection I introduced a lot of youth employment measures in Ireland in the course of the last Government.  As a result, we more than halved the rate of youth unemployment in that period.  Why is youth unemployment a persistent problem in so many countries?  Does the Commission have further plans to assist young people who are shut out of the jobs market?  I compliment Senator Dolan on his remarks because what has happened to many young people has also happened to others who suffer from a disability but would really like to be part of the workforce.</p><p> Young people are very concerned about the future of the ERASMUS programme in the event of the United Kingdom leaving the European Union.  The free movement of young people in Europe is critical to their sense of Europe and the ERASMUS programme is very important to those who go to college.  I ask Commissioner Oettinger to tell us how he foresees this matter unfolding.  Will a special side deal be negotiated for the ERASMUS programme, as suggested by many of the British universities? </p><p> I have two more questions on a hard Brexit.  Does the Commissioner have a sense of the areas where the European Union might assist Ireland?  I am aware that the Union does not want a hard Brexit in Northern Ireland but I am sure he will appreciate that the matter is a very pressing political issue for us.  It also means that if there was a hard border we would have to develop our ports in Dublin, Cork and Rosslare.  Has the European Union considered plans to counter that eventuality?</p><p> Finally, as the Commissioner will know, Ireland is a neutral country.  Recently, the European Union has indicated that a 2% target for defence spending is desirable.  Germany, which is the Commissioner's own country, for a number of reasons is not necessarily an integral part of military alliances.  People in Ireland really value the fact that their country is neutral but we participate in peacekeeping missions around the world under the auspices of the UN and the Irish Parliament.  Will the new defence configuration pose a challenge to Irish neutrality? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.162" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#S00200"><p>We discussed many of Deputy's questions before she arrived.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#S00300"><p>I am sorry but I had to attend a debate in the D&aacute;il Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.164" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#S00400"><p>I am sorry too.  To repeat is always-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#S00500"><p>I remind members that we are now working against the clock.</p><p>We agreed to finish at 4.45 p.m. and I have two more questioners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#T00200"><p>I have a few remarks to make.  A figure of &euro;200 million per day makes up the entire investment of the UK.  However, in light of what it is getting back, the figure is far less in the end at between &euro;12 billion, &euro;13 billion or &euro;14 billion per year net.  There is an ongoing figure of &euro;1.1 billion or &euro;1.2 billion.  We are working with &euro;1.1 billion because some things are not clear.  Should we integrate the European development aid fund into the budget or should it stay outside?  Which amount of money must we foresee for new programmes against asymmetric shocks for a reform delivery tool deepening and completing our European monetary union?</p> <p>  With regard to digital taxation, there is a clear demand from seven or eight member states to prepare a legislative proposal.  In parallel is the ongoing work by the OECD.  We are waiting to see what its conviction is.  In general, OTT digital platforms use a lot of data.  Billions of data come from European citizens using their services but nearly none of their revenue comes to Europe.  If we look at Google, Apple, Amazon, Facebook, Qualcomm, Microsoft and all the others, we can see that to have a bigger share of the value chain should be in our common interest.  There is no decision for the moment.  We are checking the situation and will then come to the Council and member states when there is a realistic option.</p> <p>  What can we do if there is a hard Brexit?  The Commission and Mr. Barnier are really near to the Irish Government and Chambers Ireland and are looking at the risks facing the EU 27 and Ireland, in particular.  Ireland's ports were mentioned.  If we need more capacity to transport products from Ireland to the EU 27 and from Amsterdam, Rotterdam or Antwerp to one of Ireland's ports, we can invest in respect of connecting to Europe.  We have more flexibility via our reform of the financial regulation.  We can take money from this programme to co-finance a project that is important for Ireland if there is a super-hard Brexit.  </p> <p>  I agree with the point about Erasmus+.  Erasmus+ is one of the few programmes I do not want to see reduced.  I want to invest more.  It is up to the UK.  Erasmus+ and Horizon are open to third countries.  Switzerland is taking part.  It is up to London to decide whether it is in the interest of Oxford, Cambridge or London to be a part of Horizon and whether Erasmus+, an open programme, should be for English and Scottish young people.  It then must pay something so that the younger generation can take part.  We would prefer such a European approach - a continental approach - in the interest of our younger generation and the younger generation in the UK.  </p> <p>  I agree with the point made about youth unemployment.  We can see how different Europe is.</p><p>There are some regions that are very successful with no or almost no youth unemployment.  An example would be the Baltic states, Sweden, Denmark or Germany.  We are investing more than ever via a European budget to combat youth unemployment.  My problem is that the absorption rate is not high enough.  Countries cannot use the amount of money we are offering them because the administrations are unable to use it, finance projects and reform and redirect their labour markets.  We are not a centralised European Union.  We are a union of member states and we need competent and efficient national and regional administrations.  The absorption rate is really not convincing.  I could give the committee some more background information.  Look at Spain.  It is really incredible.  There is a lot of money in Brussels and it cannot use it.  It is the same with the southern part of Italy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1336" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#U00200"><p>As a member of the Committee on Budgetary Oversight, I thank the Chairman for extending an invitation to me to attend this meeting and I thank Commissioner Oettinger for attending for this exchange of views.  It is much appreciated.  My understanding is that he is here to hear our thoughts on this process and the MFF.  I will not comb over all the issues that have already been discussed but will briefly give my view of what has been discussed.</p> <p>  In respect of overall funding, the question for every member state is whether funding for key areas we care about will be cut and if it will be cut, by how much.  The next question is whether our contributions will increase.  Obviously, the two are connected.  If we do not want to see a reduction in funding, we must increase our contributions.  Overall, broadly speaking, there is broad support across our Parliament in most political parties and within Government for some increase because we recognise that there is a huge deficit to be met post-2020 and we must all meet that together as a team, as Commissioner Oettinger noted.  </p> <p>  One of our biggest sectors is agriculture.  The CAP is a more important issue for us than it will be for other member states.  We are keenly aware that the three main member states who are supportive of CAP are France, Ireland and the UK so with the loss of the UK, the voice for CAP weakens.  Again, we are aware of this.  However, we would also make the argument that the money it generates within our economy allows us to pay our net contributions to the EU.  When Commissioner Oettinger goes to the eight remaining member states he is visiting, could he try to impress upon them the importance of CAP for the entire EU and not just those member states that may rely on it more than others?    </p> <p>  The Committee on Budgetary Oversight met with members of the EU budget committee two weeks ago and had a very in-depth discussion about Brexit.  One of the interesting points that was made by the members of that committee was that as a Union, we need to respond more robustly to the refugee crisis and those countries that are dealing with that issue more than others and that we cannot allow those member states that are at the forefront and at the borders to shoulder all of those demands.  I would make the same point with regard to Brexit.  This is a huge crisis for us.  It is very challenging and has the potential to be hugely detrimental to our country - more than other countries.  I appreciate that every member state will be affected in some way.  As a small country on the periphery of Europe beyond the UK, we need to see real and robust support from the EU and not just talking and supportive words.  We need financial supports to deal with the possible fallout from this.  It would be important for our citizens to see that the EU family is there to back us up when we need it.  Equally, I accept that we have responsibilities in terms of the migration crisis and other crises that may come down the line in the future.  We are all part of a Union and that should mean something.  </p> <p>  Defence is my portfolio within my party.  Unlike some of the other contributors earlier, I am very supportive of increasing our defence budget, which I think is far too low.  However, efficiencies need to be made.</p><p>I think that is the same for the entire EU budget.  If we are advocating for increased spending and increased contributions, we should also talk about the efficiencies we can make across the board in how we run our business.  That will go some way towards convincing other member states that 1% is not enough and they need to come up towards 1.1%, 1.2% or maybe 1.3%.</p><p> Regarding defence, three or four weeks ago I attended a meeting in Brussels as part of the OSCE.  The purpose of that meeting was to consider how Belgium dealt with the terrorists attacks in Brussels in 2016.  We met the Belgian Minister for justice and the parliamentary committee which carried out a review on how the city and country reacted in the immediate aftermath of the attacks, how they dealt with victims and what they are doing now to deal with the threat of terrorism.  I am sure the Commissioner will agree the threat is real for every member state.  While it may be more prevalent in others than it is in Ireland, nobody is immune.  From that brief visit I learned that the threat is becoming very sophisticated and more of a challenge, and therefore becoming more costly to deal with.  Technology is advancing all the time and we need to be a step or two ahead, but at the moment we are always a step or two behind.</p><p> Regarding working together, the Commissioner made a very good point.  Why have multiple member states developing or trying to develop the same technology?  Working together makes perfect sense to me.  Recently Ireland has committed to participate in two EU projects in the area of defence.  One is in the Training Mission Competence Centre, which will train our personnel for future challenges that may come down the line.  The second is in maritime surveillance.  When we talk about defence spending, defence budget and working together, it is not all about arms, bombs and tanks.  It is about working together to build the technologies and share the knowledge we have to gain efficiencies and, as the Commissioner said, present value to the taxpayer.  It is not acceptable for some member states to sit back and say, "Well, this isn't really a problem for us now.  We don't see a threat in our country, so we will leave you to deal with that on your own."  It goes against what it means to be part of a union.  From my perspective and that of my party, we see the value in sensible and reasonable defence spending to meet the challenges today and in the future.</p><p> I finish on a point mentioned by Deputy Burton.  I welcome that youth participation is one of the key areas the Commission wants to focus on post-2020.  For younger people we need to do more on communicating and showing the value of the European Union for younger people.  The issues facing young people are the same in most countries.  It is becoming increasingly difficult for them to purchase their first homes.  People are having their families later.  The cost of education is rising.  All of these challenges mean it is a very difficult time for those in their 20s or 30s.  The European Union has a role to play in that.  What is the planned budget for youth participation?  What initiatives is the Commission considering?  We need to do our best to communicate those to our younger citizens across the EU to show the value of the Union into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#V00200"><p>I know we are beyond our time; we were due to finish at 4.45.  However, before the Commissioner replies, I will ask the two Senators to ask their questions.  I will call Senator Kieran O'Donnell followed by Senator Paddy Burke, after which the Commissioner will conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#V00300"><p>I hope I am not asking questions that were asked already.  Does the Commissioner see any upside to Brexit?  Is there any way in which Brexit could be of benefit to Ireland and Europe?  I do not believe there is any upside.  What type of empirical work has the Commission completed in respect of the impact of a soft Brexit versus a hard Brexit for individual countries?  That would inform the approach the Commission would take.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#V00400"><p>I welcome the Commissioner.  I have two brief questions.  He mentioned that the overall defence budget would be about 2%.  How will it be distributed?  Will it be given to member states or will there be a new centre set up in Europe as a focus for an organised European defence?</p><p>Will there be a specific budget for European energy security?  If so how will it operate given that we are not self-sufficient in oil and gas?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#W00200"><p>The Commissioner has heard the concerns about Brexit, which are clearly understood.  There is no upside to Brexit.  It is important to remember that Ireland took one for the team, as it were, in the financial crisis and we continue to carry the burden of that.  The banks do not function as they should and we continue to pay back huge amounts of money arising from that crash.  During that period, the SME sector was decimated, as was farming.  Rural areas are under considerable pressure to catch up with some of the bigger urban centres, particularly Dublin.  There is the budget under CAP in terms of rural development.  The second one is market related expenditure and direct payments.  On the social side of it is economic, social and territorial cohesion.  No one has mentioned fishing today.  Those involved in fishing have suffered immensely in the past ten years.</p><p>Ireland is doing well now.  I do not want the Commissioner to leave here without knowing that behind that national story there is another story about rural areas that cannot be ignored in terms of funding through CAP and other measures, especially the social element of it.  Therefore, the Commissioner has a very difficult job to do.  If any of these programmes are cut to the extent of 30% or whatever it might be in the end, it will have a devastating effect on our economy.  Farming is the backbone of our economy - food and dairy production for export.  All of that has been affected in the past by banking.  Many farmers are under pressure regarding their financial structure within our institutions and are receiving absolutely no support from the banks.  To compound it by having a cut in the supports from Europe will be devastating for those sectors that are beginning to improve but are carrying enormous debt from the past.  Therefore, there is a special case to be made for Ireland in terms of the banking crisis, in terms of Brexit and in terms of what we are trying to cope with <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>our economy.  Central to that economy is Irish farming, rural Ireland and the SME sector.</p><p>Deputy Lisa Chambers made a point regarding convincing young people about their future in Europe.  I believe we need to convince all the citizens in the European Union of the importance of Europe because many would ask serious questions about Europe and its future.  In the context of these discussions, someone has to explain in detail the cost of the administration of Europe.  Someone has to explain the importance of Europe and where we are going.  However, we cannot forget the sectors within our economy that still have serious problems.  It is important for the Commissioner to understand that not every boat has risen and that many are still under water.  I ask the Commissioner to take those last few questions and make a closing statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.176" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#W00300"><p>The Chairman should understand that is the reason I am here.  Tomorrow I will be in Zagreb, Friday in Sofia, and Sunday in Berlin.  Day by day the European project needs more ambassadors than just the Commission.  It is our project.  Members of the committee and I - all of us - have to do better and do more.</p><p>Brussels bashing is the most popular game of many national governments.  If anything goes wrong it is because of these stupid bureaucrats.  If we are successful, it is because of national governments.  This game is not acceptable.  It is our European Union.  I have to convince all of our citizens and I do my best, but members of the committee have to do it also.  We have to do it.  It is not the Commission's obligation; it is a common obligation.  It is our project.  It is a project of Ireland, Germany, France, Malta and Cyprus.  It is an obligation for the Commission and all people with a mandate and a level of authority having prominence, as members of the committee have and as I have.  I do my best - not more, but I do my best.  There is no reason to accuse anybody - not members of the committee or me.<br/><br/>Maybe it was because of rural areas, agriculture and fisheries that the Commission's candidate coming from Ireland is now the Commissioner in charge.  Is that a surprise?  Considerable lobbying led to an Irish Commissioner having DG AGRI and not having another portfolio.  It is the best guarantee that the next Common Agricultural Policy is in the interest of our rural areas, our farmers and maybe especially Irish farmers.  I have a perfect relationship with him; members can be sure that we are closest partners.  In my MFF we developed from him and from me - not from me against him.  It is about trust and confidence.  I trust you and I ask you to trust me as well.  <br/><br/>Regarding energy security, I was in charge of energy for five years, which is a long time, working on electricity grids, gas pipelines, connections between Ireland and the UK, energy efficiency, diversification of routes and sources, and LNG.  Today we are much more independent and in a much better situation than we were ten years ago through investing in wind energy, supporting renewable energies and so on.  The energy union of just one energy Single Market is our vision.<br/><br/>There will be new headquarters for European defence policies, but it is not the Commission's headquarters.  The headquarters were developed through agreement of 25 member states.  We can co-finance, activate some money and organise tenders in order to be more efficient and realise added value.<br/><br/>Brexit will bring no benefit.  It is hugely damaging for the UK and it is negative for the EU 27 as well.  The winner is China and maybe President Trump.  However, we need to be cautious because these people like <i>divide et impera</i>; that is their game.  Therefore we should work together as the EU 27 in a deeper and more efficient manner than ever.  This is about the White Book process, the Bratislava and Rome process.  We have to try to stabilise and deepen our European Union after Brexit and to reduce the damage Brexit will bring.  Here Ireland is at the centre of all our work.  There is no week without a debate in the college about Ireland, Northern Ireland and the UK.  Michel Barnier is really brilliant and I ask members to trust him.  Task Force 50 is competent and I ask members to trust it.</p><p>Our problem is we have a weak negotiating partner.  It is a divided government and a totally divided coalition and if we have to negotiate, it is better to have a strong partner, a reliable partner, than to have a weak partner changing its mind week by week and having no clear priority.  We are asking for the UK's priorities and we have no clear picture for the moment but we are developing several instruments and options to act and react immediately, as soon as we know what the outcome is.  In regard to this MFF and beyond, if the committee wants to meet me again I am available to come here or the committee is invited to come to Brussels, whether in June, in September or in December to discuss common reactions of the EU 27 and Irish reactions when we see the outcome and the result of the Brexit negotiations.  I know quite well the exports, the imports and the daily operative developments and that people living here are working there.  It is one island in an economic dimension.  </p><p> I must go to meet the Taoiseach as I am late.  Afterwards there is a conference with the chamber of commerce.  These people are the main concern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#Y00200"><p>The Commissioner will be very welcome back with good news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.180" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. G&uuml;nther Oettinger" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#Y00300"><p>I will do my best.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1248" speakername="John McGuinness" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2018030600002#Y00400"><p>I thank the Commissioner for attending this meeting.  It has been very productive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-06a.182" nospeaker="true" time="15:15:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 5.06 p.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Thursday, 8 March 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>