<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:30</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.6" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600003#D00100">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600003#D00200"><p>There are five EU proposals in schedule A and 16 proposals in schedule B for discussion.</p><p>  It is proposed that the proposals listed in Schedule B do not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  Schedule A proposals include COM (2013) 36, communication from the European Commission to the European Parliament, the European Council, the European Parliament&rsquo;s economic and social committee and the committee of the regions on setting up a European retail action plan; and COM (2013) 37, Green Paper on unfair trading practices in the business-to-business food and non-food supply chain in Europe.  The communication is a significant development.  It proposes specific actions to address the key obstacles that hinder the smooth function of the European retail sector to achieve a Single Market in retail.  The Green Paper launches a consultation on unfair trading practices and has been published in conjunction with the European retail action plan.  It is proposed the committee considers in more detail aspects of those elements of these communications that fall within its remit with the assistance of the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and other stakeholders.  It may also be appropriate to alert other relevant joint committees to aspects of these communications which may be relevant and of interest to them.  It is proposed to forward these communications to other relevant joint committees for their attention with the advice note prepared by the policy clerk.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  COM (2013) 78, a proposal for regulation on a consumer product safety and market surveillance package, repeals existing EU legislation in this area.  The issue of product safety is clearly important.  The proposed regulation also contains a subsidiarity check.  Accordingly, it has been listed on schedule A for the committee&rsquo;s consideration today.  The proposal seeks to achieve a more coherent EU regulatory framework for product safety and it also seeks to clarify and simplify the product safety requirements for operators.  As the Department has indicated its satisfaction with the proposal and supports it and no subsidiarity issues arise, it is proposed it does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  COM (2013) 102, proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Council Directives 92/58/EEC, 92/85/EEC, 94/33/EC, 98/24/EC and Directive 2004/37/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council to align them to regulation (EC) No. 1272/2008 on classification, labelling and packaging of substances and mixtures.  Although this is important legislation generally, this proposal is making only technical amendments to current legislation which Ireland supports.  As it does contain a subsidiarity check, however, it has been listed on schedule A for committee consideration today.  As the proposal will have no significant impact on Ireland&rsquo;s health and safety laws and no subsidiarity issues arise, it is proposed it does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  COM (2013) 107, a proposal for establishing a space surveillance and tracking support programme, concerns a decision of the European Parliament and of the Council that Ireland supports.  As it does contain a subsidiarity check, however, it has been listed on schedule A for committee consideration today.  It is proposed it does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.9" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600003#D00400">Impact of Black Market on Small Businesses: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600003#D00500"><p>I welcome Mr. Mark Fielding, chief executive officer, ISME, and Ms Avine Mcnally, acting director, and Mr. A. J. Noonan, chairman, Small Firms Association, to the committee&rsquo;s discussion on the impact of the black economy on small businesses.</p><p>  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p><p>  I ask Mr. Fielding and Ms Mcnally to make their opening statements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.11" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Fielding" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600003#D00600"><p>I thank the committee for the invitation to present to it today.  I represent ISME, the independent body for small and medium-sized enterprises.  The committee is well aware of the black or hidden economy.  Suffice to say, it is made up of everything from criminal racketeering right across to nixers, illegitimate dole claims and undisclosed employment.  It covers a wide spectrum of problems that affect many small and medium-sized businesses such as unfair competition.  There will always be an element of a hidden or shadow economy in any jurisdiction.  However, it does seem to be exacerbated during recessions and high unemployment.  The small and medium-sized business sector contends that much of the competition that we face comes from the delivery of services for undeclared cash which includes home improvements and decoration, waste disposal, gardening services, furniture removal, etc.  The nixer culture is very much alive and well.  There has been a definite shift towards the cash-only shadow economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.14" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Avine Mcnally" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600005#F00200"><p>I thank the committee for the opportunity to attend.  I will not go over the points Mr. Fielding has made.  We are here to speak on behalf of the Small Firms Association, SFA, which represents more than 7,500 companies and seven affiliated organisations, mainly small businesses based throughout Ireland.</p><p>  The hidden economy is bad news for everyone.  It is bad news for jobs and diverts spending away from the legitimate businesses that are trading, and it is bad news for the individuals working within the black economy, who are probably the least protected workers in the workforce.  It also robs the Exchequer of much-needed tax revenue.  Another issue is that consumers also lose out, although this is a point we often miss.  For example, counterfeit goods are rarely of the same quality, laundered fuel is damaging to vehicles and illicit alcohol and fake drugs can have many harmful effects on individuals.</p><p>  The point has been made that there is always an element of a hidden economy within any jurisdiction and this often increases during times of economic difficulty.  Ireland is not alone in this, as has been seen throughout many European countries, particularly when the recession bit in Europe in 2009.  Due to the nature of this activity, it is obviously difficult to get an exact figure.  As Mr. Fielding noted, Professor Friedrich Schneider is the economist who has done most work in this area, and his January 2013 report estimated the Irish figure at some 14% of GDP, whereas the European average is in the region of 18% of GDP.  We estimate this works out at approximately &euro;6 billion per year, so approximately &euro;500 million is generated each month within the black economy to which the taxman does not have access.  While the figure for the EU is 18% of GDP, for countries such as Australia, Japan and New Zealand the figures are approximately 9%, which suggests some countries are more advanced in the steps and approach they have taken in dealing with this area.</p><p>  The scope, scale and extent of the black economy poses a very serious threat to the survival of many registered, tax-compliant companies.  The cycle of non-payment of taxes increases the burden on the legitimate economy, which in turn can affect competitiveness in small businesses and drives more people into dependency, thus raising social welfare costs.  This activity clearly undermines the ability of Government to collect taxes efficiently and effectively.  At this time, we believe it is essential that all companies should be able to play on a level playing field.  Due to the reduced overheads and lack of compliance, those who operate within the informal economy have huge competitive advantages, which distorts the reality of the competitive labour market and trading market small businesses currently face.</p><p>  In 2012, a report from Retail Ireland suggested the Exchequer is losing approximately &euro;861 million a year because of Irish people knowingly or unknowingly purchasing illegal goods.  Retail Ireland estimated this is the equivalent of 5.7% of the PAYE collected, which is a staggering figure.  The Small Firms Association's crime report showed that we must also consider the area of fraud.  There has been a massive increase in internal fraud in the past three years as well as an increase in theft of cash and property.  While people may be helping themselves for their own benefit, it must be assumed much of this stock is moving into a black, hidden economy.</p><p>  Figures from the Department of Social Protection show that one of the key areas for fraud is through jobseeker's benefit, where it is estimated the net cost to the Exchequer is 1.6% of expenditure.  We are beginning to see people's tolerance for this type of activity become less strong than it may have been in the past, and people are certainly not turning as much of a blind eye.  According to the Department, almost 12,000 calls were received in 2012 specifically relating to people who were thought to be working and claiming benefit.  These figures clearly show that the public is not willing to ignore abuse of the system or see the public finances being abused, particularly when individuals are suffering as a result of welfare cuts.  Apart from the impact on the economy and the State, we have to remember that workers in the black economy are among those least protected in terms of employment legislation and health and other social benefits. </p><p>  Before I hand over to our chairman, who will talk the committee through some of our proposed actions, we must also consider our approach to this issue.  At the heart of any black economy is one very simple notion that anyone can understand - namely, dishonesty.  The clear message coming from the Judiciary has to be that crime does not pay.  The figures from the Revenue Commissioners show there were 206 serious tax and customs cases at various stages of prosecution in Ireland in 2011.  During this period, 497 criminal prosecutions for excise and customs offences were recorded.  One might say that is quite a number, but one must remember that the level of convictions was just over 6%.  There has to be a message that crime does not pay and that the criminal justice response to this dishonesty is clear and firm.  It is vital that an adequate policy response is backed by the necessary resources to bring the criminals to justice and to protect legitimate businesses and consumers who rely on that structure.</p><p>  I will pass over to our chairman, Mr. A. J. Noonan, who will discuss some of the SFA's proposed views and actions in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. A. J. Noonan" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600005#F00300"><p>The SFA is urging the Government to become committed to a solution to the growing problems that the black economy creates for the small business sector.  Due to the scale of the drain on the economy, more focused attempts to tackle the problem are overdue and, given that sometimes controversial measures are necessary, a European initiative may be required.  We must also ensure that honest taxpayers and businesses do not suffer additional tax increases to make up for revenue losses incurred due to fraudsters and evaders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600006#G00200"><p>I thank Mr. Noonan.  I thank all three representatives for their presentations and proposed actions.  I should have said at the start that we had decided to take on this issue as a project this year to come up with a range of solutions prior to the budget to put pressure on the Government to introduce necessary changes.  It was on foot of Senator Mullins and Deputy Calleary raising the issue last year that we decided to give it a big push.  We held public hearings on the issue in Waterford and Kilkenny and will cover counties Mayo and Galway next week.  I hope we will cover further counties in May and June and meet members of ISME, the SFA and other groups to get a feel of what needs to be done on the ground.  A range of suggestions being brought forward.  The delegates have presented some new ones today which are very clear.  Our hope is that in early autumn we will compile a report with recommendations for the various Departments involved because we recognise this is a cross-departmental issue to which we need to bring a focus to help the members of ISME and the SFA and the economy in general.  We must provide a forum for this issue to push it on.  I thank the delegates for their help today in facilitating that objective and giving us their ideas.  I will now take questions from members.  Owing to D&aacute;il proceedings, we must finish around 3 p.m. I will start with Deputy Calleary who will be followed by Senator Quinn and Deputy Lyons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600006#G00300"><p>I thank the representatives of the two organisations for coming.  If any committee is able to offer the Minister for Finance &euro;500 million per month, that is what it comes down to.  One can talk about percentages, but Professor Schneider's analysis comes down to a figure of &euro;500 million per month, which is a relatively conservative figure.  That is how serious the problem is.</p><p>  In respect of the burden we put on businesses, we are crucifying legitimate businesses through regulations, yet the delegates seem to agree that nothing or very little is being done on the enforcement side.  Will they speak about that issue?  Do countries that share a land border and have different tax arrangements, be they for fuel or other items, take specific enforcement measures, particularly in the case of fuel and other goods?  What would be different about an awareness campaign?  I know Mr. Fielding has said the figure tends to rise as the economy gets weaker, but if one looks at the Schneider analysis, the level always seems to be around 14.5% or 15%.  Throughout the so-called boom times, it did not seem to shift significantly below that percentage.  If people are getting something that is cheap, do they actually care?  How would an awareness campaign make any difference in that regard?  </p><p>  The delegates favour a social welfare amnesty.  What would be the result in terms of revenue gained for the State and how would it work?  Would someone receive a fine and slap on the hand and be told not to do it again?  Would he or she pay all or part of the debt?  How many might be in this net?  I agree with Mr. Fielding about the tax wedge, which is a serious issue.  Unfortunately, we will probably not have time today to discuss that issue, but we might return to it.  </p><p>  I return to the figure of &euro;500 million per month.  It is ridiculous to think we will not employ perhaps 50 to 60 people in Revenue and the Department of Social Protection to collect that kind of money.  We will pursue this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600006#G00400"><p>I thank all of the delegates for coming today and enlightening us as much as they have.  I have a friend in the United States with a large grocery store who was caught leaving the country with a suitcase full of money.  Apparently, he operated 16 checkouts but only 15 of them were reported; the authorities did not know about the other one and he ended up with a sentence of four years in jail.  When the garlic scam took place this year, there was an outcry when the man who had admitted he had done it received a sentence of six years.  When Mr. Noonan talks about tough enforcement, I wonder whether the country is willing to take such tough enforcement measures.  How do the delegates feel about the matter, assuming there is tough enforcement, in which case some of their own members will be found to have misbehaved in various ways?</p><p>  It is interesting to hear Deputy Calleary talk about having extra staff.  A regime has been introduced in France whereby inspectors stand outside various places and insist on seeing a receipt.  If a customer does not receive a receipt or does not have it with him or her when the inspector requests to see it, he or she is found to have broken the law, in addition to the retailer.  To what extent are we ready for this?  We have a tradition in Ireland of not regarding tax evasion as a very serious offence.</p><p>  Once again, we hear about a tax amnesty.  I am a great believer in tax amnesties, which have worked very well in the past.  However, every time one introduces a tax amnesty, one encourages someone to think he or she might get away with it because there will be another.  What are the speakers' views on that issue?  I did not quite understand the suggestion of a tax incentive for homeowners.  Will the speakers give us a further insight into that suggestion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600006#G00500"><p>I completely empathise with the speakers.  It is a tough one.  I am a little confused about some of the suggestions made.  In respect of the social welfare amnesty, is there any evidence that such an amnesty works and, if so, where?  In respect of advertising campaigns, I am very familiar with the one involving the guy with the mask on his face who is making a false insurance claim.  I get it, but I am not somebody who would have gone down that road in the first place.  What research is available to suggest such a campaign works?  The other television campaign that is conducted all the time concerns the television licence.  I am sick and tired of the ridiculous advertisements involving the use of talking pigeons.  If they are effective, that is great, but can somebody please tell me whether the research backs this up?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.21" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. A. J. Noonan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600006#G00600"><p>The road safety campaigns are successful.  The Deputy is comparing different awareness campaigns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600006#G00700"><p>That is a good point.  I am not here to say the speakers' ideas are wrong; rather, I am trying to see which one we should be recommending.  Obviously, it would be silly of me to recommend something if my opinion was different.  What concrete evidence is available that television campaigns work?  Are more people now paying for television licences than before, or it is costing more to run these advertisements?  The same question applies to the insurance fraud campaign.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00200"><p>We will take some answers and then I will return to my colleagues.  At other hearings almost everybody suggested having a public awareness campaign so obviously there is a strong belief in these.  Perhaps the committee will do some research on this point.  I believe such campaigns work well in the UK and other countries.  The delegates may have some research on that.  The committee might take up this proposal for action as it has been suggested so often.  I call Mr. Mark Fielding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Fielding" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00300"><p>I might comment on the last point.  There are figures showing the insurance campaign worked and the insurance industry would be well able to advise the committee concerning that.  I cannot give straightforward figures for the television licence campaign but have been told anecdotally that both approaches have worked.  The awareness campaign is not just about throwing a couple of advertisements on the television.  We need to have a change in our culture.  We have spent 800 or 900 years dodging, ducking and diving the people who were our overlords, and this is now inbuilt.  Being an informer is something that makes all of us say, "Oh, my God".  However, part of getting this right is having people know that if they go outside the legitimate way of doing business they will be caught.  A lot more is involved, however, and I agree with the Deputy that a cultural change is involved and that we will have to start on this somewhere.  I believe an awareness campaign right across the board would have an effect over a period of time.  This will not happen in one year or even 20 years - it is a generational thing - but we have to start it sooner or later.</p><p>  With regard to whether amnesties work, I take the point that every time there is an amnesty people think it will last for a while and they will be able to catch one again in the future.  I would like to see figures from the Revenue Commissioners with regard to the previous amnesties.  This one is aimed at the social welfare side of things rather than the tax side.  Many of the people who were ducking and diving in this area may not even have a lot of tax to pay but it would be worth following through on the social welfare side.</p><p>  I do not agree with the Senator that ISME members might be caught on this.  We are all very law-abiding, something I had better put on the record.  I will pass over to my colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00400"><p>Right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. A. J. Noonan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00500"><p>I will talk about the social welfare side because we are not talking about a tax amnesty - we have had enough of them.  I refer to Deputy Dara Calleary's point on the social amnesty.  It is estimated that 3% of the social welfare budget is going out in some form of fraud.  It is those receiving social welfare who really need it who are being penalised because the total has been cut back this year by so many millions of euro.  We are open to ideas on how this amnesty would work; we do not have a magic formula.  The committee members are the legislators, the ones who have to come up with the solutions.  However, if there is an amnesty and some people come forward and put up their hands while another element does not, the latter should be severely penalised.</p><p>  Senator Quinn spoke about his pal in America.  That is right.  He was jailed because he was committing fraud.  In Ireland we must accept this will be our future, which will lead to a proper societal commitment to the whole thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.28" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Avine Mcnally" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00600"><p>I would like to pick up on some of the other points.  Obviously I concur with what Mr. Noonan has just said.  In regard to the awareness campaign, as with any of these issues it is about the message one is trying to get across.  People's opinions, though not shared by everybody, will come round to this way of thinking.  To be honest, I have never looked at any research on the impact on turnaround of a television campaign.  However, looking at the figures the Department of Social Protection has, one sees an increase of 11,000 telephone calls to its fraud line in the past 12 months, making a total of 28,000 calls a year.  I believe we are beginning to see people getting a little bit frustrated and annoyed with others cheating or trying to cheat the system.  This approach will not win everybody over but I believe we are beginning to see people's mindsets moving towards being more in favour of calling people out and perhaps reporting what is going on.</p><p>  Deputy Calleary asked what was happening in other jurisdictions.  The UK has set up a hidden economy monitoring group, some of whose suggestions are very much echoed by us.  It believed an awareness campaign was something worth considering and also suggested the need to look again at the tax system, taking the attitude that if it is more favourable for people to be involved in a taxable regime then they will do so rather than stay in the black economy.  This group has also undertaken huge work in assessing the barriers people face in getting from the black economy into the formal economy.  In other words, that is a regime which reduces the burden of setting up businesses correctly.  I realise we have done a lot of work in Ireland on this but I offer this material to give an idea of what our closest neighbour is doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00700"><p>I call Senator Michael Mullins, followed by Deputy &Aacute;ine Collins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600007#H00800"><p>I thank our three witnesses for the concise and well-presented cases they have made.  In regard to the public awareness campaign I believe people are now much less tolerant of abuses of the social welfare system and of people doing things that cost the taxpayer money.  I firmly believe a well-targeted public awareness campaign would bring many people who decide to go straight into a legitimate business operation.  Mr. Fielding really hit the nail on the head when he pointed out that in order for the black economy to thrive, as well as the seller there must be somebody who buys.  Obviously people can be prosecuted if they are in receipt of stolen goods but there should be other penalties.  We must look at having a situation where people will be penalised if they knowingly purchase illegal and illicit goods such as laundered diesel, smuggled cigarettes, counterfeit branded clothing, etc.  In addition, we need to look at what is happening at some of the Sunday markets where so much illegal and illicit material is being peddled throughout rural Ireland, Sunday after Sunday, as I am well aware.</p><p>  I believe it was Mr. Fielding who raised the point about incentives to homeowners who use regulated and registered contractors.  I firmly believe we will never get the economy moving again unless we have a fair level of activity within the building industry.  At some stage in the near future I would love to see us having a scheme for house refurbishment or the upgrading of energy efficient homes whereby people would receive some level of grant incentive on condition the work is done by registered contractors.  That is the only way.  We must do something to bring some of these people into the legitimate area of activity.</p><p>  I refer to commercial vehicles.  People are able to tax their trucks and vans at a much lower rate on the basis they are being used for commercial purposes.  All they have to do is get a garda to sign a form indicating this is the case.  However, they should have to prove they are tax-compliant and up to date with Revenue in order to qualify for the lower level of taxation on commercial vehicles.  The whole area of penalties and the sentencing regime must also be examined.  There is an acceptance that people get very small penalties in our courts for quite significant infringements.</p><p>  I am not sure how the amnesty would work but would like to see a situation whereby people who have started up small businesses in the black economy would have an opportunity to register, within a short period, and become legal.  We all hear on a daily and weekly basis that legitimate businesses just cannot compete with some of these guys who seem to be operating with impunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/988" speakername="&Aacute;ine Collins" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00200"><p>I refer to Senator Mullins's point on diesel laundering.  Much work has been done to counteract this activity.  Last October the Department of Finance introduced new legislation to ensure the traceability of diesel.  At the time it was said it would take at least six or eight months before results would be apparent.  The outcome will not be known until June or July this year.  We are working in partnership with the United Kingdom in an attempt to find a way to mark the diesel in order that it cannot be dyed.  It is a complex issue which is made more so by the Border.  We are all aware of the difficulties imposed on legitimate businesses.</p><p>  If the statistic for Australia and New Zealand is 9% and that for the rest of Europe is 15% to 18% - a figure of 16% has been suggested - what is the model being followed in Australia and New Zealand?  What can we learn from their experiences?  We need to see a change in culture.  </p><p>  With regard to start-up businesses, Revenue has ensured it has never been more easy to register a business.  Revenue's website is one of the best public service websites available and its staff provide great support and helpful advice.  I know this because I worked in the small business sector for many years.  However, small businesses, for their part, must be willing.  A bigger problem for them is that they initially do not keep an eye on cashflow management.  They forget to pay the tax man and instead use the money to drive the business.  It could be down to mentoring, a pet subject of mine.  I refer to the importance of providing advice for small businesses at an early stage, rather than regarding it as an issue for Revenue.  I acknowledge that Revenue officials visited small businesses, but there is only so much advice one can give people who must be willing to accept and understand the financial aspects of running a business.  More work is probably needed in this regard, but Revenue is available to provide support for those who ask for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00300"><p>I agree with the points made by Mr. Fielding.  I refer to the high level of operation of the black economy during the 1980s.  Taxes were lowered during the 1990s and more businesses operated legitimately.  There has been a resurgence of the black economy as taxes have increased.  However, times have changed.  People now will not pay for services in the black economy; they will write a cheque or offer a card and demand an invoice rather than pay in cash.  I have noted that this is happening in the trades and services sectors.  There has been a cultural change.  Revenue is doing much good work in this area by following up on advertisements in newspapers and the mobile phone numbers of those offering services.  For the most part, the days of people paying for services with cash are long gone.  However, there is a need for a further awareness campaign because the public needs to be made aware of the fact that the level of taxes could be reduced if everyone played ball on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00400"><p>I wish to make two brief observations.  In making a rough analysis I tend to divide this activity into two broad categories.  I refer to the nixer culture which flourishes in times of high unemployment.  During the recent construction boom the legitimate industry offered very high rewards in the carpentry and plumbing trades, for example, and people were in a position to pay for these services.  There was a dramatic decline in the level of activity referred to, in Dublin in particular.  The other category is the cross-Border phenomenon of trading in goods which had its origins in the smuggling of tea, butter and cattle, but now the trade is in diesel and cigarettes.  This activity started in Border areas and is controlled by the paramilitaries and their hangers-on and also criminal types.  We need to be aware of the two dynamics at work in these two categories in order that we can tackle them.  Two approaches are needed, as they are both equally harmful to legitimate trade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. A. J. Noonan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00500"><p>I agree with the point on mentoring which this is crucial in all businesses.  In the past 48 hours I heard of a chap who was on social welfare.  He wanted to do a few days' work and become part of the system.  The company in question wanted him to be self-employed for a few days.  He explained that if he was self-employed and then returned the following week to the social welfare office, he would receive no benefits.  That is a great obstacle.  If the committee could come up with a simple methodology to allow that chap to do a few days' work and then return to the social welfare system, it would be wonderful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00600"><p>We were assured that this issue would be dealt with and that the system would be more flexible in order that people could hop on and off.  However, it has not happened.  It is probably working in a few offices but not across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. A. J. Noonan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00700"><p>That perpetuates the black economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.38" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Avine Mcnally" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00800"><p>I refer to the point raised by Deputy Collins on the statistics for the black economy being lower in other countries.  The reason is that those countries have a more flexible social welfare system.  Their taxation systems are very different from ours, but there is greater flexibility.  It must be borne in mind that one is dealing with criminal minds when dealing with fuel smuggling.  They have a lot of time on their hands to think of ways to get around the system.  Revenue staff who have extensive experience in this area are of the opinion that the smugglers regard public announcements of successful campaigns against smuggling as an incentive to them to beat the system.  That is not an excuse, but it is the reality.  While no one has the golden ticket solution, it keeps happening because the smugglers keep thinking of ways to get around the system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Fielding" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600008#J00900"><p>I take the points being made about an amnesty and the marking of diesel.  I also take Deputy Collins' point on mentoring.  These things are happening, but they are not happening fast enough.  I refer to the view that an awareness campaign and advertising will not work.  The level of tax compliance has increased dramatically in Ireland because the system was made so simple.  I remember what happened in the 1980s before it became a little easier to pay one's tax.  At the time tax evasion was evident.  The advertising campaigns are having an effect.  As I acknowledge that public awareness will not be achieved overnight, we really need a cultural change.  The issue is multifaceted and there are not just one or two answers.  There are about 87 black or hidden economy activities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013041600009#K00200"><p>Mr. Fielding is right.  That was the reason the committee took this on.  This is costing jobs and if we get that message across, it will have an impact.  The reason we are having meetings around the country is to invite Ministers and even the Taoiseach and make them sit and listen to what is happening because this must become a Government issue.  This committee's job is to make it an issue and to push it as hard as it can.  It is fixable and that has been proved to us in most meetings we have had.  We would actually make money out of this.  This should not cost money, although it might cost a little in the short term.  It should bring a lot more money into the Exchequer, so we will keep pushing it.</p><p>  On behalf of the members, I thank the witnesses.  We will wrap up in a couple of months and we might consult the witnesses again.  Perhaps members of ISME and SFA might join us in Galway and Mayo next week.  I also thank the members of the committee and remind them of our trip to Ballinasloe and Mayo next week on 22 April.  The following week we will have an EU Presidency meeting in Dublin Castle, and there will be another on 29 April.  The reason we are not meeting next Tuesday is that it will be Question Time in the D&aacute;il with the relevant Minister.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:20:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.44" nospeaker="true" time="14:20:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:20</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.47" nospeaker="true" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600003#E00100">Private Residential Tenancies Board: Discussion with Chairperson Designate</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600003#E00200"><p>I welcome Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh, chairperson designate of the Private Residential Tenancies Board, for a discussion on her future role.  I draw to her attention the fact that, by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the joint committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against a person or persons or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  I advise Ms Walsh that the opening statement and any other documents she has submitted to the committee will be published on its website after the meeting.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>  Before inviting Ms Walsh to commence her presentation, I would like to make the following comments.  The continuing inability of people to buy homes in the current climate goes against the trend of our history.  Irish people have always aspired to owning their own homes, but this seems to be no longer possible for the vast majority of people in the generation coming up.  Accordingly, the private rental market is becoming more important and we need to ensure it operates effectively and fairly.  We need to ensure the interests of tenants and landlords are protected and that good quality accommodation is provided at an affordable price.  We also need to ensure landlords are remunerated sufficiently to allow them to maintain their properties to a high standard in the long term.  Given our current economic problems, this presents many challenges and I am interested in hearing Ms Walsh's views on how the interests of both tenants and landlords can be protected.  I invite her to address the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600003#E00300"><p>I provided a submission last week and presume it has been circulated to members.  Rather than read it verbatim, I propose to paraphrase it.  </p><p>  I am grateful for the opportunity to appear before the joint committee in my capacity as chairperson designate of the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  I will begin by outlining my career to date.  I am a solicitor in a firm in Wexford called Ensor O'Connor.  We operate a general practice in Wexford, with offices in Enniscorthy and Wexford.  We are a general legal practitioner service provider and in these challenging times are considered to be a large practice in the south east.  We have approximately 24 staff, with four partners, including me, and a new salaried partner coming on board.  I have been a solicitor for more than 17 years and a partner in Ensor O'Connor since 2002.  My area of expertise covers the District Court.  I am a District Court prosecutor and practitioner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600004#F00200"><p>Where does Ms Walsh get all the time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.52" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600004#F00300"><p>My days in the District Court are very busy and varied.  Much general litigation experience is required, in addition to a high level of understanding of legislation and its interpretation.  It is a matter of presenting cases to the District Court judges and trying to do the very best for my clients.  That is what I have been doing since 2000.  I am one of the main people in the District Court because I am there quite a lot, given the nature of the work I do.</p><p>  Although the Private Residential Tenancies Board might seem like a world apart, it runs in train with the work I do.  The board is a statutory body that was set up in 2004 and has a number of functions.  It registers tenancies and tries to regulate them between landlords and tenants.  It also has a dispute resolution service which is very broadly based on the court system.  It provides advice for the Government on questions of policy or questions the Government might have on the private rental sector.</p><p>  I am chairperson designate and awaiting formal approval.  My role in regard to the Private Residential Tenancies Board is to try to gather as much information as possible and examine the challenges it faces.  I agree with the Vice Chairman that the challenges are numerous and increasing every day.</p><p>  Let me outline the key points of importance in regard to the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  First, the dispute resolution service is broadly based on the court system.  When there is a dispute between a landlord and a tenant, it proceeds to an adjudicator or, I hope, mediation, with which everyone, even those in the court process, agrees.  Mediation is the most important process.  An adjudicator comes next.  The adjudicator makes a decision which is appealable to a tribunal of three who make the ultimate decision.  After that, it is a little like an appeal from the District Court to the Circuit Court.  One is appealing on a point of law to the High Court.</p><p>  The dispute resolution service is important.  It is important in that it affords time to people.  My experience in the District Court is that while people might complain about the decision made, it is important that they are heard and that time is allowed to hear them.  They should have the opportunity to say exactly what they want to say to put all their points across.   They ought to believe they are being heard and that a decision will ultimately be made.  Unfortunately, this means it takes quite a bit of time to get through cases in the dispute resolution service if one is going to try to provide people with that opportunity.</p><p>  Resources are a particular issue for the Private Residential Tenancies Board, particularly in these challenging times.  It has been self-financing for the past year or two.  This is to be welcomed, but it obviously brings its own challenges.  It is a public body and its staff numbers are decreasing every year.  My understanding from reading the literature is that the number of staff dropped from a high of 70, possibly in 2010, to 54.  I understand that under the programme for Government and the Croke Park agreement, the staff number will have to be reduced to 33.  This is certainly reflected across private industry.  I found the Private Residential Tenancies Board's reaction to be positive.  It wishes to comply with Government policy and has made a serious investment in information technology in recent years.  The tenancy-management registration system went online in the middle of last year.  One hopes to see the long-term effects of the information technology being rolled out in the next few years.  One hopes serious investment will in some way redress the balance following the loss of administration staff.  Nowadays, everyone seems to have an online presence, be it through the purchasing of insurance or otherwise.  It is hoped landlords will register online and that the bulk of the dispute resolution service can be offered online.  It is hoped this will reduce waiting times.</p><p>  There have been significant delays associated with the dispute resolution service and there seem to be delays at present.  From what I can gather, there are delays in the region of ten or 11 months.  In the case of an appeal, one is talking about three months.  I understand there is a facility in place to deal with urgent cases much more quickly.  However, the information suggests this means a figure of approximately five months, which is reflected across the board.  I was in the District Court in February looking for a hearing date for a contested criminal case and given a date in October.  All of the sectors that deal with this work are stretched.</p><p>  I hope there is something I can bring from my experience in the District Court and the way in which I see cases being managed in the District Court system to do something to alleviate this problem or reduce the delays somewhat.  It will be a bit of an ask, but it is necessary because, ultimately, the Private Residential Tenancies Board is all about providing a service.  The whole point of establishing the board in 2004 was to provide a more speedy, effective and cheap service than was available on the market at the time.</p><p>  These are the challenges I will be facing.  Mine is a very challenging role.  As the Vice Chairman said, the subject is very topical.  People seem to be renting more and buying less, which puts stress on the service.  Another is the Bill going through, the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2012, which will bring the bulk of the voluntary housing bodies within the remit of the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  However, some of them are excluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00200"><p>I thank Ms Walsh for her opening remarks on this challenging role.  As she is experienced in prosecuting, I would want to be careful about what I say.  Of all the prosecutions mentioned by Ms Walsh, will she address the issue of tenants' anti-social behaviour, and the impact on others of the neighbours from hell?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.55" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00300"><p>It is a real issue for the local authorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00400"><p>Will she outline the proposals she could put in place to deal with that major difficulty?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1101" speakername="Barry Cowen" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00500"><p>I thank Ms Walsh for her presentation, which was forwarded to members last week.  The manner in which Ms Walsh carried out her wide ranging duties in the District Court system is commendable.  It would appear that her skills set is a fit for what is required in this new role.  I wish to signal that I will not be present to hear the answers to my questions, but I will be able to consult the record later.</p><p>  The advancements made in the registrations systems are welcome and the system appears to be running quite smoothly.  The format to achieve a resolution to disputes has been addressed.  The representations that I receive on a regular basis are from landlords and not from tenants.  Landlords express their frustrations at the length of time they must engage in the process and the powers to enforce decisions seem limited, but perhaps I am wrong in that regard.  I hope that Ms Walsh will appear before us following a period of six months in office and then give us her feedback on how legislation might be improved to address the concerns about the resolution of disputes.</p><p>  The voluntary housing sector will be coming under the remit of the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  It has now been confirmed that the registrations costs will not be an issue for those bodies.  Ms Walsh placed the emphasis on the administration of the Private Residential Tenancies Board being cost neutral, which is commendable, but if this results in citizens being let down by virtue of cost, we need to know, and should the necessary improvements cost money, the funds should be sought from Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00600"><p>I will call the spokespersons; Deputy Stanley will be followed by Deputy Catherine Murphy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00700"><p>I thank Ms Walsh for her presentation.  She has extensive experience at District Court level.  The major issue of concern is that the workload of the Private Residential Tenancies Board has mushroomed in recent years, given the explosion in the number of registered private rented tenancies in addition to the 20,000 from the voluntary housing sector.  I can remember a time when only a small percentage of private rented accommodation was registered with the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  Given that the Private Residential Tenancies Board had a staff of 70 in the noughties, but by the end of this year the number will be down to 33, how will that be squared?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.60" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00800"><p>That is so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600005#G00900"><p>I am sure the developments in information technology will be of benefit, but the increase in the caseload will be significant and I wonder how that will be addressed?</p><p>  Deputy Cowen mentioned that he receives representations from landlords, whereas I have some representations from landlords but the overwhelming number would be from tenants.  There are good tenants and good landlords but there are also examples of bad landlords and tenants.  The withholding of deposits is an issue that never seems to be resolved.  We need a more speedy mechanism to deal with such disputes because the person needs to have his or her deposit returned in order to move to other accommodation.  Landlords may terminate a tenancy when they are selling the property, but the tenant needs to have his or her deposit returned to move on.</p><p>  The question of repairs has not been a major issue because the landlord had new housing stock but it is now starting to become an issue because much of the property was not built very well.  The heating system in private rented accommodation can be a major issue.  In general, many who are in private rented accommodation are on low incomes and one would want to be printing money to keep the expensive electric heating on.  Landlords have made little or no attempt to improve the insulation of the building.  Does Ms Walsh see that having a slot meter for electricity is an area that must be addressed?  I see the use of slot meters as a means on occasions of extracting another cash source for the landlord, in other words, the tenant may have had to pay &euro;100 for &euro;50 worth of electricity.</p><p>  The issue of anti-social activity has been raised.  We do not hear about the successful tenancies but only the minority that cause problems.  Anti-social behaviour can cause difficulties for other tenants in the middle of an estate.  We had a situation in which we had to tell a landlord we would picket his house or the shopfront of the agency that had let the property to a heroin dealer as this was the only way we could address the problem.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600006#H00200"><p>Let us hear the response first, and then I shall allow the Deputy to comment further if he so wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600006#H00300"><p>I thank Ms Walsh for her opening remarks and for the information she gave us prior to the meeting today.</p><p>  I shall pick up on the point made about the 33 staff.  Obviously the board is not a private company and there is a mountain of work to be done.  The one thing that the board must have is authority.  People must be confident that if they approach the board their issue can be remedied in a reasonable period.  Mediation is as time-consuming as court action and sometimes more so.</p><p>  I presume that Ms Walsh's role is full-time and I seek confirmation of that.  With regard to the merger of the PRTB and the Rent Tribunal, does she see any conflict?  Has the matter been sorted?  I understand the merger has taken place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600006#H00400"><p>Yes; they were merged administratively on 1 October 2009, but from what I have seen, the new Bill will put it on a formal footing.  I do not believe there should be any conflict.  It is a question of setting rents at the Rent Tribunal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600006#H00500"><p>In my experience, constituents from all sides of the debate, whether they are landlords, tenants or neighbours, will approach me with issues.  Frequently, neighbours will contact me about anti-social behaviour rather than the landlord or tenant.  That is how the problem presents itself in the first place.  I tend to advise my constituents about the PRTB remedy, although I give a health warning that there are long delays of ten months, a year or whatever.  Many of my constituents will decide not to avail of the PRTB option because they cannot put up with the anti-social behaviour for such a long period.  The delay is untenable.  I do not think we can just take account of the length of time it takes at present.  We must factor in the complaints that do not reach the board because of people bypassing it or availing of other options to remedy the matter, which sometimes include court options.  The aim of establishing the PRTB was to avoid court options.  It is important to remember that when considering the staff issue.  One can do so much with IT.  New technology is good for collection and administration but it will not solve the problem.  Very often a human approach is needed, such as mediation, in order to resolve the problem.</p><p>  New housing associations will be included, but they come in every variety because of the way they have been set up.  Their inclusion will not be straightforward.  Complaints by housing associations can differ greatly from those in the private market.  Some housing associations take a firm hands-on approach with their tenants.  A difficulty arises for other associations because the sector has been almost under-regulated.  NAMA will also play a role, as some of its properties will end up being let.  Obviously NAMA is looking at housing associations as a vehicle to administer those and the number that Ms Walsh mentioned could grow rapidly.  It is important that we mark the provision as creating a new demand when considering the voluntary housing associations that will be included.  We do not know how many will be added to the system.  I would prefer if they joined rather than letting houses lie empty.  I would also prefer that we did not have such a high number of people who are wholly dependant on rent supplement, RAS or whatever.</p><p>  With regard to rent assistance, when Threshold conducted an analysis not so long ago, 61% of its clients reported that landlords had sought rent top-ups.  Is that in the PRTB's bailiwick?  Landlords are not supposed to seek top-ups but the research proves that rent assistance is below market rent and people have struggled to get accommodation for that amount.  The findings throw light on another issue.  Very often, when rent assistance is provided we have a body of law to protect people in private rental accommodation.  Obviously, the longer a tenant resides in accommodation the greater his or her rights.  The Department of Social Protection is undermining some of those rights by asking people, within the timeframe of a contract, to negotiate rent downwards.  At the beginning of the year people might be told they can have &euro;800 for a three-bedroom house in a designated place and the tenant must pay a portion of it.  Tenants have rights in terms of not breaking the contract and an expectation that landlords will deal with them in a particular way.  Six months later, the Department of Social Protection may tell a tenant to reduce his or her rent to &euro;700.  That is a serious conflict of interest.  Tenants have tenancy rights which are being breached by the Government.  That is the kind of issue that does not come to the fore.  I am curious as to how the board will handle the matter.  I have witnessed it happen quite a lot.  Will the board be able to comment on rent control in the future?  Can the board provide solutions?  Does Ms Walsh see the PRTB as playing a role in resolving disputes?  A multi-agency approach is the only way to deal with some disputes, particularly in cases of anti-social behaviour.  For example, Deputy Stanley mentioned a case which obviously involved a drug issue.  There may be other issues that will require a multi-agency approach in order to resolve a dispute.  I would like to hear the views of Ms Walsh. </p><p>  Finally, the retention of deposits has led to delays.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00200"><p>Ms Walsh might deal with those questions, of which there are quite a number.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00300"><p>I was not sure whether I should deal with them point by point or by way of summary.  The common thread in the members' questions is that anti-social behaviour is a major issue for people.  It is very easy for me to give the standard response, which is that the Garda has a role in that, but the members said that if one makes a complaint the garda&iacute; will probably say one must contact the PRTB or send one somewhere else.  In fairness, they have extensive powers under the Public Order Acts to deal with criminal damage or the problems we hear about such as people littering gardens and causing foul smells.  I know that anti-social behaviour involves much more than that but it might even be somebody living next door not having the enjoyment of their own property.  If they are creative about it, local authorities can do something about litter pollution, but the Deputy is right in saying that the PRTB has a role in that regard.  The difficulty with anti-social behaviour is that it is across the board.  Local authorities have the same problems in dealing with anti-social behaviour.  The behaviour exhibited can be threatening to people.  It can put them in fear and therefore people may have difficulty in reporting it or saying what they want to say about it.</p><p>  The Deputy is right.  From what I can see in the literature, the PRTB deals with the problem by saying it is primarily the landlord's responsibility to regulate his or her tenancy properly and to ensure that tenancy is operated under the terms of the legislation and the law.  That is fine and dandy if someone has a proactive landlord but, as the Deputy said, if someone has a landlord who does not want to know he or she has a difficulty.</p><p>  There is a facility in the PRTB whereby if the landlord will not do anything about the problem third parties can make an application to the PRTB.  From what I have seen in the past 12 months, there was a very successful outcome in Cork.  The reason it was successful is that a band of residents got together, rather than being a lone voice in the wilderness, and made a complaint to the PRTB.  That complaint was followed up by the PRTB, it was determined through the courts, and the residents received compensation for the failure of the landlord to act.  That is something people should be thinking about also.  There is safety in numbers, but I agree it is an issue.  From what I have seen, the PRTB looks on anti-social behaviour as one of the dispute resolutions that must be fast-tracked, but the Deputy is right in that fast-tracking appears to take about five months.  Five months is a long time for somebody who is suffering from anti-social behaviour.  I agree it is an issue that needs to be examined.  </p><p>  There are common threads in what the Deputies said.  The second concerns the deposit retention issue.  There has been much talk about that.  The Minister commissioned research to be done on it.  A report was commissioned, which I believe was published at the end of the year, and it provides certain solutions to the deposit retention problem.  I understand what the Deputy is saying.  It appears to me from the figures that the bulk of the work of the PRTB - or the residential tenancy board, as it will be called - involves deposit retention issues, but I do not think it has progressed any further than that.  Suggestions have been made for dealing with that, ranging from the Rolls Royce suggestion, which would have a huge amount of Exchequer support, to other systems, but as far as I can see that is still in the mix.</p><p>  The Deputy is right that the workload has mushroomed.  The board is considering outsourcing some of the common services, such as registration of tenancies.  It is outsourcing that to allow it to concentrate on the most important issues.  It is a question of selecting the most important issue and focusing on that.  I understand that is an issue for people.</p><p>  Regarding the point about the Department of Social Protection asking tenants to renegotiate rents, I did not know that, and from what I can see of the rules of the PRTB and the legislation, rents cannot be increased or decreased without notice to the tenant, but if the Department of Social Protection is reducing the amounts, that leaves tenants in a vulnerable position.  </p><p>  Deputy Stanley spoke about repairs.  My understanding is that 80% of the tenancy fees that come in for landlords registering tenancies go to the PRTB, with 20% going to the local authority.  That specifically relates to monitoring and inspecting properties.  My understanding is that that is being done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00500"><p>It is &euro;90 if registration is carried out within a month of the tenancy being created and &euro;180 subsequently.  I believe there are then composite fees if there are a number of tenancies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00600"><p>On the issue of topping up rents, approximately 100,000 households are on local authority housing waiting lists and I would put money on it that for a fair chunk of those, the rent ceiling, which for many categories in my area would be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00700"><p>I will allow the Deputy ask a supplementary question later.  Other people want to contribute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00800"><p>I will just make this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J00900"><p>I ask the Deputy to be brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J01000"><p>People put down on paper that the rent is &euro;120, but I am aware - as is everybody here, because we see it every day - that their rent is actually &euro;130, &euro;140 or &euro;150.  They are paying that differential out of their own pockets, on top of the minimum contribution of up to &euro;50 for a couple.  In many cases they are paying that out of the lowest social welfare payment, namely, supplementary welfare allowance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.77" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J01100"><p>Deputy Murphy referred to my role not being full-time.  I have been asked to become chairperson designate, subject to the formal approval of the PRTB.  It is not a full-time role.  The chairperson is a part-time role.  The directorate that runs the PRTB - Anne Marie Caulfield and her team - are full-time.  My role is more to oversee the PRTB, organise the board and deal with the issues members have highlighted, which are relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J01200"><p>Ms Walsh is very welcome.  It is probably something of an ordeal-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.79" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J01300"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600007#J01400"><p>-----to be on the other end of the process.  I will be specific because when members do not keep to the issues it is difficult to get answers to questions.</p><p>  Ms Walsh has a wide employment history, from repossessions to child protection.  She was quite successful in 2004 in the area of environmental health with the pizza restaurant case.  It is not always easy to win such cases.  She has wide experience in that area and I can understand where her expertise comes in regarding dispute resolution, on which she concentrated a good deal in her contribution, but as the Chairman outlined at the outset, with the changes in Irish society, we are looking at the cost of rental accommodation in the Dublin region doubling over a short period.  Thirty-seven percent of accommodation in Galway is rental accommodation, and therefore this will be a strategic role for the next decade.</p><p>  What is Ms Walsh's experience on other boards?  I do not see that anywhere in the curriculum vitae.  She mentioned in the documentation the importance of her role as chair, but what experience has she had on boards?  Has she had experience of chairing other boards either in the private or the public sector?</p><p>  Ms Walsh's experience is mainly within the courts.  What attracted her to apply for the position in the Private Residential Tenancies Board?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.82" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00200"><p>Is that the case, notwithstanding the fact that determination orders have been made?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00300"><p>Yes.  The money never comes back into the system.  Does Ms Walsh agree, from a strategic perspective, that there is a strong need for a deposit retention scheme administered by her board?</p><p>  Ms Walsh touched on the voluntary housing sector which has had in the last decade a growing involvement in the provision of social housing.  She mentioned a figure of approximately 20,000.  Social housing will probably be financed through the voluntary housing sector during the next decade.  How strategically has Ms Walsh been thinking in that context and what challenges are there in that area?  What is her opinion on whether local authority housing will impact on the work of the board?  She mentioned the element of upcoming legislation governing the voluntary housing sector.  Has she considered how special needs will be addressed in voluntary housing and how current legislative proposals will impact?  She seems to be very good on dispute resolution, but I want to see where she is on the overall picture and the strategy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.84" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00400"><p>The strategy on local authority issues is a matter of policy for the Government.  Local authorities are not part of the picture, which is not to say they will not be.  Strategically, the board is very experienced and has had a long history.  I do not have a great deal of experience as a board member not having sat on a public board.  My work has been in the private sector.  From a strategic point of view, the board has a corporate policy for the period 2011 to 2015 which sets out its strategic work.  The issue of how the voluntary housing scheme is addressed will be a legislative reality in a short period and how we deal with it will be a matter for the directorate under the governance of the board.  It is difficult for me to say anything as chairperson designate.  I would have to be in place, sitting with the board and dealing with the issues to answer the Deputy.  I understand where he is coming from in relation to strategy.  While it will be difficult to bring the voluntary housing agencies within the remit of the PRTB, it will be done.  There are many exclusions in voluntary housing bodies in relation to people with specific care plans or medical needs who will not come within the remit of the PRTB.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00500"><p>Is Ms Walsh referring to Part IV of the legislation?  I am asking about policy because she said in her presentation that the question of policy would be consultative.  I am trying to see from where she is coming rather than asking about forthcoming legislation.  What are her thoughts?  She seems to have significant experience of dispute resolution, but I am trying to see from where she is coming on questions of policy which the PRTB will have to address.  There has been a weakness in recent appointments to the board of people who do not seem to have a great deal of experience of housing matters.  There has been quite a change in the board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.86" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00600"><p>There are three new members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00700"><p>A lot of experience has been lost.  Certainly, the question of policy consultation between the Government and the chairperson is vital.  That is why I am trying to tease out Ms Walsh's views on policy rather than hearing about the forthcoming legislation.  She will be consulted on questions of policy and I want to get a flavour of her views, but she is not giving it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.88" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00800"><p>I am not quite sure what I am being asked about policy and strategy.  Am I being asked what is the role of the PRTB in terms of approved housing bodies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K00900"><p>A lot of discussion has been flagged on the issue of local authority housing being included within the PRTB's remit.  Where does Ms Walsh see that happening?  Has she thought about it strategically?  Has she considered voluntary housing and the issues that will arise in terms of the reduction and management of staff and the deposit retention scheme, which represents 50% of the board's work but does not get good results?  Strategically, has she thought about how she will work on these issues?  I am getting away from dispute resolution where I have no problems.  I am interested in strategic planning.  Many Deputies have a great deal of experience in this area and have given it a great deal of thought.  Does Ms Walsh have that kind of background?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.90" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K01000"><p>The PRTB will give a certain amount of comfort to tenants of approved housing bodies through the strategies that will be imposed.  Many tenants have monthly tenancies.  The responsibilities of landlords and tenants in the voluntary housing sector will be established from a strategic perspective.  The regulation of tenancies and dealings with tenants will be much clearer for approved housing bodies.  The new regime will provide a service for tenants which they perhaps have not had heretofore to make roles and responsibilities efficient and clear.  Is that what the Deputy is interested in?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K01100"><p>Not quite.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K01200"><p>The Deputy can revert.  There are other speakers.  Ms Walsh is the chairperson designate.  There will be an opportunity to question the board on policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K01300"><p>There were no questions for the board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600008#K01400"><p>Ms Walsh is very welcome.  I take a different view on her experience.  She said she had a great deal of experience of dealing with local authority issues on the other side of the fence.  It is very valuable to bring the experience from the other side of the fence to the statutory side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00200"><p>Does the Senator have a question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00300"><p>I have lots of questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00400"><p>I would like the Senator to try to limit them if she can because we are running out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00500"><p>I have only started to speak and some people have gone on forever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00600"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00700"><p>I know that local authority houses are not included in the PRTB's remit but some are below the minimum standard and I have often seen queries about various premises owned by the one landlord.  One might call these repeat offenders.  There is a fine of &euro;4,000 for an offender but one can re-offend.  These landlords are not struck off the list as being unsuitable landlords.  Will Ms Walsh comment on that?</p><p>  The transfer of property is happening in the voluntary housing sector but in the local authority sector staff numbers have dropped as they have across the board.  In many cases the numbers went up when there was no need for them.  IT will help but will not do everything.  Is there a proposal to transfer some of the local authority staff who have so much experience in planning and registration with the PRTB, rather than making them redundant, to the PRTB, if necessary?</p><p>  A common complaint about rental houses is that they are below the minimum standard.  The legislation is being changed to make sure that property being let will meet a basic standard which is a good move.  I do not know if there are figures available for the numbers who stop paying rent.  Landlords are often demonised as ogres but that is not always the case because they often have to put up with anti-social behaviour.  People stop paying rent while the PRTB is dealing with their dispute and seem to get away with that although it is illegal.  The longer the dispute goes on the better it suits the tenant.  Some may bring spurious cases just to stop paying rent for a year.  Statistics are vital and computers make it possible to compile them.  It is vital to have statistics passing between the PRTB and the local authorities to make the system work better.</p><p>  Landlords do have a case to make.  Many of them do not bring complaints because they have an attitude of grin and bear it, get on and do it, and get the property ready and re-let it.  Just because they do not bring cases it should not be assumed that they do not have cases to bring.</p><p>  Deputy Humphreys' questions about establishing board policy and objectives were valid.  One of the main aims of the chairperson of any board is to get the board's priorities and objectives right.  I would like to see Ms Walsh here again when and if she is appointed - one cannot speak in definite terms about someone who is designated - to tell us that she has considered the whole situation from the inside out, having previously looked from the outside in, and outline her policies and objectives.</p><p>  I congratulate the PRTB on being one of the few State bodies that is self-financing.  That is positive.  I look forward to seeing Ms Walsh here again when and if she is appointed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1084" speakername="Luke Flanagan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00800"><p>I thank Ms Walsh for explaining what she plans to do.  The most important thing she has to deal with is deposit retention.  The sooner the PRTB can set up a scheme to deal with that independently the better because, as Deputy Stanley said, if a person moves out of a place and does not get his or her deposit that prevents him or her from moving to another place.  That causes serious problems in people's lives.</p><p>  Where I come from I do not hear many complaints about private landlords.  One reason for that is the availability of so much private rental property.  If a landlord does not treat tenants properly they move out fairly rapidly.  In my experience they tend to get on all right with the private landlords.  The problems I see in my office are brought by county council tenants.  Does Deputy Humphreys know whether it is proposed that the county councils will be brought under the remit of the PRTB at some stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L00900"><p>There are discussions on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L01000"><p> It is a long-term proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1084" speakername="Luke Flanagan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L01100"><p> It is essential for that to happen.  I deal with people whom I would call prisoners, not tenants, of Roscommon County Council.  There seems to be nowhere for them to go when the place is not properly insulated.  One person after another complains of dampness.  They cannot go anywhere and nothing is done about it.  If they want to move out of the house they are told they will not get rent allowance and will not be put back on the council list because they already had a house.  They are regarded as ungrateful.  The sooner the councils come under the PRTB's remit the better.  I hope it happens.  I meet many people in public accommodation whose life is made hell because there is no one they can call to solve this problem.</p><p>  It will be a problem for the PRTB to deal with this on its limited resources.  If it wants to take this problem seriously and move to a situation that someone renting a property here feels as secure as, for example, someone in Germany, the PRTB will need more staff.  I do not approve of a handful of people owning thousands of properties which the rest of us poor cretins have to rent.  I would prefer that people would be facilitated to own their own homes because that is the most secure way to deal with housing.  I wish Ms Walsh the best of luck in her role.  She has a tough job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1070" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600009#L01200"><p> I welcome Ms Walsh to this meeting.  I am sorry that I did not hear her introduction because I was in the D&aacute;il.  I apologise for my absence.  In the context of proposed legislation and amendments to that how does Ms Walsh view the provisions for the PRTB to deal with anti-social behaviour?  I am thinking of the adequacy of sanctions as a deterrent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00200"><p>That issue was dealt with earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1070" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00300"><p>I apologise.  It has been proposed that the voluntary housing sector be taken under the auspices of the PRTB.  I understand that while previously 75 staff were employed in the PRTB, that number has reduced to 33 following the outsourcing of various services.  If the voluntary housing sector is to come within the remit of the PRTB, with what percentage increase in workload, in terms of the number of houses it would scrutinise, might it have to deal?</p><p>  Like Senator Keane and Deputy Kevin Humphreys, I do not understand the reason the PRTB would have to elucidate on the issue of policy.  The PRTB is a quasi-judicial-type body which enforces property rights between landlords and tenants.  Therefore, it has little ability to manoeuvre.  What it is required to do is already set out for it and all it has to do is ensure everything is done in accordance with the legislative requirements in dealing with disputes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.110" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00400"><p>As mentioned by the Chairman, we have discussed the issue of anti-social behaviour.  I agree with much of what Deputy Mulherin had to say.  While the anti-social behaviour issue must be addressed by the PRTB, I am not sure the legislative provisions in this regard are strong enough.  The PRTB needs to send a serious message about anti-social behaviour, including that, in enforcing determination orders, it can take account of anti-social behaviour orders made.</p><p>  On the issue of voluntary housing bodies, the PRTB will have an input in this regard.  However, of all the tenancies likely to be registered, disputes may arise in respect of only a small percentage of them.  One would be hopeful that with outsourcing and information technology, this might be absorbed.  However, I will not be able to determine the position until such time as I have had an opportunity to see how the system works and whether management of loads will be an issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00500"><p>I have a further question on policy.  Because the board knows from the bottom up what-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00600"><p>I must ask the Senator to be brief as we have another delegation waiting outside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00700"><p>Properties let under licence agreement are not covered by the PRTB.  Some people who are unable to meet their mortgage repayments are taking tenants into their homes.  In such cases, the tenant has no right of appeal to the PRTB.  In other words, the owner of the house is the landlord, but because the tenant is brought in under a licence agreement, the PRTB cannot intervene.  I mentioned statistics.  If statistics in this regard were compiled, we, as legislators, could work out how many cases of this type were dealt with by the PRTB.  Could the PRTB undertake this task and provide us with the information?  As stated by Deputy Mulherin, it is our duty to enact legislation.  However, we cannot do so without information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00800"><p>In fairness to Ms Walsh, she is only chairperson designate.  I am sure she will come before us again at a later date, if we so wish.  We should, first, afford her the opportunity to bed in, make the necessary changes and establish policy in this area.</p><p>  There are a number of groups waiting outside and we must vacate this room by 5 p.m.  I thank Ms Walsh for attending and wish her well in her role as chairperson of the PRTB.  I hope this exercise has been as useful for her as it has been for us.  We look forward to meeting her again.  I wish her every success in her new position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.115" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Walsh" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M00900"><p>Thank you, Vice Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01000"><p>Is it agreed that we inform the Minister of our meeting with the chairperson designate?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01100"><p>This is a new process for us.  In this matter the committee is acting as an advisory group.  If we wish to give advice, has this been worked out procedurally?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01200"><p>We can discuss that matter later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01300"><p>I am not speaking about the committee's recommendations.  We had a discussion earlier about previous appointments and are only feeling our way.  This is part of the reform process.  If it is deemed that we act as an advisory group on appointments, what is the formal structure for the committee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01400"><p>The committee will discuss that matter later in private session.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.122" nospeaker="true" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01700">Property Insurance: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600010#M01800"><p>I welcome Mr. &Eacute;amonn Downey, acting president, Irish Claims Consultants Association; Mr. Brendan Dempsey, Society of St. Vincent de Paul; and Mr. Paul Kavanagh and Mr. John O'Donoghue, managing director, Owens McCarthy, claims specialists.  I draw attention to the fact that, by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l </i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the joint committee.  If they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against a person, persons or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p> <p>I advise you that the opening statement and any other documents you have submitted to the committee will be published on the committee's website after this meeting.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p> We have considered the issue of flooding for a number of weeks and have heard much evidence.  This is our penultimate hearing of evidence on this topic and I am interested in hearing the views of the Irish Claims Consultants Association and, separately, the views of the representatives of Owens McCarthy Limited, a claims specialist.  It is apt that we have invited insurance brokers to address us today because they are the people on the ground dealing with the householders who take out home insurance and seek compensation for the damage and inconvenience they suffer when their homes are flooded.  Accordingly, brokers have a clear insight into the difficulties faced by householders and how these difficulties are accommodated or otherwise by insurance companies.  I ask the witnesses to be open and direct in their comments.  We need to consider the issue in its full complexity and take cognisance of all aspects.  I invite Mr. &Eacute;amonn Downey to address the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.125" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. &Eacute;amonn R. Downey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600011#N00200"><p>Gabhaimid bu&iacute;ochas &oacute; chro&iacute; leis an choiste agus leis an Chathaoirleach as an deis a thabhairt don ghr&uacute;pa labhairt inniu.  I thank the Chairman and distinguished members of the committee for meeting us and I also thank the clerks to the committee, Mr. Eugene &Oacute; Cruadhlaoich and Ms Caitr&iacute;ona Dunne, for their professionalism and courtesy in getting us to this stage.  We are amateurs in this forum.</p><p>  My friend Mr. Brendan Dempsey has appeared before the committee previously.  Mr. Dempsey is a stalwart of the Society of Saint Vincent de Paul, SVP, in Cork and when he was in charge locally we read his strong comments to the newspapers regarding the way in which people were being treated by insurance companies.  We subsequently made contact with him and have been working with him and other members of SVP over the last three years.  When I say "we" I refer to my own company, Owens McCarthy Limited, which is a firm of insurance claims specialists, also referred to as public loss assessors, and not to be confused with the insurance loss adjusters who are paid by and represent the interests of insurance companies.</p><p>  Many of the claims specialists in Ireland got together over the last two years to form the Irish Claims Consultants Association with the aim of setting high professional standards for our members, regulating the profession and, in the future, offering formal education and examination.  John O&rsquo;Donoghue is the managing director of Owens McCarthy and was involved with many of the cases in which we were able to assist clients of SVP.  Separately, Mr. Paul Kavanagh, managing director of McCarthy Insurance Group has assisted SVP on related insurance problems and we all now work in the same group with SVP which, I hope, explains why we are here together.  Mr. Kavanagh has real knowledge of the marketplace in terms of obtaining flood cover for homeowners, the attitude of insurance companies and related aspects and will speak after me.  Mr. Dempsey can provide examples of the difficulties being faced by homeowners, many of whom face life challenges not confined to flooding and insurance.  My area is claims handling.  I commenced my training in 1978 and spent 25 as a loss adjuster before I changed sides and began loss assessing in 2003.  </p><p>  I appreciate the role of this committee and its brief but when I watched its meeting with the Irish National Flood Forum I was heartened by the honest comments of both Mr. Dempsey of SVP and Ms Seosaimh&iacute;n N&iacute; Bheaglaoich of the Dodder Flood Group.  No reasonable person could fail to be impressed by the passionate and honest way in which they described their experience of dealing with insurance claims.  I believe I can assist this committee in better understanding homeowners' experiences of insurance claims and the manner in which they are treated by their insurers.  While some of the bad practices are down to a small number of individuals, the remainder tend to follow suit.  I would welcome the opportunity to expand on any of the following points, which arise from the Cork floods in 2012 and from our general experience in these matters.  Insurers have not given a true commitment to fairly advise homeowners when they notify a claim of their right to retain their own representative.  The spirit of the consumer protection code is ignored on a daily basis.  Insurance companies retain part of agreed claims settlements incorrectly and contrary to their practices outside of Ireland.  Many of them are headquartered outside of Ireland and they behave differently abroad.  This is known as "retentions" within the insurance industry.</p><p>  Companies also encourage an adversarial and combative approach in their investigation and handling of claims.  This is deliberate and particularly common where a householder employs his or her own assessor.  The next point I will make is more nuanced now than when it originally arose.  Insurance companies used their builders' price as a measure of indemnity or how much should be paid.  They have the fall back position that their builders are available to carry out repairs for this price.  However, the agreed rates are not representative of the construction market and they give rise to an issue that should concern the committee, namely, builders operating in the black market.  Through a myriad of actions, insurance companies appear to want to foster an atmosphere in which the repairs are carried out by VAT unregistered contractors, hence saving them money.  This is the most pronounced effect of the retentions issue.  They attempt to use builders from panels they have set up, thereby removing the right of choice and attempting to use a scope of works that does not represent the damage caused.  Variants of this scheme include the ridiculous situation of insurers insisting on using unrealistic prices they refer to as agreed rates for repair work.  Sadly for me as a former loss adjuster, they force these practices on loss adjusters, the majority of whom are professional men and women.  The whistleblower legislation cannot be introduced quickly enough for us.  I pray for the emergence of individuals who will reveal the inside stories of what insurance companies do.</p><p>  I cannot get my head around the similarity of certain practices or how some insurance brokers are influenced - I use that word cautiously - not to advise customers of the need for independent advice.  The amount of claims and the amounts of settlement are usually a distance apart.  Members may recall the story Mr. Dempsey told about the small builder who was flooded.  The builder claimed &euro;180,000 and settled for &euro;80,000 because that was the amount he needed and he knew the game.  Insurance companies ask for a premium for a risk, whether on motor insurance or whatever, knowing that they are unlikely to get this sum.  Negotiating over a deal is a practice from time immemorial but when I submit a complete and full claim, perhaps with some trimmings for negotiation, they faint with shock.  They do not suggest fraud because the law of the land is clear on this and they know I would have them in the High Court fairly quickly.  However, they advertise constantly to warn people about fraudulent or exaggerated claims.  Ordinary decent people are made nervous by this type of advertising and many will not submit claims because of the fear of being associated with something that is wrong.  Irish society cannot encourage false or fraudulent behaviour in any part of our lives and this responsibility applies to insurance companies also.</p><p>  I cannot conclude my contribution without commenting on the Central Bank of Ireland, which has direct responsibility for insurance companies.  In our dealings with the bank, both as individual firms of assessors and as a young representative body, we have experienced only courtesy and professionalism.  It has a heavy schedule of responsibilities and it is dealing with large commercial organisations with vast sums of money and vast experience of protecting their position. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.126" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Kavanagh" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600011#N00300"><p>As a broker with over 32 years' experience on the flood plains of west and north County Cork and Cork city, I have built up a strong database of knowledge on the flooding issue and, indeed, was myself flooded in Fermoy over 20 years ago.  The house in question has changed hands a few times over the years but it has been denied flood cover despite the fact that it has not been flooded since that occasion.  It is on the south side of the River Blackwater and the flood defence work currently being carried out by the OPW will not be complete there until 2014.  However, although work is completed on phase one on the north side of the river, its twin house on that side is also being denied flood cover.  This is a major issue.  I appreciate how much the Government is spending via the OPW on flood works in Clonmel, Mallow, Fermoy and, as announced last week, Skibbereen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00200"><p>I thank Mr. Kavanagh for the presentation.  Mr. Downey stated insurance companies want to foster unregistered building contractors.  This is pretty serious.  How widespread is the practice?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.129" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. &Eacute;amonn R. Downey" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00300"><p>Enormously widespread.  It is a first cousin of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00400"><p>Is Mr. Downey talking about the prominent Irish insurers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. &Eacute;amonn R. Downey" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00500"><p>Absolutely.  It is a first cousin of what they are doing.  They do not set out with this deliberate intention.  Our country needs insurance companies and they play a very important role.  The IIF officials whom we met are very professional and it is a pleasure to meet them, but their agenda is different from ours, which is basically a St. Vincent de Paul agenda which has led to other matters.</p><p>  What happens in practice with a traditional household insurance claim in Ireland is that the amount of the loss is agreed after a protracted period.  Consider the case of Ms Seosaimh&iacute;n N&iacute; Bheaglaoich and others, perhaps known by members.  The time element is considerable.  When the damages are agreed &ndash; at &euro;10,000, for example &ndash; one may receive a payment of &euro;6,500 initially, with the balance to be paid when all the work is done and when VAT invoices are produced for it.  This could be one, two or three months later.  At that stage, eight or nine months might have elapsed.</p><p>  My colleague, Mr. John O'Donoghue, will tell members about our experience in other countries, where the practice is known as claims fatigue.  The companies wear one down.  I refer to the first party under the policy, not to a third party in a motor claim; it is the company's own customer.  The company slows down the claim and does not pay one in full, and only does so when the conditions I described are met.  The claimant cannot afford this and becomes fed up of dealing with the company and also his own assessor.  He may say, "Good luck to the lot of you," and take the &euro;6,500, leaving &euro;3,500 with the insurance company.  The claimant, through his valuation, the loss adjuster and the assessor might have agreed on &euro;10,000 as the cost of repair.  The repair is done through the black market, by painting oneself, trying a bit of rewiring or not replacing a carpet for a year, two years or three years.  We heard an amazing story about a cooker that dried out and was reused.  The Society of St. Vincent de Paul had to buy a new one six months afterwards.  What I describe is common practice among insurance companies.  The attitude is reasonably common knowledge.</p><p>  Insurance was always a very honourable profession.  Insurance companies were careful about how they spent their money.  When I began, there was small print but the companies improved.  Society developed and we started to become more realistic.  To achieve more profit, companies have changed their attitude and culture.  The retention practice is not evident in Belfast or Bristol.  If loss adjusters from Belfast are sent from my company, a national company, to a major flood in Galway, the circumstances I describe do not arise.  We have a totally different approach.  We negotiate, but on a professional basis.  This was the way things were done in the past.  Some bright spark has come up with the idea of trying retention in this State and the companies are getting away with it.  This started with a figure of 10%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.132" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John O'Donoghue" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00600"><p>Ten percent and 15%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. &Eacute;amonn R. Downey" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00700"><p>On Friday afternoon, a very respected loss adjuster who does some assessing work told me that he has been asked to retain 40% directly by the insurance company in respect of a major commercial loss.  The companies are chancing their arm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600012#O00800"><p>I welcome the delegates and thank them for attending.  I realise it took some time to travel here.</p><p>  The committee has done considerable work on this matter.  Mr. Kavanagh outlined that engagement between the OPW and IIF only began to take place in January 2013.  This is a direct result of the work this committee has done in highlighting the OPW's work and the lack of communication.  However, it is really talk about talks.  The parties are still trying to talk the same language.  The OPW operates to an international standard applying the figures of 100, 150 and 200.  The IIF is dragging its heels regarding the acceptance of the international standards.  The talks should now be concluded.  We know the international standards and the bill design.  In fairness to the OPW, it is actually very professional.  Where I have seen its work done, it has been to a very high standard.</p><p>  Ms Seosaimh&iacute;n N&iacute; Bheaglaoich was mentioned.  Shortly after the committee meeting she attended, there was a lot of rain.  I was with Ms N&iacute; Bheaglaoich's neighbours on the Friday evening.  They were concerned that there would be more flooding of the kind we saw in the Dublin area.  The Dodder rose to a very high level, as did the Tolka.</p><p>  Sometimes, the first people to react are public representatives and they ask what can be done.  Have the delegates considered outlining the first ten steps one should take after one's home has been flooded?  Most affected people are in a state of panic and have lost their livelihood.  They have lost the pictures.  It is not necessarily the cooker that they are worried about.  Older people, especially, are worried about the photographs and memories.  An older person's husband or wife might have died and they might have lost the keepsakes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600013#P00200"><p>I welcome Mr. Dempsey and the delegation back to the committee for its discussions about this important subject.  The same issues concerning insurance claims in Cork referred to by Senator Clune are arising in Dublin.  South Dublin County Council councillor, William Lavelle, explained to me that he got the council to send a letter to an insurance company explaining how flood relief works had been done in an estate in Lucan yet the insurance company refused to give them cover.  There is no excuse for that.</p><p>  Mr. Downey said that insurance companies are all acting together.  In any language, that sounds like a cartel.  As cartels are outlawed in so many spheres of life, the committee should investigate if this is happening with the insurance industry.  We need to investigate the statistics in this case.  As was said, there is a different insurance regime in Belfast?  Why is that the case?  I accept every company must turn a profit but we need to examine what amount of profit is being turned here.  It was stated one insurance company has a retention policy of 40%.  That is other people's money that this company is holding.  When we have a body of evidence that has been brought to the committee today by the delegations, this committee will need to consider it.</p><p>  Something has to be done.  We cannot leave home owners without insurance.  It would seem the insurance companies are hiding behind the geocoding information.  We have much information we can use to explore what is happening in this problem.  The delegation stated it was looking forward to whistleblower legislation being introduced.  Many other groups are looking forward to it too.</p><p>  Even during these financially straitened times, the OPW and the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, have done tremendous work in flood relief along with the local authorities.  It is recognised that flooding must be tackled.  I have seen much relief work done in my area, Templeogue, on the River Dodder.  While we must do this efficiently, the insurance companies must also match our efforts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600013#P00300"><p>I am not a member of this committee but this topic is of interest to me.  I have been following the committee's hearings on this matter.  I have also written to the insurance federation, the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, and the OPW on the problem.  There was no engagement on the issue until January and I hope it is because of the committee's work.  As Senator Keane said about a letter from a local authority to an insurance company, the direct line of communications on this matter is not very clear as the local authority and the OPW work separately.  Which agency does one go to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600013#P00400"><p>However, in Dublin the OPW and the local authorities work together.  Letters from local authorities outline the standard to which the works were carried out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00200"><p>South Dublin County Council supported it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00300"><p>That is not our experience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00400"><p>It was supported by the OPW because the local authority is the lead authority and the OPW works through it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00500"><p>They should be made to accept those letters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00600"><p>There seem to be different understandings of it.  The two heads need to come together.  If work is being done to alleviate flooding, the insurance companies must respond to that.  Geomapping is obviously not reflective of ground conditions and does not recognise undulating ground or hilly territory.  This is a small country with a few flooding hotspots and heads must be brought together on the issue.  We have all heard similar comments to those made today about individuals who cannot get insurance against flooding despite the fact that works have been carried out and assurances have been given.  I hope the work of this committee will help to produce a definitive statement.  The fact that the issue is getting an airing and that the committee is having these hearings is worthwhile.</p><p>  There have been a number of issues in Cork and we had another in the past week which got a public airing.  If work is being done, it must be communicated to and accepted by the insurance companies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00700"><p>I remind Mr. Downey that this is not solely a Cork and Dublin issue.  I come from the heart of the country, where I believe people suffer even more because they have very little prospect of getting work done and are ignored by everyone.  There is strength in numbers, but rural areas do not have huge numbers affected.  Adding to the problem in the country is the fact that due to the work being done by the OPW on geocoding, areas where some people are living are being categorised as possible flood areas.  Those people may never have had a flooding problem, but now because they are identified as being in a potential flood area, they are finding it extremely difficult to get insurance or any help.  There is nothing they can do about this as they cannot pack their bags and leave.  This is another issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. &Eacute;amonn R. Downey" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00800"><p>I and Mr. Dempsey met the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, Tony Smith from the OPW and members of the Irish national flood forum, under Enda O'Donovan, on Thursday morning in Skibbereen.  We are out of our depth here, but it was heartening to see their level of knowledge on the issue, because that will eventually lead to the problem's being sorted out.  Insurance companies can pick and choose what risks they want to take on.  This is an open market and markets traditionally balance themselves over time.  What we are trying to avoid is disadvantage.  I will ask Mr. Kavanagh to speak about the unavailability of insurance, the reasons insurance is sometimes not available and the solution to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.147" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Kavanagh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q00900"><p>It is all down to the geocoding.  Nearly every insurance company has its own geocoding "machine".  At this stage, I have the geocoding details of the various areas in Cork at the top of my head and if I am given an address in Cork city, west Cork, Clonakilty or Bandon, where I work on the ground, I will know whether there is flood cover available there, because the insurers all follow the same pattern.  The geocoding was designed by engineers.  The first example I saw after the floods of 2009 basically excluded every house between Castletownbere and Youghal.  It excluded the whole Lee-Blackwater valley.  There have been many examples of similar geocoding.</p><p>  The issue of geocoding and insurance must be tackled.  I understand insurers are working on the issue, but they need to work together.  We need a common geocoding practice.  I acknowledge the work done by this committee and the pressure it has put on the IIF to meet the OPW.  This has been fantastic, but we need more of this.   We now need pressure on the issue of geocoding.  We need a standard practice of geocoding.  We need to know that if we have a problem in Clonakilty, Bandon or wherever, we have that problem.  As we explained to the Minister of State with regard to the problem in Skibbereen the other day, the OPW plans to start work there in 2014 and it will take it two years to complete its work, which will take us to 2016.  However, I guarantee this committee that unless we put serious pressure on the IIF companies, we will be unable to get any insurance cover in Skibbereen until 2020.  Today, one cannot get flood cover in towns such as Clonmel, which has been protected from flooding now for two or three years.  Mallow and Fermoy are the same.  People in these areas cannot get flood cover even though the OPW has completed works.  At the moment, we must take every case as we see it on merit.  I read of one man whose property was 50 m above the River Lee, yet his policy was loaded 100%.  When he rang the insurance company, he was told this was on account of flood risk, despite the fact he was in Shanakiel and 50 m above the river.  Stupid decisions are being made with regard to geocoding.  We and other brokers try to support each case, but insurance companies have Fermoy, Clonmel, Blackpool, Blackcastle and other areas listed in their computers as black spots.  That is an easy solution for them, but we need to get around that.  Our estimation of between 40,000 and 50,000 houses affected is not out of the way.  People say we have underestimated the number affected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01000"><p>I have a question about something that came up at other hearings, which was raised by Mr. Dempsey the last time we were here and on which we challenged the federation.  Mr. Dempsey said that in a case in which a person gets a letter in the post saying his insurance is due for renewal, and that person seeks other quotes but is refused insurance by those other firms, if he returns to the firm offering insurance and does not declare he has been refused insurance by other firms, he is not covered.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.149" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Kavanagh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01100"><p>It depends.  I am not sure of the background to this question.  However, it may depend on whether there has been a claim or a flooding incident in an area.  One of the questions on all proposal forms asks whether a person's house is within 100 m of a water source, whether a stream or a river.  If one does not declare that and takes it as read and the house is only 50 m from the water, this amounts to a non-disclosure on the policy and the claim will not be paid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01200"><p>The proposal form also asks that a person who has been refused insurance by another insurance company make that disclosure.  Let us say, as an example, that I have a household insurance policy.  The renewal notice is issued for my house, which is in a flood plain, and I seek other quotes but am refused insurance on the basis that I reside in a flood plain.  If I do not disclose that to my original insurance provider, does that make my insurance policy with that provider null and void?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.151" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Brendan Dempsey" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01300"><p>No.  The householder took on the original contract on the grounds and questions asked on day one and, provided he answered all the questions honestly and disclosed all the relevant information as asked for at that time, he is covered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01400"><p>A lot of household insurance business is conducted over the phone.  The householder gets a quote and accepts it and pays up.  When I took out household insurance initially, I did not fill out a proposal form, but provided information over the phone.  Therefore, I would not have been asked whether I was 50 m from a stream.  That is something that is quite new on insurance forms.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.153" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Kavanagh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01500"><p>That is correct.  I would advise everybody to complete proposal forms.  I am not an advocate of doing the business over the phone or on the Internet, where many assumptions are made.  Websites assume X, Y or Z or assume a house is more than 100 m from a water source and in an area that has never had flood or subsidence issues.  However, as we now know, in both Glanmire and Blackpool we have come across hundreds of people who thought they had cover, having bought it on the Internet, but then discovered they had no cover because they did not answer the question correctly, as the assumption was made otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600014#Q01600"><p>I understand some of that information is personal and covered by the legislation on data protection, but could Mr. Kavanagh provide details on this to the committee?  Could he provide us with examples, without including names and addresses?  This would be helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00200"><p>Is that the Deputy's end of the river?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00300"><p>It is my end.  People in the area see the word "Aviva" when they look up at the stadium-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00400"><p>No commercials.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00500"><p>-----but they cannot get flood cover from the same insurance company that has put up so many big banners in the local area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00600"><p>I will allow Senator Keane to ask a supplementary question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00700"><p>Mr. Downey mentioned that agreed rates are forced on loss adjusters, particularly because of the black market situation.  I would like him to make a recommendation to the joint committee regarding something we could do to flush out the black market.  When builders submit contracts to public bodies, they must have C2 and VAT registration.  Could it be made compulsory for people who apply to do work of this nature to have this kind of registration, perhaps for insurance purposes?  What kind of recommendation does Mr. Downey think he could make?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.162" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. &Eacute;amonn R. Downey" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00800"><p>Although my colleague, Mr. John O'Donoghue, practices as a public loss assessor, he is also a solicitor.  The Senator's question is right up his alley.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.163" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John O'Donoghue" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R00900"><p>We are dealing predominantly with contracts of insurance - contracts between the insurer and the insured.  That sets out the basis of claim settlement in the contract.  Insurers have decided to adopt practices that suit them but not the consumer.  These are outside the scope of the policy.  Mr. Downey spoke about retaining 30% of the agreed claim payment, which is not in the policy.  Traditionally, these policies were policies of indemnity, which meant that those who were insured would receive a payment of money and go off to do whatever they had to do with it.  The insurers would like to have full power over how the property is reinstated.  They have suggested the use of their own builders in some cases.  Many of the policies entitle them to do that.  In the retention cases, they are saying to the policy holders that they will not pay them all of the money.  Instead, a balancing payment will be made to the policy holders after they have funded the difference between what they are initially paid and what they end up being paid.  If a policy holder wants to draw down a balancing payment, he or she will have to submit a VAT invoice from a contractor who is registered for VAT purposes.  VAT is an inherent part of the settlement.</p><p>  I will explain what many policy holders are now doing.  Mr. Downey used the figure of &euro;10,000 as an example.  If a person in such a case has a policy excess of &euro;1,000, his or her net initial settlement would be &euro;6,000.  He or she would be expected to find the difference between &euro;6,000 and &euro;10,000.  He or she would then have to prove to the insurer that he or she has spent &euro;10,000 before the balancing payment of &euro;3,000 could be made.  At the moment, the only thing that is sought is the submission of VAT invoices.  In addition, a reinspection is carried out to ensure all the work has been done.  The question is whether a demand, to the effect that these works be carried out by a contractor who is C2-registered and VAT-registered, should also be included in the policy.  Nothing like that is included in policies at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01000"><p>Does Mr. O'Donoghue think it should be?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.165" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John O'Donoghue" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01100"><p>I would not go that far because it would take a great deal of choice away from the consumer.  That was one of the issues with the reinstatement of properties.  I refer to what happened when insurance companies refused to pay any moneys and demanded that properties be reinstated on their terms by their builders.  A builder might come from Ballybofey to Dublin, or from Derry to Cork, to carry out repairs on behalf of an insurance company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01200"><p>I am just looking for a small way of getting rid of the black market in these circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01300"><p>One could ring the Revenue Commissioners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01400"><p>That is the whistleblower approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John O'Donoghue" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01500"><p>Our feeling, which is based on anecdotal evidence, is that policy holders will use competent and registered contractors when they know they will be compensated properly by their insurers.  If they receive less than a full indemnity at the outset, that encourages them to use unregistered contractors.  That is what Mr. Downey meant when he said it is fostered by insurance companies.  At this point, they must have a decent idea that this is what is happening.  Fewer and fewer people are coming back to claim the retained portion of the agreed settlement.  They are not coming back because they cannot provide the documentary evidence required.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2013041600015#R01600"><p>I thank the members of the committee and the witnesses for their presence here today.  The submission made by the delegation will be of excellent help to us when we reflect further on this matter.  I thank Mr. Downey, Mr. Dempsey, Mr. Kavanagh and Mr. O'Donoghue for attending this meeting.  That brings our consideration of this topic to a conclusion.  At tomorrow morning's meeting, the joint committee will discuss the issue of climate change with Ms Cecilia Kibe Muthoni, who is the co-ordinator of Kenya Climate Justice Women Champions; Mr. Mithika Mwenda, who is the co-ordinator of the Pan African Climate Justice Alliance; and Ms Maanda Ngoitiko of the Pastoral Women's Council of Tanzania.  I will have to improve my pronunciations before tomorrow's meeting.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.172" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.173" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.176" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600002#A00300">National Reform Programme for Ireland 2013: Discussion with Department of the Taoiseach</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600002#A00400"><p>The committee agreed in private session that we will conclude this meeting at 2.50 p.m. because the new Member for Meath East, Helen McEntee, is being welcomed to the Chamber and Members need to be present for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.179" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Callinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600003#B00200"><p>I am an assistant secretary in the Department of the Taoiseach with responsibility for economic, international and Northern Ireland affairs.  I am accompanied by colleagues from a number of Departments which, in turn, reflects the variety of issues covered in respect of our targets under Europe 2020.  They are Mr. John McCarthy, Department of Finance; Mr. Terry Corcoran and Mr. Jim Walsh, Department of Social Protection; Ms Pauline Mulligan, Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation; Mr. Stjohn O'Connor, Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources; Mr. Owen Ryan, Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, and Mr. Brian O'Meara, Department of Education and Skills.</p><p>  On my own behalf and that of my colleagues, I thank the joint committee for its invitation to appear before it and welcome the opportunity to brief it on Ireland's national reform programme update for 2013 which outlines the continuing efforts to achieve our targets under the Europe 2020 strategy.  The national reform programme update for 2013 covers a broad range of policy areas, which explains the size of the delegation.  I wish to refer to the context in which the update has been prepared and provide an overview of the document, including Ireland's five headline targets, with examples of some of the policy initiatives the Government is following to meet the targets set in each area.<br />I understand members may wish to ask questions or comment on the update.  We will be happy to hear the views of the committee on the draft and provide clarification or answer questions.</p><p>  Under the Europe 2020 strategy, each member state is required to prepare a national reform programme and make annual reports on progress.  In addition, the European Commission can make country specific recommendations arising from the process during its annual examination of the programmes and progress reports as part of the European semester process.  Ireland provided a full national reform programme in 2011.  As a party to an EU-IMF programme of financial support, we were not required to submit a new national reform programme or a full progress report either for 2012 or 2013, given the rigorous reporting to which we were already subject under the support programme.  Furthermore, the country-specific recommendation for Ireland under the process is confined to a recommendation that it continue to implement the measures identified in the memorandum of understanding with the European Union and the IMF.  Therefore, the sole requirement requested by the Commission was a letter providing an update on progress in the previous year.  However, we considered it was important to demonstrate our strong engagement with the Europe 2020 process, particularly as Ireland's goal is to exit the programme at the end of this year.  As a result, it was decided to go beyond providing a letter, as happened last year.  The intention is to provide more detailed feedback for the Commission on progress made this year.  As a result, while the document being prepared for submission is not a full national reform programme, it nonetheless provides a comprehensive update on the actions being taken.</p><p>  There is close alignment between the five headline targets under the Europe 2020 strategy which are being advanced through the national reform programme process and Ireland's domestic priorities.  This is reflected in our 2011 national reform programme and the subsequent updates.  The introduction to the update provides an overview of policies being implemented to promote competitiveness, growth and job creation in line with the priorities set by the European Union annual growth survey such as pursuing differentiated, growth friendly fiscal consolidation and promoting growth and competitiveness.</p><p>  The macroeconomic context section, as its stands, only provides the macroeconomic outlook to 2015, pending publication of general Government balance estimates by the CSO, scheduled for release next week.  The national reform programme update is prepared in conjunction with Ireland's stability programme update.  For the first time the stability programme update in 2013 will include economic forecasts for 2016, as well as a broad fiscal strategy for that year and its impact on the debt and deficit.  This will also be reflected in the national reform programme update once the CSO figures are available.</p><p>  Following on from this, the five separate sections, on employment, research and development, climate change, education and poverty, provide details of our progress and the efforts made in achieving each target are set out.  The targets should not be viewed in isolation.  Effective policy implementation requires a cross-departmental approach and there are key linkages between the five targets, mutually reinforced and supported by common policies.  A key driver of this approach has been the Action Plan for Jobs<i></i>strategy which targets all 15 Departments and 46 State agencies.  Its focus is to ensure all efforts are made to improve the overall enterprise environment, boost job creation and retention and bring about economic growth.</p><p>  I wish to comment briefly on each of the five headline targets.  The first is employment, in respect of which the Action Plan for Jobs<i></i>is a central policy response to achieving our employment target.  Ireland's headline employment target for 2020 is to raise the employment rate for men and women aged 20 to 64 years to between 69% and 71%.  The employment rate last year for this cohort was 64%.  That was unchanged from 2011, which suggests stabilisation in the labour market after the constant annual decrease from the 74% figure recorded in 2007.  In addition, the most recent QNHS figures, for the fourth quarter of 2012, which were published at the end of February, also point to stabilisation in the labour market.  The Action Plan for Jobs aims to have 100,000 more people in work by 2016 and a total of at least 2 million people in work by 2020.  Assuming the current 20 to 64 year old population cohort holds constant, attaining the Action Plan for Jobs<i></i>target would have a significant positive impact for Ireland's employment rate 2020 target, reaching 67.6% by 2016 and 70.1% by 2020, almost exactly the mid-point of Ireland's employment rate range of 69% to 71% for 2020.</p><p>  As the national reform programme update states, the Action Plan for Jobs is a multi-annual plan and we are already into our second year of implementation.  The 2013 plan builds on the momentum gained last year and will continue to support job creation.  Among the 333 actions listed in the plan are measures designed to improve access to finance, to help to build competitive advantage and further improve the skills base.  The plan also focuses on seven distinct areas in which we have the potential to make a significant difference to the business environment and capitalise on Ireland's strengths in traditional areas such as ICT and innovation, including the JobsPlus initiative.  The first progress report, covering the first quarter of 2013, will be published shortly.</p><p>  A parallel central plank in achieving the employment target is the Pathways to Work<i></i>initiative. This policy which is designed to complement the Action Plan for Jobs aims to improve labour market activation measures and supports and help to ensure that, as much as possible, new jobs go to people on the live register, particularly focusing on the long-term unemployed.  The strategy includes a new integrated employment and support service involving the transformation of local social welfare offices into a modern one-stop-shop, allowing jobseekers to access their entitlements and receive help in planning their return to work.  Quarterly targets in the roll-out of this strategy have been laid down under the strategy, including moving the long-term unemployed into employment and increasing the exit rate of persons on the live register for two years or more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600004#C00200"><p>I thank Mr. Callinan for the very comprehensive document.  I ask questioners to limit their contributions to two minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600004#C00300"><p>I thank Mr. Callinan for his report.  I assume his team is as enthusiastic about the progress that has been made over the last two years as we are in government.  It must be very satisfying for the witnesses, as a team of men and women who have endured 14 years of economic decline - plummeting to the extent that we needed a bailout and lost our sovereignty - to experience the hope that at the end of the year we will be out of the programme.  We note from the report that there are still many issues to be resolved.  We are on the way there and the grass is certainly growing greener for the nation.  If we can keep on track, we have substantial prospects of prosperity into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600005#D00200"><p>The previous Deputy's contribution has provided many opportunities for me to contribute, but I will leave that for another day because there are some very good people before us.  I will not engage in commenting on the 14 years of misery that was mentioned.</p><p>  I thank the witnesses for their report and the work they do.  It is hugely important in trying to set a framework in which we can work towards achieving the vision set out in Europe 2020.  Have the witnesses done any research about the minimum wage?  I have my own view on it but we regularly get anecdotal information from employers that seems to suggest that if the minimum wage was lower we could employ more of the cohort of people mentioned who are long-term unemployed, have little or no skills and may not have a particular educational attainment.  That suggestion is often offered to us as public representatives across all parties.  I am not making a case for a reduction in the minimum wage but I would like to be in a position to be able to retort on that based on evidence the witnesses have gathered or gleaned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600005#D00300"><p>I thank the witnesses for their comprehensive report.  I thank all the staff of all the Departments for the contribution they are making to try to get us out of a very difficult economic situation.  My question relates to the area of research and development.  We as a country are small in terms of our population and the size of our economy.  Mr. Callinan referred to the average spend of EU member states on research and development.  Given that we are a small country, should we not be aiming to spend a far higher percentage on research and development than the other member states of the EU?  One of attributes we have, which we have been to the forefront in promoting, is our education system.  We have people coming through the education sector, and it is now a question of using those young people and trying to keep them in Ireland.  Are there other things we could do to expand the area of research and development?</p><p>  Another issue I have raised previously is the consideration of Europe as a whole.  There is far more joined-up thinking in the way research and development is done in the US compared to Europe, where member states do not seem to do as much together in this area as they could.  As a result, I understand that approximately 70% of people from outside Europe and America involved in research and development end up going to the United States.  We are not bringing them in from outside Europe.  Should we not be focused on spending far more on research and development than the EU average rather than simply aiming to achieve that average?  That is something we should examine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600005#D00400"><p>I thank Mr. Callinan for his report.  It is often said that governments put in place the conditions to create jobs rather than create jobs themselves.  This document outlines a number of initiatives in this regard, stemming from the budgetary proposals that were enacted and issues related to research and development and education.</p><p>  Unemployment remains too high.  How much do the witnesses consider our high level of unemployment is related to competency issues within the eurozone and the world economy and their impact on spending?  If they consider those issues play a strong part in our level of unemployment, do they believe that these initiatives will particularly target those?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600005#D00500"><p>I thank the members of the panel for their presentation.  I have long been impressed with the five targets set out in EU 2020 and I was wondering when we might get a progress report on them.  It is nice to have this in front of us.</p><p>  I have a number of short questions.  We seem to be doing well in achieving the targets set out in the action plan for jobs.  However, the unemployment figure remains very high.  Some of that relates to structural change.  Ms Pauline Mulligan might answer on this point.  Will she comment on how we are faring in achieving change at a structural level that will translate into jobs?  </p><p>  My next question relates to the Momentum placements.  My experience of this is that they are excellent but they are for people who are more than one year out of work, which is a flaw.  I had reason to meet a group of approximately 90 people recently who begged for these placements, but quite a number of those people were under one year out of work.  A good suggestion was put forward in this respect and it might be considered.  If all the placements are not taken up and it seems that 20% are not filled by people who are out of work for more than a year, could those placements be given to people who have been out of work for under a year?  Will the witnesses comment on that suggestion?  </p><p>  I am concerned about the figure Mr. Callinan gave that one in every 24 of our households are jobless.  That is a damning figure.  Such unemployment permeates every aspect of life, from the child going to school to the teenager to the ethos of the family.  Can the witnesses give us a profile of those families?  Are there specific initiatives being targeted at those families?  How many of those families have been very long-term unemployed?  A profile of them would be useful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600005#D00600"><p>I thank our guests for the outline of the national reform programme.  I will make two or three brief comments.  To what extent has each Department focused directly on how it can contribute to that reform programme?  To what extent have the witnesses liaised with their colleagues throughout Europe to ensure that they and the witnesses are on the same track, approaching the situation in the same direction with the same objectives at the same time, and that no one country or jurisdiction is opting out of certain elements that might be beneficial to the European Union as a whole?</p><p>  To what extent has the full degree of stress testing required been undertaken by each Department with a view to identifying the weaknesses that were there during the good times and putting in place the necessary structures to maximise the opportunities for growth, development and job creation?  I ask that question because it appears that in the past, with regard to the Lisbon Agenda - the previous agenda - we waited until the end of the period covered by it to determine that it had not worked in the way we had thought.  To what extent are the witnesses monitoring the performance of every Department and in turn relating to their colleagues in similar departments throughout Europe to ensure we are all moving in the same direction at the same time and that specific targets are being set and achieved along the way?  To what extent do they review that on an annual basis and adjust their projections accordingly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600005#D00700"><p>I have one question to throw into the mix.  Currently, the country-specific recommendation is that because Ireland is part of the bailout programme we should act in accordance with the agreed programme.  We intend to exit the programme by the end of this year.  Have the witnesses any thoughts or ideas as to what the country-specific recommendations are likely to be in 2014?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.191" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Callinan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00200"><p>I will try to respond to the questions in the order they were asked.  I will hopefully cover all of them in my comments or ask colleagues to respond.  A question was asked about whether there were encouraging signs of investment in the past while and whether we are happy in our work.  Happiness is not a luxury afforded to us but there is no doubt this is a long, slow, gradual process to turn around the economy, build up investment, improve competitiveness and, ultimately, create the employment the country so badly needs.  While we are working on all fronts simultaneously, it will not happen overnight.  There is a slight tension between the encouraging signs from internal investment, such as the examples mentioned, which we are trying to achieve more of, and the process by which this converts to employment and better living conditions for people, which is not instant.  We are encouraged by the signs we are seeing but we will not be happy until we get to the point at which we are back to full employment and improved living standards and conditions for the people of the country.</p><p>  I do not have a specific comment to make on Moody's.  The Minister for Finance has suggested that, in light of recent developments, Moody's might review its rating of Ireland.  It would be encouraging if it did so but it is probably best if I do not comment any further in detail on rating agencies.</p><p>  The minimum wage is part of a broader issue.  What are the various issues that may have some inhibiting factor for people in taking up employment across the economy?  The Action Plan for Jobs 2013 contains a commitment to assess the impact of recent reforms, including sectoral wage setting mechanisms, and to assess whether further action can be taken to improve labour market competitiveness.  Within that, it will be one of the measures examined.</p><p>  Senator Colm Burke referred to research and development and whether we should aim for a higher target.  Very few people would disagree with the principle but, like everything, it is subject to budgetary conditions.  We are looking at a steady upward trajectory and we are keen to see it continue.  I will ask my colleague to make a further comment on this, including the EU and how we are doing relative to the EU.  It is often forgotten when doing comparisons that most, if not all, big-spending research and development countries have a large defence spend.  Much defence expenditure is classified.  I am not suggesting it should be stripped out but parking it to one side puts us in a more favourable light.  With such large expenditure, these countries are in a position to attract the overseas scientists mentioned.  This is not a matter of right or wrong but it is worthwhile reminding ourselves of it from time to time.  I ask Ms Mulligan to comment further on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.192" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Pauline Mulligan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00300"><p>The 2.5% target set in 2011 must be seen in context.  The EU target was set at 3%; we set a target of 2.5% of GNP based on the economic and fiscal situation at the time.  The target was considered challenging but achievable.  We are on track to achieve it towards 2020.  In terms of whether we should go further as soon as we reach the target, we should aim higher in general terms.  In terms of context and in comparison with other EU countries, we are in the second tier of countries in innovation performance in the EU.  The 2012 Innovation Union scoreboard ranked Ireland as one of the innovation followers, alongside countries such as France, the UK and the Netherlands.  This shows a performance close to the EU average, which is a significant achievement.  We must maintain it and we should have more ambition.  We should try to get into the leaders' category.  There is room for improvement.  The range of policy measures in place is about targeting investment and increasing commercialisation and collaboration in the research we are doing.  We have a strategy to improve things.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.193" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Callinan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00400"><p>The next question was from Deputy Kyne in respect of the conditions for employment, the factors affecting it and the broader EU initiative.  The unemployment crisis is so severe that one of the ideas we keep using among ourselves is to leave no stone unturned.  Whether the initiative produces one job or 1,000 jobs, every avenue and angle must be pursued.  There is no instant fix so we must fight on every front.  That applies to domestic measures and to having the optimal international and European conditions.</p><p>  In respect of specific initiatives at EU level, I will ask my colleague from the Department of Finance, Mr. John McCarthy, to speak about confidence building and its impact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.194" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John McCarthy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00500"><p>Confidence is a crucial factor in the current elevated rate of unemployment.  The main channel of its impact is through the very high savings rate.  Last year, the savings rate was 12.25%, with households saving one eighth of their disposable income.  The long-run average is 7% or 8% so there is a precautionary element, with people saving for rainy day purposes.  If confidence was to improve, we would see some fall in that, boosting consumption and domestic demand, which is the most tax or employment-rich component of demand.  An improvement in confidence would feed through into labour market trends.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.195" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Callinan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00600"><p>Senator Healy Eames asked about the targets in the Action Plan for Jobs, the structural change and how we are doing.  This is something we grapple with.  The first pass at measuring delivery of the action plan is whether a measure has been done.  We have typically hit an achievement rate of more than 90%, but that is only a step.  We are trying to put more focus on measuring the consequences, impact and outcomes of the measures and the level of job creation achieved, while bearing in mind my comment earlier that none of these measures produce instant success.  It takes time but it is an increasing topic in terms of our work and monitoring activity.</p><p>  The Senator's comment on the Momentum scheme comes up regularly.  It is a dilemma for us.  There is no doubt long-term unemployment is a major issue for us so there is pressure to do more for the long-term unemployed, to target more places for them and to have schemes designed for them.  Then we hit the problem to which Senator Healy Eames referred, whereby someone who is unemployed asks whether we are telling them they must wait longer.  In terms of the resources available, there is no instant fix to the problem but I take the point and the suggestion made that we should look at unallocated places.  Perhaps Mr. Corcoran, my colleague from the Department of Social Protection, has something to say on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.196" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Terry Corcoran" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00700"><p>The position is as has been described.  I am aware that the project, and a number of others, are the subject of representations to the Minister and the Department.  They are being individually examined.  It is only when it is clear that places cannot be taken up by a sufficient number of people in the area who meet the criteria set down by the Government for the scheme-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00800"><p>The courses are running when they are less full than they should be because not enough people fit the criteria.  These are excellent courses with high demand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.198" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Terry Corcoran" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E00900"><p>The issue is being examined by the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.199" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Callinan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600006#E01000"><p>Senator Healy Eames also reacted to the point about the high proportion of jobless households.  We are starting to examine and have a better understanding of the issue.  While the figure is stark, what gets less attention is that at the height of the boom - going back to 2006 and 2007 - the corresponding figure was 15%.  In many ways, this is a more stark comment on a time when we talked of having close to full employment.  It is a complex issue and a complex area and we need a better understanding of embedded joblessness and what it means.  It is being looked at in some detail.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-04-16a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013041600007#F00200"><p>I thank Mr. Callinan.  The delegates will be aware that national parliaments across Europe are interested in the role we play in the European semester.  It is an evolving role and one on which we have had many discussions over the past couple of months with our colleagues across Europe.  We welcome Mr. Callinan's appearance before the committee today to speak about the programme and look forward to his reappearing before us in the future to speak about future programmes.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>