<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Transport, Tourism and Sport</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 12:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Ruth Coppinger, Senator Mark Daly, Deputy Imelda Munster, Senator Frank Feighan, Deputy Catherine Murphy, Senator John O'Mahony, Deputy Kevin O'Keeffe, Senator Pádraig Ó Céidigh. Deputy Noel Rock, Deputy Robert Troy,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Jonathan O'Brien</p><p>DEPUTY FERGUS O'DOWD IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#B00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#B00200"><p>Before we commence, I remind members to turn off their mobile phones as they interfere with the recording equipment.  I propose we now got into private session.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.6" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 12.39 p.m. and resumed in public session at 1.39 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.7" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#O00100">Governance and Funding of Football Association of Ireland: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#O00200"><p>Before we commence, I again remind members to turn off their mobile phones as they interfere with the recording equipment.</p><p>The purpose of today's meeting is to consider all issues related to governance of, and funding to, the Football Association of Ireland, FAI.  I welcome the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, the Minister of State, Deputy Brendan Griffin, and officials from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport: Mr. Kenneth Spratt, assistant secretary, Mr. Peter Hogan, principal officer, and Ms Betty Griffin, assistant principal officer.  From Sport Ireland, I welcome Mr. John Treacy, chief executive, Mr. Kieran Mulvey, chairman, Ms Mary Dorgan, chair of the audit and risk committee and board member, and Mr. Colm McGinty, director of strategic programmes.<br/><br/>I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  <br/><br/>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/><br/>The Minister, Minister of State and Mr. John Treacy will make opening statements, and after that there will be a period of questions and answers of ten minutes for each member.  I will tell members when nine minutes have elapsed.  I presume because we are taking the Minister, his Department and Sport Ireland together, that members will direct their questions at whomever the appropriate person is.  The interaction will then take place.  I call the Minister to make his opening presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#P00200"><p>I am joined today by the Minister of State, Deputy Brendan Griffin, who will also make an opening statement.  I thank the committee for its tireless work on this matter and for the light it has shone on serious issues within the FAI.  Investigative journalists have also played a commendable role, particularly Mark Tighe, whom I wish to thank.  I apologise to the committee for failing to provide my opening statement in advance as requested.  As I am sure members will appreciate, this has been a very fluid situation, including significant developments as late as this morning, which would have overtaken any script provided earlier.</p> <p>  I regret that there has been a cloud over Irish sport, especially Irish soccer, since 17 March, St. Patrick's Day, when news broke about the loan of &euro;100,000 to the FAI by its then chief executive, John Delaney.  On 19 March, we wrote to Sport Ireland, directing it to engage with the FAI to clarify matters of concern.  Since then, there has been intensive activity between the FAI, Sport Ireland and my Department.  The decision of the board of Sport Ireland to withhold and suspend funding to the FAI was an extraordinary moment for Irish sport.  I do not have to remind the committee of the scale and reach of the FAI.  This is an organisation with more than 200 employees, and an annual turnover of close to &euro;60 million.  It is also an organisation with several thousand clubs, the national governing body, NGB, for the most popular team sport in Ireland by participation rate.  While it may not be among our native sports, soccer is a sport which is at the heart of Irish life and culture.</p> <p>  It would be remiss of me not to mention the importance of due process and natural justice when dealing with these matters.  While members of the committee are unfettered, the response by the officials of my Department, Sport Ireland, the Minister of State, and by me must be considered and appropriate.  Having said that, I watched the FAI's engagement with the committee and I have monitored developments since then.  Last week's appearance and events over the weekend have been very disappointing.  Yesterday's announcement that the former CEO had voluntarily stepped aside pending an "independent" investigation fell far short of expectations.</p><p>While it is the case that due process is hugely important, the committee will not be surprised that I have become increasingly concerned with these developments.  Here we have a clear case of the FAI admitting it failed to abide by the conditions for receipt of State funding.  We had a shambolic appearance by the FAI at this committee last week at which even the most basic questions, for whatever reasons, went unanswered.  Concerns remain around a financial transaction, basic levels of corporate governance, the creation of the new executive vice president role, issues of a substantial nature being considered by the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement and other developments which would suggest that all is far from well.<br/><br/>The Minister of State, Deputy Griffin, and I have made our serious concerns known.  We have impressed upon Sport Ireland the need for root and branch reform of corporate governance.  Over the weekend, I also spoke publicly about the need for strong corporate governance as a precondition for ongoing State funding, including capital works.  As late as last night, we reiterated to Sport Ireland the need for regime change.<br/><br/>As a result of the ongoing pressure, I am pleased to confirm to the committee that in the past few hours, the FAI has written to me, indicating decisive action is being taken.  I will now read the FAI&rsquo;s letter into the record of the meeting:</p><blockquote>Dear Minister,<br /><br />I would like to first of all apologise to you and your colleagues for any embarrassment caused through the association&rsquo;s engagement with the Oireachtas committee in relation to recent controversies.  I can assure you no disrespect was intended by me or the association in relation to our engagement at the committee.  Whilst I am acutely aware that our &ldquo;response&rdquo; to date has caused considerable frustration and has not appeased public demands for action, I have a responsibility to ensure that we act legally and follow due process in relation to both employment matters and our engagement with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement.<br /><br />Since the controversies first arose, the board of the association formed a sub-committee to progress all issues involved and this sub-committee has been working hard to try to ensure all matters are fully investigated and that progress is made.  The need to reform governance structures is recognised and it is intended that we will put in place both structures and processes that meet best practice from both a corporate and sporting body perspective.  We have already taken significant action in this regard.<br /><br />We have commissioned Mazars to undertake an in-depth review of all the matters of concern.  This is a fully independent exercise which will be carried out to the highest professional standards and will be forensic in its approach.  We are pursuing all steps, with legal advice, in relation to ensuring that all matters that arise from this review are actioned as appropriate.<br /><br />The processes that have been put in place are significant and will have far-reaching effect.  They will, of necessity, however, take some time, having due regard to the need for detailed examination and to respect the rights of all individuals who may be involved.<br /><br />In relation to the board structure, we have engaged with Sport Ireland in relation to both the membership of and terms of reference for a new governance group which will, among other issues, bring forward proposals for the restructuring of the board and other governance requirements.<br /><br />We have asked that this group commence work immediately and bring forward recommendations as speedily as possible.  It is our intention that recommendations in relation to restructuring the board will be brought to the membership for their consideration and adoption at our annual general meeting in July (or at an extraordinary general meeting, if the work of the group facilitates an earlier date).  At that point, when a new structure has been put in place, it is the intention that the existing board will step down to allow for a new board to be constituted in the best interests of football.<br /><br />It is our considered view that it is imperative that the board would be allowed to facilitate the management of these processes to conclusion and this will address, in a very real way, all of the concerns that have been raised in recent weeks.  It also provides that this resolution is managed in conformity with UEFA and FIFA statutes regarding governance.<br /><br />In the interest of all players, coaches, volunteers, fans, employees, sponsors and Government stakeholders, we are utterly committed to ensuring that the FAI moves to a position where trust and confidence is restored.  I hope that this letter will provide some assurance in that regard.<br /><br />Yours sincerely,<br /><br />Donal Conway,<br /><br />President [of the FAI]</blockquote><p> I welcome the fact that the Football Association of Ireland is engaging with Sport Ireland in a process and that they have now indicated that the board will step down.  I believe that an emergency general meeting should be called before the July date as soon as the active investigations have been concluded to facilitate a transition to a new board by way of transparent elections.  Given the ever growing lack of public confidence in the FAI, this move is to be welcomed and it is hopefully the first step on the road to rebuilding trust in this important national governing body of sport.</p><p> Considering the issues over which most of this board has presided, and the fact of those issues being obvious even before the various investigations have started, it is clearly time for a regime change.  As regards Government funding, I welcome the swift and decisive action of the board of Sport Ireland to suspend and withhold the funding.  I can add that there will be no further Government funding for the FAI until we see real change and reform in the association's corporate governance and until we have received credible answers.  With regard to future allocations under the sports capital programme and the large scale sport infrastructure fund, I will be closely monitoring developments on corporate governance and the conditions that must be met before Sport Ireland's funding to the association is reinstated.  In this regard, no new capital payments will be made by my Department to the FAI until I am satisfied with the new measures put in place.</p><p> I am pleased that the FAI will work with Mazars to overhaul the association's governance.  It is well known that I have great difficulty with organisations conducting internal reviews and investigations so I welcome the invitation by the FAI to Sport Ireland to input to the terms of reference of the Mazars exercise.  I trust that the FAI will continue to liaise with Sport Ireland throughout this challenging process and in implementing any changes recommended therein.</p><p> As Minister, I have responsibility for a considerable number of appointments to State boards and I am well aware of the importance of appointing individuals with a broad range of skills and experience, especially financial and legal expertise in this context.  The FAI should take meaningful steps to improve the process for the election of its board and implement any recommendations with regard to the appointment of independent directors.</p><p> As we have heard, Irish football includes a broad range of stakeholders extending far beyond the FAI headquarters at the National Sports Campus.  On the new board it would be appropriate to include representatives of the players - male and female - supporters, coaches, volunteers and leagues.</p><p> It has been abundantly clear in recent weeks that there is an immense frustration throughout grassroots soccer in Ireland.  We have seen protests at recent international matches and at League of Ireland fixtures.  Every committee member has received a vast number of letters and emails from volunteers and supporters across the country who are furious with the leadership of the association and the way it has responded to the recent controversy.  Many have highlighted other issues that are important for the future of soccer in Ireland, such as youth development, participation of women and girls as well as the challenges faced by League of Ireland clubs.  It is now time to convene a stakeholders' forum to allow representatives from every level of football in Ireland, including the international teams, the schoolboy leagues, the local community clubs and those playing in the League of Ireland Premier Division, to come together to shape the future for their association and their sport.  This is quite the crisis for the FAI but it is also an opportunity to develop an inclusive vision for the development of soccer in Ireland.  The Minister of State with responsibility for sport, Deputy Griffin, and I will facilitate that long overdue conversation.  I would welcome the committee's observations and any questions committee members have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#R00200"><p>Thank you, Minister.  Before I call the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Brendan Griffin, I think it is appropriate that I would welcome the regime change in the FAI to which you referred in your letter.  It is important.  It is also important that the Minister would hold a stakeholders' forum that is as broad and as representative as possible to ensure what everyone wants, which is the best soccer teams at local, regional, national and international level that we can possibly have.</p><p>That is very positive news.  I invite the Minister of State, Deputy Griffin, to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#S00200"><p>I am a long-standing supporter of Irish soccer and of the teams that have represented our country on the world stage.  The current situation is extraordinary.  There has been friction for a long time in the Football Association of Ireland and many have been critical of the association's leadership.  The League of Ireland has had particular challenges and there have been calls for more investment from the association and more support for clubs and players.  At the same time, great progress has been made in respect of grassroots soccer.  The inclusive nature of Irish soccer is remarkable, with teams and competitions for all regardless of gender, level of ability, ethnicity, socioeconomic background or age.  I have been greatly impressed by the ambition of the FAI to hold international competitions, including next year's UEFA Euro 2020 games at the Aviva Stadium.</p><p>As the Minister said, the questions being asked by members of this committee and Sport Ireland are being asked by soccer supporters throughout the country.  We understand that individuals are entitled to be treated fairly and to due process.  Nobody wishes to see a trial by media of people who have worked hard for their sport over many years.  However, I am incredibly disappointed by the lack of answers from the FAI.  As the members will be aware, those of us elected to D&aacute;il and Seanad &Eacute;ireann have a responsibility to the people of Ireland to ensure that public funds are used wisely and carefully to deliver real outcomes across all programmes.  When discussing an organisation such as the FAI, whose public funding represents a modest proportion of its total income, there are limits to what we can do.  I share the frustration of members of the committee.  Nobody who witnessed last Wednesday's meeting with the representatives of the FAI could feel differently.  </p><p>There is an obligation on the Government to use any levers of influence it has to ensure that the FAI provides Sport Ireland, its members and all supporters of Irish soccer with a full explanation of the circumstances of the 2017 loan and with assurances that failures in oversight and governance have been addressed.  The Department's sports capital programme is one such lever.  The vast majority of capital grants go directly to sports clubs and organisations throughout the country.  There is no suggestion that we would penalise local soccer clubs for issues in their national association.  However, national governing bodies of sport may also apply and the FAI has been directly allocated a total of &euro;130,000 under the programme since 2016.  All payments under the sports capital programme are made retrospectively following receipt of, <i>inter alia</i>, proof of payment of the relevant invoices and a signed certificate of compliance with the terms and conditions of the programme.</p><p>The national sports policy, which we published last July, provided for a large scale sport infrastructure fund, LSSIF, with at least &euro;100 million available over the coming years.  The fund was launched in November 2018 and closes for applications tomorrow.  It is confined to national governing bodies of sport and local authorities, all of which received letters inviting them to make applications.  The new fund has generated great interest and I expect it will take a number of months to have all applications assessed by our officials and recommendations made on allocations.  As the Minister indicated, no new capital payments will be made by our Department to the FAI until we are satisfied that it has given us a full and complete account of the 2017 loan, we have seen the outcome of the governance review, meaningful change has been implemented on the basis of the findings of that review and until all other relevant conditions have been complied with.  The sports capital programmes are a very important resource for the Irish sporting sector and I am sure this will also be true of the new large scale sport infrastructure fund.  In the interests of fairness to all applicants we must insist that the FAI addresses these serious concerns before any payments to that organisation can be considered.</p><p>Finally, I remind the FAI and its board that there are further risks for the association if it fails to address satisfactorily the questions and concerns which have been outlined.  If we conclude after a due process that there are lingering doubts about governance and that appropriate recommendations for improvement are not being implemented, the risks for the FAI would be considerable.  As matters stand, the FAI board has problems and it has time to address them.  I hope it uses that time wisely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#S00300"><p>I will shortly ask Mr. John Treacy, chief executive of Sport Ireland, to make his opening statement.</p><p>The people outside these Houses might not be aware that it has come to our notice that proper books of accounts are not being kept by the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, and that form H4 was filed in the Companies Registration Office yesterday with an effective date of 12 April.  That will inform people watching or listening to these proceedings of exactly what is going on.  I ask Mr. John Treacy to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.18" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#T00200"><p>I thank the Chairman.  I am joined today by my colleagues, Kieran Mulvey, chairman, Mary Dorgan, who is chair of our audit and risk committee, and Colm McGinty, director of strategic programmes.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland appeared before this committee on Wednesday, 3 April, where we gave a comprehensive account of our dealings with the Football Association of Ireland, including our funding to the organisation and the control mechanisms and management arrangements relating to this grant funding.  Today, we will take the opportunity to provide the committee with an update on developments since Sport Ireland last appeared, including the significant decision of the board of Sport Ireland to suspend and withhold funding to the FAI.</p> <p>  Before continuing, I would like to give Sport Ireland's view on the meeting of the committee with representatives of the FAI on Tuesday last.  Sport Ireland had the expectation that the FAI would engage with this committee in an open and transparent manner on all relevant issues and answer the committee's key questions as directly and straightforwardly as possible.  The FAI delegation chose not to answer important questions, which was extremely disappointing.  Nevertheless, through the committee hearing, Sport Ireland learned some information that we did not previously know from correspondence and meetings with the FAI.  This new information gives an insight into the corporate governance practices in operation within the FAI.</p> <p>  We now understand the following.  Not only was Sport Ireland not notified of a material deterioration in the FAI financial position in 2017, it appears that the board of the FAI was similarly not notified.  That such a serious financial situation existed and was not reported to the FAI board is concerning from an internal financial control and general governance perspective.</p> <p>  The events of 2017, as described by the FAI, give rise to serious concerns on the FAI board's application of its governance and oversight role as required under Sport Ireland's terms and conditions of grant approval.  As a State body that invests substantial funds in the FAI, Sport Ireland is also very concerned about the FAI's adherence to appropriate internal financial and management control procedures during this period.</p> <p>  Following the meeting of 3 April of this committee, Sport Ireland again wrote to the president of the FAI on 4 April seeking a response on behalf of the board of the FAI.  A copy of this letter has been provided to the committee.  On the afternoon of Friday, 5 April, I received a call from the president of the FAI seeking a meeting with them that evening.  Sport Ireland agreed and a constructive meeting with the president and two members of the board of the FAI took place at Sport Ireland offices that evening, with Sport Ireland represented by the chairman, myself as the chief executive, and Colm McGinty.</p> <p>  At that meeting, the president of the FAI provided to Sport Ireland a written response to our letter of 4 April.  A copy of this letter has also been provided to the committee.  At the meeting, the contents of the letter were discussed at length and the following actions agreed: the outcome of the Grant Thornton ongoing internal review of the association's book will be provided to Sport Ireland; the terms of reference of the review by Mazars will be provided to Sport Ireland once they are finalised; Sport Ireland will be consulted by Mazars as part of the review process; Mazars' full and final report will be provided to us in a timely manner; the review by consultants Jonathan Hall Associates will be provided to Sport Ireland; and the FAI will discuss the composition of the new governance review group with Sport Ireland.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland issued a formal response to this letter on Thursday, 11 April.  A copy of this letter has been provided to the committee.</p> <p>  As outlined to the committee on 3 April, the Sport Ireland Act confers considerable authority in Sport Ireland.  That is reinforced by our responsibility in investing substantial amounts of public funding into sport.  As a statutory agency, we seek to develop strong sporting organisations and recognise the considerable public interest in a successful Irish sports sector.  That said, we are also mindful of the limits of Sport Ireland's legal powers and we respect the autonomy of the national governing bodies of sport.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland is responsible for the investment of public money in sport and, subsequently, oversight and accountability of this investment.</p><p>All procedures and interactions with the national governing bodies reflect this responsibility.</p><p> At our meeting on Tuesday, 9 April, the board of Sport Ireland unanimously made the decision to suspend and withhold funding to the FAI.  This decision followed a lengthy discussion by the board on the &euro;100,000 loan and related matters.  The suspension and withholding of funding to the NGB is not a decision that the board of Sport Ireland takes lightly.  It is typically an intervention of last resort, and is only ever used very reluctantly.  Sport Ireland is acutely aware that this action causes uncertainty and disruption to the delivery of very important strategic programmes.  However, Sport Ireland is ultimately responsible for the security and accountability of approximately &euro;2.9 million in public funding invested in the FAI.</p><p> In the course of the board&rsquo;s discussion, it was noted that in the FAI&rsquo;s written opening statement submitted to this committee ahead of last week&rsquo;s hearing, the association acknowledged that clause 4.3 of the further reporting section of Sport Ireland&rsquo;s terms and conditions of grant approval was not met.  This relates to 2017, whereby the FAI did not notify Sport Ireland of any material deterioration in its financial position.  Notwithstanding some positive steps taken by the FAI in the preceding days, it has been acknowledged by the association that it was in breach of clause 4.3.  For the committee&rsquo;s reference, clause 4.3 states: "In addition each organisation undertakes to notify Sport Ireland in writing without delay in the event of any material deterioration in its financial position or of any other matter which may jeopardise the organisation&rsquo;s overall financial viability and/or its ability to comply with its commitments in the Approved Submission, and thereafter to provide Sport Ireland with such information and documentation as Sport Ireland may request in connection with the relevant matter and any steps being taken to rectify it."</p><p> In light of this clear acknowledgement, the board of Sport Ireland made the decision to suspend and withhold funding to the FAI in accordance with clause 1.1 of Sport Ireland's terms and conditions of grant approval.  In making this significant decision, the board of Sport Ireland is aware that 50% of the youth field sport funding has been paid to the FAI in 2019.  The next payment to the FAI is due in the third quarter of this year.  The board of Sport Ireland, in its deliberations to suspend and withhold funding outlined above, was of the clear view that this interim period should be used by the FAI to take whatever actions are required to enable Sport Ireland to restore funding.</p><p> On the limited number of occasions in the past when Sport Ireland has had concerns about governance and financial controls and has acted to suspend and withhold funding to a sporting body, I will outline the process followed.  First, an audit of the sporting body&rsquo;s governance and financial control is undertaken.  Second, a liaison process is established with the sporting body to closely monitor, verify and support the NGB's implementation of the audit recommendations to verify compliance with the terms and conditions of grant approval.  Third, the liaison process is overseen by Sport Ireland&rsquo;s audit and risk committee, with periodic updates and recommendations made to the board.  Fourth, grant funding is withheld until sufficient progress has been made on implementing the audit recommendations, and governance and financial control issues have been progressed.  Fifth, once progress is made on implementing the audit recommendations, and assurance is received of the effectiveness of governance and financial controls, staggered payments are generally made to the NGB in question.</p><p> Sport Ireland will follow this established process with the FAI, as it has in the past with other NGBs when similar situations have arisen.  Sport Ireland's audit and risk committee will meet on 18 April and will discuss the specific requirements, from a governance and financial control perspective that will be required of the FAI.  The audit and risk committee is also scheduled to meet again in May and will review FAI progress.  The executive of Sport Ireland, with the oversight of our audit and risk committee and the board, will continue to liaise with and meet with the FAI to progress all important matters.</p><p>The board of Sport Ireland has agreed to review the decision when it is satisfied that the FAI has addressed its current governance and financial issues.  Important steps in that regard include but are not limited to the completion of the Mazars review and adoption of its recommendations by the FAI, as well as the completion of the Grant Thornton review and adoption of corrective actions by the FAI.</p><p> Depending on what emerges from the Mazars and Grant Thornton reviews, we will also consider a full audit of the FAI by Sport Ireland&rsquo;s appointed auditors, as per Sport Ireland&rsquo;s terms and conditions of grant approval.  Last night we agreed with the FAI that a full audit would be carried out.  The scope will be defined by Sport Ireland&rsquo;s audit and risk committee.  It will be set with reference to our satisfaction with the scope and findings of the Mazars review.  In the light of the acknowledgement by the FAI that there was a breach of the terms and conditions, the audit will be as broad and extensive as necessary to satisfy Sport Ireland that the FAI is compliant with our terms and conditions of grant approval, including that its internal financial controls and management, as well as its general governance, are of sufficient standard in order to restore funding.  The specific mechanisms to satisfy Sport Ireland on the effectiveness of the FAI&rsquo;s governance and systems of internal financial control will be proportionate to the significant level of Sport Ireland;s investment in the organisation.  Our specific requirements will be informed by the response of the FAI during the liaison process.</p><p> Sport Ireland is also cognisant of the FAI&rsquo;s engagement with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement in its particular inquiries which we understand are substantial.  We will continue to observe this process closely and with keen interest.</p><p> On the next steps to be taken, Sport Ireland has accepted the FAI&rsquo;s offer of engagement on the composition of its new governance review group, to include a majority of external members, as well as to assist in identifying its external chairperson.  Sport Ireland has identified a potential candidate, Aidan Horan, a director of the Institute of Public Administration.  It has been agreed with the FAI that he will take up the role.  The terms of reference of the group will be agreed with Sport Ireland and finalised by the group once it is established.</p><p> Noting the FAI board&rsquo;s ability to appoint an independent person-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00200"><p>I apologise for interrupting, but does the committee have this information on the external chairperson?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00300"><p>Is this additional information not contained in the opening statement?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.23" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00400"><p>We had a meeting with the FAI last night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00500"><p>We have not been given this information.  This is different from the statement submitted to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00600"><p>It is just that one little piece of information.  We had a meeting with the FAI last night which finished at 7 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00700"><p>With respect for the members, we would like to receive copies of the additional content Mr. Treacy has given.  Will his staff arrange for that to be done?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00800"><p>Yes.</p> <p>  Noting the FAI board&rsquo;s ability to appoint an independent person to the sub-committee which is examining these matters, Sport Ireland will also nominate a person with relevant experience to sit on the committee.</p> <p>  In the light of our role as a development agency, Sport Ireland will also seek to expedite the level of additional governance support, training and assistance which can be provided for all national governing bodies, NGBs.  It will include a chairpersons network to bring together NGB chairpersons for the consideration and discussion of topics of mutual interest, to share ideas and learning, as well as to inform the development of good public governance.  This is in accordance with actions already identified and being progressed in the Government&rsquo;s national sports policy.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland is aware that the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, as well as the Minister of State, will also have additional questions for and requirements to make of the FAI.  Sport Ireland has no role in the sports capital programme beyond what applies to the provision of large-scale national projects on the Sport Ireland Campus.  In that regard, it will liaise with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport before any decision is taken to restore funding to the FAI.</p> <p>  The board of Sport Ireland has agreed to keep the FAI&rsquo;s progress in dealing with all relevant issues under review at each and every board meeting.  Sport Ireland will continue to provide non-financial assistance and guidance for the FAI which may be helpful in advancing matters.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland with representatives of the FAI last night.  An update on the meeting will be given to the committee today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00100"><p>Before I open this to the floor, I want to ask about the additional information Sport Ireland is to give us and which is being copied now.  For clarity, with regard to the pieces that are new, I have just one question.  Is Mr. Treacy saying, on page 5, that there was an agreement last night for a full audit?  His statement says that he would consider it rather than actually do it.  Will he explain that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00200"><p>We have limited powers under our Act in terms of full audit.  We can only follow the money, which is the &euro;5 million, as we explained to the committee at our previous meeting.  It was agreed with the FAI that we would carry out a full audit - a deep dive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00300"><p>Would that be a forensic audit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00400"><p>It will be as extensive as we need it to be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00500"><p>That is not the question I am asking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00600"><p>I will add to that. The piece that became apparent to us yesterday is that the Mazars review will be a full investigation into the issues that have come into the public domain, and that will be forensic in nature, as outlined in the FAI's letter.  We have also said that we will also bear in mind the findings of the Mazars report when we are conducting our own audit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00700"><p>On a point of information, if I am reading it correctly, the FAI is saying that it will have an in-depth review.  I do not see the word "forensic".  We want this to be forensic in its approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00800"><p>It will be forensic, if needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W00900"><p>Surely it is needed.  That is the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01000"><p>The Mazars piece will be forensic in nature, as outlined.  We have said that we will review where that is at and our audit will also be forensic in nature, if we need it to be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01100"><p>However, it will not be forensic initially.  We move to the next round of questions.  I want to make sure members are happy the additional information is being circulated.  I express my concern that we are only getting it now.  We held people to task last week for introducing full statements, and this is additional information that we should have had before this meeting commenced.  I call Deputy Catherine Murphy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01200"><p>I welcome Mr. Treacy.  In the first instance, people who are interested in and love the sport will be both embarrassed by and angry over what has transpired in recent months, but they will probably not be surprised because there has been a problem for a very long time.  Did Mr. Treacy know about the letter to the Companies Registration Office, CRO, or of the submission of the form H4 to the CRO in advance of meeting the FAI last night?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01300"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01400"><p>Does that change the dynamic in that I presume the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement, ODCE, will now get involved and it will itself do an audit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.42" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01500"><p>Yes, it will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01600"><p>That will be as extensive as it is required to be.  Will Sport Ireland engage with the ODCE in this regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01700"><p>Yes, we will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01800"><p>Obviously, there could be very significant penalties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W01900"><p>We will engage with the ODCE if we are required to do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W02000"><p>Does Mr. Treacy have any idea of the timeline associated with that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.48" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W02100"><p>We only read about it this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W02200"><p>Obviously, that could end up in the criminal code.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W02300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#W02400"><p>Once it gets into that area, we are precluded, but we have been notified about it at this stage.  The very fact there is Government funding allocated to an organisation like the FAI gives it legitimacy across the board and, in fact, it could have a bearing on other income streams as a consequence.  This is very important in terms of not doing more damage than needs to be done.  Mr. Treacy might come back to us and let us know exactly what the timeline is, how the ODCE will get involved, how that will play out, and how it can be managed.</p><p>Where Sport Ireland has outlined the conditions for the restoration of future funding, that changes that quite considerably. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00200"><p>It does, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00300"><p>Does Sport Ireland need more powers, as a consequence of this matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.55" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00400"><p>We said the last time when we were in here that we did not want to be a regulatory body.  We are a development agency and if that dynamic changes then things will change.  In terms of the power of audit, we follow the money to save money.  For larger organisations, our funding is &euro;3 million out of a budget of &euro;50 million.   We are limited by that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00500"><p>We might need to consider that matter again when the dust has settled on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.57" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00700"><p>I hope that will not be so far into the future that huge long-term damage will be done.  There was a previous experience with the Olympic Council of Ireland, OCI, and money was withheld.  How long did it take for the money to be restored?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.59" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00800"><p>It took the best part of nine months for the OCI to put corporate structures in place.  Sometimes it takes a long time to put all of the structures in place.  The FAI is not at that stage yet and must hold an annual general meeting, AGM.  The OCI held an AGM fairly quickly and had new board members in place.  The OCI is a good model in terms of what needs to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X00900"><p>I have reminded myself of some of the main findings of the Moran report on the debacle.  The report stated, about Pat Hickey, that:</p><blockquote>&quot;his style of leadership was characterised by strong personal control over decision making ... it was an autocratic style of leadership ... there was an over-dependence on the power of one individual ... The Inquiry had a concern at a possible absence of control in the operation of O.C.I. bank accounts.&quot;</blockquote> <p>The situation has completely turned around since.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01100"><p>One of the findings was that best accountancy practices were not followed.  Is there a correlation between the two organisations from what the witnesses have seen so far?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.63" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01200"><p>The organisations are very similar with a strong personality leading the organisation.  This is probably one of the issues that we have discussed with the FAI in recent times, and I did say it at a meeting a couple of weeks ago that there is an impression out there that the FAI board was following as opposed to leading the organisation, and that was fairly clear.  That type of regime needs to be reversed.  The board leads any organisation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01300"><p>I thank Mr. Treacy.  I addressed this issue with the Minister two years ago; ironically, it was in 2017.  I stated that the Genesis report, as it was then, 13 years ago sought two independent directors of the board, which could have made a sizeable difference.  The Minister agreed with me but it appears nothing was done about it.  Does he regret that at this stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01400"><p>Yes.  It would have been far better if something had been done about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01500"><p>You were the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01600"><p>Yes, that is absolutely right.  It would have been far better if something had been done about it, of course it would, and if there had been independent members put on the board.  The Deputy should not exaggerate my powers as Minister.  With the FAI, I do not have control over the board and I do not make appointments to the board.  We contribute 5% in grants.  What we have done is make representations to the FAI when it made its changes, in accordance with corporate governance, earlier this year to indicate that we were not totally satisfied with what was happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#X01700"><p>The real leverage is the money.  We can see that the dynamic changed when the money was withheld.  A sizeable grant was allocated and quite a debate took place between the Department, Sport Ireland and the FAI; I do not begrudge a penny of it as it was totally needed for women's football.  There was an opportunity for leverage there to insist on that change.  Does the Minister regret that he did not do so?  He has said that he does not have much power.  However, we can see there is great power when money is withheld.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Y00100"><p>We were constantly making it clear what we thought and what our view was of corporate governance, particularly regarding independence, women and the fact that the longevity of the people on the board was something that worried us.  In retrospect we regret a lot of things that happened.  That particular payment to which Deputy Catherine Murphy referred was a payment of &euro;195,000, which was made because of the appalling conditions in which women in sport had to suffer, particularly on the international scene and we are all familiar with that.  We gave a direction to Sport Ireland to produce that money after representation was made to us, because it was a very urgent case that was very well publicised and women needed that money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Y00200"><p>The Department could have done more, by insisting on a governance change, the very change that was sought in the Genesis report regarding the independence of members on the board.  We got a document from the Department on 10 April 2019, telling us of changes that were likely to happen that would have pushed out changes on the board to 2022 and 2024.  That was very tame, moving at the speed of an iceberg.  The board member who is the chairperson of a standing committee or national league executive committee and who has served more than ten years on the board may be re-elected for up to four years.  Every one of them would have fulfilled that criteria.  This problem did not happen on 17 March.  There was a very good piece of journalism by Mark Tighe that opened up a window on this, but this has been a problem way before that.  The Department for Transport, Tourism and Sport needs to learn a very big lesson about money and power and making changes where something like this appears.  I am disappointed that we have come to this point.  Some of the fallout could have been avoided if members of the board with the necessary independence had been in place.</p> <p>  I will now refer to the Jonathan Hall report.  There is a relationship between what has happened in FAI and what was said about the importance of the then president of the Olympic Council of Ireland Pat Hickey to the OCI and how it was vital to have this person on the OCI.  The Olympic Council of Ireland has been transformed.  There is an idea that one person is absolutely central to the organisation.  It seems to me that the Jonathan Hall report, which I am sure the Minister has read at this report, was written with one thing in mind, namely to deliver a situation where John Delaney could stay as a member of the UEFA Board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Y00300"><p>The Deputy's time is up.  We will get the answer to her question, but there will be a second round.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1226" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Y00400"><p>Does Mr. Treacy think that is a fair comparison?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.73" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Y00500"><p>We were not consulted on the Jonathan Hall report.  We read about it in the newspaper like everybody else.  I think it is a fair comparison.  Nobody is indispensable and sometimes an organisation needs to move on and put new people in place to drive it forward.  That has been our experience with the renamed Olympic Federation of Ireland, OFI, which is a totally different type of organisation from the then OCI and is now leading from the front.  Last week we did an event with OFI where they had the Japanese over to sign an agreement on where the Team Ireland Tokyo training camp is going to be; the ticketing agency was announced where the priority will be to ensure that parents and family members have their tickets; and, the team management was put in place with the OFI which will comprise Sport Ireland Institute people and the Olympic Federation of Ireland people.  The Olympic Federation of Ireland has totally and utterly transformed itself in a very short period and is led by people who know corporate governance extremely well.  They know what is good, what is right and that is what they are putting in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00200"><p>To add to what Deputy Catherine Murphy said, I do not believe that any sporting organisation should be a personal fiefdom.  Based on what we see and what we know, does the Minister, Deputy Ross, have an understanding as to whether the FAI has accepted Mr. Delaney's offer to step aside?  The FAI's statements on this matter have caused some confusion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00300"><p>I have had no indication of that at all.  I am not privy to what happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00400"><p>Given that he met with the FAI yesterday evening, does Mr. Treacy know the situation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.77" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00500"><p>I do not really know what is going on.  I gather that Mr. Delaney has stepped aside on a voluntary basis and is still on the payroll while the investigation by Mazars continues.  That is as much as I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00600"><p>To clarify, Mr. Delaney's offer to step aside has been accepted by the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.79" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00700"><p>I understand that to be the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00800"><p>We have received many statements, some of which contradict others.  This one was particularly unclear, and as far as I was aware the media were refused answers on that questions last night.  I just want to put that on the record.</p> <p>  The statement of the Minister, Deputy Ross, and the letter from the FAI both say that the board of the FAI is stepping down.  Is this a part of the normal course of events, as in the members will step down and potentially seek re-election?  Is it the Minister's understanding that they will not seek re-election?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z00900"><p>I received this letter late this morning, and I have not communicated with anybody about it yet.  It came as a surprise to me.  The contents of the letter are the contents of the letter.  I cannot expand on it.  My reading of the letter is that the entire board will step down.  I cannot shed any light on whether they will offer themselves for re-election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01000"><p>It is interesting that in the written version of the Minister's opening statement there are inverted commas around the word "independent" when it is used in the context of the reviews being undertaken.  Why is that?  Does the Minister not believe they were truly independent reviews?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01100"><p>The investigation was called an independent investigation by those who set it up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01200"><p>Nothing else appears in inverted commas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01300"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01400"><p>The word "review" is not in inverted commas, only the word "independent".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01500"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01600"><p>Is it the Minister's view that this was a truly independent review within the terms of reference set by the association under investigation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01700"><p>I do not know at this stage whether it is an independent review or not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01800"><p>The Minister cannot say why that word was in inverted commas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z01900"><p>It is simply there because it is a quotation of what was said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z02000"><p>The other words are not treated as such, but we will park that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.93" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z02100"><p>I might be able to add more to this.  I apologise for the delay in getting the name but we were working on this overnight.  We will provide the name of the nominated independent chairperson of the corporate review to the Deputies.  Yesterday our delegation had an opportunity to look, on a confidential basis, at the Mazars proposal, the terms of reference of which are going to the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement for approval.  What I saw and read suggests that there will be an extensive investigation which will have senior counsel attached to it.  The terms of reference have to be agreed with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement because they relate to matters under company law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z02200"><p>Could the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement carry out the investigation instead of Mazars?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.95" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z02300"><p>I do not know.  I presume there is a conversation going on between both parties as to whether it would be normal.  I know that the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement usually appoints its own inspectors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z02400"><p>Mazars was appointed by the existing board.  I am not casting any doubts on the company, but it does not seem to me to be totally transparent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#Z02500"><p>How did those reviews interact exactly?  Will the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement conduct a separate parallel inquiry or will it now dovetail with the Mazars inquiry?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.98" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00100"><p>I can understand everyone's confusion because we are trying to get over some of this confusion also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00200"><p>Of course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00300"><p>As we understand it, with regard to Mazars, the phrase "investigation" is within the terms of reference that are currently being discussed with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement.  That will also have senior counsel.  That is over a wide range of issues, largely relating to financial issues within the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, that have come to our attention in recent days, including as late as last Sunday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00400"><p>I am sorry to cut across Mr. Mulvey, but will that include issues such as those raised in Mark Tighe's report in <i>The Sunday Times</i>?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.102" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00500"><p>Yes, from my understanding of what I have read.  I had a cursory read of it.  I did not have possession of the document.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00600"><p>Would it include board expenses?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.104" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00700"><p>Those issues will be covered and are listed in the document to be covered.  I went through it.  I was trying to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00800"><p>And aspects such as third party payments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.106" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA00900"><p>-----go through it in the limited time I had, as forensically and as best I could.  All of those are certainly listed for investigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01000"><p>Can I clarify that Mr. Treacy knows the third party payments would be included?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.108" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01100"><p>My understanding is that, yes, they will be included.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01200"><p>All third party payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01300"><p>Okay.  That a form H4 is being filed is obviously a significant and serious development.  Only two other such forms have been filed with the Companies Registration Office in the past 12 months.  This is a matter of great gravity.  Has any organisation that is a recipient of grant funding from Sport Ireland had a form H4 filed against it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.111" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01400"><p>Not that we are aware of.  I never heard of it before.  We are hearing about this for the first time.  We heard about it this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01500"><p>It is a significant development in and of itself.  Perhaps we will get into that later on.  We will not get too deep into company law bearing in mind that I only have one minute remaining.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01600"><p>No, you have not.  The Deputy is actually two minutes over believe it or not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01700"><p>Can I close on one "yes" or "no" question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01800"><p>I will give the Deputy some latitude because I had asked a question also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA01900"><p>I appreciate that.  Based on what he has heard and based on what the Chairman has said, is it the Minister, Deputy Ross's personal and ministerial opinion that there is a need for a full forensic audit of the FAI?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA02000"><p>I would say there is a very good case for it and I would not oppose it in any way if it was thought to be necessary.  There is no reason that should not take place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1304" speakername="Noel Rock" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA02100"><p>So that is  a "Yes".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#AA02200"><p>I have a question for the Minister and for Mr. John Treacy from Sport Ireland.  At the committee last week the FAI said that it wanted to regain trust and proper governance.  Everything it has done, however, since these matters became public knowledge is evidence to demonstrate that it is actually doing the opposite to regain trust.  I will not go into last week's meeting: everyone has already commented enough on that.  Even at last night's meeting with Mr. Treacy and Mr. Mulvey the FAI did not refer to the H4 form being filed.  From the letter I can see that the complaint was filed on 12 April, which was last Friday.  In an answer to a question by me about the Mazars' report last Wednesday they said that it was for the FAI eyes only and it would not be published.  Now, thankfully, Sport Ireland has got assurances in its meeting with the FAI that the report will be published.  My point is that the FAI is being brought kicking and screaming to this, and it is ongoing to the present time.  I would like comment from Mr. Mulvey and Mr. Treacy on that, especially in relation to the restoration of funds.  With everyone the committee has met we are aware there are many innocent parties on the front line who are suffering and who will continue to suffer, but there is no way that funding can be restored in a timely fashion with all that is going on such as the board stepping down and all of the audits that will be required as a result of the H4.  I believe that August was mentioned as the time for the second 50% of funding.  The witnesses also referred to Sport Ireland's own audit of the FAI.  Has it been decided yet who will do that audit and will it be publicly available when it is done?  What is the scope of that audit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00100"><p>We went to tender for our audit a few weeks ago and we had no takers.  We will now be out looking for auditors to do the work.  We agreed last night with the FAI that the audit will be as extensive as we want it to be, which is definitely a step in the right direction.  It was one indication to me that some members of the FAI are trying to do the right thing.  It was good to know that the FAI is willing to let us have an extensive audit.  We will be doing this as quickly as we can.  The Mazars' work, however, needs to start and get going.  That is an investigation we will need to bear in mind when we are doing our piece of work but we would like to be seen to get this going, probably in May at some stage.  There is a degree of urgency.  The Senator is correct that all of these things take time.  The nature of the Mazars' work, and what we saw last night in the terms of reference, is very extensive.  They were talking about an interim report at six to eight weeks and then a more extensive report.  It will be quite a while.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00200"><p>In reality will no restoration of funds happen in the next year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.122" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00300"><p>There is a lot of work to be done over the next three to six months and over the course of the next year.  There are a number of steps that can be taken by an FAI board to advance the corporate governance structure.  Sport Ireland will get its audit of the FAI done.  All of the indications down through the years from the FAI's auditors were that taxpayers' money was expended for the purposes for which it was given.  We have that letter for every year from their auditors.  Sport Ireland will be doing all of that piece of work.</p> <p>  If there are some assurances - and it is a big "if" - we have a mechanism where we can fund on a monthly basis and account for the money that would be going for a specific position.  That is an issue for when all the various bits and pieces have been done, when there is advancement with regard to the corporate governance and when Sport Ireland has an audit completed.  We are aware that the work of the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement and Mazars will take some time but we will begin to get a flavour.  If there is an AGM of the organisation and a new board in place all of these factors play into possibly being in a position where one might be able to make a decision.  If, however, we are not ready to make a decision then we will not make a decision.  That is the key point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00400"><p>Who will carry out the audit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.124" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00500"><p>We have not yet identified an auditor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00600"><p>Okay.  The Minister, Deputy Ross, clarified at the weekend that the large infrastructural funds could not be allocated until everything is in order.  How does that stand now with all of this going on?  When had the Minister intended to make announcements on the large-scale structural funds?  Does this mean that there will be a total delay on announcements for all sporting organisations, even those that have proper governance?  Based on this there is absolutely no way it will all be cleared in the next year.  Are properly governed organisations going to be put at risk for large infrastructural developments as a result of this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#BB00700"><p>Let me answer the first question first.  Applications for the large-scale infrastructure funds close tomorrow.  That will be a six month process.  It will be a long and very thorough process, obviously, as there is a lot of money involved.  I certainly hope that the corporate governance reforms in the FAI will be adequate at that stage to enable us to look at it as we would have done with any other body that is in good stead.  If it is not then we will report back to the committee and let the members know about it.</p><p>That is what we anticipate being the case.  All those applications will be considered on their merit, including the FAI.  If it got its corporate governance in order by that stage, it would be fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00200"><p>The point I am making is that, based on what we have heard, that will not be possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00300"><p>I have to be fair to everyone.  If the Minister wants to respond, that is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00400"><p>I think it will be possible.  There is a great difference between applications and the drawdown and payment of grants.  They can make applications and no doubt the applications will be in tomorrow.  The crucial period will be when the drawdown happens.  I would not discourage them from making applications.  The issue arises when the drawdown comes, which will be later.  I anticipate that if it takes the necessary urgent measures, it will not be penalised in any way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00500"><p>I thank the Chairman for his indulgence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00600"><p>I want to be fair to everybody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00700"><p>I know, but I-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00800"><p>I want to make sure that everybody gets a chance.  The Senator is eight minutes into his five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC00900"><p>I will clarify this because I do not want there to be ambiguity about it.  There will be applications tomorrow, then there will be allocations, and then drawdown.  It is a three stage process.  I do not anticipate that by the time it comes to drawdown, there will the sort of problems that the Senator anticipates.  I think there would be a problem if a decision was made tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC01000"><p>To be helpful, the Senator has used eight of ten minutes rather than eight of five.  If he wants to talk for another two minutes, that will mean he has completed his ten minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC01100"><p>Could some of these infrastructural projects for the FAI be allocated funding, provided that its governance is in order?  Is that what the Minister is saying?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC01200"><p>It can be allocated.  It will not get any funding whatsoever if it is not in good standing.  There will be no drawdown.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC01300"><p>I think there is a precedent where the Olympic Council of Ireland got funding, notwithstanding the problems, when it proved to the Department that it had made certain changes on leadership and other issues.  It is not a sacrosanct "No" but a definite "Yes" if the changes are made.  It is important that people across the country need not fear this and that if the changes happen, the witnesses can change the way they do business, even though they want it in black and white and for the people to be changed.</p> <p>  Many of these issues revolve around the existing body which will retire at a particular time.  How does Mr. Treacy know that all the documents he will seek are secure?  How does he invigilate that?  Nobody has yet been appointed to do that.  Significant trust has been placed by the system in an organisation about which we have substantial queries.  A chief executive is to be appointed.  Is that by this board or the new board?  There is a drift in management and accountability.  It is not a case of simply asking the board if it agrees with doing this.  The witnesses need to be more determined and there must be certainty about all the information being available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.140" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC01400"><p>There is an interim chief executive in place, with whom we are currently dealing.  There are 200 staff in the FAI so there are people to deal with.  We met board members twice.  I know some of the board members I met last night want to do the right thing.  They want to be transparent.  That is what I am seeing and being told.  As I said to the Minister, they will step aside or step down when the time comes.  They are determined to bring about this reform and take something to an annual general meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#CC01500"><p>I am making a different point.  It is a question of the security of all the data and information that is being managed by people other than the State or Sport Ireland.  What further steps could Sport Ireland take?</p><p>I do not know company law but a company can often put someone in place to ensure that the process is transparent.  I know Mr. Treacy is getting reassurances and that some of people want to do the right thing but the evidence we have here is quite the opposite to last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00200"><p>We had not thought about that point.  This is a due diligence exercise related to a number of issues including financial controls and corporate governance and responsibility; one could probably engage in creating a data room for the repository of necessary documentation, and we will take this up with the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00300"><p>Also a data controller, protocols and procedures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.145" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00400"><p>Normally, in due diligence under the Companies Act, a repository called a data room is created for the information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00500"><p>Part of Grant Thornton's work was to secure all the documentation.  Grant Thornton undertook to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00600"><p>It was appointed by the FAI.  I do not doubt its professionalism but the evidence provided to it.  I call Deputy Troy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00700"><p>Mr. Treacy said the board wants to be seen to be transparent and that it has said so in meetings.  Its actions signal the contrary.  It has been totally evasive with this committee-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.149" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00800"><p>I agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD00900"><p>-----and with Sport Ireland.  It is not helping itself by any stretch of the imagination.  The Minister, Deputy Ross, said that he would not be opposed to a forensic investigation.  He is the Minister.  Sport Ireland reports to him.  If he feels a forensic investigation is warranted, surely he can request it?  Does the Minister believe a forensic investigation is warranted into the affairs of the FAI?  It is a yes or no question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01000"><p>I will leave that matter to Sport Ireland.  If it advises me that it is necessary, I would totally approve of it.  I have no objection.  I think the most thorough, necessary-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01100"><p>I asked for a yes or no.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01200"><p>Yes.  I am happy for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01300"><p>The Minister stated:</p><blockquote>Yesterday's announcement that the former CEO had voluntarily stepped aside pending an &quot;independent&quot; investigation fell far short of expectations.</blockquote> <p>When asked by Deputy Rock why &quot;independent&quot; was in inverted commas and whether he felt that it was independent, the Minister said that he did not know whether it was or not.  Has the Minister confidence that the investigation will be fully independent?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01400"><p>I do not know the answer to that question because I do not know what the construction of that particular inquiry is.  I do not know the terms of reference at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01500"><p>What will the Minister do to ensure that the investigation is independent?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01600"><p>That is a matter which I will leave to Sport Ireland because it is communicating on my behalf with the FAI and is doing an extraordinarily effective job of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01700"><p>The Minister said that he constantly made known that he was not happy with the board of the FAI <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>the lack of independence, the term limits and the length of service of certain board members.  He constantly made it known.  How did he constantly make it known considering that, following the extraordinary general meeting, EGM, in February this year, his Department and Minister of State approved the exemptions to existing term limits for certain board members?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01800"><p>I will expand on that for the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD01900"><p>I ask the Minister to be tight with his answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD02000"><p>When I became aware of the EGM and what the FAI was doing to comply with the code with which it has agreed to apply, I asked Mr. Kenneth Spratt, who will probably elaborate on this, to get in touch with them and express my personal unease with what it was doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#DD02100"><p>With due respect to Mr. Spratt, I understand that the exemption needed the Minister's approval.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00100"><p>They did not need my approval at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00200"><p>I read a press statement.  The reason approval was given was to ensure continuity and the Minister did not wish to see a brain drain from the organisation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00300"><p>That is not the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00400"><p>We will come back to the issue later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00500"><p>It is not the case, Deputy, so let us get it right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00600"><p>I can come back to the matter later as I have the statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00700"><p>The organisation does not need my approval at all.  What I can do is express my concern if it is not complying with what I think it should comply with.  The organisation does not need my approval for that at all.  The leverage I have is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00800"><p>Was there no approval requirement for the exemption in term limits that was adopted at the AGM in February of this year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE00900"><p>None at all.  Absolutely none at all, Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01000"><p>Okay.  I want to discuss the suspension of funding by Sport Ireland.  When Sport Ireland was here almost a fortnight ago there was a resistance to taking this course of action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.173" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01100"><p>We were involved in a process.  All of those issues are a matter for the board.  The first opportunity we had at the board to discuss it was in April so we made that decision very quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01200"><p>There was a resistance I would say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.175" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01300"><p>No, Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01400"><p>It is my understanding that there was resistance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.177" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01500"><p>There was not resistance, Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01600"><p>My apologies but as there is a vote in the D&aacute;il or Seanad we will have to adjourn.  I suggest that Deputy Troy finish asking his question and he can continue his questioning when we resume.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01700"><p>This is not the first time that funding for the FAI was suspended.  It was suspended in November 2004.  We had the Genesis report but all of its key recommendation were not implemented.  Does Sport Ireland accept that the FAI has shown a lack of respect for it in terms of not complying with its requirements?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.180" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01800"><p>The Deputy will have to ask the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE01900"><p>I am asking Mr. Treacy for his opinion on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.182" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE02000"><p>In my opinion we have had good relationships with the FAI over the last number of years.  We have continued to do our business.  Our programmes are well supported by the FAI.  It had been business as normal until this crisis hit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE02100"><p>Does Mr. Treacy accept that business as normal was not good enough?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#EE02200"><p>I will allow Deputy Troy straight in when we resume but the meeting is suspended until after the D&aacute;il vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.185" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.58 p.m. and resumed at 3.23 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00100"><p>I call Deputy Troy, who has five minutes left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00200"><p>Is the Minister, Deputy Ross, happy for the existing board to remain <i>in situ</i>, given that this board has been in place and has overseen the practices that led us to where we are today?  It continues to be evasive and refuses to answer basic questions about, for example, who signed off on a press release stating the members were all in full knowledge of the &euro;100,000 bridging loan.  Is the Minister satisfied that the existing board will remain in place until July?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00300"><p>No.  I am not happy for them to stay where they are but I am happy that they have declared their intention to step down at the extraordinary general meeting, EGM, which will be called before July.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00400"><p>We do not know that the EGM will be called before July.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00500"><p>The letter states:</p><blockquote>[Re-structuring the] Board will be brought to the membership for their consideration and adoption at our Annual General Meeting in July (or at an Extraordinary General Meeting if the work of the Group facilitates an earlier date).  At that point, when a new structure has been put in place, it is the intention-----</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00600"><p>Yes, but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00700"><p>Just let me finish this.  It continues: "the existing Board"-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00800"><p>I have read the statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK00900"><p>I am answering the Deputy's question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#KK01000"><p>Hold on.  Deputy Troy asked the question and the Minister just has another line to read.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00100"><p>I have read the statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00400"><p>Hold on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00500"><p>I am answering the Deputy's question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00600"><p>No, Minister, I have read the statement-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00700"><p>There is no issue about the Deputy asking the question but the Minister has just another line to read from the letter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00800"><p>Chairman, I have read the statement and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL00900"><p>Let the Minister answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01000"><p>I have just a short point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01100"><p>No.  I am not going to cut the Deputy's time but I just want the Minister to get the complete answer in.  I will give the Deputy extra time for his.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01200"><p>I thank the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01300"><p>The FAI email goes on: "At that point, when a new structure has been put in place, it is the intention that the existing Board will step down to allow for a new Board to be constituted in the best interests of football."  That is really a breakthrough and I am very pleased with that.  It would be my preference that they were not there today but there has to be someone to start the corporate governance reforms we discussing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01400"><p>I put it to the Minister that they have been <i>in situ</i>.  These are the people who have not overseen adequate corporate governance for the last years.  These are the people who have overseen the procedures that brought the Minister to the committee today, the FAI to the committee last week and Sport Ireland to the committee the week before.  Does the Minister have confidence that these people can oversee the needed reforms in the FAI given that they oversaw the problems that have led us to where we are today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01500"><p>I have made it quite clear that I would prefer that they were not there today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01600"><p>Okay.  There seems to be a resistance or reservations about conducting a full, independent audit.  Sport Ireland seems to be relying on Mazars and Grant Thornton.  Given that Mr. Mulvey said he has had a cursory look at the terms and conditions for the Mazars piece of work how can Sport Ireland be satisfied that the terms and conditions will adequately address the wide ranging issues that pertain to the FAI?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.210" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01700"><p>I want to be clear that Sport Ireland has no resistance to conducting a forensic audit.  It is a moving game - so to speak - and we do have to clarify and be clear on what will be the terms of reference for the Mazars report, what it is to investigate and how it intends to conduct that investigation.  It involves the Companies Act, it may involve an existing person in respect of whom certain matters may arise, and legal advice to the FAI is clouding some of these issues and therefore it is not clear and I have to be careful regarding that.  I have enough knowledge of employment law to know we need to be careful on that.</p> <p>  There are a few parallel processes, one of which is the Grant Thornton work.  We believe this exercise can be completed very quickly because it relates to internal oversight and the &euro;100,000.  Mazars will go into more detailed issues - as we understand - that have arisen recently in the media around certain transactional arrangements and third party arrangements.  That work will also be going on.  It is Sport Ireland's view that there is no point in us duplicating what is being done.  We will oversee and conduct oversight.  If that includes a forensic audit then it will be done.  At the moment my concern is who is auditing the auditors?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01800"><p>Exactly.  Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.212" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL01900"><p>I give this committee a full reassurance - and the Minister has indicated to us that he does not need to give us a direction on it - that we will do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL02000"><p>The current situation is as follows: an improper financial transaction has not been reported; there has been non-adherence to a basic level of corporate governance; substantial matters are being considered by the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement; there is a continual refusal by the existing board to answer basic questions; and the FAI auditors have filed a notice to the Companies Registration Office that proper books of accounts were not being kept.  What will it take for Sport Ireland to actually say that an independent forensic examination is needed?  Sport Ireland has said that it is still only considering such a measure and will not adjudicate that decision until such time as it knows the terms and conditions of the Mazars work.  When will Sport Ireland know terms and conditions for the Mazars work?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#LL02100"><p>How long has Mazars been there? Has it been for weeks?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.215" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00100"><p>I have just given a firm commitment on behalf of Sport Ireland that we will conduct a forensic audit.  We will have to engage-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00200"><p>When will it commence?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.217" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00300"><p>It will commence as soon as we are in a position to appoint auditors.  Our chief executive has already indicated that we are having difficulty appointing auditors who will undertake this work for us.  We will undertake that work under the normal procurement rules we are required to follow under the Department of Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform regulations, as we always do in regard to this.  We do not, however, want to have a situation where Sport Ireland is expending a considerable volume of money in duplicating work that is being done and paid for by the FAI, or work that is being done by the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement, ODCE.  In front of the Minister I assure the Chairman, the Deputy and the committee members that we do not need the Minister to tell us this.  We will do this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00400"><p>On that point, when I asked earlier the Sport Ireland representative said that Mazars was consulting with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement on the work to be done.  Surely it is now time for the ODCE to take over and be proactive, <i>in situ</i>, in this situation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00500"><p>The last time Mr. Mulvey was before the committee I asked if the board of Sport Ireland was made aware at any time of potential irregularities within the FAI.  Mr. Mulvey said that it was not and that he was unaware.  This is despite the fact that there was a well-publicised case in the High Court with a member of the Sport Ireland board that came about - I understand - because of concerns being raised with the FAI.  Does Mr. Mulvey consider Sport Ireland to have failed in its duty of oversight of the FAI in the last number of years?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.220" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00600"><p>Chairman, do I have absolute privilege here?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00700"><p>You have yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.222" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00800"><p>I do?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM00900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.224" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01000"><p>The issue to which the Deputy refers related to certain members of the former Irish Sports Council engaging in corporate practises that were contrary to the code of governance of State bodies.  On behalf of the board I took action on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01100"><p>In relation to concerns-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.226" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01200"><p>It was not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01300"><p>-----around the FAI irregularities-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.228" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01400"><p>It was not in regard to the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01500"><p>Does Mr. Mulvey have any regrets around the oversight by Sport Ireland-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.230" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01600"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1250" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01700"><p>-----over the last number of years?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.232" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01800"><p>I do not.  I have no evidence of it and I did not have evidence of it.  On behalf of Sport Ireland, and with the board's support, I had to stop certain members of the board meeting in concert outside the board of Sport Ireland and deciding who would get grants and what grants they would get.  I do not want to go into that.  I do not want to name the individuals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM01900"><p>I think that is exceptionally clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.234" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02000"><p>The Minister at that time supported me on that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02100"><p>Was Kerry on that list?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.236" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02200"><p>No, Kerry was not on that list.  My memory of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02300"><p>It might be on it now though.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.238" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02400"><p>I am fed up of Kerry meeting Roscommon all the time in football and beating us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02500"><p>I hear you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02600"><p>And Louth would like to do well in football too if you could fix a few matches: an All-Ireland or even a Meath-Louth game.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02700"><p>On the statement from the FAI board today about the board planning on stepping down what, if anything, would preclude those board members from putting themselves forward for re-election at the following AGM?  Will Sport Ireland make it a condition of planning to preclude any former board members from putting themselves forward or that the funding would not be reinstated?  Is that to be a condition of funding being reinstated?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.242" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02800"><p>No, it cannot be.  Regrettably it cannot be.  We do not have that authority.  That is a function under the Companies Act.  The only office that is allowed to disbar directors is the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM02900"><p>Was it under the Companies Act that funding for the former Olympic Council of Ireland was withheld?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.244" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM03000"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM03100"><p>Is the option not open to Sport Ireland to withhold funding until a new board is elected that does not include former members of the existing board?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.246" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#MM03200"><p>No.  For the reasons I have explained to the Deputy we cannot put in that precondition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00100"><p>Yes, but Mr. Mulvey said it was as a result of the Companies Act 2014, but how did that come about with the OCI board being fully replaced?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.248" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00200"><p>As I recall it at the time, the OCI was taking these actions internally.  We then received certain instructions in that regard on the funding of the OCI.  We funded the OCI to a level that was almost, apart from its own resources, 100% of its funding for office staff, etc.  We do not have authority under the Sport Ireland Act 2015 to determine who should be elected, appointed as directors or as representatives within NGBs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00300"><p>Given the seriousness of all of the issues that have arisen, does Mr. Mulvey believe Sport Ireland's powers need to be extended to include that authority?  Is it not time for Sport Ireland to have such powers because otherwise we are looking at the FAI board stepping down and its members being able to put themselves forward for re-election such that nothing will change?  I was looking at the FAI's statement and it literally states the board will oversee the investigation.  It is actually being allowed to stay <i>in situ</i>while the restructuring is taking place.  It will recommend that it be allowed to facilitate the management of the processes to their conclusion.  That is ridiculous.  It is running rings around Sport Ireland.  It is hard to credit this could be considered to be a step in the right direction.  That is not the case; it is anything but.  Is Sport Ireland allowing the FAI to run rings around it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.250" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00400"><p>I come back to the powers and authority under the Sport Ireland Act 2015-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00500"><p>I asked Mr. Mulvey a question about the extension of Sport Ireland's powers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.252" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00600"><p>I am sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00700"><p>-----in order that it can be effective, in some shape or form, because, as it stands, it does not look as if it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.254" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00800"><p>It is open to the Legislature to amend the Act to give us greater authority within the constraints on our funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN00900"><p>Will the Minister consider extending the powers provided in the Sport Ireland Act 2015 in order that Sport Ireland will have more powers and to ensure this will not end up being a complete and utter farce, given the seriousness of the issues involved?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN01000"><p>The answer to that question is yes, of course, I will consider it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN01100"><p>That is good.  If those powers could be provided as soon as possible, at least it would stop what will predictably or is likely to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.258" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN01200"><p>We will revisit the conditions attached to funding to look at areas where they need to be strengthened.  They are not included in the Act but in regulations that we apply.  We certainly have a job to do, given what has emerged.  We must ask if they are robust enough and sufficient to ensure we will not see a repeat in the FAI or any other organisation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#NN01300"><p>As a committee member, I suggest Sport Ireland look at the conditions attached to funding and extending its powers in order that we will not see what I suspect is a possibility at the next annual general meeting of the FAI.  We are three weeks into the process and it appears to me that the only investigations being carried out into the FAI are those being carried out by or commissioned by it.  I am wondering - I know that other Deputies have asked this question - given the seriousness of the issues involved, why Sport Ireland did not initiate its own investigation in carrying out a forensic audit?  I know that Mr. Mulvey said he had no resistance to a forensic audit being carried out, but he also said the investigation would be forensic in nature.  That is not the same as a forensic audit.  He said it would be as extensive as he would like it to be or would want it to be, but it is still not a forensic audit.  We were critical of what he was saying about the terms of reference for the Mazars review.  He has said he is unsure, but he thinks it will be similar to a forensic audit.</p><p>We were critical of the FAI for refusing to give answers and hiding behind the Mazars review and the Grant Thornton review, but it appears that Sport Ireland has been sitting back and leaving the FAI to investigate itself or a commission or others to investigate it and that Sport Ireland has done nothing of that nature.  It has not actually stated it will go ahead and commission a forensic audit.  Will it confirm that it will do so and when it will be done?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.261" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00200"><p>We are forgetting what the powers of Sport Ireland are.  The last time we were here we went through our powers verbatim.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00300"><p>I am sorry to interrupt Mr. Treacy, but the Minister said he would be in favour of having a forensic audit carried out, but that it depended on Sport Ireland.  Therefore, it does have the power.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.263" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00400"><p>We do not have that power under the Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00500"><p>We need clarity because the Minister said he was favour-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.265" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00600"><p>I will clarify the matter for the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00700"><p>It is a point of clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00800"><p>Questions and answers are very important.  As there will not be a time penalty, will Mr. Treacy, please, answer the question?  The Deputy can keep listening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.268" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO00900"><p>Last night we agreed with the FAI that we would carry out an in-depth audit of it.  We are open to suggestions on the kind of audit of the FAI, forensic or whatever else, we should carry out.  We will do it without question, if it is required.  We know exactly what we need to do, but we needed the FAI to approve this in-depth audit because we do not have the power to do it.  It is as simple as that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO01000"><p>Sport Ireland was due to carry out an audit this year.  The last one was carried out in 2016.  Will Sport Ireland or the Minister confirm that this audit will be different, that it will not be like an ordinary audit and that it will be a forensic audit, given all of what we have witnessed and all of the remaining questions that are unanswered?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.270" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO01100"><p>Yes.  I said and reiterate that it will be.  One of the other reasons is we were not aware last night that there was a report to the Companies Registration Office.  It was our legal advisers who advised us this morning.  We would have brought the matter to the attention of the Chairman as soon as we found out about it.  To be honest, that event alone changes my mind, as chairman of Sport Ireland.  My view is I would have reported it to the board and told the chief executive.  I want no more surprises or drip feed of information.  I do not want to read about what I need to know and should know and the information I should be granted as chairman of a statutory agency that gives &euro;2.9 million to the FAI, even if it is only 5% of its funding.  We have an obligation that will be met.  There will be no drip feed of information and no relying on second or third party information.  We need to satisfy ourselves and the board of Sport Ireland that everything is being done appropriately and properly within the FAI and within the appropriate time period, whatever it is.  I hope it will be done sooner rather than later.  We want the development officers to be paid in August.  Some 60% of our grant of &euro;2.9 million goes towards paying development officers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#OO01200"><p>That is why I stress that everybody wants to see those at the top and at the helm in the board being held responsible.  We do not want those in the grassroots to suffer because of it.  That is why it is important that people be held to account and that the powers of Sport Ireland be extended to ensure that if people are stepping down, they will not be able to put themselves forward at the next AGM and that the situation on the following day will be the same.  That is why the Minister needs to extend the powers and remit Sport Ireland to ensure this issue will be nailed on the head once and for all.  Is Sport Ireland confident that the FAI is not in breach of the Companies Act 2014 in the expenditure of public funds?</p><p>I know Mr. Mulvey cannot answer in respect of private funds but in respect of public funds, is he confident? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.273" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00200"><p>I cannot give an absolute assurance at the moment in regard to the current expenditure until we conduct the audit.  For previous years, yes, according to the auditors' report we have received.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00300"><p>Then it is all the more important that Sport Ireland carries out that forensic audit this year.  As John Delaney is not a member of the board anymore, will he also be resigning?  Did the Minister get any clarification or did Sport Ireland get any in its meeting yesterday?  What is going to happen with John Delaney?  He is stepping aside temporarily while the FAI carries out an internal investigation while leaving the door open for him.  This again comes back to strengthening and extending the powers of Sport Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.275" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00400"><p>My understanding at the moment, from my experience in employment law, and Mr. Treacy can correct me if I am wrong, is that there is the term that an individual is on gardening leave.  I assume that is where Mr. Delaney is.  I am not party to the arrangement, the deal, that was made between the legal people representing both sides.  I am always conscious of not interfering in a third-party contract.  I would understand, from what is normally the case, that where there is a question raised regarding an individual's performance, they are put on gardening leave while that investigation takes place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00500"><p>Mr. Mulvey is saying that is involuntary - to be "put".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.277" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00600"><p>I do not know.  What I understand is that a legal agreement was arrived at.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00700"><p>I am just asking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.279" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00800"><p>The statement from the FAI said it was a voluntary stepping aside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP00900"><p>Would Sport Ireland be of the belief, given the board allowed Mr. Delaney to voluntarily step aside, that this also points to the fact the board is totally dysfunctional and cannot stay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.281" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01000"><p>The Deputy has to understand that I cannot give her a "Yes" or "No" answer to that because we would be involving ourselves in commentary that may eventually end up in a court of law.  An individual's contract and his relationship with his employer is the issue here, and we are not party to that and we do not pay any element of that.  That is for them to decide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1333" speakername="Imelda Munster" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01100"><p>Finally, will Sport Ireland give a commitment to the committee-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01200"><p>I am sorry.  The Deputy's time is up.  I call Deputy Coppinger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01300"><p>I welcome the witnesses back to the committee.  The players' association last week said something is rotten in the FAI.  If something is rotten, it needs to be completely excised.  I am sure the witnesses would agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.285" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01500"><p>Following on from that, I would ask the witnesses two questions.  They just answered Deputy Munster by saying that Sport Ireland cannot make John Delaney, the executive vice president, step down.  However, there is a moral authority so I am going to ask Sport Ireland and the Minister if they are going to ask the board of the FAI to abolish the role of executive vice president that it created.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.287" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01600"><p>They are in a process at the moment, as I understand it.  If we did something like that, we would wind up in a court of law.  I believe that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01700"><p>This is a position that was created for one person, with no other candidates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.289" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01800"><p>Yes, I agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP01900"><p>Does Mr. Treacy not think he needs to ask them to abolish it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.291" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP02000"><p>I think if we did that, we would wind up in the High Court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP02100"><p>I will ask the Minister the same question.  Will he ask the FAI board, whenever he meets them, and he has not had a chance to meet them since the statements, to relinquish that position of executive vice president that it created?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP02200"><p>I would echo exactly what Mr. Treacy said.  I do not want to end up in the High Court.  I do not want to say anything here which would prejudice what is going on, so I am not going to answer that question with a "Yes" or "No".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP02300"><p>How would asking them to relinquish a position that they never should have created land the Minister in the High Court?  He is the Minister responsible for sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP02400"><p>That does not mean I am immune from being called to the High Court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#PP02500"><p>The second question relates to the board.  Everybody seems extremely confident, based on the latest epistle from the FAI board, that they will step down.  However, given they have concealed information from Sport Ireland in terms of their financial stability in 2017, and they have concealed information from the public and from all of us, does the Minister not think the board is part of the problem, not the solution?</p><p>Why, therefore, is the board being left in charge of cleaning up the FAI?  I direct that question first to Sport Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.298" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00200"><p>I will make two points.  We were extremely disappointed when we read the statement this morning because it had an opportunity to tell us last night and it did not do so.  That was really disappointing in the context of the actions we had taken in recent days to put pieces in place to get it back on an even keel and iinto calm waters.  That is one piece.  The trust piece is weakened because of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00300"><p>Sport Ireland did not have the chance to do so, but will it ask it the next time to step down immediately?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.300" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00400"><p>Yes, I will.  We are going through a process with the FAI and need a board with which to deal.  We cannot deal in a vacuum.  That is the critical issue for us at this time.  If everybody was to step down, there would be a vacuum.  There is then the question of how long would it take to put new board members in place.  There would be a vacuum and we would then be talking about real delays.  That is one issue.</p> <p>  The second issue - it really is an important issue that we all need to bear in mind - is that all of the sports organisations would not be long in telling us that they were autonomous organisations.  They are all accountable to international bodies which would also not be long in telling us.  There has been plenty of experience during the years of countries and governments telling national bodies this.  All of these things need to be borne in mind when talking about the issues involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00500"><p>Does Mr. Treacy agree that it is quite a weak answer to say it would take a little time to set up a new board and that, therefore, we should leave the rotten board in place that has led us to all of the problems in the first place?  Would the Minister like to answer that question?  Is he going to ask it to step down straightaway?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00600"><p>I am very glad that the Deputy asked that question.  She asks whether I believe the board is part of the problem.  Yes, absolutely, it is part of the problem and imperative that it step down.  What we have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00700"><p>Now or in July.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00800"><p>We have a commitment that it will step down, to which it will be held.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ00900"><p>A commitment from the FAI does not mean an awful lot, as we found out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ01000"><p>What we have is a commitment.  The Deputy wants it to step down today, something I would like to see.  It was in my initial statement before I received this information today.  I would like it to step down and it is my desire that it would step down, but, as Mr. Treacy said, if it was to step down today and we had to put a new board in place, it would take some time to do so and there would be a vacuum which would delay implementation of the corporate governance reforms.  I believe it will step down because of the letter it sent to me today.  I want it to happen as quickly as possible, before the AGM, not afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ01100"><p>I have another few questions.  I would have thought having an interim board in place would be better than keeping the current board.  Two weeks ago at this committee Sport Ireland stated it was reluctant to impose the ultimate sanction.  Obviously, a week later it did impose it.  Was it far too slow and cautious?  Should it not have been done years ago, given what we all know now?  The Minister of State said in a statement there had been long-running friction in the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.308" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ01200"><p>We had to go through a process.  The board makes the decision and we needed very good reasons to suspend funding.  The FAI admitted that it had not kept to the terms and conditions attached to funding.  We knew we could not be challenged when it admitted it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ01300"><p>Today the Minister of State said there had long been friction in the FAI.  He is right.  The dogs in the street have seen the carry-on in the FAI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ01400"><p>There is friction in many national governing bodies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#QQ01500"><p>I would like to finish the question.  The reason we were told that the sanction could not be imposed was that the grassroots would suffer and kids would no longer be able to play football.  Today the Minister of State tells us that there is no issue and that we would penalise local soccer clubs for problems in their national association.</p><p>If that is the case, why did it take years for the Ministers - I am not blaming Sport Ireland - to do something about what is going on?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00200"><p>It very important to point out and reiterate that our primary purpose is to ensure that people who want to play soccer and who want to be active in sport can do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00300"><p>Why did it take so long to act?  Rather than giving us a long-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.315" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00400"><p>What the Deputy is advocating would hurt those who need our support most.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00500"><p>The Minister of State said he did not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.317" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00600"><p>Our position is that we want to ensure-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00700"><p>Hang on.  In his own statement, the Minister of State says that people will not be hurt by these actions.  That is what I am saying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.319" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00800"><p>I allowed the Deputy to ask the question-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.320" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR00900"><p>I am sorry but I note to the Minister of State and Deputy Coppinger that we are doing exceptionally well here today.  If the Deputy and Minister of State can-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.321" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01000"><p>I quoted the Minister of State's statement to him but he is answering about something else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.322" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01100"><p>No Deputy or Senator is precluded from asking questions but witnesses must be given the opportunity to answer.  If the Minister of State goes on longer than the Deputy expects, she will still get the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.323" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01200"><p>Can I explain what I am asking?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.324" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01300"><p>Hold on a second.  I want to work this out.  The Minister of State is answering.  The Deputy should let him do so.  The Deputy can then ask further questions.  There will be no time penalty for the Deputy arising from the answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.325" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01400"><p>As the Deputy knows, these revelations came to light recently.  The process, which started recently, is of concern to us all.  As a result of that, it is important that we use whatever leverage we have to ensure a speedy resolution to the issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.326" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01500"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.327" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01600"><p>One of the areas in which we have leverage is the sports capital programme.  It is critically important, however, that we ensure that the people who are affected by our actions are the people whom we need to affect, rather than those who would ultimately become victims - the people on the ground, the grassroots members who want to play and participate in sports and the volunteers who facilitate that.  That is why we need to be very targeted in what we do.  As we know, the specifics about which we are talking only came to light recently.  I believe we have acted accordingly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.328" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01700"><p>The Minister has said "those of us elected to D&aacute;il ... &Eacute;ireann have a responsibility to the people of Ireland to ensure that public funds are used wisely".  Were public funds used wisely by the FAI over the years given what we read regarding expenses, travel and the salary of the ex-CEO, reports which we have not heard the board deny?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.329" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01800"><p>I know that some people want to be judge, jury and executioner but there is a process in place and we need to allow it to continue in order to gather all the facts and establish an answer to that question.  We are concerned.  That is why we are all here.  We want to get the answers to the questions that need to be answered.  I am not happy that many of the questions which all of us have, and which soccer supporters around the country have, have not been answered to date, but that is what we are trying to establish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.330" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR01900"><p>It is established that the ex-CEO salary was, at one point, more than &euro;400,000.  It has been reduced dramatically and terribly to &euro;330,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.331" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR02000"><p>There is an awful lot of information in the public domain.  I hope that we will also get the information we do not yet have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.332" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR02100"><p>I refer to the note from the auditors to Sport Ireland, which said that the FAI is in breach of one or more of the sections of the Companies Act, which is a criminal offence.  The Minister of State only found this out today.  Are such people fit to oversee a root-and-branch review and overhaul of the FAI?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.333" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR02200"><p>We need to be careful.  I am sorry to say that, but we do.  If we say things like that we will all end up in the wrong place - the High Court.  We are dealing with people who are in position within the FAI.  They are the only people with whom we can deal at the moment.  That is what we are doing.  We do not elect these people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.334" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR02300"><p>In fairness to the question, it is valid.  The Deputy is asking about the board to which the note refers.  She is not implying anything about the people.  It is a fair question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.335" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR02400"><p>I am referring to the board that was in place when this was discovered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.336" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#RR02500"><p>The FAI has a council of 60 people.  As I understand it, these people are the real legislative and governing authority within the association.  They elect the management board and the officers.  It is up to them to act if they so wish.  As Mr. Treacy said earlier, we have to deal with the people who are in place at the moment.</p><p>If the view is they have questions to answer, and obviously they do, we can only deal with them and hopefully work with them to achieve a solution if necessary.  We have already indicated that we have been disappointed with the performance to date.  Certain assurances have been given this morning and last night.  I can assure the committee that I have been in the business of industrial relations and dispute negotiation, nationally and internationally, for a long time.  I do not think the word "stupid" has been written on my forehead at any point.  If I find that this committee is not dealing with us in an upright, forward and transparent manner, I will have several things to say to the Chairman of this committee and to the Minister about whether we are making any progress. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.338" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00200"><p>With regard to Sport Ireland I note that we have had issues with the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, with boxing and with the Olympic Council of Ireland, as it then was.  In response to a previous question, the witnesses said there were similarities with the Olympic Council of Ireland in that strong personalities are at the helm of these organisations.  Would Sport Ireland's representatives agree that personal aggrandisement and nest-feathering by the strong personalities at the helm also seem to be features of these organisations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.339" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00300"><p>Those characteristics would seem to make sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.340" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Mulvey" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00400"><p>There is a lot of hubris around.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.341" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00500"><p>As such, can the witnesses imagine how frustrating it is for members of the public to hear that the best that this committee and this Minister can do is to put one of those people on gardening leave?  We are told that is enough and we cannot do anything about this.  Can the witnesses imagine how frustrating that is?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.342" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00600"><p>Yes, we can imagine that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.343" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00700"><p>My last question is about the new board.  I know nothing about the person concerned and it is no reflection on that person.  Do the witnesses not agree that it is now time for a complete change in how the boards of sporting organisations are run?  For example, should the boards not include representatives of the players, the supporters and the public, that is, the people who go out on a Saturday and drive their children to matches?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.344" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00800"><p>I will be clear.  That is exactly what the governance review that has been set up will be looking at; who will be representative of the new FAI in the future.  It will be looking at representation and who will be the appropriate people.  Very importantly, it will also consider the appropriate skills.  We face this issue this in a lot of sports.  Boards are not tracksuits.  They are made up of people who know what good corporate governance is.  The failing of some sporting organisations is that board members sometimes come up through the ranks and through branches.  When they come to Sport Ireland for training they do not have the appropriate skills.  As such we are starting all over again with new board members.  That is the nature of sport.  A lot of board members are drawn from various representative organisations and different branches.  That is the limitation of sporting organisations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.345" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS00900"><p>The Minister wants to contribute.  Before he does so, I note that a couple of members have suggested we should suspend for about 15 or 20 minutes after this.  Witnesses are entitled to a break as well, not that they have asked for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.346" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#SS01000"><p>I commend Deputy Coppinger on saying that representatives of supporters, fans, coaches, volunteers, leagues and players should be on the board.  That is absolutely essential.  One of the glaring problems in the FAI is that there appears to be a very well-heeled and powerful elite at the top.  However, football is about the people the Deputy has mentioned, namely, the supporters and the players.  In my opening statement, I stated absolutely categorically that their voices should not be confined to committees or a low level.  In my view they should have places on the board of the body that runs football.  Let us not be equivocal about it.</p><p>The Deputy is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.348" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1434" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#TT00200"><p>Will the Minister change the regulations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.349" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#TT00300"><p>I am not the one to change them, but I will make that suggestion and do everything I can to see that it happens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.350" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#TT00400"><p>One issue arises, but we may not be able to get the answer today.  I understand Deloitte was obliged to tell the FAI when it assumed there were issues with its keeping of accounts.  It then had up to seven days to tell the Director of Corporate Enforcement.  Both we and the Minister need to know when Deloitte told the FAI.  When did it form that opinion?  While I am not saying it has happened, it could be the case that in the meetings we had it already knew that this was going on.  Why did it not tell the Minister last night?  It does not make sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.351" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.05 p.m. and resumed at 4.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.352" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>