<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.2" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="">Select Committee on Health</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.3" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 09:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Jim Daly (Minister of State at the Department of Health), Deputy Alan Kelly, Deputy Bernard J. Durkan, Deputy Kate O'Connell, Deputy Billy Kelleher, Deputy Margaret Murphy O'Mahony, Deputy Louise O'Reilly.</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL HARTY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.5" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#A00200">Estimates for Public Services 2018<br />Vote 38 - Health (Revised)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#B00300"><p>The select committee is now in public session.  The purpose of this morning's meeting is the consideration of the Department of Health's Estimate for 2018.  The D&aacute;il ordered that the following Estimate for public services, Vote 38 - Health, be referred to the select committee for consideration.</p> <p>  I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health with special responsibility for mental health and older people, Deputy Jim Daly, and his officials.  The purpose of today's meeting is to consider the Revised Estimates for 2018 - Vote 38.  I invite the Minister of State to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#B00400"><p>F&aacute;ilt&iacute;m roimh an deis labhairt leis an gcoiste.  I welcome this opportunity to address the select committee on the Revised Estimates for 2018 for the Department's Vote 38.  Unlike many other Votes, the health Vote is not configured along programme lines.  While the Department is working towards the development of programme budgeting, this will take some time as the financial systems in the HSE will have to be adapted to allow for this in the context of the financial reform programme currently under way.  </p><p>The level of funding provided in the 2018 Revised Estimates will allow the Department and the Health Service Executive, HSE, to deliver better access, more health for families and more supports for disability, mental health and older and vulnerable people.  In addition, the welcome increase in the health capital budget over the period to 2021 will allow completion of key developments such as the new children's hospital and will ensure capital investment supports our strategic initiatives and ehealth improvements.  </p><p>The improving economy has enabled the health service to achieve much-needed budget increases in each of the last three years.  We are very aware that there are areas where further improvements are required and the Department will continue to work with the HSE to optimise service provision within the constraints of available funding.  </p><p>The gross provision for the health Vote in 2017 was &euro;14.801 billion, comprising &euro;14.347 billion in current expenditure and &euro;454 million in capital expenditure, inclusive of &euro;195 million granted by means of a Supplementary Estimate.  The supplementary requirement arose due to new initiatives approved in 2017, central pay decisions, a shortfall in income and additional funding required in the State Claims Agency.  Funding was neither sought nor granted for deficits that arose in service areas which were within the management control of the HSE.</p><p>In framing the 2018 budget, the Oireachtas allocated &euro;15.332 billion in Exchequer funding for the health sector.  This represents an increase of &euro;492 million on the 2017 post-supplementary current expenditure budget and &euro;39 million, or 8.6%, on capital expenditure and recognises the Government's commitment to providing a health service that seeks to improve the health and well-being of the people of Ireland. </p><p>The issue of health funding is a major policy challenge internationally.  Despite welcome increases over recent years, the need for effective financial management remains crucial as the health service deals with a larger and older population, with more acute health and social care requirements, increased demand for new and existing drugs and the rising costs of health technology.  The costs associated with these service pressures will increasingly need to be managed not solely through increased Exchequer allocations but also through improved efficiencies, productivity and value from within the funding base in 2018 and beyond.</p><p>I would like to address the recently published Project Ireland 2040 and the Government's capital spending plans for the next ten years.  Capital funding for our health service has been agreed at &euro;10.9 billion for the next ten years, which is 165% higher when compared with the past ten years.  We now have a solid ambitious plan to build a better health service for the future through the combination of this significant capital investment programme alongside the implementation of the Sl&aacute;intecare reforms.  The &euro;10.9 billion funding over the next ten years provides a real long-term opportunity to improve our health services, provide modern fit-for-purpose health facilities, increase bed capacity and modernise how we deliver services through ehealth, reformed pathways of care and the implementation of Sl&aacute;intecare.</p><p>Capital investments over the coming decade will support existing Government priority projects and commitments and will enable the roll-out of new additional capacity, guided by the Sl&aacute;intecare report and the recently published health service capacity review.  </p><p>The strategic investment priorities for the public health sector in Project Ireland 2040 include a number of major investment projects and programmes over its lifetime, including: the new children's hospital at St. James's campus Dublin and the two children's outpatient and urgent care centres at Connolly Hospital, Blanchardstown and at Tallaght hospital, Dublin.  The priorities also included the national maternity strategy developments, including the relocation of stand-alone maternity hospitals to acute hospital campus such as the move of the National Maternity Hospital, Holles Street to the St. Vincent's campus; national cancer strategy capital developments, including the national programme for radiation oncology at Cork, Galway and Dublin and the expansion of BreastCheck; building the new national forensic and mental health service hospital at Portrane, Dublin; the primary care centre construction programme at various locations around the country; and the replacement and refurbishment of community nursing units for older people and long-term residential care units and housing in the community for people with disabilities at various locations across the country.  In addition, the national development plan provides capital funding to implement the health service capacity review.</p><p>With this unprecedented capital investment in the health services we must ensure that we carefully plan and select projects.<b></b></p><p>To achieve that, we will put in place a robust method of project appraisal, assessment and selection in order to implement health strategies, including developing capacity to meet the population health needs and achieve value for money.<br/><br/>Along with my ministerial colleagues in the Department, I am committed to advancing a programme of both investment and reform for our health and social care services.  The recent Health Service Capacity Review provides an evidence base to determine the extent and nature of the capacity that will be required up to 2031.  It forecasts that by 2031, we will need an additional 1,000 general practitioners, GPs, and additional capacity requirements in primary care, acute hospitals and services for older persons for that period.<br/><br/>The Government is committed to making tangible and sustainable improvements in our health services and the Sl&aacute;intecare report, published last March, provides a framework to do that.  There is now an unprecedented level of consensus and support for the vision and strategic direction outlined in the report.  We must harness that and work with colleagues across the political spectrum and with all stakeholders to move forward on a programme of health reform.  The Government has already given its approval to move ahead with the establishment of a Sl&aacute;intecare programme office in the Department of Health.  This office will be tasked with implementing a programme of reform, as agreed by Government, arising from the Sl&aacute;intecare report.  The recruitment of an executive director of the Sl&aacute;intecare programme is under way.<br/><br/>It is important to note that many recommendations in the Sl&aacute;intecare are already policy priorities.  These include: the roll-out of our ehealth and health and well-being strategies; the development of a new GP contract and proposals for an enhanced community nursing service; further roll-out of integrated care programmes; the undertaking of a capacity review; and development of an integrated workforce planning framework.  The majority of additional funding for new health initiatives in budget 2018 has been targeted at areas identified in the Sl&aacute;intecare report such as the primary care fund, additional home care and transition beds, reduced medicine and prescription charges and targeted funding for waiting list reduction.  These actions are important first steps in a long-term reform process.<br/><br/>Work is under way in the Department to develop an implementation plan in response to the Sl&aacute;intecare report.  A steering group, with representation from both the Department and the Health Service Executive, HSE, has been directing this work over the past months.  Work is well advanced and the Minister, Deputy Harris, expects to bring proposals to Government shortly.  Furthermore, a memorandum will be brought to Government in the coming weeks with the general scheme for a Bill to introduce a governing board for the HSE, which is a key recommendation in Sl&aacute;intecare.<br/><br/>Reducing waiting times for hospital procedures is a key priority for this Government.  The HSE has been allocated &euro;12 million for scheduled care measures, &euro;10 million of which has been ring-fenced for scoliosis and Merlin Park University Hospital orthopaedic capacity and &euro;2 million for other priorities.<br/><br/>Waiting list figures for the end of February published by the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, show that 72% of inpatient day case patients and 61% of outpatients are waiting nine months or less.  There was a reduction of 1,165 patients waiting for an inpatient or day case procedure compared to the end of January 2018 and a reduction of 7,175 when compared to the numbers waiting at the end of July 2017.  That is against a background of increasing demands on our acute hospitals which, since 2000, are carrying out four times more procedures for patients aged 65 and over and twice as many in the under 65 age group.  An additional &euro;35 million has been allocated to the NTPF for commissioned patient treatment, which brings its total budget for 2018 to &euro;55 million.  It is estimated that the NTPF initiatives in 2018 will enable the provision of treatment for up to 20,000 patients on the inpatient-day case waiting list across a range of specialties and procedures.<br/><br/>This winter has been very difficult for our health services.  During February, there was a 7.7% increase in attendances and a 5% increase in emergency department admissions compared to February 2017.  That growth in demand is well ahead of population growth and reflects international evidence that emergency department demand is driven by more than demographic factors.  This increased demand was further exacerbated in March by the impact of Storm Emma and the associated severe weather experienced across the country since the beginning of March.<br/><br/>While demand for services is growing considerably, the inpatient bed capacity to meet the demand is constrained, resulting in an 11.8% increase in the number of patients waiting on trolleys, compared to February 2017.  While fully acknowledging the need for productivity improvements and reforms across the health service, the bed capacity review outlines that in order to reach international standards of bed occupancy levels, the acute hospital system needs an immediate injection of additional beds.  It is only through continued investment in capacity, in hospital staff and in reform of our health services, in line with Sl&aacute;intecare, that we will deliver better services for patients.<br/><br/>The Government provided an additional &euro;40 million for measures to alleviate the pressure on emergency departments during winter 2017-2018.  Timely discharge of patients is vital to ensuring that a ready supply of beds is available to those patients requiring to be admitted through emergency departments.  Delayed discharges are a major contributory factor to emergency department overcrowding and adversely affect patient flow throughout the hospital.  It is essential that, in so far as is possible, egress meets demand, and that hospital and community health care organisations, CHOs, processes support timely and safe discharge.  Accordingly, over 60% of the 2018 funding for unscheduled care access measures is being targeted towards providing additional social care supports.  These additional supports have been targeted at the hospitals with the greatest number of patients awaiting discharge home and will help improve patient flow in those hospitals, which will in turn help to relieve congestion in their emergency departments.  As of today, 189 additional beds have been opened this winter and further beds will open throughout 2018.<br/><br/>In the light of the recommendations of the Health Service Capacity Review and the current pressures on the hospital system, the HSE has been asked to develop a plan to identify the location and mix of beds across the hospital system which can be opened and staffed by 1 November 2018 in order to improve preparedness for winter 2018-2019 and relieve overcrowding in hospital emergency departments.  In addition, the HSE and the Department have started the process of reviewing the winter initiative 2017-2018, with a view to providing a report in late April and ensuring the learning from this year will inform the agreement and early implementation of measures for next winter.<br/><br/>Primary care services can provide key opportunities in the implementation of Sl&aacute;intecare as it proposes the adoption of a new model of integrated care, centred on comprehensive primary and community care services.  In 2018, primary care funding of &euro;850 million will continue to build on the significant additional resources that have been invested over the past number of years in the State&rsquo;s primary care services.  For example, we have seen the extension of eligibility for GP cards to the under-sixes and the over-70s and the development of the diabetes cycle-of-care programme.<br/><br/>Quite significant investment has also been made in the development of primary care capacity, particularly in the therapy area, continued investment in the development of community intervention teams and enhanced community diagnostic programmes with the delivery of ultrasound and X-ray in the community.  We have also invested significantly in our primary care infrastructure providing modern, well equipped primary care centres - 114 to date - to enable patients access health care in their communities in a more integrated manner.  Capital funding of over &euro;29 million will continue to support the roll out of these centres.<br/><br/>The funding allocated in 2018 will continue to deliver these key services and dedicated additional funding of &euro;25 million therein will focus on disease prevention and early intervention, particularly through the further development and expansion of GP services.<br/><br/>In line with the Government&rsquo;s commitment to promoting care in the community, the Department is developing a new statutory scheme for the financing and regulation of home care services.  Pending this, the Department and the HSE are continuing efforts to incrementally improve the existing services.  Home support services were a particular area of focus in budget 2018, with an additional &euro;18 million allocated.  The additional resources made available brings the total budget for the direct provision of home support services to &euro;408 million.  The HSE&rsquo;s national service plan provides for a target of 17 million home support hours to be provided to 50,500 people.<br/><br/>Of course, there will always be a cohort of people who require long-term residential care, and the nursing homes support scheme, NHSS, commonly known as fair deal, continues to provide financial assistance to those who need long-term nursing home care.  The aim of the scheme is to ensure that long-term nursing home care is accessible and affordable for everyone, and that people are cared for in the most appropriate settings.<br/><br/>Mental Health remains a priority care programme for the Government.  For this reason, budget 2018 made allowance for an additional &euro;57.5 million for mental health services for 2018, inclusive of &euro;22.5 million of pay-related costs and &euro;35 million to continue to progress new initiatives.  The additional funding will help build on the work commenced in 2017 on the enhancement of community teams for children, adults, later life and mental health intellectual disability services.  It will also help to continue our move towards a full 24-7 service, with an initial focus on increasing the provision of services on a seven-days-a-week basis.  The HSE has been asked to prioritise this work in 2018 as well as develop a service response which is as seamless as possible for every service user.<br/><br/>Budget 2018 announced a reduction in the prescription charge and the drug payment scheme, DPS, monthly threshold.  Since 1 January, medical card holders have benefited from a 50 cent reduction in the prescription charge, from &euro;2.50 to &euro;2 per item, and the maximum monthly cost reduced by &euro;5, from &euro;25 to &euro;20.  For approved treatments under the DPS the maximum monthly payment reduced by &euro;10, from &euro;144 to &euro;134.  This will benefit all families who exceed the threshold in any month.<br/><br/>While we<b></b>have secured a significant increase in funding for the health services in recent years, I do not underestimate the challenges involved in the delivery of a safe, efficient health service for the Irish people.  Despite welcome increases in recent years, a financial challenge remains as we deal with a larger and older population, with more acute health and social care requirements, increased demand for new and existing drugs and the rising costs of health technology.</p><p>The costs of payments under the State Claims Agency are also rising, adding to the overall cost of health above the operational costs funded to meet the health demands of a growing and ageing population.  We must maintain our focus on improving the way services are organised and delivered, and on reducing costs, in order to maximise the ability of the health service to respond to growing needs.  It is essential that those managing and delivering the service demonstrate good practice by delivering the best possible health care within the limits of the resources that have been made available by Government each year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#D00200"><p>I will now bring in the party spokespersons on health, starting with Deputy Kelleher and continuing with Deputies O'Reilly and Kelly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#D00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  As we go through the Estimates for the year, it is looking at things in a historical context to a certain extent as well as everything else and trying to learn from what has been done to date as regards funding and policy itself.  In that context, the Minister of State referred towards the end of his opening statement to primary care.  There is no doubt that a couple of related issues are being discussed at other fora currently, including the GP contract, which is a critical component of the delivery of health care.  That was also alluded to in the Sl&aacute;intecare report where we talked about the transfer of services from the hospital-centric system we have at the moment to the community by way of bolstering primary care, community diagnostics, therapy and so on.  The following is an observation as much as it is a criticism.  I think often that officialdom lives in a parallel universe when it comes to what is happening on the ground in terms of investment figures showing increases in home care packages and home help hours.  When one drills down into it, one still finds huge problems in trying to deliver the very basics in terms of home help hours.  Where a person is deemed to need home help hours to get out of bed, there may only be funding to get out of bed five days a week.  As such, the person has to stay in bed two days a week.</p> <p>  We have almost dehumanised our health services in some key areas.  It is not a reflection not the people at the coalface, but it seems we do not have that ability to understand in officialdom and through the system what individuals go through in their lives.  We have to look harshly at how we assess and view cuts to services or the lack of a service in the first place and the impact that has on an individual's life.  I have an 84 year old woman whose husband cannot get out of bed himself.  They need a hoisting system and all of that is in place, which she appreciates very much.  However, she is only funded six mornings a week.  On the seventh morning, every Sunday, she has to get neighbours or friends to help her get her husband out of bed.  She only wants 20 minutes.  That is an issue that has to be addressed if we are to have any meaningful change of heart in the delivery of health care in primary and community settings.  It is just an individual case but it can be extrapolated across the whole are of home care packages, home help hours, access to diagnostics, access to therapy and all of that.</p> <p>  When we talk about primary care, which is the Minister of State's particular area, we talk about extending eligibility for free GP care.  While I opposed it at the time, I did so on the grounds that I did not think the GP services in place would be able to cope with what would be thrown at it in the context of the roll-out of universal GP care given the demographics of both the population and of GPs.  We are at the crossroads in how we look at primary care and its delivery.  We talk about it a lot but we have not resourced and funded it accordingly.  The Minister of State refers to the availability of &euro;850 million for primary care, but when one looks at what we expect that to do from a policy and demographic perspective, the two will not match and marry very well.  We will end up with a gravely abused primary care system which is incapable of delivering in the key areas the Minister of State has identified from a policy perspective or, primarily, from the perspective of Sl&aacute;intecare.  That is chronic disease and illness, more diagnostics, retention of people in home or community care settings or step-down facilities.  That requires a great many more GPs.</p> <p>  I refer to the involvement of GPs in home care delivery and primary care teams and where we are with the number of GPs, the numbers who are retiring, the capacity of the primary care system in general and its funding and the tortuously slow negotiations around the GP contract, if it is even possible to say there are negotiations at all.  I am beginning to think this is just window dressing.  If negotiations are not moving between the primary actors, namely, the Department of Health and the IMO, others must intervene to push this on.  It is the central and most critical issue in terms of how we deliver care in community and primary care settings in the foreseeable future.  Obviously, we would like to see a rolling contract that is revisited on a regular basis, but we will have to get the basics right or we will end up in circumstances where no GPs are coming into the system while those who are trained and qualified are leaving.  Meanwhile, those at the other end of the scale approaching retirement age will step off because they have had enough.  We could end up with a very difficult situation in which policy refers to primary care but everybody is sent to hospital.  These are observations but they are important from the point of view of the focus on funding.</p> <p>  There was an RT&Eacute; report yesterday by Brian O&rsquo;Connell who visited Cork and spoke with GPs and families in Munster on the availability of psychiatric services.  The fact remains that child and adolescent mental health services in the Munster region are not what the Minister of State and I would like.  Certainly, they are not up to standard for those who depend on them.  We have situations in which GPs have no choice where a child attends who is at risk of self-harm, has suicidal ideation or has attempted suicide.  He or she must be referred to an emergency department.  If that is not done, the person is put on a waiting list.  That goes back to my original point about how we dehumanise the health system.  It causes trauma to the individual, the family and the medical professionals trying to deal with it that they cannot access any particular service.</p> <p>  The Minister of State referred a few times in his opening statement to the number of people we require to expand the health service.  We must carry out a full root and branch manpower assessment as to what we need in our health services beyond the horizon.  We talk about training health professionals and it is seven to ten years before some are fully qualified.  It requires a great deal of long-term planning but we have not carried it out in enough areas.  We have not assessed the demographics and the demands the changing profile of the population will place on health service.  We have not determined what professionals we need to meet those demands.  That means getting involved with the training bodies and agencies to expand and enhance capacity in key areas.  We all speak, for example, about the fact that we will be older.  When one looks at investment in training in geriatric services, however, we are not crowning ourselves in glory notwithstanding the fact that we know the population will be quite elderly down the road.  That is one key area where a failure to drill down and determine what illnesses like diabetes and obesity, which are evident in the population, will mean.</p><p>We do not seem to have enough capacity to assess what our manpower requirements will be, not next year or the following year but in five, seven, ten or 15 years' time.  That is something that is never referred to in speeches or in policy other than it being said that we know we need additional doctors.  We have never carried out a detailed analysis.  The last time such an approach was taken was in the context of the Hanly report on consultants.  We need a detailed analysis of all grades - including physiotherapists and occupational therapists - right across the spectrum.  I urge that such an approach would be taken in the context of the Sl&aacute;intecare report and the funding of same or that the Department would independently get someone to carry out a detailed assessment of manpower requirements and then put in place the capacity to train them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#E00200"><p>I bid the Minister of State and his officials a good morning.  When members ask these questions, we tend to throw about 57,000 issues at the Minister, which means we tend to get very vague answers.  It is hard not to take such an approach because there are deficiencies in so many areas but if I can I will try to focus on a number of areas.  One is scoliosis.  That is something we have raised time and again.  We are not alone in that, as other Deputies, including Deputies in the Minister of State's own party have raised it.  The waiting lists are still unacceptable.  I do not think anyone would defend them.  It is not that long since the Minister was on television apologising in what I am sure was a very sincere way about it, but the waiting lists are unacceptable, in particular for those who have complex medical conditions.  The Minister had promised a detailed action plan for parents, which I suppose is just like a normal action plan but is perhaps a bit longer.  Parents have still not seen the action plan.  They are contacting me and I am sure they are contacting Deputy Kelleher and others as well to ask if we can ascertain when the detailed action plan will be ready.  When the plan is ready it could just be put with all the other detailed action plans.  What people really want to know is when the children will be treated and whether there is a plan to increase the operation of the theatre in Crumlin from three days to five.  If there is, could the Minister of State advise how many staff have been recruited to deal with that?  Given the length of the waiting lists, there is a case to be made for increasing the theatre openings to seven days a week until the crisis is over.  Could the Minister of State outline the position in terms of the recruitment of doctors, nurses and everybody else who will be needed to open the theatre for extra days?</p> <p>  That brings me to my next point.  Deputy Kelleher raised a similar point.  We all know that if additional beds are to be opened additional staff will be needed.  Could the Minister of State give an indication of the age profile of staff?  Doctors, nurses, allied health professionals, porters, theatre assistants and everybody else are coming into the system - I do not believe we are getting anywhere near the numbers needed - but at the other end people are leaving because in some instances the workplace is intolerable but there are also people whom we know will leave due to retirement, for example.  It is my understanding that there is not a plan in place to deal with the retirements.  Perhaps the Minister of State could point us to the section in the Estimates concerning recruitment and where the additional moneys for the additional capacity have been put aside.  The Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, has said it himself and the Minister, Deputy Harris, has definitely said that one could open a bed in the morning but it is just sitting there if one does not have the staff to care for the patient in it.  How much of the additional &euro;530 million is allocated for additional staff and potential pay increases and how much is just for standing still and maintaining the current level of services?</p> <p>  During Storm Emma the Minister for Health announced that &euro;5 million would be provided for additional capacity.  Could the Minister of State give us a breakdown of where the money was spent and whether money was taken from the budget for other areas and ring-fenced for that purpose?</p> <p>  It is hard to believe that there are negotiations, much less intense negotiations of any sort going on with general practitioners, GPs.  Can the Minister of State provide us with information on whether any discussion has taken place with regard to salaried GPs?  All of the reports in the media and from the representative organisations suggest there is a crisis in capacity in terms of GPs at the moment.  One issue identified in Sl&aacute;intecare is that we might look at salaried GPs to alleviate the crisis.  I understand that it would not be a panacea.  Could the Minister of State advise us if that has formed part of the discussions and perhaps give us an update?</p> <p>  The Minister of State referred to 179 beds that had been opened and that a detailed plan would be provided, perhaps on 1 November, for the opening of additional beds.  Could he give a breakdown of the staffing for those beds?  Is there recruitment in the pipeline?  One cannot just fill out a form.  It is a long process to recruit a staff member at any grade into the health service, except as it turns out, administrative staff because we saw over the weekend that they are being recruited at a rate of knots, unlike health professionals.  That is not to say administrative staff are not needed because of course they are but it strikes me as a bit odd that the recruitment of administrative staff is outstripping the recruitment of front-line health care professionals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#E00300"><p>I welcome my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, and his officials here today.  I assure him that while he is busy with his ministerial ship, I will mind the ship in west Cork.  He can rest assured of that.</p> <p>  On a serious note, I see the budget for people with disabilities is on par with that for 2017.  I would have expected more progress with the transport support allowance, for example.  I know that is within the remit of the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, but perhaps the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, has some comments to make on it.</p> <p>  In the Minister of State's own area of mental health, I note there is a 10% increase in funding, which is very welcome and should not be knocked.  However, the Minister of State must admit that not enough is being done.  Without the likes of organisations such as Pieta House, the country would be in a very difficult place.  I would welcome a comment in that regard.</p> <p>  Does the Minister of State think the extra 4% spend could help to tackle the waiting lists which are now at 288 for an autism spectrum disorder, ASD, assessment in Marian House, Cork?  Both the Minister of State and I have a lot of constituents who are on the waiting list for two years.  Because of the importance of early intervention, two years is not good enough.  Will some of the extra funding be channelled in that direction?</p> <p>  Deputy Louise O'Reilly mentioned scoliosis.  The Minister of State put a strong emphasis on what would be done to address the issue in his speech.  A boy in west Cork was diagnosed at the age of 11.  He is now 16 and he has yet to be treated five years later.  What is happening is not good enough.</p> <p>  What resources does the Minister of State envisage being put into rural hospitals such as Bantry General Hospital in our constituency?  As he is aware Bantry General Hospital has been seeking a rehabilitation and endoscopy unit for some time.  The Minister of State might just tell me what resources will be allocated to Bantry General Hospital?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00100"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for their attention and questioning thus far.  I will answer to the best of my ability.  I do not have the answers for all of the questions but anything I can answer I will to the best of my ability and anything I fail to answer I will come back to the members directly or to the committee with more detailed information.</p> <p>  Deputy Kelleher spoke about humanising the system and officialdom versus reality.  The role of politicians and politics and the role we play all day every day as representatives is to attempt to humanise it.  I appreciate where the Deputy is coming from.  A lot of the figures, facts, percentages and statistics tend to mask the reality and be a protective mechanism, and appear as such to us as public representatives.  Nonetheless, that is how systems are run and analysed and metrics have to be involved but I take on board the point and I accept what the Deputy has said.  Our job is to keep humanising it and bring to the fore real examples as the Deputy did, of the 86 year old lady who is in a bed and getting help six days a week but not the seventh day.  These are real challenges for the system.</p> <p>  The Deputy asked what can we expect from the &euro;850 million funding for primary care.  He made the point that if we are to move towards primary care and go along with Sl&aacute;intecare, which we all accept is the way forward, it will be important.  If we are going to put such emphasis on primary care we will have to fund it accordingly, which will be a real challenge, and the Deputy will appreciate this from his years of observing the health system and other areas where he has served.  The challenge will be in trying to reorient a system away from the here and now, and the day to day pressures on the demand-led scheme, and trying to pull funding back and reorient it into a new system.  It takes time and it is a huge challenge, and the very best we can really hope for is that a lot of it will be done with new funding, and that as new funding comes on stream, a larger proportion of it will go into primary care and this is how we will slowly and, hopefully, substantially build the funding to run it.  We are aware of the Sl&aacute;intecare report.</p> <p>  The Deputy made a point on requiring more GPs, and in my opening remarks I acknowledged that we will need up to 1,000 new GPs.  The GP contract and negotiations were mentioned by a number of members.  I understand negotiations with the IMO will recommence in the coming weeks.  They have been stalled since the end of last year.  They are due to commence with intensity and there is an expectation.  It is not for me to put a timeline on it, but I hope that by the end of the year significant progress will be made on this to substantially address the issues that are there.   There is the FEMPI issue about which the GPs are very vocal and there are a number of other issues.  The Government will make the point that in return for any additional funding new ways of doing business will be required along with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00200"><p>The IMO has already indicated that it is not in that space and it wants to talk about the reversal of FEMPI first and then any additional services.  I do not mean this disrespectfully in any way and I am sure that is not how the Minister of State will take it, but every time there is an intervention from a Minister or Minister of State we get further away from any possibility of there being any agreement on this.  The Minister of State does not have to take my word for it.  It is in the newspapers.  The GP service is in crisis.  Laying down markers such as this in advance of a negotiation while, at the same time, the Minister of State states he thinks it might be finished by Christmas, is pushing it further back every time.  I apologise for the interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00300"><p>The Chairman will appreciate I will not go into this type of discussion here.  I will not negotiate the GP contract across the floor with anybody or go into its details.  I have made some points on this.  I addressed the National Association of General Practitioners, NAGP, over the weekend and I am merely reiterating some of the points I made to the GPs there.  It is not in my gift.  I will not be leading those negotiations and neither would it be appropriate or helpful for me at this stage to start entering into such discussions at that level.</p> <p>  Deputy Kelleher also mentioned child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS, in Munster.  I am aware of the challenges, particularly in the Cork area.  One of the biggest issues we still have in mental health is recruitment, and we are blue in the face from listening to it on every Topical Issue and parliamentary question, but it is a fact.  If one always does what one always did, one always will get what one always got.  If we continue just to acknowledge that challenge and to struggle on, we will be in the same place for a long time to come.  My attitude as Minister of State with responsibility for mental health is to look at how we do what we do and look at a new way of doing it.  The future of mental health, from looking at international best practice and what is done abroad, is to look at online delivery of the service.  This is the space we need to go to.  It does not make sense for a consultant psychiatrist to leave Cork to travel to Castletownbere to see somebody given the amount of time it takes.  These are posing real challenges while we want to have a seven-day week service and availability in every area.  If we look at a model where somebody with a mental health issue can go into his or her local primary care centre where there is an interactive screen and he or she can speak to a mental health professional, whether a therapist, psychologist or psychiatrist and avail of the services online, that could be a new way to revolutionise and radically look at how we deliver online mental health services.  I have asked the HSE to trial the online delivery of mental health services and to select a primary care centre where we can start to trial this.  We need to consider this.</p> <p>  There is an ancillary issue, which is the management of waiting lists.  Various people manage their waiting lists in various ways.  There is huge disparity in various parts of the country where the numbers and percentages are broadly the same, such as 70% filling of posts and a certain number of people coming through, but there are various ways of managing it.  Every list must be prioritised on an immediate basis.  If someone presents with a serious mental health issue that person must be seen immediately.  I heard the report with Brian O'Connell yesterday to which the Deputy referred.  Nobody should be told he or she has to wait seven or 12 weeks.  There is supposed to be continuous prioritisation.  The consultant psychiatrist in charge of the team is supposed to look and assess.  There are various ways to do this to deliver the service.  I am aware of the issue and, ultimately, the solution will be to continue with this.  We should not, as politicians, continue to accept recruitment is a challenge.  It is a challenge, but there are ways around everything and the online space offers enormous potential.</p> <p>  Long-term planning for staffing is something on which a certain amount of work has been done by the HSE.  A staffing skill mix has been looked at and a review was launched recently into nursing in particular.  I also take the point that we should look at the challenges that will come from a range of illnesses that will present, such as obesity, diabetes and chronic illnesses, and not just look at particular skill sets.</p> <p>  Deputy O'Reilly raised the issue of scoliosis and the detailed action plan.  I will have to come back to her on that.  As she knows, there was an initiative last year and an additional &euro;10 million was put into it.  A new theatre was opened in Crumlin and its capacity is to be increased this year.  It went from carrying out 220 procedures in 2016 to 321 procedures in 2017, which is a 46% increase.  It will take time to catch up.  When one launches an initiative one does not get an immediate result and return.  It takes a bit of time.  Work is ongoing and I will get the Deputy more details on the action plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00400"><p>Does the figure include patients who were sent abroad or is it an increase in operations carried out in the State?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00500"><p>As I understand it, it is operations carried out at home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00600"><p>To be very clear, because we fall out sometimes and perhaps that is because the questions are not clear, I want details on when the plan will be published and information on how, precisely, the staffing arrangements will be organised for the increase in the number of days the theatre is open.  The plan is to increase it from three to five.  I would also like information on the timelines by which this will be achieved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#F00700"><p>I will ask the Minister to revert to Deputy O'Reilly directly on that.  I will address the rest of her questions as best I can, but a number of them are staffing related.  I know this is her background and interest but I cannot go into that level of detail as to how many staff are apportioned to new beds and what percentage will go on staffing.  These are operational matters and are done by the HSE.  They are not part of my remit in the Department.  If the Deputy wants to ask specific questions she can address them to me and I will ask the HSE to come back to her directly on them.  I believe the HSE will come before the committee on 6 May for its quarterly update, and its representatives will be better placed to address staffing issues.  They really do not come under my remit.</p> <p>  The Deputy sought a detailed breakdown regarding the &euro;5 million in respect of Storm Emma but I do not have it to hand.  I can ask somebody to come back to the Deputy on it.  Again, it is a HSE matter.  The Department will not prescribe where exactly the &euro;5 million will go.</p><p> We have already addressed the general practitioner negotiations and the salary of general practitioners.  I am not aware of what the Deputy described and would not be involved on that side of it.</p><p> On the staffing of new beds, 189 new beds have been opened but I would not be aware of the staffing arrangements for them or any future new beds.  Those will be operational matters for the HSE.  I am sure the HSE will answer those questions for the Deputy when its representatives appear before the committee on 7 May.</p><p> On the question on the additional &euro;530 million, the Deputy was wondering about the proportion for additional staff.  Again, I do not know.  I suppose the HSE has a standard.  I am not sure what it is.  In any new development, I assume staffing would be accommodated but I do not know.  I presume the HSE will answer that for the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00200"><p>These are the kinds of things the Minister of State should know.  If the Minister for Health says he is confident that a certain number of beds are to be opened or that a certain sum of money is to be put aside and the Minister of State then comes in and says he does not know what it will be spent on, it does not inspire a massive amount of confidence.  It certainly does not do so in me.  It will not inspire a massive amount of confidence among people waiting on these services.</p> <p>  I apologise for the interruptions.  I have asked several questions related to health expenditure but they cannot be answered.  I fully appreciate that the Minister of State is here to deputise for the Minister but it is not acceptable for him to say he does not believe it is the job of the Department or the Minister to answer.  Of course we will ask the HSE &mdash; we do so when its representatives appear before us.  On the one hand, the Minister of State is telling us a certain number of beds will be opened and that there will be plans for this and that but on the other hand, when he is asked for the detail, he says it is someone else's responsibility.  I do not believe that is acceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00300"><p>All I can do is repeat what I said to the Deputy.  I do not manage or micro-manage those operations at that level, even within my own area of responsibility.  It has nothing to do with whether the Minister, Deputy Simon Harris, or any Minister of State is here.  In my area, I do not micro-manage the system as suggested.  The HSE is in place to deliver the services.  It is an operational matter.  Some of the questions the Deputy has asked are clearly related to operational matters.  There are generic headline percentages that would be accommodated for any new development.  Of course staffing would be accounted for.  I cannot tell the Deputy how many staff will be required for each of the new 189 beds.  I cannot give that kind of detail.  I hope that is acceptable to the committee.</p> <p>  Deputy Margaret Murphy O'Mahony mentioned mental health and the great work of organisations such as Pieta House.  To go back to the answer I gave to Deputy Kelleher about mental health, I believe the issues and challenges are similar across the country.  Pieta House does wonderful work but it is funded by my Department, as is any such organisation.  One of the issues I referred to a number of times is that the organisations do wonderful work but I am concerned that there is a challenge when somebody with a mental health issue in west Cork or anywhere else wonders whether he should go to Pieta House, Jigsaw, Lisheens House in my constituency, the Samaritans or ChildLine.  On one's best day, it would be a challenge.  When one has a mental health issue and is feeling down when trying to figure out where to go, it is particularly challenging.  One of the objectives I have set is to ask the Department to lead with the HSE to put in place one single telephone number that people with a mental health issue can dial.  The number would be universal.  One would be assigned to the most appropriate service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00400"><p>The person answering the phone-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00500"><p>There would be a person answering the telephone who would be appropriately qualified to signpost where people should attend.  If one says one is Jim Daly from Clonakilty and has an ongoing feeling of anxiety in the stomach that has not gone away in two weeks-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00600"><p>It makes it easier on such people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00700"><p>The person answering the telephone would say the most appropriate thing would be to call to Jigsaw in Bandon, for example, rather than figuring it out oneself.</p> <p>  We are also examining the delivery of the solutions online and through texting facilities whereby people could text and receive a response.  A lot of our research shows that young people are much more comfortable texting than picking up the telephone and ringing.  These are developments we are considering and trying to grapple with.  A number of working groups have been set up within the HSE and the Department to drive forward this particular initiative so that there will be one single point of contact for those who wish to reach out to mental health services and which would refer one appropriately to the most suitable service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00800"><p>Does the Minister of State envisage that happening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G00900"><p>Every four or five weeks, I meet the groups to receive an update on the work.  There is a lot of work involved.  I hate setting a timeline because I may not be able to live up to it.  I am confident, however, that by the end of the year I will have very significant progress made on this, irrespective of whether the telephone number will be available then.  There are many challenges because existing services must be integrated and brought in under the new arrangement.  One is not just going to ignore the Samaritans and all such organisations, which have done superb work.  They must be brought in and an effort must be made to streamline the service.  We are meeting the challenges head-on.  There are some wonderful people working behind the scenes.</p> <p>  On waiting lists and Marian House, there is a challenge for the Department in respect of any of the organisations that are funded separately.  How they do their work comprises an ongoing challenge.  I will get Minister of State Deputy Finian McGrath to provide the Deputy with more detail on that, particularly on the waiting list at Marian House.  I will work with the Minister of State and we will send the Deputy a response on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G01000"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G01100"><p>The Deputy asked me about Bantry General Hospital.  I met the management there last Monday.  I met senior management from the South/South West Hospital Group.  There is a proposal, of which the Deputy has been very supportive, to develop the rehabilitation and endoscopy facilities.  Both projects have gone to the HSE and have been technically cleared.  They have proceeded to the Department and are in the mix for funding with hundreds of other applications for capital developments at various hospitals throughout the country.</p> <p>  As the Deputy will be aware, the operating theatre in Bantry General Hospital is open for only two and a half days per week.  I am very anxious to have it open for five days per week.  These are the kinds of solutions required in hospitals throughout the country, not just in Bantry General Hospital.  The smaller hospitals offer unique services.  Bantry hospital is unique because it is the only remote rural hospital in Ireland.  As the Deputy knows, it has a mixture of long-stay beds, continuing-care beds and acute beds.  It is very unusual.  We will continue to work with the HSE.  I will continue to try to get the theatre working for more than two and half days per week and to have more surgeons down from Cork, resulting in more outreach.  I will try to get the relevant services up and running.  That will contribute significantly to addressing the issues in Cork University Hospital.  Bantry hospital has enormous potential in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G01200"><p>The next to contributors are Deputies Kate O'Connell and Bernard Durkan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#G01300"><p>I thank Deputy Bernard Durkan for allowing me to contribute before him.  I have to leave shortly.  I thank the Minister of State for attending this morning.</p> <p>  The Minister of State spoke about online therapies.  This is interesting.  The Minister of State might follow up on what occurs in the other jurisdictions where these therapies are practised.  How are conditions triaged?  In recent years, our attitude to mental health has changed and there is not as much stigma attached to mental illness but I do not imagine that we or the Minister of State could say, hand on heart, that everybody from Bantry to Donegal is happy to talk about his or her mental health.  While I do regard the initiative as having value in taking pressure off the services, I wonder about the absence of the general practitioner.  General practitioners, who tend to have a whole-of-person approach to health care, note that if people's mental health is segregated to be dealt with by another entity, be it somebody online or a service in another jurisdiction, there is fragmentation.  We heard last week or the week before about fragmentation of services.  Having the general practitioner in the community as the anchor person for people's health care, be it physical or mental health care, has considerable value.  Is the pilot to complement existing services or to serve as an add-on, bearing in mind the increase in the diagnosis of mental health issues and the significant rate of prescription of antidepressants and such medications in Ireland at present?  We all know there are problems in the Irish health service.  I am not against the initiative but would be interested in knowing the international evidence supporting it.  How will it cascade down into the practical setting?</p> <p>  If general practitioners, in the first instance, and then psychiatrists are not seeing the genesis of mental illness and how it progresses in people's lives, will there be a deficit in education when it comes to health care professionals?</p><p>It is very hard to engage with some people when it comes to mental health.  Are we going down a road where the people most resistant to treatment will be segregated and we only sort out the people who have a willingness to engage?  I do not see how this will help that cohort of people who, whatever their personal or family circumstances, do not engage with the services.  Will the Minister of State outline that, perhaps after the meeting?  I would be very interested to hear where this is coming from.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#H00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and the statement and information he has given to the committee.  There are two or three things that came to my attention.  I am delighted to see the move towards programme budgeting.  One of my fetishes has always been comparison with the health boards, which always had programme budgeting.  Since that finished we do not seem to be able to go anywhere with certainty.  That has been one of the intrinsic problems in the health service over recent years.  It was a woefully bad decision to move away from that.  With programme budgeting, they can assess fairly regularly where they are going in the first, second, third or fourth quarter well in advance.  It cannot be done any other way because it is too vague.</p> <p>  In the area of home help carers and home care packages, there is a need for some co-ordination with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  The carer's allowance is the first step to deal with situations in which older people do not require institutional care or a home care package but can benefit from being looked in on by a friendly neighbour or family member.  They can have meals prepared at crucial times and can be looked in on in the morning and the late evening and so on.  Most families have done this themselves.  Modern labour force requirements do not allow that to happen to the same extent it used to.  I saw a file last week where a person caring for a person in his or her 90th year was deemed to be ineligible on the basis the person he or she was caring for was insufficiently immobile.  The presumption is that when the person tripped and fell and hit his or her head on something, he or she would become eligible.  It is then too late for that level of care and requires either hospitalisation or institutional care.  It is quite common, as the Chairman knows.  I would like some interaction between the two Departments in that area as a matter of some urgency.  It will not cost anything and it will dramatically improve the quality of life for those who need care and will relieve the pressure on the Department of Health.</p> <p>  Waiting times are another of my hobby horses.  There are waiting times for everything and I cannot understand it.  I will never begin to understand why we have them.  It is almost as if somebody decides to pick a time in the calendar and tell people they will deal with them then.  I do not accept it.  I think it is just as easy to tell a person he or she will be dealt with next week.  Waiting lists become longer and longer as time goes by.  It is an acute system.  We need a fairly rapid response.  If we are going to be successful we need a rapid response.  I am anxious that all areas where waiting times occur, whether as a result of a lack of theatre space, lack of adequately qualified nurses in theatre, consultants or GPs, waiting times have to stop because they go on forever.  It will have to be done.  The lists will have to be caught up with and overtaken.  The question of how to eliminate those waiting times is important.</p> <p>  I agree with Deputy O'Reilly on the GP contract.  We are long enough talking about it.  We need to see some progress but not in the future.  We are talking about waiting times again.  Why do we have to wait for that?  Why not do it now and have done with it?  At least then we would have some certainty in the future.  I do not want to talk about the procedure or negotiate here but it is not helpful to have a long waiting period in which we promise this in the future.  It has been long enough promised so we should get on with it and do it soon.  Let us produce something in the very near future that will indicate we are serious or not serious about it.</p> <p>  Deputy Louise O'Reilly referred to recruitment and I know the Minister of State may not want to comment on it.  Somebody approached me recently about the issue and will come back to me with further information.  There are some strange things happening in recruitment.  Administrators seem to be of greater importance than the front-line staff.  That should not be.  I know we have to have administrators but the fact is we are in a crisis and we need the people on the front line dealing directly with the patients.  We need them as a matter of urgency or else we are back to long waiting lists again and it will go on forever.</p> <p>  I have some questions for a different time.  There are a couple of little niggling parts that I am not too sure about, for instance, the issue of medical cards.  The number of full medical cards has dropped and there has been an increase in the number of GP visit cards.  We are a bit uneasy about it.  It is not always to the benefit of the patient.  I would like some comment on it.</p> <p>  I try to avoid being parochial at these meetings but when everybody else does it, I think I should do it.  My local hospital in Naas is in the picture.  The endoscopy unit extension is much wanted and has been for some considerable time.  I am anxious to clear the air, get it out of there, have it approved and get on with it.  There is also an oncology unit upgrade required as well.  It is a very busy hospital in a very important location.  To drag out what is required now only reduces the confidence of the staff in the hospital.  We need to avoid that.</p> <p>  The shortfall in the health budget has been reducing slowly but surely over recent years.  In 2014, it was something like &euro;600 million or &euro;700 million.  Gradually it has reduced to &euro;295 million or thereabouts.  Could we be coming to the spot where we can identify almost precisely what is required?  I referred already to programme budgeting.  I presume that as we move into that area, we should be able to get dead-headed budgeting.  We should not need to be vague.  A shortfall of &euro;600 million or &euro;700 million is way off target in terms of planning in advance.  If we are going to plan for the health services in advance, we need to be more precise about the exact cost, where it will come from and where it will go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#H00300"><p>I thank Deputy Durkan.  Before the Minister of State answers those questions, I will put a few questions to him.  The Minister of State referred quite often in his opening statement to the Sl&aacute;intecare report and the need for health reform and the shift from secondary hospital services to primary care services.  Is there anything in the Estimates to indicate there is a start in attempting to move from the expensive secondary care services to much more practical and efficient primary care services?  Will the Minister of State point out where that is in the Estimates?</p> <p>  There is also reference in the Minister of State's opening statement to the expansion of eligibility for medical cards and free care to those under six and those over 70.</p><p>There has been an expansion in delivering medical cards to people in receipt of disability allowance.  There is now a proposal to increase eligibility for those who receive carer's allowance.  However, there is limited capacity in general practice to deliver these services.  General practice is at its maximum, yet eligibility is increasing without any recognition that there is a huge manpower crisis.  I do not expect the Minister of State to negotiate the GP contract across the floor of the committee room this morning but there is huge difficulty relating to GP manpower.  The Minister of State would have heard it at the weekend.  How can we propose to shift from secondary care to primary care if we do not have the GPs to deliver the service?  General practice is at maximum capacity and many areas are facing the possibility of not having a GP at all.  Many practices have closed their lists.  We need to move to a new model of care and the GP negotiations are critical.  They have been ongoing for two years.  The Minister of State said they are a challenge and hope to deliver a contract by the end of the year but we have been listening to that for two years.  Perhaps the Minister of State could address the accelerators to develop that contract.</p><p> Every part of our health service is interconnected, so if we fail to invest in primary care, naturally, people will gravitate towards secondary care.  Therefore, we have trolley queues, increasing outpatient waiting lists and increased waiting lists for inpatient elective care, so there is a connection.  Will the Minister of State outline his view on how those interconnections can be changed so that primary care can relieve the pressure on our hospital service?</p><p> Will the Minister of State address bed capacity?  He identified a number of capital investments in his opening statement.  One of the proposals in Project Ireland 2040 was to build three elective hospitals which would just deal with elective care and would not be overwhelmed by patients coming in through casualty departments and displacing people who are waiting for elective treatment.  It is not mentioned in the Minister of State's opening statement but it is in Project Ireland 2040.</p><p> Model 2 hospitals are coming under severe pressure regarding recruitment and retention, particularly for nurses and medical specialists, because they are seen as unattractive places to work.  There is a huge number of consultant vacancies - up to 400.  Many of those are in model 2 and model 3 hospitals.  Certainly University Hospital Kerry in Tralee is under severe pressure at the moment because it is losing three of its major specialists and is having difficulty recruiting.  Ennis Hospital is having difficulty in recruiting geriatricians, so there is a difficulty in recruiting people in specific areas in our health service.  Perhaps the Minister of State might address that.</p><p> The Estimates contain an allocation of &euro;1 million to development the Sl&aacute;intecare office and the implementation office.  Will the Minister of State refer to how this is progressing?  Regarding the funding of our hospital services, &euro;670 million comes from private health insurance.  This figure seems to be dropping because private health insurance companies are encouraging patients who come through emergency departments not to designate themselves as private patients because it will not give them any additional care.  This is leading to a reduction in the amount of money coming from insurance companies to fund our public system.  The appropriation-in-aid part of the budget is &euro;460.2 million.  Will the Minister of State let me know what this funding consists of and where it comes from?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00200"><p>Will the Chairman repeat the last question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00300"><p>Appropriation-in-aid is &euro;460.2 million.  When it is added to the Vote, the total allocation for the health budget for the year comes to &euro;14.871 billion.  I want to know the detail of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00400"><p>Deputy O'Connell asked about online therapies.  She offered to have a conversation with me afterwards.  Shall I do that or does the Chairman want me to go through it on the record?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00500"><p>The Minister of State can go through it for the record if he likes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00600"><p>I was not 100% clear whether the Deputy was talking about the phone line or the online service.  I think she referred to the online service but when she spoke further, it was more about the phone line.  She said that it would be assumed that certainly the online delivery of any mental health therapy would done in primary care centres under the guidance of the GP.  I think she seemed to be concerned about that.  Of course, the GP would be central to a phone line but GPs face a challenge as well.  If someone presents to a GP, the GP is supposed to be an expert in every area when obviously they cannot be.  They are also expected to be up to date on the whole range of services so GPs would be central to directing people.  What I want to do is create that directory and signposting and make tools available to people regardless of whether people ring to find out the nearest available mental health support or go to their GP, who will also have immediate access to this directory and can direct people to the most appropriate means, because we do have an issue with people being referred.  Not every teenager who presents with a mental health issue, be it anxiety, stress or bullying, needs to go to CAMHS.  In some cases, they do not need to see a consultant psychiatrist.  There can be interventions at different levels, therapies, psychologists and so on.  It is about appropriateness and appropriate referrals but GPs will always remain central and will be the front door and first point of contact for people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00700"><p>I have a question about the phone number because it is very interesting.  The idea is that a person will ring in and will just be directed to the right service.  I could probably say something smart about the waiting list but I am not going to.  Will that person be qualified or will he or she be more of a telephonist?  If somebody rings up and says he or she anxiety, which I think was the example used by the Minister of State, that person would be directed to the service.  If somebody rings up and says he or she anxiety but actually that person might have something else, the person dealing with that could be an administrative person.  Is intended that this person would be a triage person or merely a telephonist?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#J00800"><p>Obviously, they are taking on a degree of responsibility when they are referring so they would need to have an appropriate qualification and they must be a triage person because they would have to be able to detect if it is much more serious than the person presenting says it is.  For example, has the person suicidal ideation?  The person at the other end of a phone line would need a level of qualification.  The challenge is actually making the directory of services available because a lot of these organisations are opening up and collecting money through voluntary activity.  Some of them are funded by the HSE while others are not.  We need to streamline that.  It is about creating the directory.</p> <p>  To answer Deputy O'Connell's concern, the GP will still be very central and the focus of all of this and will use this directory.  However, some people will choose to ring a phone line and not go to their GP, so we are trying to cover all angles.  Is it a complement or an add-on to existing services?  Again, it is both but it is mainly to complement the existing services.  Again, it is about how we do it, what we do and doing it better as opposed to continuing to do what we have always done.</p> <p>  Deputy Durkan asked about the presentation of budgets and programme heads.  I was in the Department during the week preparing for this meeting.  Some of the officials there mentioned to me that Deputy Durkan has been very consistent in his querying and challenge to have this presentation done.  The challenge is acknowledged and recognised.  Basically, it is a case of syncing the Department's accountancy practice with the HSE.  The HSE is developing a new model of financial accountancy and presentation.  Once that is done, the Department can tie into it.  I apologise that we are still on the outdated model this year but we live in hope.  Certainly Deputy Durkan's consistency in highlighting this has been acknowledged and recognised and has been instrumental in forcing the change to come about.</p> <p>  Deputy Durkan made a very interesting point about home help, carer's allowance and tying up between the two Departments.  It is something of which I am aware as a practising politician but I am not sure I was aware of it in my role in a Department as a Minister of State.  As the Deputy knows, we are trying to devise a statutory scheme to provide home care and to make sure that people can get it as a right as opposed to the current haphazard arrangement where a lot of it is down to a postal code lottery.</p><p>As things stand, a lot depends on waiting lists, queues etc.  We want a system similar to the fair deal scheme, where everybody is entitled to the service.  People will merely have to go through the formalities of the paperwork and they will get it.  To accomplish that, several challenges must be met.  Obviously we have to upskill the workforce and make sure it is sufficient to deliver the service.  We must also ensure that there is transparency and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00200"><p>The Department of Health must liaise with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  The two are very interconnected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00300"><p>As a result of Deputy Durkan's contribution today, I will certainly ensure that there is more liaison with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection as we progress that statutory scheme.</p> <p>  Waiting lists were referred to.  Why are there waiting lists?  I know the point being made.  Why can we not deal with everything today or tomorrow?  It is not all about money, but money helps.  It is about how we do what we do.  We allocated an additional &euro;85 million to deal with waiting lists for this particular winter.  Some &euro;40 million was allocated to winter initiatives.  A further &euro;11.6 million was allocated directly to waiting lists, and an additional &euro;35 million was allocated to the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, to source procedures outside of the State.  We could talk about why we have waiting lists all day.</p> <p>  I take the point that GP contracts have been waiting to begin for a while .  I am assured that they will begin very shortly.  In regard to recruitment, I am not sure what specific question was asked-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00400"><p>The question concerned administrators versus front-line staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00500"><p>I have heard that argument being made.  Senator Colm Burke makes much of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00600"><p>Unfortunately he cannot be here today but if he was, he certainly would be raising it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00700"><p>We have to be careful.  A lot of administrators are front-line staff.  People assume that administrators are people in back offices, pushing paper around.  However, they are involved in processing medical cards and things like that.  We must think carefully about whether we want to institute a pause on the hiring of administrators.  Deputies should feel free to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00800"><p>I am sorry to interrupt again.  Yes, that is true.  However, if we are beset by waiting lists, as we have been for many years now, there has to be some reason for it.  Maybe it is a shortage of administrators.  Maybe administrators are what we need.  I do not know, but I do know that we have to overhaul our waiting lists.  Otherwise we may as well close the shop altogether and go home.  The fact of the matter is this; if we cannot identify the snags in the system and resolve them, then we are wasting money, because time is money.  The costs of running the health service will be reduced very considerably if we can identify and remove those glitches.  It goes back to the old system.  We may ask, for example, how long one has to wait for the result of an X-ray, a scan or whatever.  One should not have to wait at all.  If time is money, then we need to know the results as quickly as possible.</p> <p>  I would emphasise this point.  Some time ago, the comparison between private sector and public sector hospitals was brought to my attention.  It appears that a consultant could work a full day in the private sector uninterrupted.  If they change over to the public sector the following week, they might have a day's work, but they might not.  That might be because some part of the system is not ready.  There may be insufficient staff in the theatre, theatres may be unavailable or whatever the case may be.  All of these are serious contributory factors that make the health service less efficient, and that is what we need to address. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K00900"><p>I take the Deputy's point on board, but I am not sure that there is any policy of focusing on additional administrative staff instead of front-line staff within the HSE.  I can only speak for myself however.  If we want to be pedantic about it and talk about what administrators do, I am sure they would argue that a lot of their time is spent dealing with the political process, that is, portraying accountability, openness and transparency.  Are we to cut back on that as well?  However, that is just an aside.</p> <p>  Deputy Durkan also asked about Naas General Hospital and its endoscopy unit.  That is part of the capital plan that is being developed at the moment.  As I said to my colleague about Bantry General Hospital, all of those projects are currently being progressed through the national capital plan within the Department and the HSE.  Deputy Durkan's enthusiasm and support for the project is noted.  </p> <p>  The Chairman asked about Sl&aacute;intecare, its development and where the corresponding proposal is included in the estimates.  An additional &euro;25 million has been allocated to primary care, which is part of that.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, has committed to bringing several specific proposals on Sl&aacute;intecare and its development to Cabinet in the next several weeks.  We will have to wait for those to come through the Cabinet before I can bring them to this committee.  Those proposals will answer the Deputy's questions about the specifics of Sl&aacute;intecare and progress thereon.  </p> <p>  On the technical side-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K01000"><p>That report was due at the end of December, and then due before Easter.  When is the next deadline?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K01100"><p>I do not know if the Cabinet is meeting in the next two weeks.  I understand that the Minister will bring specific proposals on developing Sl&aacute;intecare to Cabinet in the next three to four weeks.  An executive director will be appointed within the same period.  That recruitment process is substantially under way at the moment, and should be completed within the next three to four weeks.  The appointment of an executive director is the starting point for driving forward the proposals that are cleared by the Government.</p> <p>  The expansion of medical cards and GP practice were raised.  As the Chairman will be well aware, there is a proposal in the programme for Government to increase the number of training places for GPs to 259.  I appreciate that it takes so many years to train a GP.  The number of training places this year has increased to 190, up from 120 trained last year.  There were 400 applications last year for those 190 training places.  That is a significant increase.  The future in the medium term looks reasonably promising, notwithstanding the challenge involved in bridging the time before those people become GPs.</p> <p>  On the topic of recruitment, I note-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K01200"><p>I wish to respond before the Minister of State leaves that topic.  Increasing the number of training places for GPs does not actually address the manpower issue.  We are training GPs in order that they will emigrate because no young aspiring GP will sign the existing GP contract.  Nobody who is recently qualified is signing a new GP contract.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#K01300"><p>We must be careful not to talk the GP career down to new aspiring candidates.  My own son was with me at the event last weekend, and he told me he would love to be a GP.  We have to ensure that we protect the future.  These efforts will be made in tandem.  We must increase the number of training places.  We cannot simply state that all new GPs will all emigrate and throw our hat at the issue.  However, we also have to reform the contract.  We must make it fit for purpose and make it an attractive career.  Those goals must be pursued together and I think the Chairman and I both recognise that.  It is not a case of doing one or the other.</p> <p>  I was recently in New Zealand, representing the country on St. Patrick's Day.  I was amazed to hear New Zealanders tell me of their high regard for the Irish medical workforce.  They see it as incredibly talented and well trained, which we can be very proud of.  They had one difficulty, however; they cannot retain these workers.  They all want to go back home.  This is the issue they are experiencing on the other side of the world.  Irish professionals come for a short while, but they do not commit.  They are not willing to stay.  That includes different disciplines, including nurses, GPs, physiotherapists and everything in between.  That is the other side to this.  The New Zealanders said to me that the Irish workforce is very mobile, even in the far-off countries to which they go.  They do not necessarily settle there but they like to go for a while.  That has always been part of the Irish psyche and make-up. </p> <p>  Bed capacity and ambulatory care have been referred to.  The move towards ambulatory care is a part of the national development plan.  It informs the decisions on where to locate elective procedures and where those hospitals will be built.  They will always be connected and related to the acute hospital but those decisions are being taken.</p> <p>  Recruitment for model 2 hospitals has been raised.  The questions mentioned are challenges for Kerry General Hospital and Bantry General Hospital.  This is a particular challenge for remote hospitals, model 2 hospitals and some model 3 hospitals.  The South/South West hospital group is currently undertaking a review of all its consultants and their particular skill sets to see where the demand is more acute and attempt to find solutions.</p><p>I discussed it with the hospital group on Monday of this week.  It assured me that the review would be completed within the next two to three months and that it would devise proposals to deal with the consultant challenges that have been mentioned.  I expect a number of recommendations from the South/South West hospital group, which I suspect will be replicated nationally.</p><p> I do not have information on insurance companies to hand but I can get someone to revert to the Chairman on the issue.</p><p> As to the &euro;460.2 million figure of appropriations-in-aid, the recovery of cost of health services provided under EU regulations is &euro;280 million and the receipts from certain excise duties on tobacco is &euro;167.605 million.  They are the main components.  There are a number of others, including recoupment from social insurance for certain ophthalmic and dental treatments, miscellaneous receipts, the Dormant Account Fund, which is &euro;2.7 million, and receipts from pension-related deductions in public service remuneration, which is &euro;3.9 million, but the bulk of the figure relates to the recovery of cost of health services provided under EU regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  Do Deputies Murphy O'Mahony and O'Reilly have further questions for him?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00300"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00400"><p>When I asked specific questions about scoliosis, the Minister of State undertook to revert to me.  Will he do that as soon as possible?  People have been waiting a long time and they want to get a few answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00500"><p>I will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending to review the Revised Estimates.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.65" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00700">Message to Dail</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HES2018032800002#L00800"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 90, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Committee on Health has considered the following Revised Estimate for public services for the year ending 31 December 2018: Vote 38 - Health.</blockquote> <p>Under Standing Order 89(2), the message is deemed to be the report of the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.67" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 10.42 a.m. sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.68" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="">Select Committee on Justice and Equality</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.69" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 09:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Colm Brophy, Deputy Charles Flanagan (Minister for Justice and Equality), Deputy Jack Chambers, Deputy Jim O'Callaghan, Deputy Clare Daly, Deputy Mick Wallace.</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Donnchadh  Laoghaire.</p><p>DEPUTY CAOIMHGHN  CAOLIN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.70" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A00100">Domestic Violence Bill 2017 [Seanad]: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A00200"><p>All mobile phones, including the Cathaoirleach's, need to be switched off as they cause interference with the recording equipment.  This meeting has been convened to consider Committee Stage of the Domestic Violence Bill 2017.  On behalf of the Select Committee on Justice and Equality, I welcome the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Charles Flanagan, and his officials.  I invite the Minister to make any opening remarks he may wish to make.  If not, we will proceed to address the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A00300"><p>I am pleased to be here this morning to address this important reforming legislation, the Domestic Violence Bill.  Members will be aware that there was considerable debate on this Bill in the Upper House, following which a number of amendments were made.  Members will be aware of the fact that this Bill has been the subject of debate for some time, published as it was in February of last year.  I would hope that we could have constructive engagement.  We do not have too many amendments.  I acknowledge the co-operation of Members of the committee and the input of its members on Second Stage.  I hope that we might be in a position to conclude matters this morning.  I wish to assure Members of my consideration of any points made.  I would like if we could move matters in such a way that we could report progress in a couple of hours or perhaps even complete the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A00400"><p>I thank the Minister.  Before moving on to the business, just as I noted the Minister's hope for constructive engagement, I would like him, members of the committee and anyone else who is interested to note that we always conduct our legislative business in a constructive fashion.  There have been no exceptions to that at any time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A00500"><p>Are you sure you are the Chair, now?  I thought Deputy John McGuinness was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A00600"><p>There you are.  There is no end of people who might covet the role.  We will proceed to section 1 of the Bill.  There are no amendments on section 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.76" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.77" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A01000"><p>Amendment No. 1 is grouped with amendments Nos. 15 and 16 and they will be discussed together.  Amendment No. 1 is in the Minister's name.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A01100"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 6, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:&ldquo; &ldquo;civil proceedings under this Act&rdquo; means&mdash;<br /><br />(a) proceedings relating to an application for the making, variation or discharge of a safety order, a barring order or an emergency barring order,<br /><br />(b) proceedings, consequent on the making of an application for a barring order, for the making, variation or discharge of an interim barring order which relates to the application,<br /><br />(c) proceedings, consequent on the making of an application for a safety order or a barring order, for the making, variation or discharge of a protection order which relates to the application,<br /><br />(d) proceedings by way of appeal or case stated which are related to proceedings to which<i>paragraph (a), (b) </i>or<i>(c) </i>applies;&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>For the record, I am not one of those who covets the Chairman's role.  I had it 20 years ago.  I enjoyed it and I wish him well for the remainder of his term here.  Amendment No. 1 is a technical amendment to section 2.  It provides for a definition of civil proceedings under the Act, which is a term used throughout the Bill.  This was the definition that was included in the Act of 20 years ago when I was Chair of the committee.  It was inadvertently omitted from section 2 of the Bill, as published, and this amendment merely proposes to reinstate it.  Amendments Nos. 15 and 16 are technical amendments which improve the clarity of sections 25 and 27 which relate to civil proceedings under the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A01200"><p>If nobody has a contribution regarding the Minister's proposal or amendments Nos. 15 and 16, which are also in his name, I will proceed to a decision on amendment No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.81" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A01350"><p>Amendment No. 2 is grouped with amendments Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, 19 and 20.  These are all in the Minister's name and I invite him to address this grouping.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#A01400"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 7, between lines 29 and 30, to insert the following:&ldquo;(3) For the avoidance of doubt, a relationship does not cease to be an intimate relationship for the purposes of this Act by reason only that it is no longer sexual in nature.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Deputies will recall that during Second Stage in the House and during the Seanad debates, certain issues were raised about the use of the term &quot;intimate and committed relationship&quot; in the provisions that specify who may apply for orders under the Bill.  I also know that groups such as Women's Aid have expressed concerns about the issue in a formal submission on the Bill.  The background to the matter is that section 60 of the Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2011 introduced access to domestic violence orders for persons living together in intimate and committed relationships, replacing the provisions of the Domestic Violence Act 1996 that applied to persons living together as husband and wife.  The intention was that same-sex couples who were not civil partners would have the same access to the protections under the 1996 Act as opposite-sex unmarried couples.  The wording was taken from the definition of cohabitant in section 172 of the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010.  The term &quot;intimate and committed relationship&quot; was framed to provide a threshold to which the court must have regard in deciding whether to make an order.  While concerns raised by voluntary sector groups about the suitability of the wording were given careful consideration, it was decided to proceed with the amendment unchanged.</p><p>I have considered this matter further in consultation with the Office of the Attorney General.  I am of the view that it would not be in the interest of victims of domestic violence if perpetrators could try to avoid having orders made against them by arguing that the relationship was not committed, for example, because of their sexual activity with a third party, or because the victim of the violence had previously sought to end the relationship.  This is particularly relevant to safety orders now that section 6(1)(<i>a</i>) of the Bill will remove the cohabitation requirement for couples who are not married or, indeed, couples who may not be in a civil partnership.  Amendments Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, 19 and 20 provide that the term &quot;intimate and committed relationship&quot;, where it applies in the Bill, will be amended to delete the words &quot;and committed&quot;.  To ensure protection for victims of domestic violence who are or were in an intimate relationship which is no longer sexual in nature, amendment No. 2 proposes to make clear that a relationship does not cease to be an intimate relationship for the purposes of the Bill merely because it is no longer sexual in nature.  The text of the amendment is drawn from section 172(3) of the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B00200"><p>I support and welcome that change in the definition.  It was raised at length in the Seanad, and I commend the Minister and the Department for taking it on board.  My colleague, Senator Rose Conway-Walsh, raised it on a number of occasions during the debate, and I want to acknowledge that.  Returning to a point I made at Second Stage, I acknowledge that the engagement of numerous organisations, in particular SAFE Ireland, Women's Aid Ireland and the National Women's Council of Ireland, has been very successful in improving this Bill considerably and I commend them for that.  This is a further example of the efforts of those organisations.  It is an appropriate change to the definition, one that is required and improves protections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B00300"><p>I, too, want to acknowledge the points raised on this issue by Members of the Upper House and by the groups mentioned.  In particular, I acknowledge the support of Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.87" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.88" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.89" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.90" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B00700"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 9, line 21, to delete &ldquo;and committed&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.92" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.93" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 6, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.94" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B01100"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 11, line 25, to delete &ldquo;and committed&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.96" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.97" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 7, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.98" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 8 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.99" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B01600"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p><blockquote>In page 16, line 12, to delete &ldquo;and committed&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.101" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B01800"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 are related may will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B01900"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p><blockquote>In page 16, to delete lines 16 and 17 and substitute the following:&ldquo;(2) The court may only make an order under this section in respect of a place where an<br /><br />applicant or a dependent person resides and where&mdash;&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>The purpose of these amendments is merely to improve the clarity of the provisions of section 9 in the matter of applications for emergency barring orders.  They are self-explanatory and I do not intend to say anything further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.104" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B02100"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p><blockquote>In page 16, line 22, to delete &ldquo;Where the court, on application to it under subsection (2), is of the opinion&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Subject to subsection (2), where the court, on application to it, is of<br /><br />the opinion&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.106" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.107" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 9, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.108" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 10</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B02500"><p>Amendments Nos. 8, 9 and 14 are related may be discussed together.  I should point out that an amendment in the Minister's name proposes to delete the section to which amendments Nos. 8 and 9, in the names of Deputy Mick Wallace and Deputy Clare Daly, respectively, apply.  I do not know whether the Minister's position regarding section 10 has a particular impact on the positions of Deputy Wallace or Deputy Daly regarding same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B02600"><p>We will make a few points and consider where we are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B02700"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><blockquote>In page 18, line 23, after &ldquo;communicating&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;by telephone or secure electronic means&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B02800"><p>The two amendments tabled by Deputy Wallace and I try to do the same thing.  They attempt to provide a remedy for women in situations where they need an emergency barring order in the evening or late at night when the courts are closed.  Obviously, we can envisage such scenarios and we want to avoid a situation where somebody could effectively be driven out of their home in the middle of the night and have no recourse and nowhere to go.  This was discussed at length in the Seanad, and the Government said it would look at it again.  The Minister's proposal is the Government's re-examination of the matter, and I welcome that there has been some movement on it.  By deleting the section, the Minister's proposal provides for special sittings of the District Court to issue emergency or interim barring orders after hours.  We welcome that.  The point we are trying to highlight, however, is that there are practical problems associated with that.</p> <p>  Firstly, there is the issue of cost.  There is a call-out charge payable to judges on each occasion where there is an out-of-hours hearing, and obviously there are costs related to opening the court, staffing it, closing it afterwards, etc.  Having consulted with members of domestic violence support services, the opinion of SAFE Ireland is that actually these hearings are rarely convened, for whatever reason.  I suppose it is speculating that it is for reason of cost.  Why is it that these hearings are rarely convened or rarely happen?</p> <p>  Other practical issues arise around a woman's ability to make her way to an emergency court sitting in the middle of the night when she lacks child care and so on.  I appreciate the Government is trying to address these problems.  I am not sure that our answer is the right one either.  However, these issues need to be looked at.  We have obligations under the Istanbul Convention.</p> <p>  The worry is that the Government's proposal might make it appear that there is a provision for out-of-hours emergency barring orders, but the practical reality would be that they would be out of reach to women.  Our amendments allow for a garda to make application for an order by telephone in an emergency situation.  The woman can then appear and swear an affidavit the next day and the issue can be dealt with that way.  I do not think it is a brilliant solution, but it is an attempt to overcome that problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#B02900"><p>My amendment is quite similar.  It is clear that there is no perfect solution.  We are trying to avoid a situation where the victim is obliged to stay in the house with a possible abuser, and that for various reasons there is no quick remedy.  I am not so sure.  I would like to hear from the Minister.</p><p>As amendment No. 14 may address it, let us see what the Minister has to say.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#C00200"><p>What we are providing for is that in the absence of the hearing, a Garda could ring or email an out-of-hours judge and get the emergency barring order instead of the hearing that is being sought the next day or afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#C00300"><p>I now invite the Minister to address this grouping.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#C00400"><p>I acknowledge the importance of the points raised by Deputies Wallace and Clare Daly.  I know where they are coming from and am familiar with the issue.  Unfortunately, it is an issue that arises from time to time and does present difficulties.  I acknowledge the Seanad amendments, particularly those in the name of Senators Ruane and Black.  I do not see how I can go along in its entirety with the point raised by the Deputies for reasons that are not only obvious but appropriate.  The section provides that on request from a garda attending a domestic violence incident, a garda of appropriate rank can authorise communicating with an on-call judge to apply for an out-of-hours barring order.  There is always an on-call judge.  That is not an issue.  Judges are rostered and are on call to expect appropriate calls for sittings and action.  My officials, in consultation with the Courts Service, the Garda and the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel, have examined section 10 to see what improvements and adjustments may be needed to the text.  Amendment No. 14 proposes a new section 25, as referred to by Deputy Wallace, to provide for the arrangement of the out-of-hours sitting.  The new section will apply to applications for interim barring orders, protection orders and emergency barring orders but would be limited to cases where a garda actually attended an incident.  It is broad enough to include cases where a victim of domestic violence walks into a Garda station to immediately seek assistance or to seek immediate assistance.  I am proposing that this new section, which has been drafted by the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel, would replace the current section 10.  To my mind, the new section is legally clearer and will be workable on the part of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Courts Service.</p><p>I have a problem with amendments Nos. 8 and 9.  The interests of justice demand that the court has an opportunity to assess the case fully and the demeanour of the applicant for any order on a face-to-face basis.  This is where I have a difficulty in respect of telephone calls, emails or what might be regarded as a less regular point of view.  We must remember that these applications are being made on an <i>ex parte</i>basis and only one side is being heard.  The respondent may not even be around and will not be on notice.  Consequently, I do not believe it appropriate or proportionate to allow for a telephone call or an email application for a barring order from anyone, given the serious consequences for the respondent and the likelihood that this person would be immediately barred from the property.  Allowing applications to be made by telephone - allowing applications that might be made in a rather casual manner where it would be really difficult to verify the identity of the applicant - would give rise to serious problems.  I also believe there could well be applications of a mischievous nature or even worse, applications of a malicious nature by parties with an involvement here.  The sections of the Bill that provide for different orders do not provide for applications for such orders to be made by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Applications are to be made by the person who will be the subject matter of the order and who will ultimately benefit from the order except in certain cases where the Child and Family Agency may make an emergency application as provided for in section 12.  I have a concern that even if the amendments were to accepted, which I am not minded to do, they do not set out any criteria or threshold for a court to determine that a telephone call or electronic application would be appropriate in a particular case.  In conclusion, where there are cases in which there is an immediate risk of harm, the new section 25 proposed to be inserted by amendment No. 14, which provides for the special court sitting on an emergency basis, will resolve the fundamental issue for victims of domestic violence, which is really quick access to court and a speedy hearing all, of course, in exceptional circumstances having regard to the fact that we are dealing with an emergency application in the first instance.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#C00500"><p>I find it difficult to understand section 10 as it is drafted.  It talks about a garda of appropriate rank.  It does not specify or define what appropriate rank is.  It then talks about how such a garda can authorise communicating with a on-call judge.  As it does not say who they authorise, I do not understand the purpose behind it.  If an applicant wishes to make an application to a judge, they can do so on an emergency basis.  I think section 10 as drafted is a bad piece of drafting.</p><p>Deputy Wallace's amendment aims to limit the communication to telephone or secure electronic means.  On a lot of previous occasions, people would just call to a judge's house and get an <i>ex parte</i>order, which has happened previously, so I would be concerned.  While section 10 is badly drafted and should be deleted, the amendment would limit the communication even more because communication includes telephone or secure electronic means but it would limit it to these means were Deputy Wallace's amendment to be accepted.</p><p>I have the same concerns about Deputy Clare Daly's amendment because it provides it &quot;may be made by telephone or other secure electronic means, subject to the applicant&rsquo;s undertaking to swear a grounding affidavit&quot;.  Obviously, the situation with which people are dealing here arises is the middle of the night when there is an issue and the Garda is called.  If the members of the Garda believe the husband has assaulted the wife, they should and can arrest him for a criminal offence.  That is what should happen.  I share the Minister's concerns about people being able to simply apply easily for an <i>ex parte</i>order to get a barring order to get somebody out of the house in the middle of the night.  Obviously, if there is any evidence of violence, the Garda should intervene and arrest the person suspected of violence but aside from that, section 10 confuses the whole issue.  I would take it out.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#C00600"><p>What we are both trying to deal with is a situation similar to the powers the Garda has relating to children who are at risk, which we discussed at length in this committee, whereby the Garda is given exceptional powers to intervene in an immediate situation.  This was similar, although I take Deputy O'Callaghan's point that the Garda could simply arrest the person.  However, there may not have been the level of violence that would warrant an arrest.  I am not sure.  The Minister said that anyone could ring up and it could be malicious or vexatious.  I find myself in the unusual position where I am in staunch defence of the members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  We are not talking about just anybody ringing up.  We are talking about a call made by a garda who is on the scene, who has assessed the situation and who believes there is a requirement to remove the violent party from the home dwelling.  Rather than requiring a sitting of the District Court, we propose that such a garda be authorised to simply get the permission of the judge in the immediate situation by phone or email.  It was certainly not our intention to preclude members of the Garda from calling out to the judge if that is what they wanted to do instead.  Our intention was to ward off the idea of cost or logistics preventing the special sitting of the court referred to by the Minister.</p><p>Maybe we have not got the wording right and we might need to look at it again on Report Stage.  I agree there are issues.  I am a little uncomfortable with emergency barring orders being issued <i>ex parte</i>and in the physical absence of the applicant.  If the Government could give a commitment to ensure the out-of-hours sittings for emergency barring orders either do not incur a cost or that the cost would be covered, that would give some reassurance to overcome the deficit with which we are trying to deal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00200"><p>SAFE Ireland raised this point.  What happens if there are children involved?  How long might it take for the court to sit on the matter?  What are the costs involved?  If garda&iacute; at an incident see an unsavoury situation, they should arrest the man involved.  However, that generally does not happen and there are reasons for that too.  There is no easy solution to it.  I will not press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00300"><p>We need to look at the redrafted version with the section deleted and the other amendment inserted.  I acknowledge there has been some movement since the Seanad debated this issue.  We will look at it again on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00400"><p>I am anxious to meet the concerns portrayed by the Deputies.  However, I need to do so in a clear and proportionate manner.  I take Deputy O'Callaghan's point about section 10.  I and the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel are on the same page on this and want to ensure that adjustments are made to bring about improvement to the text.  I will examine it again because what we need is clarity, particularly in emergency situations, which are often in the middle of the night involving a tense atmosphere.</p> <p>  We must also ensure we do not blur the distinction between the role of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the role of the judge in these cases, as well as the need to separate entirely the judgment call of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in terms of the urgency of the situation and the role of the member of the Judiciary in deciding a case on certain circumstances.  I will examine the wording of section 10 again to ensure there is clarity.</p> <p>  As far as costs are concerned, I do not see that as an issue.  There is a roster of duty judges for emergency situations.  These are not hearings which take much time.  They can be dealt with speedily having regard to the circumstances, urgency and importance of the cases involved.  Oftentimes they are heard at short notice in the residence of the district judge.  Costs are not really an issue and I would not like it to be portrayed that emergency court hearings are in some way not accommodated because of financial considerations.</p> <p>  These are serious and emergency issues.  Unfortunately, they are becoming more frequent.  The law must respond to the needs of the citizens and the public.  That is why my feeling on section 10 is that it needs considerable improvement.  We must see what we can do between now and Report Stage, particularly in the area of clarity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00500"><p>The Minister proposes to delete section 10.  In his amendment No. 14, which involves a replacement section, he proposes a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na not below the rank of sergeant may request the Courts Service to arrange a special sitting of the District Court.  In an ideal world, we might have a sergeant in every Garda station but we do not, which might limit this proposal.  Section 10 does not contain such a threshold.  Will the Minister clarify this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00600"><p>I would not like to see a situation develop where a garda at an emergency situation feels he or she is not of an appropriate rank to make a call or the Garda rank required is not on duty and the case goes unattended.  It is a valid point and we will look at it.  It is important, however, that the attending officer is of sufficient rank to be in a position to make this call.  I will re-examine the areas of the garda attending or a garda with sufficient knowledge to be in a position to exercise that call before Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00700"><p>Deputy Jack Chambers made a good point.  It goes back to the training and education of garda&iacute;.  We are well aware that matters could be better in that area.  Any garda attending such a scene should be trained to deal with it in a good way.  That is not rocket science.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00800"><p>Yes, I suspect the Chair will not allow me to digress into discussing Garda resources but &euro;1.6 billion is allocated for training.  I agree training and expertise are issues.  There are ongoing retraining programmes to ensure we have best practice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D00900"><p>It is unfortunate, however, that the guy heading Templemore college is subject to two inquiries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D01000"><p>We are digressing now.  For the record, we are always interested in the resourcing of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.130" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#D01200"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p><blockquote>In page 18, line 24, after &quot;order&quot; to insert the following:&quot;and, where necessary, out of hours where the applicant and any dependent children are at risk of immediate harm. If the order is not made in this way, such an application may be made by telephone or other secure electronic means, subject to the applicant's undertaking to swear a grounding affidavit or information before the next available ordinary sitting of the court&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.132" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.133" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 10 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.134" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 11 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.135" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 19</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00200"><p>Amendments Nos. 10 and 11 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00300"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p><blockquote>In page 24, to delete lines 14 to 17.</blockquote> <p>Section 20 of the Bill provides for copies of the orders under the Act to be given to various persons, including the respondent, by the court.  These provisions are included in section 20.  Order 59, rule 10, of the District Court rules provides that the clerk of the court shall give a copy of the order under the Domestic Violence Act to the respondent or send it to him or her by prepaid post.  This is set out in the District Court domestic violence rules in SI 202 of 2005.  It should be noted that if a respondent is present in the court when an order is made he or she will have been notified of the order.  This is provided for in section 19 of the Bill, which replaces section 10 of the 1996 Act.</p><p>A new subsection (3) was inserted into section 19 on Committee Stage in the Seanad, on foot of an amendment tabled by Senator David Norris and others.  The new subsection provides for the service of orders by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  My officials, in consultation with the Court Service, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel, have examined section 19(3) to see what further improvements and adjustments might be needed by the text.  Amendment No. 11 proposes to insert a new subsection (5) into section 19, to provide that a court may direct personal service of an order by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  This will apply in cases where the respondent was not present, where the order was made in the absence of the respondent and where there are reasonable grounds for believing he or she may evade service, or where there is a good and sufficient reason to direct that an order be served by a garda.  I propose the new subsection (5), which has been drafted by the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel, would replace the current subsection (3).  Amendment No. 10, therefore, proposes the deletion of the current subsection (3).</p><p>Are we dealing with amendment No. 11 also?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00400"><p>Yes please, it is in the grouping.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00500"><p>The points I have made cover amendment No. 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00600"><p>Would any member like to make an observation or question anything in relation to this grouping?  There are no takers, and the Minister has nothing further to add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00700"><p>I take the silence as support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00800"><p>The Minister takes the silence as assent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E00900"><p>I do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01000"><p>Be careful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01100"><p>I rarely get it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01200"><p>The Minister should be careful what he wishes for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01400"><p>This is the justice and equality committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01500"><p>I will not say any more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.150" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E01700"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p><blockquote>In page 24, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:&quot;(5) A court may direct that a relevant order be served personally by a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na on a respondent who is not present at a sitting of the court at which the order is made in any case where&mdash;<blockquote>(a) there are reasonable grounds for believing that the respondent may evade service of the order, or<br /><br />(b) there is any other good and sufficient reason to so direct.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.152" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.153" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 19, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.154" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 20 to 22, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.155" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 23</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02200"><p>Amendments Nos. 12 and 13 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02300"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p><blockquote>In page 27, lines 4 to 11, to delete all words from and including &quot;The&quot; in line 4 down to and including line 11 and substitute the following:&quot;The jurisdiction of the court in respect of civil proceedings under this Act may be exercised&mdash;<blockquote>(a) as regards the Circuit Court, by the judge of the Circuit Court within whose circuit, and<br /><br />(b) as regards the District Court, by a judge of the District Court for the time being assigned to the district court district within which,</blockquote>the applicant resides or, if the application is for a barring order or an emergency barring order, the place, in relation to which that application was made, is situated.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>Amendment No. 12 is a technical amendment to improve the clarity of section 23(1) of the Bill, which provides for the geographical jurisdiction of the District Court and Circuit Court in civil proceedings under the Bill.  The proposed new text of section 23(1) makes it clear that jurisdiction of the District Court under the Bill can be exercised by any judge who is assigned to the relevant district.  As regards amendment No. 13, I am advised that deletion of section 23(2) is necessary to ensure compliance with the principle that the District Court exercises jurisdiction by reference to districts.  This principal has been the subject of case law in the Supreme Court since the 1996 Act was enacted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02400"><p>Would any member like to offer an opinion or comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02500"><p>I was a bit unclear as to why it was proposed.  Originally the provision stated if a District Court judge was not available people could go to any District Court, but now we are saying they cannot and there is a legal impediment as to why this is the case.  I could not understand why the change was being made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02600"><p>This is something we need to look at in the longer term.  I have been discussing the whole basis of the jurisdiction of the District Court under current divisions and whether we might update and modernise District Court jurisdiction to allow for a broader jurisdiction.  At present, the judge of the District Court is the person who is assigned to the appropriate district.  If that person is not available there is an issue to ensure the temporary assignee has an association with that district.  It has been enshrined in our courts legislation for many decades.  Obviously, we want to ensure there is full compliance and there are not any legal or jurisdictional issues.  This is why the amendments are necessary, to avoid any doubt or legal uncertainty that might arise in the context of an application made or having been made, or a consequent or subsequent judicial review or action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02700"><p>Before going back to Deputy Clare Daly, the Minister has indicated this is something he has been considering, and he suggested in the long term.  Is he looking at it in the context of this legislation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02800"><p>No, I am not.  I am looking at it in the context of the broader District Court and its jurisdiction in the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E02900"><p>It is not something the Minister will necessarily-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03000"><p>It is not peculiar to this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03100"><p>-----close on in this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03200"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03300"><p>I thought that would be informative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03400"><p>I get it.  It is part of a bigger problem.  I thought it was peculiar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03500"><p>Does any other member wish to comment?  Does the Minister have anything further to add before we go to a decision on these amendments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03600"><p>It is a mere technical amendment to ensure certainty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.171" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E03800"><p>I move amendment No. 13:</p><blockquote>In page 27, to delete lines 15 to 17.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.173" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.174" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 23, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.175" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 24 agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.176" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E04200"><p>I move amendment No. 14:</p><blockquote>In page 27, after line 36, to insert the following:<b>&quot;Special sitting of District Court</b><br /><br /><b>25.</b>(1) A member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na not below the rank of sergeant may request the Courts Service to arrange a special sitting of the District Court for the purposes specified in <i>subsection (2)</i>&mdash;<blockquote>(a) where a person has informed the member that he or she wishes to make an application referred to in <i>paragraph (a)</i>of that subsection, and<br /><br />(b) at the time the person so informs the member, there is no District Court sitting in the district court district in which that person would make such an application if that court was sitting.</blockquote>(2) The purposes referred to in <i>subsection (1)</i>are&mdash;<blockquote>(a) to facilitate the making and determination of an application for an interim barring order, an emergency barring order or a protection order, and<br /><br />(b) where necessary for the purposes of an application referred to in <i>paragraph (a)</i>, to facilitate the making of an application for a safety order or a barring order.</blockquote>(3) The Courts Service may, with the consent of a judge of the District Court exercising jurisdiction in accordance with <i>section 23</i>, arrange such special sittings of the District Court in the district court district referred to in <i>subsection (1)(b)</i>as may be necessary for the purposes specified in <i>subsection (2)</i>.<br /><br />(4) In this section, &quot;special sitting&quot; means a sitting of the District Court at a place and time not standing appointed for the time being under section 26 of the Courts of Justice Act 1953 or section 40 or 42 of the Courts (Supplemental Provisions) Act 1961 for the transaction of the business of the District Court.&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.178" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.179" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 25</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#E04500"><p>I move amendment No. 15:</p><blockquote>In page 28, lines 2 and 3, to delete &quot;In an application for a safety order, a barring order, an interim barring order, an emergency barring order or a protection order,&quot; and substitute &quot;In civil proceedings under this Act,&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.181" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.182" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 25, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.183" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 26 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.184" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 27</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#F00300"><p>I move amendment No. 16:</p><blockquote>In page 28, line 35, to delete &ldquo;In proceedings under this Act, other than proceedings for&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;In civil proceedings under this Act, other than proceedings for the making of&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.186" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.187" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 27, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.188" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 28 to 32, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.189" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 33</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#F00800"><p>I move amendment No. 17:</p><blockquote>In page 31, to delete lines 11 and 12 and substitute the following:&ldquo;commits an offence and is liable&mdash;(i) on summary conviction, to a class A fine or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 12 months, or both, or<br /><br />(ii) on conviction on indictment to a fine not exceeding &euro;10,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 5 years, or both.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Generally when there is a breach of a court order the remedy is for the applicant or the person affected to bring an application for attachment and committal.  That obviously places a lot of obligations and burdens on the applicants.  The fact that it is specified in section 33 that it is an offence to contravene a safety order, a barring order or the other orders set out in the legislation is to be welcomed.</p><p>This amendment is probably unusual.  It seeks to make the offence of breach of a court order not just a summary offence but also an indictable offence, based on the serious nature of the breach.  If it is an offence that is prosecuted on indictment there would be a further penalty.  I am conscious of the fact that breaches of court orders are not offences, so I welcome the fact this is being made an offence without prejudice to the fact that contempt of court jurisprudence will still operate.  I am interested in what the Minister has to say in response to the proposal that it be an offence prosecutable on indictment as well as summarily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#F00900"><p>Deputy O'Callaghan acknowledges that his amendment is somewhat unusual.  I am somewhat concerned that there might be unintended consequences detrimental to victims if an offence of breaching a domestic violence order was triable on indictment and punishable by imprisonment of up to five years.  There would be adverse consequences for the availability of these orders.  Orders granted under the Bill will be civil orders.  The threshold of proof in these cases is the balance of probabilities.  This is not as onerous a threshold as for criminal cases, where the threshold is beyond all reasonable doubt.  In addition, orders are granted in most cases in the summary jurisdiction of the District Court.  There is concern that if a breach of an order attracts a punishment of up to five years imprisonment, it could have a very distinct chilling effect in relation to the granting of orders.  Respondents would be expected to contest the cases in a more vigorous manner and in the interests of justice the courts might, in certain circumstances, be less inclined to grant the orders.  I have no doubt that this would be to the disadvantage and detriment of victims and those seeking redress.</p><p>These concerns were highlighted by the Law Reform Commission in its report of 2013 entitled, Aspects of Domestic Violence.  The commission expressed concern that increasing the possible punishment for breach of a domestic violence order to five years imprisonment might well lead the courts to a conclusion that <i>ex parte </i>orders should no longer be permissible.  Of course, if that was the case it would really undermine the efficacy of the legislation.  The Law Reform Commission pointed out in its report that the purpose of criminalising a breach of a domestic violence order is primarily to deter respondents from acting in breach of the order, and also to punish respondents who are in breach of the order.</p><p>Making the breach of a domestic violence order a crime does not replace other criminal offences, such as assault, or indeed the issues referred to by Deputy O'Callaghan in a discussion on an earlier amendment where he cited An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na's ability to arrest a respondent for a criminal offence.  If an offence of assault or criminal damage is committed by a person acting in breach of an order, the other offence should be prosecuted as an additional charge.  I see that happening on a regular basis.</p><p>Criminalising the breach of a domestic violence order would not have the effect of punishing serious misconduct, such as assault causing harm.  I am concerned about unintended consequences or unintended practices that might arise.  Deputy O'Callaghan is seeking to underline the seriousness of the issue, but I do not propose to accept the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#F01000"><p>In light of the concerns expressed by the Minister and the unusual nature of the amendment I will withdraw it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#F01100"><p>The Minister made good points.  On the face of it, it appears to give an indication of how seriously we take breaches of safety and protection orders, which is good, but we can see how the idea of a chilling effect might play out.  While it looks good, it goes against what I believe in terms of reducing incarceration.  I do not believe we should go in the direction of mandatory minimum sentences either.  I am glad the amendment has been withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.194" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.195" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 33 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.196" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 34</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.197" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 34 be deleted".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#F01600"><p>Section 34 provides that the provisions of Part III of the Criminal Evidence Act 1992, which relate to the giving of evidence in criminal proceedings by television link or through an intermediary, will also apply to proceedings for an offence under section 33 of the Bill of breaching a domestic violence order.  Deputies will be familiar with section 30 of the Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Act 2017, which was enacted after the publication of this Bill.  That Bill, in the form of section 30 of the Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Act 2017, provides for a substantial amendment of Part III of the Criminal Evidence Act of 1992.  It would be simpler and clearer to make provision in this Bill for specific amendments to section 12 of the Criminal Evidence Act which defines the relevant offences to which Part III of that Act applies.  These amendments, which have been provided for in amendment No. 21, will ensure that the full protections of Part III of the Criminal Evidence Act 1992 will apply to victims of offences for breaches of domestic violence orders.  It also applies to the issues of control and forced marriage.</p> <p>  As section 34 of the Bill will no longer be necessary if amendment No. 21 is accepted, it is appropriate that it be deleted in its entirety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.199" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.200" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 35 to 38, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.201" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 39</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G00400"><p>I move amendment No. 18:</p><blockquote>In page 34, between lines 15 and 16, to insert the following:&ldquo;(9) Where a person has been acquitted of an offence in a place other than the State, he or she shall not be proceeded against for an offence under this section consisting of the alleged act or acts constituting the first-mentioned offence.<br /><br />(10) Where a person has been convicted of an offence in a place other than the State, he or she shall not be proceeded against for an offence under this section consisting of the act or acts constituting the first-mentioned offence.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Section 39 provides for a new offence of forced marriage.  The section will allow criminal proceedings to be brought in Ireland for forced marriage offences committed by Irish citizens or residents anywhere outside the State, subject to a requirement known as &quot;dual criminality&quot;, that is, that the act must also be an offence in the place where it was committed.  Offences committed outside the State on Irish registered ships or aircraft can also be prosecuted here in Ireland.  The purpose of this amendment is merely to ensure that criminal proceedings may not be brought in the State for a forced marriage offence where criminal proceedings have already been determined in another country in respect of the same act.  This is a standard provision in legislation where provision is made for jurisdiction for offences that may be committed outside the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.203" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.204" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 39, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.205" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 40</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G00900"><p>I move amendment No. 19:</p><blockquote>In page 35, line 13, to delete &ldquo;and committed&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.207" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.208" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 40, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.209" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 41</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G01400"><p>I move amendment No. 20:</p><blockquote>In page 36, line 10, to delete &ldquo;and committed&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.211" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.212" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 41, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.213" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 42 to 44, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.214" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G01900"><p>I move amendment No. 21:</p><blockquote>In page 37, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 12 of Criminal Evidence Act 1992</b><b>45.</b>Section 12(1) (amended by section 30 of the Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Act 2017) of the Criminal Evidence Act 1992 is amended in the definition of &ldquo;relevant offence&rdquo;&mdash;<blockquote>(a) by the insertion of the following paragraph after paragraph (d):<br /><br />&ldquo;(da) an offence under <i>section 33, 39 or 40 of the Domestic Violence Act 2018;&rdquo;,</i><br /><br />and<br /><br />(b) in paragraph (e), by the substitution of &ldquo;(c), (d) or (da)&rdquo; for &ldquo;(c) or (d)&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>This amendment was discussed when we discussed the deletion of section 34.  I am happy to leave it at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G02000"><p>As the Minister is happy, that is fine.  He is quite correct, we have, of course, reflected on it.  Is he happy to leave it at that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G02100"><p>If the members are, I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G02200"><p>There is no member wishing to further address this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.219" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.220" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 45 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.221" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 46 to 50, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.222" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 51</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.223" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 51 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G02800"><p>I wish to comment on section 51.  These sections, as members will see, are in Part 4 of the Bill which provides for replacement of the reference to the Domestic Violence Act 1996 in existing legislation with reference to the corresponding provisions in this Bill.  Since this Bill was published last year, a number of Acts, for example, the Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Act 2017 and the Criminal Justice (Spent Convictions and Certain Disclosures) Act 2016, have been enacted.  They contain reference to the Domestic Violence Act 1996, so on Report Stage I intend bringing forward some technical amendments to provide for the updated references.  I merely make this point now in order to facilitate this on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G02900"><p>It is a cross-referencing situation that will present on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.226" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.227" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 52</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.228" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 52 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G03300"><p>I presume that Minister's points refer to each of these sections and not just section 51.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G03400"><p>They refer to Part 4 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.231" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.232" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 53 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.233" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.234" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G03900"><p>As the Bill has now completed Committee Stage, it is recommended that members submit amendments to the Bills Office without delay as Report Stage may be taken at short notice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G04000"><p>In response to Deputy Clare Daly, who raised the ratification of the Istanbul Convention, as soon as this Bill is enacted, one legislative Act will be required to enable that ratification.  That Act is on the matter of extraterritorial jurisdiction for certain offences.  It is my intention that that Bill will be published within the next couple of months and it will follow the enactment of this Bill.</p> <p>  I thank everybody for their constructive proposals and engagement.  I have taken careful note of a couple of points raised and I hope we can get to Report Stage as soon as practicable after the Easter vacation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G04100"><p>I thank the Minister for his acknowledgment of the constructive engagement.  The words I would add are "at all times".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.238" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#G04300"><p>I again thank the Minister and his officials for attending today.</p> <p>  I want to flag an important meeting to members before we all leave.  I remind members of our informal engagement with members of the Commission on the Future of Policing in Ireland.  It will take place at 11 a.m. tomorrow with Ms Kathleen O'Toole and others in room A in LH2000.  These off-committee informal meetings have tended to leave the Chair very much isolated and alone.</p><p>Tomorrow, that is not on.  I need your attendance and participation, otherwise we will not get the full value out of the engagement with Ms O'Toole and her colleagues.  It is at 11 a.m. tomorrow in room A.</p><p> The select committee will adjourn until 10.15 a.m. on Wednesday, 18 April, when we will have the Minister back with the 2018 Estimates.  We will meet first privately in joint committee at 9 a.m.  It just remains for me to wish you all a very happy Easter.  Enjoy the break.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.241" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#H00200">Message to Dil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2018032800002#H00300"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 90, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Committee on Justice and Equality has completed its consideration of the Domestic Violence Bill 2017 and has made amendments thereto.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-03-28a.243" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 10.10 a.m. until 10.15 a.m. on Wednesday, 18 April 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>