<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.2" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.3" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Richard Bruton, Ollie Crowe, Louise O'Reilly, Paul Gavan, Matt Shanahan, Marie Sherlock. David Stanton.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy Maurice Quinlivan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.4" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#A00100">Offshore Renewable Industry Forum and Ireland’s Offshore Wind Industry: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#A00200"><p>The proceedings of Oireachtas committees will be conducted without the requirement for social distancing, with normal capacity in the committee rooms restored.  However, committees are encouraged to take a gradual approach to this change.  Members and witnesses have the option to attend meetings in the relevant committee room or online via Microsoft Teams.  All those attending the committee room and environs should continue to wash their hands properly and often, avail of sanitisers, be respectful of other people's physical space and practise good respiratory etiquette.  If they have any Covid symptoms, no matter how mild, they should not attend in the committee meeting room.  Members and all in attendance are asked to exercise personal responsibility in protecting themselves and others from the risk of contracting Covid-19.  As they are well aware, if members are participating remotely they are required to participate from within the Leinster House complex.  The only apologies we have received so far are from Senators Garvey and Gavan, and Senator Gavan intends to join later; he is running late.</p> <p>  Today we are discussing offshore and renewable energy with Wind Energy Ireland.  The importance of wind and offshore energy has only grown with time.  It is vital that we harness these sources in the right way.  The climate action plan sets out a target of 5,000 MW of offshore wind electricity by 2030.  Events in recent years and months, such as the war in Ukraine and climate change, have highlighted the importance of utilising these sources of energy.  Ireland is particularly well placed, especially around the west coast, to avail of wind energy, and we need to take this opportunity so we can have a real and positive impact in achieving our climate action goals.  Job creation in this area is something we hope to see grow and prosper and I hope the witnesses can inform the committee about this.</p> <p>  I am pleased we have the opportunity to consider the matter further with the following representatives.  I welcome from Wind Energy Ireland Mr. Noel Cunniffe, CEO, and Mr. Justin Moran, director of external affairs.  I welcome Ms Vanessa O'Connell, head of Inis Offshore Wind and vice-chairperson of the offshore supply chain working group.  From Green Rebel I welcome Mr. Kieran Ivers, CEO.</p> <p>  Before we start I wish to explain some limitations to parliamentary privilege and the practice of the Houses in respect of references witnesses may make to other persons in their evidence.  The evidence of witnesses physically present or who give evidence from within the parliamentary precincts is protected pursuant to both the Constitution and statute by absolute privilege.  Witnesses are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of a person or entity.  Therefore, if witnesses' statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks.  It is imperative they comply with any such direction.</p> <p>  The opening statements have been circulated to members.  To commence our consideration of this matter, I invite Mr. Cunniffe to make opening remarks on behalf of Wind Energy Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.6" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#A00300"><p>On behalf of Wind Energy Ireland I would like to thank the Chair and the committee for this opportunity .  I am joined by my colleagues: Mr. Justin Moran, director of external affairs; Ms Vanessa O&rsquo;Connell, head of Inis Offshore Wind and vice-chairperson of our offshore supply chain working group; and Mr. Kieran Ivers, CEO of Green Rebel.  Wind Energy Ireland represents the Irish wind industry, working to promote wind energy as an essential part of our low carbon energy future.  It is important to emphasise that we represent the whole supply chain.  As might be expected, our members manufacture turbines, develop projects and operate wind farms.  They also include Irish engineering, transport, surveying and planning companies.  Together, our industry employs approximately 6,000 people.  For us, it is not enough that we develop the 5,000 MW of offshore wind energy set out in the climate action plan and the even greater potential in the deeper waters off our south and west coasts.  We want to see Irish wind farms creating jobs in Ireland, supporting Irish businesses, providing training and education opportunities for Irish workers, and growing a thriving new industry.</p> <p>  I would like to begin by briefly telling the committee the story of two countries, Ireland and Scotland.  Ireland&rsquo;s only existing offshore wind farm, Arklow Bank, became operational in 2004, nearly two decades ago.  It consists of seven wind turbines and, at the time, it was one of the largest offshore wind farms in Europe.  It was the first time a wind turbine with a generating capacity of 3 MW was ever installed anywhere in the world and it is still operating today.  I would ask members to consider this for a moment; at one time Ireland was at the cutting edge of offshore wind energy and then we stopped.  It was a full three more years before the first Scottish offshore wind farm started generating electricity but Scotland did not stop.  As of 2019 there were 4,700 people employed in Scotland&rsquo;s offshore wind sector and it contributed nearly &pound;1 billion to the Scottish economy.  Today, there is almost 2,000 MW of offshore wind operational in Scotland and another 8,400 MW in construction or advanced development.  It is no surprise that in 2020 renewable energy provided 97% of Scotland&rsquo;s power.  Put simply, in the 2000s we did not take advantage of an enormous opportunity and I am here today to ask for the support of committee members to ensure we do not make the same mistake again.</p> <p>  With climate change and the crisis in Ukraine there is an even more urgent responsibility to transform our energy system to one that is clean, secure and equitable, while protecting our marine environment and securing the confidence of fishing and coastal communities.  Offshore wind will deliver greater energy security; it is the key to our energy independence.  With the right approach - with Government, industry and coastal communities working together - we can build a new industrial sector, supporting regional development, creating thousands of jobs and driving sustainable growth.  Other European countries, like Poland and Britain, have put in place an industrial strategy and a sector deal between the domestic offshore industry and those Governments.  These bring together the offshore renewables industry and the relevant state agencies and Government departments to maximise the value of the industry domestically for clean growth, which includes a strong focus on building the domestic supply chain.  We want a sector deal for Ireland but first we need to ensure our port infrastructure is ready.</p><p> In May 2020, we published an analysis called Harnessing our Potential.  It was produced by the Carbon Trust, which is a leading UK-based consultancy.  Harnessing our Potential is still the most comprehensive analysis to date of Ireland's offshore supply-chain potential.  It included a thorough examination of Irish ports and harbours.  Ports have two key roles in supporting offshore wind energy.  They can serve as an operations and maintenance base for an offshore wind farm.  Larger ports with extensive infrastructure can provide construction or marshalling services.  Several Irish harbours are suitable as operations and maintenance bases.  Members of this committee may be aware that two of our members, namely, Codling Wind Park and SSE with its Arklow Bank Wind Park, have already announced that if their projects are successful that they will use Wicklow and Arklow harbours, respectively, as their bases.</p><p> Each base translates to approximately 80 full-time jobs.  Each base is normally accompanied by extensive investment in local services and port infrastructure.  However, when it comes to construction and marshalling services, at present the only port on the island of Ireland can do this, which is Belfast Harbour.  The facilities at Belfast are first class but we will need much more.  We cannot deliver our offshore energy ambitions from a single port.</p><p> It is important that members appreciate that if projects cannot find suitable available ports in Ireland, they can, and will, build from ports on the west coast of Britain, from France and even from the Netherlands.  Some of these ports already engage with our projects.  Irish wind farms could create jobs in Cherbourg and support businesses in Rotterdam.  As we stated in May 2020, strategic investment must be directed urgently into Irish ports to enable them to build the infrastructure needed to support the construction of offshore wind energy.  We are currently carrying out a new analysis of existing port infrastructure and the expansion plans to meet the needs of offshore renewables that a number of these ports are bringing forward.  We will complete this analysis over the summer and I look forward to sharing it with the committee then.</p><p> As well as an infrastructure gap, we face a skills gap.  For example, we will need hundreds of new wind-turbine technicians.  Right now, with the support of Skillnet Ireland, we train between ten to 20 people every year with our partners in Green Tech Skillnet.   In addition, a turbine technician apprenticeship programme in Kerry awaits validation but these initiatives will not be enough.  Already we have seen our members and State bodies struggle to recruit ecologists, marine biologists and planners.  We will literally need thousands of civil, electrical and marine engineers.</p><p> I spoke to colleagues from the British and Scottish offshore wind energy industry at an Enterprise Ireland event last week.  I was struck by how they too have identified a shortage in skills and personnel as one of their most significant challenges.  Last year, the expert group on future skills needs published the Skills for  Zero Carbon report and I will highlight a small number of its recommendations.  The report recommended co-ordinated planning for training within the renewable energy sector through partnerships between Government, industry and training providers, the prioritising of training for jobs in renewable energy that are set to be in high demand, including marine planners, turbine technicians, hydrogen specialists and other technical roles, the expansion of existing maritime training to meet demand from the offshore energy sector and engagement with the fishing community to give people with experience working at sea the option to transfer into the offshore wind sector.  The report concluded by noting "Given the urgency of meeting Ireland&rsquo;s climate action goals, it is crucial that ... these recommendations are prioritised ... and are centrally driven by Government ... working in close collaboration with industry and the education and training system."  We fully endorse the report and urge the committee to support the establishment of this implementation group, as quickly as possible.</p><p> It is important to acknowledge several significant recent positive initiatives that have been taken by the Government.  Late last year, the Department of Transport published an updated policy statement that set out a strategy for commercial ports to facilitate offshore renewable energy.  The Department also worked successfully with other EU member states to amend the Connecting Europe Facility criteria to allow EU funding of port infrastructure for offshore wind.  This initiative has enabled some Irish ports to apply for that funding to expand for servicing offshore wind energy but not all.   The Department has also established a port co-ordination group to discuss issues around port </p><p> We would like to welcome the establishment of the cross-departmental offshore wind delivery task force, which will include a focus on supply-chain issues.  Our industry would welcome the opportunity to join the task force and work together to ensure that there is a determined focus on maximising the economic benefits of offshore wind energy to Ireland.  Finally, I commend the efforts of Enterprise Ireland in particular, which last week launched an Irish offshore wind supply-chain cluster called the Gael Offshore Network.  The network consists of more than 65 Irish companies, including many of our members.</p><p> Irish businesses are already getting ready for Ireland's offshore renewable energy potential and some are starting to compete internationally.  We have enough offshore wind power to power this country and export energy as both electricity and green hydrogen.  The need is there and the potential is there.  If Irish ports and businesses are not able to take advantage of this opportunity, then there is no doubt that others will step in.  The chance to develop a skills base and an industry that can compete internationally in a rapidly growing global renewable energy market will be lost.  This is the time for Ireland to seize the opportunity, and bring together industry, policymakers and communities to ensure these multi-billion euro investments in zero-carbon generation create thousands of skilled jobs at home, and regenerate coastal communities right around the island.  We need to unite industry, Government, the relevant State agencies, and our fishing and coastal communities behind a shared vision for true energy independence and the creation of a thriving offshore renewable energy industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#B00200"><p>I thank Mr. Cunniffe.  I invite members to discuss the issue with the representatives and remind members participating to indicate to me when they want to speak.  The first person who has indicated a wish to speak is Deputy O'Reilly and she has 14 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#B00250"><p>I thank all our guests for attending.  Interestingly, it seems that Ireland's potential for offshore energy generation is envied by a lot of Europe but we are just not quite there.</p> <p>  On floating offshore energy generation, I understand the ESB has stated "Ireland needs a ring-fenced auction for 1 GW of floating offshore wind" to begin to harness the potential of the seas off our southern and western coasts and to meet a 2030 target but also that the Government has no plans for floating offshore until after 2030.  Please explain, as those two comments do not make sense to me and I believe that one must be part of the other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.10" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#B00300"><p>At this time last year, we published a report called, Revolution - A vision for Irish floating renewable energy.  I am happy to share a copy of the report with members after the meeting.  We represent a large number of members with commercial interest in floating wind energy projects.  Many of these projects are developing to compete for 2030 and deliver as part of the phase 2 process for Government.  Phase 1 will be an initial phase of offshore wind energy development, which will include five projects located off the east coast and one project off the west coast.</p> <p>  Floating wind energy is a huge opportunity for Ireland's south and west coasts.  We believe that in order for floating wind energy to develop during this decade then there will need to be specific pot within the second renewable electricity support scheme auction for offshore renewables.  At the moment this has not yet been decided upon.  There was a Government consultation on that a few months and we expect to hear the results very soon.  The reason that this sector will need its own pot in the middle of the decade is that floating wind energy this decade will not be able to compete directly on price with fixed-bottom offshore wind energy, which will be the predominant technology that will be developed off our coasts this decade.  We believe that despite not being able to compete economically just yet, they will become economically competitive in the 2030s.  For Ireland, particularly off our west coast, there is an enormous potential for floating offshore wind energy as we transition to overall energy independence.  So we feel that it would be a worthwhile investment by the State to invest and allow some floating offshore wind energy projects to connect by 2030 in order that we can take those learnings and start to bring in the supply chain and develop that within Ireland.  While this is nascent technology in many countries around Europe, the supply chain is not yet there so we have not lost that opportunity yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#B00400"><p>This technology then is specifically for the west and south coasts of Ireland and it will be fixed-bottom wind energy for the east coast.  Why?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.12" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#B00500"><p>It is primarily based on the geography of Ireland.  Fixed-bottom turbine technology is deployable in water depths of up to about 60 m.  Off the west coast and for parts of the south coast the water tends to get very steep very quickly so one needs to move into floating offshore energy for that as it can be deployed up to depths of almost 1 km, in some cases.  For the west coast potential, generally speaking there are limited areas that are suitable for the development of fixed-bottom turbines so it will be floating offshore wind off our west coast.  Off the south coast, there will be some fixed-bottom turbines but there will be a lot of floating technology.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#B00600"><p>I wish to talk specifically about the east coast.</p><p>Some people say that fixed-bottom technology is available and cheaper and that the east coast is not suitable for anything other than fixed-bottom wind farms.  They also say that fixed-bottom wind farms have to be closer to shore and floating ones can be farther out, which is a point on which I would like Mr. Cunniffe to comment.  He will understand that people on the coast have an interest in how close a wind farm will be to them.  It is my understanding that fixed-bottom wind farms can be located so far out that they will not impinge on the view, but there is also a belief that, since they have to be closer in than floating wind farms, it would be better to wait until the floating technology was ready.  I do not agree, as the time for this is now, but the view has been expressed to me that we should perhaps wait until the floating technology is a little more developed.  Is it correct to say that fixed-bottom technology is fairly developed, is in place elsewhere and can be located far offshore?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00200"><p>Exactly.  There are approximately 25 GW of offshore wind energy deployed in the world right now, and almost all of it is fixed-bottom.  There are other countries in Europe that can deploy fixed-bottom technology farther out to sea, but that is because they have much shallower waters close to their coastlines.  Even off the east coast, Irish waters get very deep very quickly.  As such, deploying fixed-bottom technology is the right approach to take.</p> <p>  We represent floating wind energy members as well as fixed-bottom wind energy members.  The floating wind energy community says that we need to establish a supply chain in Ireland and get offshore wind going right now so as to harness and take advantage of the floating wind energy opportunity fully.  In order for us to do that, we need to deploy fixed-bottom technology as soon as possible this decade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00300"><p>I am concerned that the Government has no plans to implement floating technology until after 2030.  That will be a missed opportunity.</p> <p>  The port co-ordination group does not include representatives of the offshore wind energy industry.  Does Mr. Cunniffe have any idea as to why that is the case?  Has the industry been given a reason for being left out of the group?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.17" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00400"><p>I might pass this question over to my colleague, Mr. Moran.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.18" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00500"><p>The port co-ordination group was set up by the Department of Transport.  It brings together parts of that Department, the Irish Maritime Development Office, IMDO, and a number of ports.  We include a number of Irish ports among our membership.  The group is concerned with trying to find ways of building port infrastructure and readiness for offshore renewable energy and is a good initiative.  The challenge is that it is our members that are developers rather than our members that are ports that will be setting out the specifications for what they would like to see in a port, for example, pier length and water depth.  There is something that we can bring to the table in terms of discussing our needs and readiness, which is one of the reasons that we commissioned the report that Mr. Cunniffe mentioned in his opening statement.  In that all-island report, we identified 13 ports north and south of the Border and investigated what port infrastructure existed right now to construct and marshal an offshore wind farm.  It also considered what could be in place in two or three years' time if ports like Rosslare and Shannon Foynes delivered on their infrastructural development plans.  We have been happy to support those plans in terms of their applications to the Connecting Europe Facility.  I hope that, when we bring the report to members of this committee, we will have a much clearer understanding of what is in place and what needs to be in place.  Fixed-bottom and floating requirements are a little different, so we need to prepare not just for what can be done today, but what can be done in the late 2020s and 2030s.  When we finish the report, we hope that it will be taken seriously by the Department and will inform the thinking of the Department and members of this committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00600"><p>That would be valuable.</p> <p>  Thousands of jobs were mentioned - of course, everyone's ears pricked up - but that figure was boiled down to 80 jobs at each port plus a benefit for its community, which does not exactly sound like thousands of jobs.  What is the scope for jobs?  Mr. Cunniffe will not be able to give us the exact numbers, but will he give us an idea of the potential and what we might be missing out on if we do not have a supply chain of apprenticeships?  I have met members of the Connect Trade Union who are anxious to be involved in this area.  It is new technology and they have an interest in ensuring that the jobs being created are not just jobs for the sake of jobs but are instead good union jobs with set minimum rates of pay and everything else that we associate with the trades.  We can see where the 80 jobs will be but we cannot see where the benefits for the community will be as clearly.  Will Mr. Cunniffe discuss this matter?  What could we miss out on if we do not get the apprenticeship approvals in place and start that pipeline?  It is proving difficult to attract workers because we are in the midst of an accommodation crisis, which presents challenges, so our best chance of progressing this work is to educate people who are already in Ireland.  What could we miss out on if we were slow to get everything up and running?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.20" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00700"><p>I will provide a general overview of the number of jobs before passing over to my colleague, Ms O'Connell, on what we can learn from the UK's experience and then to Mr. Ivers as one of our supply chain members to discuss their experience on the ground.</p> <p>  Today, approximately 6,000 people are employed in the wind industry in Ireland.  They are not just people who are installing the turbines, but also planners, hauliers and the entire supply chain, including people working in financial institutions across the country.  We have commissioned a report, entitled "Harnessing our potential: Investment and jobs in Ireland's offshore wind energy", which I referenced in my opening statement.  It examined Ireland's old target for offshore renewable energy, which was 3.5 GW.  We have since increased that to 5 GW.  The report identified that, between 2020 and 2030, approximately 2,500 jobs would have been created by the offshore wind energy sector deploying the 3.5 GW.  Scotland already has 4,700 people employed.</p> <p>  The potential for jobs in our industry is as limited as Ireland makes it.  Ireland has an enormous marine area and we are the envy of Europe.  We can become not just energy independent, but a significant exporter of energy.  To do that, though, we will need the right types of skill, training and facilities.  That is why having a task force that devises an action plan for developing the right jobs, the right training facilities and the right collaboration with third level institutes will be vital.</p> <p>  A sector deal was put in place in Britain.  Ms O'Connell was central to that, so I will pass over to her to discuss that experience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.21" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Vanessa O'Connell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#C00800"><p>To give some context to where I am coming from, I moved back to Ireland from the UK last year having spent the previous ten years working in offshore wind there with a Danish energy developer, &Oslash;rsted.  I was involved in development, construction and operations.  Something that I saw that was a success and that has since become a platform for growth of offshore wind and ensured that the benefits of offshore wind energy are harvested for the UK was a sector deal that was signed in 2019.  Effectively, it was a partnership between the British Government and industry.  It was a handshake whereby industry and the British Government were committing to actions in terms of delivering offshore wind energy in the UK.  At the time, the target was to deliver 30 GW of offshore wind energy by 2030.  That target has since been accelerated to 50 GW.  In terms of the industry, part of that was to be 60% local content.  This was not a mandatory target, but a vision that the industry committed to working towards together.</p> <p>  There is an opportunity in Ireland that is not just about the green electrons, but about creating a whole new industry that can benefit the people of Ireland and generate many jobs.  We have some work to do to figure out what that means in terms of tangible numbers.  The UK had a target of 30,000 jobs in the industry by 2030 and has already smashed that target.  According to a report it has released, there are now 30,000 people working in the industry.  The UK envisages that that figure will be 100,000 by 2030.</p> <p>  The scale of the opportunity is probably more than we understand today.  That is why we are here.  There is a significant opportunity, so let the Government, industry and communities sit down and figure out what is right for Ireland, what our ambition should be and how we will work towards it together.  In terms of working together, we welcome the offshore wind energy task force that has been established by the Government, but let us bring the industry to the table and work together in collaboration more frequently.  Under the offshore wind sector deal, the UK set up the Offshore Wind Industry Council, through which the industry and the British Government work together, set an action plan and work through it over time.</p> <p>  It is great for us to attend this meeting to discuss what we want, but this is a matter of us continuing to work together on delivering for Ireland.  The reason I came home to Ireland was my excitement about this opportunity.  Now that I am here, I can see the market beginning to move.  There is much that we can do by working together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00100"><p>They have smashed the target of 30,000 jobs, which is brilliant.  We cannot say that often enough or loud enough.  Could Ms O'Connell provide us with information about the type of jobs, who is doing them, wage rates, trades and non-trades, etc.?  I have one more question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00200"><p>The Deputy's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00300"><p>It is about apprenticeships.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Ivers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00400"><p>There is a narrative in Ireland at the moment that we cannot do all of this by ourselves.  We are not here to say we can do it all by ourselves but Green Rebel is certainly an example of a company with a lead time whereby it can deliver not just for offshore in a DevEx phase but actually deliver competency that can compete on a global level.  Up to last week, we had a trade delegation in from Norway representing over 250 companies with over 10,000 employees, many of which are diversifying from oil and gas.  If Ireland does not move quickly, they are the skills and services that will be imported into Ireland.</p> <p>  We mentioned floating offshore.  It depends on the context of our ambition.  If our ambition is just to service our own needs then the jobs created will be designed to service Ireland only.  When we look at innovations like floating offshore and the opportunity this presents to Ireland given the west coast of Ireland, it is a basis for innovation.  Ireland has an opportunity to more than export energy to other markets.  It has an opportunity to deliver expertise and competency and develop intellectual property in Ireland that we can export all over the world.  If we can develop a platform where Government, officials and industry can come together and plan that, we will see maximum effect regarding the employment created.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00500"><p>Coming from Galway on the western seaboard which, as I am sure the witnesses will be aware, has the highest wind speeds in Europe, I believe in the enormous potential and opportunities wind energy can provide not just in terms of meeting our energy needs and climate change commitments but also in terms of job creation, as a number of witnesses stated earlier.  I appreciate that the witnesses are carrying out analysis of port infrastructure so they may not be able to answer this specifically but perhaps they can offer some level of detail regarding the level of investment that is required to sufficiently address the infrastructure needs at our ports and the sort of timeframe they believe that would take.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00600"><p>I might pass that question on to Mr. Moran.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.28" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00700"><p>It is quite difficult to put a figure on it because it varies from port to port.  Some ports have different levels of infrastructure.  In the past 12 months, we have seen developments like the Doyle Shipping Group facility at the port of Cork and developments in Rosslare and Shannon Foynes and there is a proposal to build a new port in Bremore in north County Dublin.  They are all coming forward with proposals, ideas and plans and the cost of each of them will vary because some ports have different levels of infrastructure in place.  In terms of a ball park figure, we are talking about tens of millions of euro but the actual figure will vary from project to port to port.  They have also applied for funding to the Connecting Europe facility so their hope is that they would be able to draw down funding from Europe that would enable them to carry out those investments and put in place the infrastructure that is needed.</p> <p>  The last point raised by the Senator is the critical one.  It concerns the timing of this and how quickly we can get those ports ready.  If we are looking at our phase one projects, those five ports on the east coast and one off the coast of the Senator's home county of Galway near Rossaveel, we are looking at projects in respect of which we hope to apply for planning permission next year.  We hope to start construction in 2025 or 2026 at the outside so the question for us is whether ports other than Belfast will be ready then for those projects.  Belfast will be able to take some of that work.  It is a first-class facility but it cannot build six Irish offshore wind farms at the same time.  If those ports are not ready, those projects will be looking to other ports and other infrastructure opportunities to provide the construction marshalling services.  This is why it is not just important that the investment is there but that the investment comes through quickly and the ports are helped to get through the planning process to put in place the infrastructure they need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00800"><p>When we talk about tens and even hundreds of millions of euro in terms of port investment, people can often think this is a staggering figure.  To put that in context, any one of these projects that are being developed around our coast line will be investing between &euro;1 billion and &euro;2 billion - &euro;1,000 million and &euro;2,000 million.  When we talk about a &euro;100 million investment in a port, it might sound like a lot of money but these ports will be servicing these projects that involve multiples of that figure.  They will benefit from that for years to come.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D00900"><p>Mr. Moran referenced Shannon Foynes and Rossaveel.  What has been the level of engagement of Galway Port?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D01000"><p>The Port of Galway is one of our members so we would engage quite a lot with it.  It is already a key part of the port infrastructure that supports the development of onshore wind energy because many of the turbines that are used for onshore wind farms in the west of Ireland come through the Port of Galway.  They are landed there and taken to the wind farms.</p> <p>  We are not here to pick a port winner.  There will be enough work in the development of offshore wind energy in Ireland to provide opportunities for every significant port in this country.  Even for some smaller ports and harbours, there are opportunities for them to be operations and maintenance bases.  When we look at the west coast in particular, and as the Senator noted, the wind speeds out there are fantastic, it is not just about the opportunity to construct, marshal, operate and maintain those projects.  We can be innovators and leaders out there because we will be developing offshore wind energy in some of the windiest parts and deepest waters of the world and we can take the skills we develop there, and I do not know if Mr. Ivers would like to come in on this because I know it is an area in which Green Rebel has worked, and take them around the world and compete internationally.  One of the things we want to get across here is that if we can build an Irish supply chain to support Irish offshore wind farms, there is no reason those Irish companies will not be building wind farms off the coast of China, the US or Africa in 15 or 20 years time or less.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.32" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Ivers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D01100"><p>Green Rebel has quite a lot of scientists.  We have people who have literally written books about the continental shelf and Ireland and they will identify the west coast as our basin for innovation.  The context of ports will be different given the water depths off those ports and the types of structures that will be deployed off the coast line on the west versus the east.  We would identify Galway and Rossaveel in particular as bases where innovation and centres of excellence can be created and where robotics can be deployed.  The west coast of Ireland has deeper water and harsher conditions than anywhere on the planet.  It is virtually impossible to simulate that in any environment other than the real thing.  Given the opportunity for innovation presented by the west coast of Ireland, it will surely present an opportunity for exporting that level of expertise but that is not being done in the world at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D01200"><p>That is all very positive.  Hopefully, the timeframe will be short.  In terms of skill shortages, have any actions resulted from the recommendations in the Skills for Zero Carbon report or are there plans to address those recommendations because, naturally, the skills shortage is critical?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.34" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D01300"><p>Absolutely - as I mentioned in my opening statement, one of the recommendations from that was the establishment of a high-level implementation group.  We are not aware if this has been established yet.  We would like to see that established as soon as possible.  It was referenced by Deputy O'Reilly, who asked what type of skills were in short supply.  We are already experiencing across the industry a shortage of planners, marine biologists, ecologists and tradespeople.  We need to see apprenticeships begun immediately and partnerships with technological universities and third-level institutions around Ireland and to do that, we need that action plan to be brought together so that we can come at it as a country rather than each individual college, some of which have stepped forward on their own volition to try to develop apprenticeship and third-level programmes to service the needs of the industry.  We need to see co-ordinated action and for that reason, we need that implementation to be established as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#D01400"><p>To be quite positive about something, we would partner with Skillnet Ireland in the delivery of training courses to get people involved in this industry and to possibly transition from other sectors.</p><p>One of our colleagues was talking recently to a woman from County Cavan who emigrated to Australia, where she was working in a gold mine.  She is now a wind turbine technician.  She completed the green tech Skillnet Ireland course and retrained.  She is now working on wind farms in Ireland, England, Norway and Scotland.  There are programmes delivered through Skillnet Ireland that we can develop and build on.  There is certainly the demand and the interest to get involved in the sector.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Ivers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00200"><p>We have identified that there are considerable numbers of the Irish diaspora already working in the industry.  In the first instance, organisations such as Green Rebel and others to follow will encourage them to move back.  That is an area that we need to focus on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00300"><p>I would like to ask a question about ports, and the capacity for a port to develop more than one platform.  The development has been completed at Belfast Port, whereas we are waiting for our ports to be ready.  If Shannon Foynes Port was ready, could two or three platforms be developed at once or would they have to be done one at a time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00400"><p>Mr. Moran will respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00500"><p>It depends on what exactly is needed from the project at a specific period in time.  The period of construction for an offshore wind farm is two to three years.  There could be a situation where different pieces of work for perhaps two wind farms are coming out of the same port at the same time.  There could be a situation where a main port is being used for marshalling services and a nearby port is also involved in taking on some of that work.  There can be multi-port opportunities.  The facility at Belfast Port is fantastic.  If the committee members ever get the chance to visit it, I highly recommend it.  It is an example of what first-class facilities for construction and marshalling look like.  With the best will in the world, you cannot build 5,000 MW of offshore wind simultaneously in five different projects from that facility.  Either you put them in a queue, basically, and do them as quickly as possible to get through the work, or you find other port facilities or infrastructure.  With Shannon Foynes, there is enormous potential for the port to be a hub not just for the construction of offshore wind farms but as a place where we can bring power onshore and create green hydrogen, which is one of the real exciting export opportunities for Ireland.  There is also an opportunity to take that green hydrogen and decarbonise some the sectors of our own economy that are quite difficult to decarbonise, such as heating, transport and electricity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00600"><p>Shannon Foynes has great potential.  I call Deputy Bruton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00700"><p>I than the witnesses for their presentation.  I think this is a really exciting opportunity.  It is important to say that the renewable ambition in Ireland is extremely high.  For an electricity generation system that is as isolated and as small as ours is, it is a remarkably-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00800"><p>A participant has left their microphone on.  Can it be muted, please?  Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E00900"><p>It is important to state that our grid is regarded as an international exemplar of the extent to which it has successfully taken renewables on board.  We are now aiming for an 80% renewable figure.  It is important to put the issue in context and it is worth saying that Scotland is different.  That brings me to the following question.  With capital and construction capacity scarce for public investment in Ireland, the organisations represented today are urging the Government to do more and to put more of its money into accelerating offshore wind beyond what it is already anticipating.  I want to tease that out.  Are the organisations' higher ambitions conditional on export?  Is that really the context, rather than greening our existing grid?  Will it require additional interconnection and the development of the green hydrogen sector?  There are obviously different phases to the work, and different elements have higher priority at a time of constrained resources, a housing crisis and all of the other issues.  The challenge facing the Government is choosing which of these things are most urgent.  How do the organisations represented assess that urgency in the context of other issues, as well as the fact that it requires the development of a hydrogen sector that is still relatively underutilised?  There needs to be a hydrogen strategy here that gives us a context for that.</p> <p>  The witnesses have stated that there the water off the west coast is extraordinarily  deep, conditions are harsh, and will still be difficult to work in.  Should this be more of a European infrastructural play than simply an Irish play?  Should we be looking to the longer-term global context in which the Atlantic resource will be tapped into?  Does that alter the view of the witnesses on how this opportunity should be developed?</p> <p>  I am also interested to know what the successful elements of the Scottish strategy were, and what mistakes were made so that we can perhaps learn from them.  I know that the Scottish project is different.  Scotland has a bigger connection and a bigger demand source on its doorstep.  Those are my questions.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E01000"><p>I might refer to my colleague, Ms O'Connell, to respond to the Deputy's question on the Scottish strategy.  I agree with the Deputy that the target that we have to deliver 80% of our electricity from renewable sources by 2030 is extremely ambitious.  We definitely think it is deliverable but in order for that to happen, a lot of things need to fall into place in terms of our planning system, our grid system and our route to market.  We appeared before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action a few months ago.  We stated that we have a 50:50 chance of achieving the 5 GW the target for offshore wind energy specifically.  We are not here to say that we need a higher target for offshore wind.  We are saying that we really need to double down and focus on delivering that 5 GW of offshore wind energy.  That said, we want the highlight the opportunity that that target presents for the domestic supply chain.  It is true that capital and resources are scarce but those projects will be built.  The question that we would like to highlight today is whether they will be built from Irish ports and by Irish companies.  That is why the establishment of a delivery task force on supply chain to try to produce an action plan is critical, so that as much of that potential and investment that we are going to see to deliver our 2030 targets remains within Ireland.</p> <p>  On whether the potential we are talking about is really for the export opportunity, we will need an enormous amount of electricity to service Ireland as we go towards 2050 and towards becoming a climate-neutral country.  We did some analysis with UCC's MaREI centre looking at a zero-carbon economy for Ireland.  It showed that electricity demand will triple between now and 2050, predominantly as we electrify heat and transport.  We are going to need around 25 GW of offshore wind energy purely for our own domestic purposes before we even contemplate the export potential opportunity that we have off our west coast, which we believe to be equivalent to around 70 GW to 80 GW of capacity.  The establishment of a hydrogen supply chain will be very important to that over time.  We are not talking about purely direct electrification for everything.  The electricity grid that we currently have is not capable of managing the level of energy that I have just spoken about.  We will need hydrogen in order to decarbonise heat and transport, but the source and the base of that will be offshore wind energy.  The more that we can establish our own supply chain, the better.</p> <p>  On the European side of things, currently, countries across Europe are trying to get off fossil fuels as quickly as possible, following the crisis in Ukraine.  We are seeing countries right across Europe increasing their targets for offshore wind energy every week.  Two years ago, the 2030 offshore wind target in Europe was 60 GW.  Just two weeks ago there was an announcement that Belgium, Denmark, Germany and the Netherlands will be developing 65 GW by themselves between now and 2030.  Right across Europe, we are hearing that supply chain constraints are a big challenge.  All the countries will need to pool together their resources and supply chains if we are to have any chance of meeting Europe's target.  I will refer to my colleague, Ms O'Connell, to respond to the Deputy's question on Scotland.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Vanessa O'Connell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#E01100"><p>I will answer the Deputy's question in the broader sense of the UK context.  When the sector deal was signed, it was looking at offshore wind in the whole of the UK.  As it has developed, Scotland has started to focus on what Scotland can do itself, rather than with England and Wales.  Looking at the whole of the UK, one of the lessons learned is thinking about what the different parts of the country need.  Originally, there was the Offshore Wind Industry Council, which was for the whole of the UK.  Now, Scotland has its own Scottish Offshore Wind Energy Council.  It is looking at what Scotland needs, rather than what the rest of the UK needs.  That is one of the lessons learned.</p><p>It has also been a focus in the UK.  The benefits of offshore wind are not concentrated within one area.  The wind farms are all around the coast.  We need therefore to look to understand where we can develop clusters for innovation for the development of the supply chain.  That is in around areas such as Cork, the west, Foynes and the east.  That cluster effect is important for having a national strategy, as well as for thinking about what we need in different parts of the country.  That is one key lesson that has been learned.  It is also safe to say that the UK and Scotland are still on the journey in offshore wind.  They have been successful to date, but they still have much work to do.  We are also facing some of the challenges they are facing.  There are lessons to learned by working together.  Some of those challenges, particularly for Scotland, relate to grid infrastructure.</p><p> The Deputy raised the point of export opportunity around interconnection.  That is also a challenge for Scotland.  We must understand that they are nearly at 100% renewables on their system.  They are already exporting their energy to England.  They are looking to see where they can export it abroad.  System integration is a challenge.  Resourcing is also a challenge.  That is a key challenge for Ireland.  It is a matter of resourcing within the industry as well as across the industry, for example with the likes of EirGrid, An Bord Plean&aacute;la and the environmental organisations.  This comes back to our point that it is important that we come together to learn the lessons from other markets.  Those primarily come from the industries.  It is a matter of many international players coming to Ireland and people like myself coming back to Ireland.  We can share the lessons we have learned.  We can ask what is right for Ireland.  We can ask what we want the vision to be.  Then we can work towards that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00200"><p>I note that there is a debate in the D&aacute;il this morning on energy security, which is related to what we are doing here.  When a witness comes before an Oireachtas committee, they usually have an ask.  What are the witnesses&rsquo; top three asks of us as members of the enterprise committee?  We are focusing on business, enterprise and trade.  What would the witnesses like us to do?  That is my first question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00300"><p>Our first ask relates to the need for the offshore delivery task force to sit down with industry to agree an action plan for how we develop our domestic offshore supply chain.  That task force is up and running.  It does not have industry representation on it at the moment.  We do not know what topics it is covering.  We believe the supply chain is part of the task force&rsquo;s remit.  We want to be at the table to try to explain the opportunities we have seen in other jurisdictions, as Ms O&rsquo;Connell outlined.</p> <p>  The second ask is for more investment and strategic investment into port infrastructure.  As we have said this morning, port opportunities are being developed across Ireland in many of our ports.  However, in order for them to be ready to help to deliver for 2030, they need investment now.</p> <p>  The final ask relates to the Skills for Zero Carbon report we referenced earlier.  We need to see an implementation group set up so that there is a co-ordinated response right across government and across all Departments as we develop the people, the training and the skill sets to be able to deliver on the opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00400"><p>May I briefly add a point to that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.52" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00600"><p>One of the reasons we are delighted for the opportunity to meet with the committee today is that when we talk about renewable energy it is often seen as the remit of the Department of Environment, Climate and Communications.  It is seen as something that that Department does.  If there is a wind farm, an offshore wind farm or anything to do with climate or decarbonisation, that is considered a matter for Department of Environment, Climate and Communications.  Absolutely, they are the people we deal with most on a day-to-day basis and the people we engage with.  However, jobs, trade and employment are matters for this committee and this Department.</p> <p>  I want to stress that we welcome the offshore wind delivery task force as an initiative because it will get us to the ambitious targets that Deputy Bruton mentioned.  There is a group of people that is working through its agenda and to-do list.  They are trying to sort out the planning system and they are trying to sort out the grid infrastructure.  If the supply chain is the eighth or ninth item on its list before any other business, it is often the item it spends the least amount of time focused on.  What we want to see from the Department or the committee is that somebody will take responsibility for the jobs opportunity that offshore wind energy will bring.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00700"><p>My second question relates to the Revolution report, which was published in July 2021, before the terrible war in Ukraine.  We have seen reports across the board about how costs have gone up dramatically.  There are supply cost issues, supply chain issues and so forth.  The costs of the material have gone up.  Mariupol had the biggest steel plant in Europe.  That is kaput now; it is not producing anymore.  What impact will that have on the witnesses&rsquo; levelised cost of electricity projections that they cite in the Revolution report?  They talk about the flow costs per megawatt in 2021 being &euro;135 and how they will go down to &euro;40 in 2050.  Do they think that when the war finishes, the costs will level off again?  Can they talk about the costs, in the context of the impact that the changed world will have on them, since the Revolution report was actually commissioned?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.54" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00800"><p>I am happy to do that.  We have just come out of the more recent renewable electricity support scheme auction for onshore renewables.  It gives us a clear example where there have been increased costs relating to materials for onshore wind energy and for solar energy.  That is not the only reason costs are going up.  There are still many uncertainties in terms of policies related to grid infrastructure and planning systems.  These are being baked into driving up costs.  When it comes to costs specifically for offshore wind and for floating offshore wind energy, we do not yet have a good example in Europe for what the costs of developing floating offshore wind energy for commercial-scale projects will be.  Britain and France are both in the process of developing and running auctions specifically for floating wind energy.  In the next six to 12 months we should have a good idea of what the real commercial costs will be for developing floating offshore wind energy.  We will be happy to share that with the committee whenever that comes to light.</p> <p>  There is concern among the development community for offshore wind projects for this decade about how they will source those materials, the right supply chain and the right ships.  We mentioned that every country right around Europe right now is looking at how to increase its renewable energy targets.  Right now, the European supply chain is just not capable of keeping up with it.  That is why it is important that we get on board and we start contributing to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F00900"><p>There is a built-in assumption that if we do not get moving here, we could be left behind in all kinds of ways.  It was put to me recently that Scotland is moving ahead.  It has connectors to Northern Ireland and across here.  If we do not move here, could we end up importing offshore wind-generated electricity from Scotland rather than producing our own?  Is that a risk?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F01000"><p>It is a possibility.  They have huge ambitions for developing offshore wind energy in Great Britain.  They have a target of 50 GW, compared to our 5 GW.  We believe that our 5 GW target will supply 30% to 40% of our electricity demand by 2030.  When you couple that with the onshore wind energy sector, which is continuing to grow in Ireland, and with solar energy, we should be able to hit the target of having 80% of our own electricity from renewables by 2030.  Our goal as a country should be to try to achieve net zero-carbon electricity by 2035.  We have the resources there.  That is not up for debate.  What is up for debate is how cheaply we can deliver that, how efficiently and how much of that investment we can keep within Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F01100"><p>I join with Deputy Bruton and others here who have spoken about the potential for green hydrogen and the capacity for it to be generated from offshore wind-generated electricity.  This is really exciting and far-seeing.  How far away are we from that happening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F01200"><p>Earlier this year, we published a report on hydrogen and wind energy which looked at the policy asks we would have as a renewable industry to get hydrogen up and running in Ireland.  We can share that with committee members afterwards if that would be useful.  There are two key issues to highlight.  We need a hydrogen strategy for Ireland.  Such a strategy is in the process of being developed, but we do not have it yet.  We understand the consultation for that will be published shortly.  As a country, we need to stimulate not just the supply of hydrogen, which is where the renewable energy comes in, but also the demand for hydrogen.  How are we going to shift industries which are currently using oil and gas in particular to try to move them towards hydrogen?</p> <p>  The other point I would make, and the report called it out, is that what will drive the cost of hydrogen is the cost of the renewables that we are developing.  The more certainty that we can provide to the development community for renewable electricity through having a planning system, a grid system and a supply chain that works, the cheaper we can produce renewable power and the cheaper we can transition to hydrogen.  There are projects involving the development of hydrogen at the moment around Ireland.  We think that will play a big role towards the end of the decade and into the 2030s.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#F01300"><p>The grid interconnector to France is in the planning stages at the moment.  It is to be located in my part of the country.  It has caused a certain amount of angst among some residents.  There is the whole issue of the grid upgrade.  We hear of more pylons being spoken about.  I am sure Mr. Cunniffe has been down that route as well and has heard about it.  If we need more pylons to upgrade the grid but people do not want them near their houses, or anywhere near them, how do we get over that issue?  They get very emotional and very angry about them.  Can the witnesses speak to that point, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.60" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#G00100"><p>Our grid infrastructure is in serious need of development.  We developed our electricity grid substantially in the 1980s, 1990s and early 2000s.  We have been benefiting from the capacity that was created in that grid for the past two decades, and it has helped to drive much of the economic growth and employment we have seen in Ireland.  We are starting to reach a point where our electricity grid will need further levels of reinforcement, along the coasts in particular, to deliver offshore wind energy and, in the midlands and other parts of the country, to deliver onshore renewables as well.  We are going to need political and public support for our grid infrastructure if we are to have any chance of meeting our decarbonisation targets.  We will need more pylons, more underground cables and more substations.  We cannot do this if we do not have them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#G00200"><p>One point we often make is that if we appear before a committee at the end of 2030 and the members ask why we did not hit the 80% target, the answer will relate to grid infrastructure.  We do not need to wait until 2030 to say that either.  Either the grid infrastructure will be there and we will achieve the target, or it will not and we will not.  It is as simple as that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1616" speakername="Matt Shanahan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#G00300"><p>I welcome our guests.  I have met Mr. Cunniffe and Mr. Moran at exhibitions and so on and we have engaged.  I have a specific concern, as I have highlighted to them, about the potential for wind energy off the south-east coast, not least in the Copper Coast area, and the potential for damage to amenities.  It is important that this committee has an ongoing engagement with the wider wind energy sector, but I would support our guests' call for at least a sector deal and for a representative from the offshore industry to sit on the co-ordination group.  Perhaps that is something the committee can speak about in private session.</p> <p>  As I have said to our guests previously, I have concerns about a lack of State ownership in the wind energy sector as it develops, primarily because we do not have expertise and I can see that something similar to what happened with the oil industry is going to happen.  Ultimately, we will sell the licences, foreign players will come in and provide everything and we will ask what we really got out of it.   We might not even get a good rate of electricity charged to the State.</p> <p>  I am also worried about how the coastal communities will be looked after.  One issue I have previously raised relates to how a community dividend, which in general in the wind sector is looked at for about 15 years over the lifetime of a farm, should be paid every year.  If a turbine turns at sea or on land, a community needs to be resourced from that.  I am worried not only about amenities in tourism but also about the fishing industry.  Ms O&rsquo;Connell might speak about Scotland in a moment.  Some of the largest spawning grounds in Europe are to be found off the south coast of Ireland, so she might comment on the effects of talking about putting wind infrastructure out there.</p> <p>  Is any potential tie-up being signalled for people who are coming in to invest in wind infrastructure whereby they would also tie in hydrogen development?  Rather than say we are going to create wind farms and then talk about creating hydrogen plants, are any conglomerates interested in coming with that package and saying that as part of their wind farm licence, they would be prepared to invest in hydrogen development onshore?  In the south east, we have one of the most significant gateways to composite developments in the form of turbine manufacture.  Mr. Cunniffe referred to a course starting in Kerry, but we need very significant academic linkage and his organisation mentioned it was hoping to engage with higher education.</p> <p>  We are at an early stage, but I would like to see a sectoral deal done, with our guests getting representation and with us, as a committee, engaging with them twice a year.  It would be good to get committee members out - visits to Belfast, Scotland or wherever were mentioned - to understand where this wind generation deal is going.  There is no doubt there is opportunity in this for Ireland, but I very much fear it is going to pass us by.  I fear that foreign players will dominate the space and that we may not see much out of it other than, as I said, a not very competitive tariff on wind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.63" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#G00400"><p>I might hand over to Ms O'Connell to take the fishing question relating to Scotland and to my colleague, Mr. Moran, to comment on coastal communities.  In regard to the State ownership question, there are many active State-owned companies in the energy sector in Ireland right now.  Everyone will be familiar with the ESB, one of the largest owners of onshore wind energy in Ireland.  Through a partnership between the ESB and Coillte, Future Energy Ireland has been established as a State company developing onshore wind energy and Bord na M&oacute;na is very much established as an onshore wind energy and solar developer as well.  There is a great deal of State involvement in that.  Moreover, the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund is one of the main investors in Ms O&rsquo;Connell&rsquo;s Inis Offshore Wind.  We will see investment from the State in that.</p> <p>  Any offshore wind farm that is developed around Ireland will also pay a seabed lease, so revenue for the State will be generated from every offshore wind farm that is developed.  We are also seeing considerable levels of investment in, as I mentioned, many ports throughout the country, which are putting up their hands and saying they want to invest here and to keep as much money in Ireland as they can.  We have seen those announcements in Arklow and Wicklow from maintenance and operations bases being set up.</p> <p>  My one concern, as has been suggested by a number of groups previously, is that if we were to take a step back and to establish a State body to develop offshore wind energy, it would take a very long time to resource that and to establish both it and a regulator.  We would not develop a single offshore wind turbine for the next ten to 15 years if we were to do that.  Many of the projects around our coasts have been in development for years or, in some cases, decades, and those projects need to proceed and we need to be able to establish that.  There is a significant role for the State in resourcing Departments.  We need a functional State Department, through An Bord Plean&aacute;la, EirGrid, the Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, and the National Parks and Wildlife Service, to be able to deliver the full potential for this industry in order that we can get a return for the people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.64" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Vanessa O'Connell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#G00500"><p>In regard to fishing, I was working primarily in England but had some interaction with Scotland as well.  It is always a challenge because it involves putting infrastructure in an area that may be fished, so we need to find a way to resolve that.  In the UK, some lessons have been learned relating to coexistence and compensation, and we have looked at opportunities to get the fishing industry involved in the offshore wind industry as guard vessels and in construction and operations.  Nevertheless, it is important that when we come back to Ireland, we understand the concerns of the fishing industry here and how we can solve those problems.  Some lessons will be learned, but Ireland is unique and the fishing industry is really important to the country.   For us at Inis Offshore Wind, it is the number one stakeholder we have.  Very early on, we engaged with it to understand its concerns and how we could mitigate its concerns whether through the wind farm design or by finding ways to coexist.</p> <p>  I will pass over to Mr. Moran to discuss the initiative going on within Wind Energy Ireland, specifically as it relates to the fishing industry and the groups that have been formed.  I was very happy to hear the Deputy welcome the sector deal.  It is something we can take away to contacts we have who are involved in the UK sector deal because I think they would be more than happy to help.  A number of people within the UK industry are also looking to Ireland.  They would be more than happy to welcome us over there, perhaps to visit a wind farm to understand what is going on.  That is something we can take away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#G00600"><p>I might first touch on one of the points the Deputy made, which he has made to me a number of times previously.  It relates to community benefit and to ensuring that will be spread over the lifetime of the project.  It is something we would like to see as well and we would expect to see it from our members, but the community benefit fund as a requirement of the contract an offshore wind farm will get is related to the duration of the contract.  We will clearly say to our members that just because the contract is running out, that does not mean they get to close shop and go away.  They will still need to support those local communities but the contract will run out after 15 or 16 years.</p> <p>  As for our engagement with the fishing community, we both do that at a project level, whereby officers talk to fishermen on specific piers and around harbours.  We are also increasingly doing it on a national level with the existing fishing organisations.  The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage recently appointed a chairperson for what is called the seafood offshore renewable energy working group, which will bring together about 11 or 12 fishing organisations and us, representing the offshore wind sector, but also - this is important - the Departments and State agencies that are relevant to this, such as Bord Iascaigh Mhara, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  These people have been put together to sit around the table and ensure that when we develop these wind farms, we will be conscious of the impact they may have on marine biodiversity and the environment and, in particular, on the coastal and fishing communities that depend on those waters for their livelihoods and to pay rent and send their kids to college.</p><p>Not only should these wind farms not be an impediment to them, there is an opportunity here.  I might bring Mr. Ivers in to talk about this in a moment.  There is enormous opportunity here for people with marine skills and there are very few people in Ireland with more marine skills than fishermen.  They would be able to work and be part of the development of offshore renewable energy.  It would also be useful to hear from Mr. Ivers about getting Irish companies into the supply chain.  We want Irish companies, whether semi-State bodies or private sector companies, to get into the Irish supply chain.  Green Rebel is one of the leaders in that at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Ivers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00200"><p>As the only one of the witnesses here who has feet on the ground in the supply chain, I assure the Deputy that we share his concerns.  We are well aware that the bounty achieved in Cork from the Kinsale gas field was the contract for catering.  That needs to be reversed.  We cannot make the same mistakes again.  Ireland has a poor history in the context of benefiting from our own natural resources.  A sectoral deal is not an off-the-shelf solution.  It can only be achieved with collaboration between the Government, industry and officials.  The by-product of that type of collaboration is a sectoral deal that is bespoke to Ireland and that we can benefit from.  That should encourage the development of an indigenous supply chain, as well as foreign direct investment into Ireland.  We cannot do it all ourselves but we can encourage investment and make provisions so those who want to do business in Ireland have to invest in Ireland and not just create a postcode.  Deputy Bruton spoke about dipping into Ireland's coffers.  In Scotland, the industry stimulus that was provided, from the developer's pocket, as a result of that collaboration has been critically important.</p> <p>  Collaboration between entities will also help the Government identify some of the surmountable challenges the industry is facing right now.  One example in Green Rebel's world is this issue around licensing and foreshore licences.  Right now we have a buoy, a floating LiDAR innovation, which is best in class globally and was developed in Ireland specifically to target floating offshore wind.  We are having to send it to Rotterdam, and will continue to do so over the next two years, investing north of &euro;3 million, in order to get its certification because we cannot get licensing here.  We are not talking about the licensing of an offshore wind farm.  This is a tiny piece but these are surmountable challenges that can only be brought to this type of forum.  This opportunity for Ireland, including the economic opportunity, cannot be lost.  That is what we are passionate about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00300"><p>The potential here is enormous.  That comes across from the witnesses' passion.  I ask Mr. Ivers and Ms O'Connell to tell us a little about their companies, what they do and what their ambition is.  I would like to give them the opportunity while they are here, if the Chair does not mind, to give an idea of what they do.  Mr. Ivers said he has feet on the ground.  What are the witnesses doing and what are their ambitions for the near future?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Vanessa O'Connell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00400"><p>Will I start?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.70" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Ivers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00500"><p>As we were taught in school, it is always ladies first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Vanessa O'Connell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00600"><p>Inis Offshore Wind is an Irish company.  We were formed over two years ago by the Temporis Aurora fund.  One of our key investors is the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund.  The core purpose of Inis Offshore Wind is to develop offshore wind in Ireland for the people of Ireland.  The Irish people have a direct stake in our success through our backers but as a company we are also committed to ensuring the benefits of offshore wind come to the people of Ireland.  I worked in the UK for ten years and I have the experience of seeing the growth of an industry.  It was exciting to be there and I had a great career, but there was always something calling me back to Ireland.  It is so windy in Ireland, and we have huge opportunities here.  Now I have the opportunity to head up a company that is looking to do that.  I am personally very vested in what we are doing.</p> <p>  Specifically, we are a developer.  We have five projects all around the coast of Ireland and are looking at another project with a capacity of up to 4 GW.  We have two projects in the east, one in the south and two in the west.  Our interest is in the potential in all of Ireland.  We want all parts of Ireland to develop from a supply chain perspective.  It is not just about the jobs.  If we think about the interest of a developer, having a local supply chain makes sense from a cost perspective but also from a resilience perspective.  We talked about the global challenges in the supply chain.  I had the same conversations as Mr. Cunniffe at the Enterprise Ireland event last week.  Everyone was talking about the global challenges in the supply chain and the market.  Ireland is a new market.  We need to work together to attract the supply chain and tell people Ireland is open for business.  We have this vision and the targets but there is more we can do to show we are really open for business and are going to deliver.  That will help the supply chain come.  It is important that we develop Irish companies but as Mr. Ivers was saying, we also need foreign direct investment and to make sure that when companies do invest, it is long-term investment that creates jobs here for the long term.  We have our projects and we are in the early development phases.  We are looking to get foreshore licences in order that we can go out and survey the seabed, but, ultimately, we have a long pipeline to deliver projects up to 2030 and beyond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.72" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Kieran Ivers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00700"><p>Green Rebel is a company headquartered in Cork but with offices in Limerick, Cork Airport and Crosshaven.  We are a marine services company.  We acquire data for developers that help inform them through the consent process as they apply for planning permission.  Those data are designed to inform them on how to minimise the ecological impact of offshore wind farms and maximise the efficiency.  We have invested significant capital in the acquisition of aircraft to run baseline ecology surveys, tracking bird and mammal migration patterns and densities to ensure we are ecologically sound.  We have invested in a fleet of marine craft.  It is like cutting the lawn at home where you go up and down in lines.  We do the same on the investigation areas, identifying the seabed and its nuances in order to inform ecological and engineering requirements.  We acquired a company last year, IDS Monitoring in Limerick, which makes up our MetOcean team.  That team has developed the innovations I described to Deputy Shanahan and measures wind density and velocity.  Those are the bankable data offshore wind farm developers need to release capital to develop these projects.  It is a critical component of what they do.  This is a real example of "Ireland can".  In the space of two years we have gone from an idea to 75 employees, with ambition to grow well beyond 100 by the end of the this year.  We have received extraordinary support from Government agencies like Enterprise Ireland, which are helping accelerate what we do in markets as far away as Australia.  Ireland is the accelerator for Green Rebel but it is also the brake for our supply chain in the instances I explained to Deputy Shanahan.  We will continue to invest in Ireland and use Ireland as our proof of concept in many cases.  We will use it as a trampoline, for want of a better word, to show Ireland can compete and be a world leader in this industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.73" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00800"><p>I would add one thing to that.  Ms O'Connell mentioned clusters earlier.  Having clusters of excellence is an important part of this.  Looking at Green Rebel based in Cork and the infrastructure of wind energy companies that are there at the moment, they are also coming around Cork's youth.  Irish companies like DP Energy and Simply Blue are focused on floating wind energy and are building things, employing people and putting infrastructure in place.  Some of the biggest global developers, like &Oslash;rsted and Statkraft, are also based there.  Other companies in the supply chain, such as the Doyle Shipping Group, are looking at the Port of Cork facility as an opportunity.  Mr. Cunniffe and I often joke that we will have to open up our own office in Cork-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H00900"><p>Dead right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.75" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H01000"><p>-----because half our members are based there.  That is an example of how, when there is that critical mass of companies focused on an area, it just grows and grows.  If we can do that in Cork, we can do it in Shannon Foynes on the west coast or in Galway.  Those clusters can expand from there and create jobs in the decarbonisation of our economy, which has to be one of the top priorities for Ireland over the next 20 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#H01100"><p>To clarify, who is on this task force that the witnesses are suggesting needs representatives from the industry?  Is this an internal cross-Government group or does it have a lot of outside sectoral players?  One of the central concerns seems to be that some of the knowledge within the sector is not being brought to bear on those framing the policy.</p><p> My second question is for my own understanding.  We have regional enterprise strategies that are drawn up on a three- or four-year cycle.  We also have regional skills fora.  It seems to me that if you are talking about a number of clusters in Ireland, these might be the vehicle for developing the thinking, as well as for preparing the universities, the colleges of education and the education and training boards, ETBs, for the opportunity.  This would also embed within Government thinking where this opportunity could flow further.  To what extent have the witnesses sought to embed this into these emerging regional enterprise strategies and skills fora that are run regionally?  It seems to me that that is the way to get clusters to work.  It will not be by going to Kildare Street or Merrion Street and by getting someone to call the shots.  It may be the case that a bottom-up, as well as a top-down strategy might be good.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.78" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00200"><p>I thank the Deputy for the questions.  His first question relates to who exactly is on the taskforce.  It is our understanding that the taskforce has recently been established and is cross-departmental.  It also has inputs from the likes of Enterprise Ireland and others.  There is no industry representative on it at the moment.  We believe that we can bring the experience to the table.  Ms O'Connell and others, are bringing that back to Ireland having spent years in other jurisdictions in developing offshore wind energy and learning through its peaks and troughs.  They may have learned lessons in other countries that can help deliver it here.</p> <p>  Earlier, Ms O'Connell mentioned the Offshore Wind Industry Council, which has been established in the UK.  It has considerable industry, Government and State buy-in to develop something similar to this.  The Scottish Offshore Wind Energy Council has something similar too.  There was a Norwegian delegation in Wexford last week.  They also mentioned that there is industry involvement in their establishment.  Their partnership is not quite a sector deal, but people are coming together to deliver this.  We are asking for the best practices that have been put in place in other jurisdictions to establish global leaders in offshore wind industry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00300"><p>-----walls, compared to the various auctions that are run.  There is no compromise for the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.80" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00400"><p>Exactly.  I may bring Ms O&rsquo;Connell in to speak to that point.  We recognise that it is not appropriate for us to be at every table, but we believe that we should be at many of them.  We have much to add.  Does Ms O&rsquo;Connell want to comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.81" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Vanessa O'Connell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00500"><p>In effect, the Offshore Wind Industry Council sits outside of governance yet includes Government and industry representation.  We would have to figure out exactly how it would work in Ireland.  It could probably be an offshoot of the offshore wind industry taskforce.  The industry and the Government would be involved.  It would then be a matter of figuring out what the focus areas should be.  Today, we are very focused on the supply chain.  When you look at the sector deals in the UK, Poland and elsewhere, supply chain is a key focus.  Other elements that are focused on include the points around system integration and resourcing.</p> <p>  One issue I have not mentioned today, which is extremely important, is the environment.  There is now a big focus on having a net-positive effect on the environment from offshore wind.  We can only get that by working together.  As it currently stands, offshore wind farms will do their own environmental assessments on a project-by-project basis.  The environment is much broader than that.  There is much work now ongoing in talking about some sort of strategic compensation and looking across the board.  We would have to work together to figure out how the implementation would work.  The Government needs to do its business, but there needs to be collaboration.  We must figure out where it makes sense to do it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00600"><p>Would anyone  like to deal with the regional question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.83" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Justin Moran" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00700"><p>I will deal with that question.  At the moment, a number of our members in those areas are engaging with those regional economic strategies.  They are engaging particularly with councils, for example, on their plans for developing.  They are looking at how wind energy can be part of that.  We are also finding a real enthusiasm from the regional economic groups, regional assemblies and county councils who want to be involved in it.  We are not encountering resistance there.  It is an open door.  They see the potential that will be in their geographic locations.</p> <p>  That is driven more by groups of members in various areas, rather than by Wind Energy Ireland.  To be honest, from our perspective, that is a capacity issue.  We would love to be more involved in that, but we are focused on the national view.  Our members are focused very much on areas such as Shannon, Cork and Wexford, where companies are coming together to work with existing regional local apparatuses.  This is to see if, for example, there is to be port in Rosslare, what benefits will come out of that for all of the enterprise opportunities in Wexford and in the south east.  Members are actively involved in doing that.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00800"><p>The merit of those regional enterprise strategies is that they bring in the players.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J00900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J01000"><p>They bring the ports, Enterprise Ireland, the IDAs, the councils and the education interests to the table.  If they sign off on a sectoral opportunity being the priority to be developed for the next four years or ten years, suddenly everyone will be pushing in the same direction.  The councils are great.  They have a strategic role in planning, in environmental control and so on.  However, these are bigger forums.  They are certainly worth the witnesses&rsquo; while.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Noel Cunniffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J01100"><p>If it is possible, I would like to highlight one issue that we have not spoken about yet, which is the interest in Ireland from the international supply chain.  It is enormous.  We have already mentioned several delegations.  In the past week, we have had delegations from Norway and from France.  I have been with delegations from the Netherlands, Belgium and Great Britain.  We have had contact from as far away as Brazil to try to bring their supply chain here.  They see the opportunity that Ireland can provide in this decade, as well as the growth that it can provide.  We would like to ensure that while we are delivering this industry we have that domestic supply chain in place to capture as much of that as possible.  Therefore, in years to come, we will be able to send delegations to other countries.  Mr. Ivers already spoke about some of the great work that Enterprise Ireland is doing in that regard.  We have an established, world-leading onshore wind sector here.  Let us take those skills and develop them nto an offshore wind sector we can be proud of and can export.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2022061500002#J01200"><p>I wanted to add that I met with the Danish ambassador and the Dutch ambassador in Limerick on this issue of wind energy.  As nobody else wants to come in and everybody is happy enough, I thank the witnesses for coming before the committee.  It was an important and informative session.  It will not end there.  We will discuss further in private session ourselves how we can progress this.  I take on board what Deputy Shanahan said about having the witnesses before the committee again in near future.  We will visit Belfast and maybe Scotland as well, but definitely Belfast.  We will be in touch with the witnesses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.89" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 10.57 a.m. and adjourned at 11.25 a.m. until 9:30 a.m. on Wednesday, 22 June 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.90" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.91" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 13:10</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:10</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Pearse Doherty, Maria Byrne, Bernard J. Durkan, Pat Casey, Mairéad Farrell, Alice-Mary Higgins. Jim O'Callaghan.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy John McGuinness sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.92" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#A00100">Secondment Policy in the Civil and Public Service: Engagement with Department of Public Expenditure and Reform</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#A00200"><p>I remind members of the note on privilege.  Those on the Leinster House campus are covered by full privilege and those who are not have limited privilege.  I remind them of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p> <p>  The minutes of out last meeting held on 1 June were adopted in private session.  </p> <p>  I welcome the officials from the Department of Expenditure and Reform.  There will be an opening statement and an engagement with members.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#A00300"><p>I thank the committee for the invitation to attend the meeting today and I am happy to have this opportunity to discuss the Civil Service secondment policy and related matters with the committee.  In this context, it is important that the committee is aware that the secondment circular issued by my Department last year is for the Civil Service.  I will comment on certain other secondments but my Department&rsquo;s role in sanctioning secondments under this policy is only within the Civil Service.</p> <p>  In relation to secondment, the Civil Service secondment policy and associated terms were introduced in December 2021.  They were designed to complement the Civil Service mobility scheme, which is for permanent moves between Civil Service organisations, in that it enables the filling of positions concurrent with a strategic project/placement that require specialist knowledge and skill sets for a defined period.  The policy recognises that a number of administrative arrangements had evolved across the Civil Service over time and was not intended to replace such sector-specific arrangements. </p> <p>  Secondments facilitate the release and movement of staff and may provide opportunities for staff to broaden their skills and continue their professional and personal development while retaining the right to return to their substantive or equivalent position.  It is a valuable arrangement that facilitates shared learning, good practice and new ideas.</p> <p>  Currently there are 17 staff of my Department that are seconded in from the civil or public service and there are 19 staff of my Department that are seconded out to the civil or public service.  Included in these numbers are two staff members who are seconded out to administrative roles in the third level sector.  One member of staff is seconded to Dublin City University and the other is seconded to the Technological Higher Education Association.</p> <p>  Also included is one staff member who is seconded in to my Department from National University of Ireland, Galway as a researcher as part of the Science Foundation Ireland programme.  </p> <p>  While the policy applies for secondments in the Civil Service, the policy also provides that the same principles should apply to secondment arrangements between a parent Department and a non-Civil Service body.  It is not a requirement for public service bodies, as distinct from Civil Service organisations, to seek sanction from my Department to fill a position through secondment.  That is a matter between the public service body and its parent Department.</p> <p>  Correspondence from the committee referred to recent secondments to third level institutions.  In respect of the recent secondments of two former Secretaries General to posts in third-level institutions, on the expiry of his term as Secretary General, Dr. Fergal Lynch moved on secondment to NUI Galway.  On the expiry of Mr. Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Foghl&uacute;&rsquo;s term as Secretary General he moved on secondment to NUI Maynooth.</p> <p>  These appointments were in line with Government decisions dating from October 2011 regarding the offer of an alternative position in the civil or public service or an international institution at a salary equivalent to Secretary General until preserved pension age and that retirement before that age would not be the norm.  These terms are reflected in the advertisement booklets for Secretary General posts.  Both secondments are time-limited, for periods less than five years.</p> <p>  Responsibility for third level institutions is a matter for the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation, and Science in the first instance.  More generally however, the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform is involved in a number of ongoing cross-sectoral initiatives that aim to strengthen links between the Civil Service and the university sector in the area of public policy development.  In this regard, I draw the joint committee&rsquo;s attention to a number of such initiatives being pursued by the Irish Government Economic and Evaluation Service, IGEES.  IGEES operates under the aegis of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform and its collaboration with academia is facilitated through the IGEES external advisory group, which consists of representatives from universities, the Economic and Social Research Institute, ESRI, the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council and the Nevin Economic Research Institute, NERI.</p><p>IGEES seeks to further foster knowledge transfers and skills development of IGEES policy analysis by building more extensive networks across academia, through collaborative research, a research fund and various different events.<br/><br/>The secondments of Dr. Lynch and Mr. &Oacute; Foghl&uacute; support, <i>inter alia</i>, progressing the work programme in this policy area, including links to the work being carried out under the Civil Service Renewal 2030 Strategy, led by my Department, and the recently established joint initiative of the Department of An Taoiseach and my Department, Strengthening Policy Development and Strategic Foresight in the Irish Public Service, which is a project being supported by the OECD.<br/><br/>Previous correspondence of the committee also referred to the proposed secondment of the Chief Medical Officer.  On this matter, my Department received a sanction request from the Department of Health on 31 March.  As part of this request, the Department of Health indicated the outgoing CMO would be moving to Trinity College Dublin to take up a professorship on a long-term secondment at the end of June and that it was expected that the secondment would continue until his retirement.  No further detail or material was provided in relation to that secondment.  As is usual with such requests, there was subsequent engagement at official level between my Department and the Department of Health in relation to it, and in relation to the funding aspects of it.  Following the announcement of the CMO of his intention to retire in July, the proposed secondment and associated arrangements were not of relevance to the sanction request for a replacement CMO and a letter of sanction for the post of the CMO issued from my Department on 21 April.  The subsequent report prepared by the Department of Health acknowledges that elements of the arrangements were not communicated well.  The independent review commissioned by the Minister for Health into the process related to the proposed secondment is ongoing and is a matter for that Department.<br/><br/>I trust this is of assistance to the committee and I am happy to take any questions members may have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B00200"><p>Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat as ucht teacht &oacute;s comhair an choiste chun an &aacute;bhar seo a phl&eacute;.  I thank Mr. Moloney for coming in front of the committee to discuss this topic.  To start off on secondments, the crux of the issue that people have been querying over the last number of weeks and months is in relation to a temporary nature of a secondment.  If we look at the HR section on the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform's website, it states that a secondment is a temporary arrangement that facilitates the release and movement of staff members for a specified period of time in a way which does not affect their employment status.  It goes on to note that the maximum time period for this temporary arrangement is five years.  The circular Mr. Moloney referenced was published on the 31 December 2021.  Does this differ from previous circulars in relation to secondments because I, and people generally, would understand that a secondment is of a temporary nature?  Can Mr. Moloney comment on that?  Does he see a secondment as a temporary situation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.97" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B00300"><p>I thank the Deputy.  The purpose of trying to formalise the secondment policy in the circular, which is, I think, the first time it was done, was to try to clarify some of the issues that arose over time, where secondments were conducted in a variety of different ways.  In effect, many secondments became permanent by being rolled over on a continual basis.  The Civil Service mobility scheme, which was introduced and now covers all general service grades between clerical officer and assistant secretary, formalises the process of permanently transferring staff between Departments in the Civil Service.  Therefore, the remaining bit for secondment policy to do, outside of niche areas, specialist expertise or long-standing arrangements that are in place, is to try to regularise how temporary secondments take place.</p> <p>  There is a further complication in that where we second from the Civil Service to an outside body, the terms and conditions such as pension and other entitlements sometimes need to be maintained through a secondment arrangement and in some cases - for example, the two cases of Secretaries General I mentioned - that would make the secondment time limited but there is not an anticipation return to the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B00600"><p>In theory secondments are supposed to be temporary but in practice sometimes they are not.  Is it a technical matter?  Is that what Mr. Moloney is saying? Sometimes secondments are forever.  Does Mr. Moloney think there is a concern in relation to that?  Does he think there needs to be further clarity to make it very clear how secondments work if they are to an external body, as mentioned, and if they are basically long term?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.99" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B00700"><p>Yes.  This is our first attempt to try to bring clarity to this, just within the Civil Service.  Many of the issues that have arisen are in relation to proposed secondments between the Civil Service and the wider public service.  That is an area we can certainly look at.  The one thing I would say is that there is a huge number of secondments, they are really valuable to the system and they occur in a huge variety of different circumstances.  They occur in many different ways - for example, with international institutions, with the Irish Government Economic Evaluation Service, the Attorney General's office and the Central Statistics Office.  Experts are seconded for periods of time into Government offices.  On occasion, those experts become quite imbedded in those Government offices and the secondment evolves in a way that makes it permanent.  What we are trying to do is to twin mobility and secondment policy.  We are trying to make all of that more transparent and make the conditions under which that could happen clearer.  The mobility policy is preferred as the vehicle to achieve permanent transfers and secondment policy, by and large, is there to facilitate temporary transfers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B00800"><p>What would other examples be of secondments being used on a permanent basis?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.101" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B00900"><p>Quite often where somebody is seconded to an international organisation, such as the European Commission, traditionally, they would go on secondment but, in effect, they would be seconded there on a very long-term basis.  Sometimes people would spend their whole career in an international institution-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01000"><p>Why exactly is secondment used for that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01100"><p>This is because the person going to the EU institution would retain the rights to return to the domestic Civil Service and retain their rights to the pension and other pay-related benefits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01200"><p>What impact would that have on hiring someone else to replace them, if they were technically gone for the whole time?  Say, for example, I was in the role just below somebody who was seconded and everyone knew they would be gone the entire time.  What impact would that have on me?  Would I be taking on the duties and responsibilities but not the actual role?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.105" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01300"><p>In practice, the situation often gives a fairly good guide to how long the secondment is likely to be.  In the main, secondments of that nature would be backfilled.  It would not disadvantage or reduce any of the existing staffing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01400"><p>Could that cause an issue if the person came back?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.107" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01500"><p>What happens when the person comes back is that it is often a condition of the secondment that they would not have an automatic right to go back to the job they left, but that they would go back to an equivalent job.  The person would give notice that they were coming back and then a suitable, equivalent job is what they would go back into.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01600"><p>Of the current secondments, how many are at Secretary General and assistant secretary general grade?  Does Mr. Moloney have a figure of the number of people who have gone on secondment because that is the kind of thing we have been talking about?  He mentioned some in his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B01700"><p>We do not.  We only get the sanctions for secondments within the Civil Service.  We do not have data on broader secondments.  The only two Secretaries General secondments of which I am aware are the two I mentioned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#B02000"><p>That is fair.  Some of the questions have already been answered but in relation to the secondments Mr. Moloney mentioned to Maynooth University and the National University of Ireland, Galway, these are secondments that have been raised with us and people have asked serious enough questions.  It is easier to be frank and honest with Mr. Moloney and to ask these questions.  Concerns have been raised that the job descriptions for the work being carried out in both of these roles are very similar and both reference, as was said, the Civil Service renewal strategy, furthering public policy and so on.  What appears to be the case, or at least publicly - maybe Mr. Moloney has other information - is that there is a question on what actual research they are carrying out.  I know some academics and different people working in the field have been asking that same question.  To be fair, it is a valid question.  Would I be right in saying the two individuals would be too young to have full pension rights?</p><p>I do not mean to reflect badly on anyone or anything like that but the following question has been raised.  Are the secondments being used to allow early-retiring senior officials who do not have full pension rights a way of maintaining their incomes?  As I said, this is not to reflect on either of the two people; I would just like to hear Mr. Moloney's thoughts and views on that because it is something that is being raised with us and this point needs to be addressed frankly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.112" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00200"><p>I will take the last point first.  The Government decision in 2011 was a clear one.  It said that when a retiring Secretary General reaches the end of their term and has not yet reached preserved pension age, the minimum pension age, the Government may offer them an alternative position.  In the case of the two Secretaries General we are talking about, the Government made the decision late last year to do that.  It is a term and condition of the appointment of Secretaries General since 2011.  It is detailed in the Public Appointments Service, PAS, booklets on those competitions that at the end of their term, if they have not reached full retirement age, the Government can choose to offer them a post in the Civil Service, the public service or an international institution.  That is the policy that has been in place since 2011.</p> <p>  The Deputy said that concerns have been raised about the similarity of the roles and there is a similarity.  Having decided to offer these two people a post, the Government took the opportunity to further one of the Civil Service renewal actions in public policy and improving public policy and particularly in terms of developing communities of practice that link in the academic sector with our work in the Civil Service and with Enterprise Ireland and other researchers.  We do part of that through IGEES but we want to do more of it under the banner of Civil Service and public service reform.  This was an opportunity to place them in universities and develop those networks.  Within my Department they are both involved in public service reform and there are slightly different public service reform aspects to this work.  One of the retired Secretaries General is involved in the organisational capability reviews and is chairing the group of Secretaries General who drive and oversee the organisational capability reviews.  For example one such review has been done in the Department of Defence and one has been done in the Office of Public Works, OPW.  The other retired Secretary General is more involved in a specific OECD project on strategic foresight, evidence-based policies and the structure and hierarchy of the Civil Service.  Both jobs are a mixture of a role within the university, networking and an attempt to build a greater community partnership within academia and the Civil Service and public service.  The elements of reform involved in each post are slightly different, as I have described.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1579" speakername="Mairead Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00300"><p>That is interesting and that probably covers most of my questions.  Mr. Moloney is saying he is fully confident that they have a great job of work there and about the research they are carrying out.  In fairness Mr. Moloney has given more detail on that there but sometimes we need to be honest about these things because we have unfortunately had a history in this State of a huge lack of transparency in appointments to roles.  It would be beneficial for that information on the research they are carrying out to be provided in a more open and transparent way.  This matter has been raised with us in the committee by certain people as they have not been able to get that information.  It is important that this information be readily available to people.</p> <p>  That rule on Secretaries General is quite interesting and I would say that a lot of people watching on would say that it is not a bad gig if you can get it.  It is good that you have provided that clarity on the work that is being done.  I thank Mr. Moloney.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00400"><p>I thank Mr. Moloney and his staff for coming before the committee.  I agree with him when he says there are benefits to secondments in staff being able to broaden their skills and continue their professional and personal development.  Would I be correct in saying that we have an issue in Ireland with retired Secretaries General and what to do with them when their seven years are up and they have not reached retirement age?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.115" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00500"><p>I thank the Deputy for the question.  We have a policy in place on that since 2011.  The December 2011 decision on this sets out what to do with retired Secretaries General and it offers a number of options.  In practice the option to extend the term of Secretaries General has often been taken.  There is the option of reassigning them within the Civil Service and public service and the option of seconding them to another position in the Civil Service, in the public service or in an international institution is also there.  The 2011 decision is clear that the object is not to make the retirement of Secretaries General at the end of their terms before preserved pension age the standard and usual practice.  I understand the question but I see it slightly differently, in terms of it being part of the terms and conditions under which the posts are advertised.  There is a clear understanding that at the end of your term, these different options exist to take you up to preserved pension age, which is what both of the cases we discussed today involve.  In explaining that policy, that is seen in an overall context where it would potentially be difficult to recruit people into those roles if they did not have a path at the end of their terms.  That is something the performance review group has identified as an issue.  It is also something the de Buitl&eacute;ir group that the Government has recently established to review senior public service recruitment and pay processes is looking at.  The treatment of Secretaries General at end of term in this context is one of the issues the group will look at, among the gamut of processes around the appointment of and remuneration for Secretaries General.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00600"><p>The reason I asked the question is that I am conscious, as I am sure Mr. Moloney is, that in recent times we have had two Secretaries General who have gone on to become ambassadors.  The Secretaries General referred to in Mr. Moloney&rsquo;s submission to the committee have gone on into third level institutions.  All of them are highly qualified and talented people but the impression I get as a Deputy is that suitable jobs are being looked for to see what we can do with this talented person whose seven years is up and where can that policy go.  Are the options that are available to retired Secretaries General getting broader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.117" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00700"><p>The 2011 policy replaces an earlier policy which would, in the main, have given one ten years added service and put one into pension payment immediately.  The 2011 policy was created in the context that people were not happy that people before preserved retirement age were immediately put into significant pensions.  The policy decision was taken that instead of giving added years, alternative posts would be offered up to pension age.  That is why it might appear to be more frequent; this policy is only in place since 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00800"><p>When did the seven-year term for Secretaries General come in?  I should know that myself and I apologise that I do not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C00900"><p>I should also know that.  I am going to guess that it was in 1984.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01000"><p>Between 1984 and 2011, from Mr. Moloney's recollection what was the general pathway for Secretaries General whose seven years had expired but who had not reached retirement age?  Where did they generally go?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01100"><p>To the best of my knowledge, those Secretaries General would have been entitled to the immediate payment of pension-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01200"><p>So they retired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.123" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01300"><p>-----and they would retire but they would get a severance payment, a lump sum and the immediate payment of pension, regardless of age.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01400"><p>Prior to 2011, the vast majority of them, having done their terms as Secretaries General, retired irrespective of their age.  Would that be fair to say?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.125" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01600"><p>The point that Mr. Moloney is making to the committee is that this is as a result of the changes brought in during 2011 as a result of the financial crisis at that time.  Does that mean they simply cannot retire if they want to avail of their full pension entitlement?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01700"><p>Up to the 2011 policy change they would have been entitled to retire at 50 and immediately get the full pension.  However many years of service they had, which might be 30 years if they were 50 years-old, they would get ten added years and they would get a full pension.  A Secretary General currently serving who retired at 50 would get a pension of a large amount of money immediately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#C01800"><p>Prior to the secondment of individuals to third level institutions and as ambassadors, had that happened prior to recent times?  Had retiring Secretaries General gone to academia or the diplomatic corps?</p><p>The Deputy will understand I do not have full visibility but, as I understand it, it is a common enough practice within the Department of Foreign Affairs that the Secretary General of that Department would take up an ambassadorship-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00300"><p>-----post at the end of that particular term.  That is the only one I can think off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00400"><p>The individuals are fine individuals and I make no criticism of them.  My understanding is that one of them was from the Department of Foreign Affairs and another was outside that Department.  Is that something that is generally seen as being available to retiring Secretaries General, that they can become an ambassador?  I am not asking Mr. Moloney to disclose any interests he may have in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00500"><p>No.  I will hopefully reach preserved retirement age by the end my term.  It is an option.  It was a 2011 decision.  If you were appointed post 2011, you served seven years and got a three year extension.  That is why these issues are arising now.  Reflecting on the experience of them for the first time in 2021 and 2022, the independent review panel has an opportunity to look at those issues and to make an assessment of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00600"><p>When it comes to appointment as an ambassador, these are jobs that are not generally advertised. They may be notified internally in the Department of Foreign Affairs.  I can understand why they would not be advertised.  In respect of someone who is going into an academic institution, the policy issue or the public concern voiced by many Members of the House of the Oireachtas was that if a Secretary General, or a very high-ranking civil servant, was going to go into a third level academic institution, that is all well and proper but there should be an opportunity for others to apply for the position being filled.  What would Mr. Moloney say to that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00700"><p>Again, it is back to the 2011 policy which is where we started.  The Government decision means someone can be offered a post to the end of their term and the subsequent Government decision agreed that with the two individuals involved.  In a sense and in general terms, the policy of advertisement and competition for posts is absolutely correct policy but in specific terms, the 2011 decision creates a policy framework where retiring Secretaries General, before preserved pension age, may be offered a position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00800"><p>From the point of view of the third level institution, it is not costing it anything in terms of taking on the Secretary General in a new position.  Is that a fair assessment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D00900"><p>The payment of the Secretaries General involved are made by the third level institution but obviously they are funded by the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01000"><p>Okay.  I thank Mr. Moloney.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01100"><p>Does Deputy O'Callaghan have a question around the Members and their retirement?  Where do Members go when they retire?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1553" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01200"><p>The next time we are looking for an ambassador to the United States, we should start by looking at chairmen of committees like yourself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01300"><p>I think so, yes.  It is unusual that there would be all these concerns expressed about Secretaries General, who are reasonably well-paid and so on, but no one is concerned about the future of the Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas who make, or are supposed to make, the policy.  I thought Deputy O'Callaghan might have raised that question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01400"><p>That was an interesting conversation.  I wish to point out that I probably have a different view from other people on this issue.  The people who have served their full-time, or not yet served their full-time, in the public service, may still have something to offer and it should not be lost.  Their experience and their ability should not be consigned to the waste.  They still have a lot to offer and while secondment may be an emotive issue, it does not take away from the fact that as, I think, Galbraith used to say, members of the older generation still have a lot to offer and although they may require longer holidays, they still could offer a great deal in terms of experience that should remain available to the public sector in the event that the public sector was of a mind to accept it.</p> <p>  There is a possibility that we have become "soundbite-ist", for want of a better description, in terms of our reaction as public representatives.  I do not contribute to that at all.  There was a situation in the military sector once upon a time where an army officer or anybody serving in the army would, after 21 years, avail of a full pension and go elsewhere.  That had the double effect of renewing the membership of the Defence Forces on a regular basis.  Without any particular intervention, people went elsewhere.  People, however, decided to change that and said it was not fair that some people were offered this concession, despite the fact that the original intention was to achieve the result of getting people to retire from the Defence Forces and giving them an incentive to do so.</p> <p>  I refer to taking the soundbites, the emotionalism and the populism out of it.  Everybody will oppose somebody getting something they think they should not get.  I know we have to protect ourselves and the integrity of the public sector but at the same time, we should keep in mind that the people retiring may still have something to offer.  The best way to utilise or to harness that energy, experience and enthusiasm, or whatever, needs to be found.  We have not always found it.  There are particular options open to some people, such as the Secretaries General referred to, in some Departments, but we need to look further and see how we can utilise those people's services to a greater extent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01500"><p>I thank the Deputy.  Certainly, I agree.  I absolutely agree it is true across all grades.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01600"><p>It is.  I agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01800"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Uasal Moloney chuig an gcoiste.  A lot has been asked so I am not going to go over old ground in relation to this but I have one or two questions that I would like to ask on the secondment policy within the public service.  We have looked at and discussed the recent circular stating that secondments are not supposed to be for more than five years.  If he has not already done so, can Mr. Moloney tell the committee how many secondments of over five years are in existence in the public sector?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D01900"><p>I am afraid we only have, since the operation of this policy, information on sanctions within the Civil Service.  That is only since the end of last year.  We do not have a role in secondment in the wider public sector generally and we do not have the data on it.  Secondments are, as I said, very commonly used in order to generate knowledge and broaden experience.  I am afraid I do not have the numbers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D02000"><p>The Department of Public Expenditure and Reform deals not just with the Civil Service but with the public sector as well.  Does the Department have any insight into what is happening in terms of secondments within the public sector?  Obviously, the title of the Department includes reform so is there any way for the committee to find out whether there is 5,000, 10,000 or 50,000 secondments or whether 8,000 of them have been for a duration of nine years?  Are there people who have been seconded and have been forgotten all about?  The committee would like to know some of this data.  Is it possible to have it collated?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.148" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#D02100"><p>The Deputy is quite right.  The Department has an interest in public service reform, end to end, right across the public service.  Our responsibilities as an employer are related to the Civil Service so when we talk about having information on the Civil Service it is because we are the employer of the civil servants.  Whereas in the wider public sector, you are probably the employer of the board of your particular part of the public sector.  The HSE board is probably the employer for a lot of the HSE.  The Department does not have the HR data outside of the Civil Service.  In terms of whether it could be collected, it is certainly an issue we could discuss, for example, at the public service leadership board.  Again, there is a very wide variety of public service organisations across 360,000 people so it is quite a data exercise.  We could look to see what insights might be gleaned and it might, in fact, be a natural next step to the review of the secondment policy that we are due to do after six months - in effect, starting next month in any case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00100"><p>It would be extremely helpful to get a sense of where we are at this point in time.  As parliamentarians, we can table questions to every Department and agency and ask them how many secondments they have but I expect it would be better if that was collated by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform and presented to the committee rather than us doing it individually, which we can do and I might do that.  It is important to get a sense of where we are at and, in particular, whether there are long-term secondments that should no longer be secondments, whereby people probably have been in those roles for so long that those positions should be permanent.  With permanency comes particular conditions.  Has Mr. Moloney found that to be the case in the Civil Service and in the public sector or has he got an insight into any of this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.150" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00200"><p>What I said earlier is probably relevant in this context.  With the development of a mobility policy for all grades between clerical officer and assistant secretary, we would like that to be the mechanism within the Civil Service that is used for permanent assignments because we think that is much more open, transparent and clearer.  We would like secondments to be predominantly temporary, although we recognise there is a great variety of secondments and they have different characteristics, and we set out some exceptions in the guidance.  The difference between seconding somebody and permanently moving somebody is sometimes to do with the different terms and conditions that can occur.  For example, we only have a mobility policy for the general grade civil servants.  We do not yet have a mobility policy for the professional and technical grades.  For particular areas of specialism, there would be worries for people involved about how much they carried their existing terms and conditions with them but that is all there to be worked through and we are working through it for the technical professional grades for the Civil Service.  Certainly, those lessons can be taken on board in our review and in how we might progress that for the wider public sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00300"><p>Some of those elected to the D&aacute;il or the Seanad can avail of a type of secondment.  If one worked in the public sector prior to be elected to one of these Houses, is it not the case that position remains open to that person?  Is Mr. Moloney familiar with that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.152" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00400"><p>There is a number of arrangements.  They are generally called special leave arrangements.  They would apply, as the Deputy said, to public representatives.  They could apply to jobs in international institutions.  There are various special leave without pay arrangements that can maintain that entitlement to come back into an equivalent role.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00500"><p>Is it Mr. Moloney's view those special arrangements should be of an indefinite nature as they are at present?  Mr. Moloney can correct me if I am wrong but my understanding is a teacher - not to pick on teachers as my three sisters and my wife are teachers - could be elected as a Member of the Oireachtas and 25 years later, having lost the job, that person could return to teaching as the position would have been kept open for that person.  Does Mr. Moloney believe a timeframe should apply to these special leave arrangements?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.154" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00600"><p>The justification for them is not to discourage people.  It is quite a big step to be a teacher, then get elected as a public representative for four years and not to have a permanent job to which to return.  It is not that the teaching job is not filled.  It is filled and when one is prepared to go back to being a teacher again, an available teaching job will be allocated to the person.  It Is not that the job the person left 40 years ago is still there waiting for that person.  It is that the person has an entitlement to come back to a teaching post or an equivalent post.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00700"><p>My understanding is it is the job the person left that is available to the person because the position that is backfilled is a temporary position.  The person who backfills it is not given permanency and that is a problem.  There is an issue in terms of workers&rsquo; rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.156" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00800"><p>We can look at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E00900"><p>To move away from the Houses of the Oireachtas and turn to the public service and Civil Service, I am familiar with cases where, for example, a professional working in a publicly-funded hospital but not one that comes under the remit of the HSE has been seconded to the Department or the HSE and that person's hospital position would have been backfilled but it would only be on a temporary basis because it the post holder is on secondment.  The professional can return to that role when the secondment finishes.  I know of cases where five or six years later, a professional backfilling that position is still temporary.  The consequences of that are significant.  If a person want to get a mortgage, he or she will not get one on having a non-secure employment position.  People are seconded for long durations over a five-year period and the backfilling of those positions is still temporary.  Is that fair in this day and age in terms of the public sector and those publicly funded institutions such as our hospitals?  It is no wonder people are seeking more permanency and travelling across the water in some cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.158" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E01000"><p>Within the Civil Service, which is the area with which I am familiar, in general, we avoid those situations where we can.  Sometimes it means the person returning to a position faces a delay or has to go into a different but equivalent job.  Even in terms of the relevant legal provisions, maintaining somebody on a temporary basis but really permanently is undesirable and questionable.  That certainly is not the intention of the Civil Service policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1462" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E01100"><p>I welcome the fact that in the Civil Service that is not the case but I would encourage Mr. Moloney to take it to the next step.  Let us have a bird&rsquo;s eye view of where we are at with secondments, which is an important role in the transferring of experience and so on.  I would like to know if there are people who have been seconded for ten years and if so, perhaps those should be permanent positions now.  I know of a case of a former Deputy who was a member of Deputy Durkan&rsquo;s party and who used to be my headmaster.  The person who replaced him in the school was temporary.  That is happening in the public sector.  People with professional degrees in our health sector, having been five or six years in the position, are not able to get a permanent contract because the position they are filling was vacated by somebody who was seconded to another position.  Two jobs of work need to be done.  We need to get an idea of where we are at with secondments and with the backfilling of roles.  We also need to apply the same principles Mr. Moloney mentioned that apply to the Civil Service to the public sector and those publicly funded bodies.  That would be helpful in recruiting and retaining some of those key personnel we need.  I thank Mr. Moloney for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.160" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E01200"><p>I thank the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E01300"><p>In terms of the public service versus the Civil Service, Mr. Moloney said the circular letter of 2021 relates to the Civil Service only.  What is the process for ensuring there is a similar type of policy shared by the public sector?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.162" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E01400"><p>The Civil Service versus public service distinction is around the employer.  The Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform really is the employer of civil servants.  Public servants are employed by the governing body of whatever organisations they are in, by the board generally.  What we try to do through the public service reform and through the public service leadership board is to articulate and consult on the policies being developed for civil servants and encourage public service bodies to adopt like policies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#E01500"><p>These public service bodies are generally agencies of a Department.  In terms of the circular letter that was issued, it is interesting to hear the explanation being offered that it applied only to civil servants and, therefore, the public service was left to one side.</p><p>That is not good practice.  If we are expecting one policy to be followed by a civil servant, any agency that comes under a Department should at least share, in a general way, that Civil Service policy.  Otherwise, a completely different approach is adopted to different actions that might be taken, be it secondment or whatever it might be.  Relative to the current issue of the Secretaries General where one was to be seconded and the other who was seconded, it appears now that circular does not cover them.  Is that right?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.165" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00200"><p>There are a few points there.  First, the secondment policy is one for the Civil Service because in terms of our governance and legislative function, that is what our function is.  On the other hand, the policy contains within it the hope, exactly as the Chairman said, that the public service bodies would follow the lead of that policy.  That is very much the framework we use.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00300"><p>In this case the hope has not succeeded because this has now been put forward as a distinction.  The circular applied to a civil servant but it does not apply to a body that is part of the public service.  What process is in place to make sure the hope Mr. Moloney has that the public service will follow the line of the Civil Service in respect of the policy, and the letter that was issued in 2021, will be followed, adhered to or, in general, be the guideline for what the public service will do?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00400"><p>The two secondments of the civil servants we talked about broadly fit within the policy set alongside the Government decision.  In terms of the public service and it following the policy, this is a policy that has been approved by the Civil Service Management Board and the Secretary General of each Department is in a position to encourage the bodies under its aegis to use it.  We do that with quite a number policies in terms of general standards and guidelines.  However, we must respect the fact that the legislation gives the HSE board governance responsibilities over the HSE.  We have many different avenues to push out these guidelines and encourage bodies to align with them.  Broadly speaking, within the particular context, bodies are happy to do that.  The blended working framework is one of the more recent examples.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00500"><p>To return to Mr. Moloney Department, he said, in his opening statement, "my Department's role in sanctioning secondments ..." therefore, he sanctions them.  What does he look at when sanctioning a particular secondment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00600"><p>We ask the proposer of the secondment what they have done in terms of what need they have identified, have they identified whether there is anyone in their organisation who could fulfil that need and in what way they intend to operationalise the secondment - for example, will they use an advertisement through the Public Appointments Service, PAS?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00700"><p>Would Mr. Moloney cover such matters as the salary for the person?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.171" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00800"><p>The general principle we adopt in the Civil Service is that the salary is not related to the person, it is related to the post.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F00900"><p>When Mr. Moloney considers the person holding the post in the Civil Service or in the public service who is about to be seconded to a university, what would he look at in terms of that sanction?  Is it as broad as what he has just said and that is it?  Does he consider the knock-on effects of that person departing their role, will that person be paid by the Department or by the university and if there are any other strings or costs attached to it?  Does he go into that type of examination?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.173" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01000"><p>It would depend.  I am not sure of the example.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01100"><p>The example is obvious.  The reason we are having this discussion today is because of the arrangement that was being made with Trinity College.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.175" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01200"><p>In terms of the arrangement with Trinity College and that particular example, in effect, because the proposal was withdrawn we never got a proposal around that secondment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01300"><p>You did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.177" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01400"><p>We got a request for the sanctioning of a replacement Chief Medical Officer, CMO, and that was the first time we were made aware of it.  We got that on 31 March and very shortly after that the CMO - and we are still discussing that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01500"><p>Is it fair to say Mr. Moloney, as the Secretary General of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, you knew nothing about this prior to the request for sanctioning having been made by the Department of Health?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.179" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01600"><p>Yes.  That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01700"><p>Was Mr. Moloney in any way alarmed by the initial suggestion of the secondment, the salary and the other financial attachments to that position?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.181" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01800"><p>Again, no proposal was submitted to me regarding the other financial attachments.  What I would have expected was early engagement on any funding consequences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F01900"><p>There was no engagement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.183" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02000"><p>Prior to 31 March, that is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02100"><p>Yes.  There was no engagement prior that and what about after 31 March?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.185" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02200"><p>After 31 March the proposal was very quickly superseded by the CMO&rsquo;s decision to retire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02300"><p>When did he decide to retire?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.187" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02400"><p>I do not have that date but between 31 March and 23 April when we sanctioned a replacement-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02500"><p>Three weeks after  31 March.  Therefore, nothing happened in that three-week period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.189" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02600"><p>The relevant Vote management section in the Department was engaging with the Department of Health on it.  There was a report, I think, to this committee from the Secretary General of the Department of Health.  I am not sure to whom that report-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02700"><p>From Mr. Moloney's knowledge of it, it was not something that came across his radar.  Was it dealt with by the section?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.191" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02800"><p>To be clear about it, secondment is not something that would have necessarily crossed my radar in any great way.  It was a secondment into the public sector.  The lack of engagement on the funding characteristics is the issue we would have begun to follow as we became aware of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F02900"><p>There was a lack of engagement on the funding aspect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.193" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03000"><p>We would have preferred earlier engagement on the funding aspects.  Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03100"><p>It is clear that now we know there was a lack of engagement regarding the funding arrangements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.195" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03200"><p>We still do not have a funding proposal because the issue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03300"><p>Mr. Moloney just said there was a lack of engagement on the funding arrangements-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.197" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03500"><p>-----so there was no funding arrangement, no funding proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.199" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03600"><p>Then the CMO's intention to retire superseded that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03700"><p>Yes but that funding arrangement would be part of the consideration in terms of the secondment, I presume.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.201" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03800"><p>We did not get a proposal so I am only going by what I see in committees and what I read in the newspapers but it appears the two issues were linked.  Certainly we would have preferred earlier engagement on the funding issue but normally funding issues would not be that linked to a secondment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F03900"><p>Funding issues of five years at &euro;2 million or of five years the cost of a salary or more, or for a longer period of time, must surely have been an issue somewhere.  Correct me if I am wrong but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.203" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F04000"><p>No one ever proposed that to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F04100"><p>No one ever proposed that.  That is fine.  We can leave it at that.</p> <p>  In terms of anyone going on secondment to the Civil Service or public service, does that person's salary continue to be paid by either the parent Department or by the Department itself if the person is a Secretary General?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.205" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#F04200"><p>The policy states in the case of secondments between the Civil Service and public service and secondments within public service bodies the human resources, HR, pay and other arrangements are for discussion between the two parties.  There would be a discussion about that.  Regarding the two Secretaries General secondments we spoke about earlier, both of those are being paid for by the university.</p><p>They are on the payroll of the universities.  Obviously, they are funded through the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science Vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00200"><p>While they are being paid for by the universities, they are also being paid for, in some of the cases, by the Department of Education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.208" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00300"><p>Yes, as all public service salaries are paid through the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00400"><p>Would it be the case that any of the Secretaries General who are on secondment would continue to be paid by the Departments they are leaving?  In other words, they would go to the university-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.210" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00500"><p>I am only aware of two secondments, and it is not true in either of those cases.  They are not being paid for by their Departments; they are being paid for by the university.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00600"><p>They leave and there is no further cost on the relevant Department as far as they are concerned.  It comes out of the Department of Education's budget.  Is that the same level of salary?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.212" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00800"><p>If, therefore, I am on a certain salary when I go on secondment, I will continue to get paid that same level of salary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.214" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G00900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01000"><p>I agree with the whole idea of secondment in terms of the knowledge that is shared by those who go into the public sector or a field of education or those who perhaps share with enterprise.  That person is sharing knowledge he or she gained in the Civil Service or the public service.  That is understood.  How do they bring that knowledge back to the relevant Department?  In terms of education, a person might have been in Trinity College Dublin or wherever.  Where is the value in that for Departments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.216" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01100"><p>Is this in respect of the two secondments of Secretaries General or generally?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01200"><p>Yes, or any secondment.  A person is there to share information and knowledge.  How does any Department benefit from having this arrangement?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.218" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01300"><p>People would generally accept that there is a benefit to having people who have experience of more than one administrative system, Department and policy area.  There is a great benefit.  That kind of mobility to really-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01400"><p>To whom and where?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.220" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01500"><p>To the whole Department and to the various sets of skills within a Department's groupthink to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01600"><p>That is what I am trying to get at.  When the people who are seconded to these positions come back into their Departments, the hope then is that they bring back the knowledge and experience they garnered through that new position and that they open up, as it were, the view of their Departments on different things.  How many of them have come back?  Would it have been expected that the two Secretaries General who have gone on secondment would come back at some stage and share that knowledge?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.222" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01700"><p>Around secondments generally, this arrangement of sanctioning has only been in place since the end of the year. However, the experience within my Department is that people generally come back after secondment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01800"><p>Would Mr. Moloney have expected, say, one of the Secretaries General who are currently on secondment, without naming them, to come back?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.224" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G01900"><p>In the context of Government policy and the decision of 2011, it is clear that the secondment lasts until preserved pension age.  The intention behind that policy, which is slightly different to the generality, is clear that the secondment lasts until retirement age.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02000"><p>That is my point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.226" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02100"><p>The Chairman should bear in mind that there is engagement over the course of the secondment.  Both are involved in the civil and public service reform process in the ways I described earlier.  Both are involved with the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science in trying to create this community of practice about which I spoke earlier.  Our hope is that during their period of secondment, and they are senior leaders in their field, they will feed into the public sector reform process and into greater engagement between academia and the public service generally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02200"><p>Is there any big-ticket item Mr. Moloney can think of in terms of reform that was caused by this exchange of knowledge between one position and another when a Secretary General or person who was on secondment came back?  Secondments have gone on for so many years and involved so many people.  Deputy Doherty is trying to get to the bottom of that in terms of how many there are.  Are they still there?  Who is paying them?  What knowledge did they bring back?  I have not seen a great deal of reform in the Civil Service which suggests to me that some magnificent piece of information came back that caused reform to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.228" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02300"><p>I would respectfully say that there has been considerable reform in the Civil Service and public service over that last decade.  Of course, we are continuing a process of public sector reform and transformation.  Where we are with ICT and digital, skills development, staff, managerial expertise, shared knowledge and back office function has changed very significantly over that period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02400"><p>That would have come from that shared experience and information coming back.  It would have helped the direction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.230" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02500"><p>It would have come from many things.  It would have been helped by secondment, mobility and a focus on professionalisation within the civil and public service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02600"><p>That is grand.  I am anxious to learn about this.  Mr. Moloney covered the part in his opening statement in which he spoke about the public service and the Civil Service.  He might tell me about the public sector leadership board.  How does that function?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.232" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02700"><p>I chair the public sector leadership board, which comprises the Secretaries General of a number of Departments and the heads of the main agencies that fall under the remit of those Departments, namely, the Chief of Staff of the Defence Forces, the Garda Commissioner, the chief executive officer of the HSE, etc.  The board meets on a regular basis - three to four times per year - and seeks to further the actions in the public service reform programme.  It has a particular focus on equality, diversion and inclusion, EDI, initiatives across the public service, for example, and developing a toolkit for organisations with which they can address EDI policies.  It has only been established since 2018 or 2019.  It is a forum in which we hope to drive many of the things the Chairman talked about such as good practice and shared learning throughout the civil and public service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02800"><p>All the Secretaries General are on that board and then there are outside agencies, one of them obviously being the HSE.  How many people are on that board?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.234" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G02900"><p>It has a subset of them.  I do not know exactly how many are on it.  I would guess there are approximately 18 people on that board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03000"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.236" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03100"><p>I can check that for the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03200"><p>The board meets three or four time per year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.238" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03400"><p>Is the practice of Secretaries General being appointed as ambassadors a normal thing?  I heard Mr. Moloney's earlier exchange with Deputy O'Callaghan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.240" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03500"><p>All these appointments are regular in accordance with the relevant Government decisions.  The point I made to Deputy O'Callaghan was that there was a tradition within the Department of Foreign Affairs, in particular, whereby a retired Secretary General from that Department would often take up an ambassadorial post at the end of his or her term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03600"><p>Is that still the case?  Obviously, it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.242" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03700"><p>That is the case for the previous one anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03800"><p>Okay.  I will go back to the recruitment of Secretaries General in Departments.  The arrangement of a secondment during which a Secretary General retires and is not of pension age is part of the offer in terms of the job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.244" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G03900"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04000"><p>How long has that been in place?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.246" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04100"><p>Since the Government decision in 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04200"><p>What happened before then?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.248" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04300"><p>Secretaries General who reached the end of their terms were entitled to immediate pension payment regardless of age.  If they were below preserved pension age, they were entitled to up to ten years extra service to age 65.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04400"><p>Did that policy come through the public sector leadership board or something of its kind?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.250" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04500"><p>No.  The public sector leadership board did not exist at the time.  It was a separate Government decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04600"><p>That is what I am saying.  Was it some other entity like that or was it Government policy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.252" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#G04700"><p>I am told it was a Government decision dating from 1987.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00100"><p>From 1987.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.254" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00300"><p>I want to understand this.  There are not many jobs like that are there?  For example, if you are given a seven-year term as a Secretary General and if you reach the end of that seven years before retirement, that is generally it in the private sector.  You can then get a job with the experience of your previous seven years or get an extension of seven years.  Is it not better to promote the extension?  Deputy Durkan made the point - and I agree with him - that we are losing good people from many positions because there is some notional retirement age.  These people could still do the job, and some of them want to do it.  Is it not time to review that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.256" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00400"><p>It is within the terms of reference of the independent review panel to look at these questions of how we recruit and what we would do with extension and end of term issues around Secretaries General.  The security of tenure is one of the characteristics of Civil Service jobs that is part of the terms and conditions generally and that is reflected in the various ways of calculating the benefits and attractiveness of the job to prospective applicants.  That has been an issue.  Those are all within the ambit of the independent review panel and can be examined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00500"><p>Who is on that panel?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.258" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00600"><p>It is a panel of three people and Dr. Donal de Buitl&eacute;ir is the chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00700"><p>This is the panel that has just been appointed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.260" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00800"><p>Yes.  It was appointed a month or two ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H00900"><p>Remind me who is on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.262" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01000"><p>Dr. Donal de Buitl&eacute;ir is the chair of it.  Mr. Bryan Andrews is another member.  He is a former chief executive of the Public Appointments Service.  Ms Jenny Smyth is a senior client partner with Korn Ferry, and she is the third member.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01100"><p>How long has Mr. Moloney been in the Civil Service?  How many years has he been Secretary General?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.264" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01200"><p>I was appointed in August of last year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01300"><p>Mr. Moloney would have been promoted through the Civil Service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.266" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01400"><p>Yes.  I started in the Civil Service so long ago that I am having difficulty recalling the date.  It was in 1990.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01500"><p>My point is that Mr. Moloney has experience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.268" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01700"><p>Is the practice of hiring or employing people in the Civil Service good enough or should it be changed?  Is there better practice in the private sector that could be introduced to the civil and public service?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.270" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01800"><p>The Civil Service has been successful in attracting high-quality people over the years, but there is always more to be done and there are always ways of looking around and seeing what can be improved.  The independent review panel will do that for senior public service posts and to be fair to the Public Appointments Service, it is constantly looking at new ways of recruiting people, and is aware, particularly in the current labour market, of the need to get people in.  Many of our processes are driven by the need to be meticulously fair, to follow the Commission for Public Service Appointments guidelines.  Sometimes they can be perceived to be slow and people might go off and get other jobs, which is a particular challenge in the current environment where people have such choice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H01900"><p>The reason I am asking is because we have not had great success in attracting people from outside into the senior ranks of the Civil Service.  Is that to do with salaries or is it to do with them going off and getting different jobs while they are waiting, as Mr. Moloney said, for decisions to be made?  What can we do to make it more attractive to those outside to come in and bring in some fresh thinking or new direction if it is needed?  Is there anything obvious that Mr. Moloney thinks should be done?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.272" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H02000"><p>There has been some success in attracting people into the Civil Service at senior levels, including at assistant principal and principal officer level.  We have seen the progression of some of those people up to and including Secretary General level.  What is sometimes talked about is bringing people in directly at assistant secretary or Secretary General level.  The general view is that the level of applications and interest we get in those has not yielded in the last two years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H02100"><p>Is it the salary then?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.274" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H02200"><p>It is hard for us to tell why people have not applied or do not choose it as a career.  It is notable that in tougher economic times there appeared to be better private sector interest in Civil Service jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#H02300"><p>That is an interesting conversation which refers to many aspects of working in the public service and transferring on to the private sector, and <i>vice versa</i>.  However, Deputy Doherty made an interesting reference to the teachers who become Deputies or Senators.  It could be significant in their pension entitlements in the event that they serve one term or a short term of office in the Oireachtas and then find themselves with insufficient pension entitlements.  They might go back to the public service in teaching positions and they may have several years to go, a short number of years to go or insufficient years to go to achieve a full pension.  They could well find themselves at a distinct disadvantage.  My humble suggestion would be that those who are replacements should be able to go forward on the basis that they could achieve permanency after a short number of years and acquire full pension entitlements.  That is one of the things that needs to be looked at and done.</p><p>I am sure the Chairman already knows the following.  I made reference to the Defence Forces and much is made today of the fact that it is difficult to recruit and retain people there.  It is difficult because the Oireachtas took away those entitlements they had where the person who had entered the Defence Forces spent 21 years there and walked away with a full pension.  This person could take a part-time job or a smaller job that was sufficient to meet their requirements and that may have been in line with their needs to do less work and so on.  We have taken that away and it creates an obstacle to recruitment in the Defence Forces.</p><p>The following matter also needs to be borne in mind.  There is a system in the Defence Forces involving individuals who suffered personal injuries and who claimed and obtained compensation, be it 20 years ago, 30 years ago or whatever.  In those cases, assuming the person has been discharged from the Defence Forces as being unfit to serve due to their injuries, they then qualify for a pension.  In the course of the payment of that pension, a sum is deducted on a monthly basis to recover the payment made in respect of compensation, which is an appalling decision and this measure is regularly enforced.  The phrase in the Army Pensions Act 1927 states that &quot;The Minister may&quot; recover all or part of the amount of the previous award in determining the amount of pension the person may get.  It is an appalling thing to do to people who have served the country and who have been injured to the extent that they were no longer able to serve in the Defence Forces.  The Act says &quot;The Minister may&quot;; it does not say &quot;The Minister shall&quot; but we know all about that phrase over the years, what it means and the implications for the public service.  That is another matter that needs to be looked at in order to be fair to people who work in the public service and the private sector and who have reason to change over.</p><p>Those two issues need to be looked at.  Deputy Doherty is right regarding the point relating to teachers.  I would like to see a major change on the issue I referred to in respect of the Defence Forces.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00200"><p>Is the Deputy asking Mr. Moloney to make a------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00300"><p>I am not asking him to run in my constituency but I am sure he knows about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.278" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00400"><p>I am not fully sighted on it for this meeting but we can certainly have a look at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00500"><p>The Ministers and Secretaries Act is something this committee is interested in.  We are having a paper prepared on it by the Library and Research Service of the Houses.  We have asked for some guidance and information from Mr. Moloney's Department.  That would come under its area of remit.  We want to take that Act and other amending Acts down through the years to get an understanding of how the legislation operates and what changes to the accountability element might or should be made.  We want to understand the current arrangement and see if we can we suggest any better ways of doing business and making individuals accountable.  Has Mr. Moloney&rsquo;s Department done any work on that in the past?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.280" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00600"><p>I sent the committee a letter on various aspects of accountability.  We have responsibilities in regard to it on an ongoing basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00700"><p>If there was a change in the legislation it would be Mr. Moloney's Department that would bring forward that legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.282" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00800"><p>Yes.  That would be my understanding.  In respect of the Ministers and Secretaries Act, we would bring forward that legislation.  In respect of any of the functions exercised on it, we would bring forward legislation on behalf of the Taoiseach.  I would just make that distinction.</p> <p>  Regarding the independent review panel, it is probably not that obvious but when we talk about the legislative arrangements in respect of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform setting the terms and conditions of civil servants, the terms and conditions are encompassed broadly.  Therefore, it would be relevant to the Ministers and Secretaries Act.  That would be one of the items the independent review panel would be free to look at.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J00900"><p>The independent review panel could look at-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.284" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01000"><p>It could look at that.  Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01100"><p>-----how individuals are held responsible.  The idea of the Minister accepting all of the blame and all the rest of it could be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.286" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01200"><p>It covers the terms and conditions of civil servants who are employees like everybody else.  Setting in place the arrangements around which that employment is conducted is within its scope.  It is a very large area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01300"><p>Has that independent review panel being asked to look at this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.288" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01400"><p>That element of examining the legislative provisions around setting the terms and conditions is one of the elements it has been given.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01500"><p>When is it expected to report back?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.290" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01600"><p>We would expect at least an interim report or some feedback from it later in the year, perhaps in quarter 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01700"><p>I presume the members of it will talk about the salary and the terms and conditions for the overall work.  How was increasing the salary of one Secretary General by &euro;86,000, or whatever it was, taken by the public sector leadership board?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.292" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01800"><p>We did not discuss it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J01900"><p>Was there any concern around it?  I mean that in a way-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.294" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02000"><p>The Chairman will be familiar with the way-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02100"><p>Okay.  That is fine.  It was agreed.  How it was agreed is a little bit disserving.  Because of that arrangement, is it time to look at individual Departments and to offer more to one departmental Secretary General than another because of the volume of work, the extent of the Department or the budget it has?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.296" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02200"><p>It is certainly something that fits into the remit of the independent review panel, following on from the report of this committee as well as several related issues.  We have in place a three-tier structure but we also seen very significant movements in departmental responsibilities over time.  That impacts on how one might access a three-tier structure.  That is one of the issues we have asked the Donal de Buitl&eacute;ir group to look at and make recommendations on.  Certainly the Minister is conscious of the concerns that have been raised about how salaries are set and has explained to the committee and others, in great detail, the evolution from the former review body on higher education, moving into pay cuts and the financial emergency measures in the public interest, FEMPI, legislation reductions and restoration to our now emerging into a different phase.  Therefore, it is appropriate to consider how we might look at pay determination into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02300"><p>That once-off increase would not be the norm in terms of the process.  There is a different process there, is there not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.298" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02400"><p>The issue is that having stood down the review body on higher education, having provided for senior public pay through the FEMPI legislation and now being at a stage where the FEMPI legislation is coming to an end, the question is what process will now take place because there has not been a process outside of FEMPI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02500"><p>The &euro;86,000 increase was not part of a formal process.  That is not how Secretaries General get increases, is it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.300" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02600"><p>If we reflect back, my understanding is it is the only change in Secretary General pay for a long number of years.  Because we do not have a review body or a mechanism for setting and establishing what the correct rate is, the Government sees a need for the setting of a rate.  The Minister has no choice but to make that decision based on the Government&rsquo;s assessment of what is needed in respect of a particular post.  As the Chairman will know, that has happened in a small number of instances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02700"><p>From that process we saw there is no process currently in place.  No benchmarking was done, for example, of similar positions across Europe.  No one can explain where that figure came from, the make-up of it, or how that figure was arrived at.  That is why I am asking Mr. Moloney about this.  It is clear there is no process.  It is clear there is no information around how that figure was arrived at.  It was a decision of the Government and that, too, will be examined by the independent review  panel, not that particular issue but the issue of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.302" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02800"><p>The broad issue of how the settlement of remuneration-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J02900"><p>The broader issue.  It is simply not good practice.</p> <p>  In terms of the performance of Secretaries General, there is the leadership board but I was a bit taken aback to find out during the course of our engagement with Mr. Fraser, when he was in before us, that there is no single boss.  To whom are the Secretaries General answerable?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.304" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J03000"><p>The Secretaries General are answerable to the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J03100"><p>I understand that part of it but I mean within their own workplace, as it where.  I always thought Mr. Fraser would have been the all-powerful Secretary General who would control the other Secretaries General or tick them off or praise them, as needs be, but he said that is not the case.  Does Mr. Moloney think there is a need for perhaps an all-powerful Secretary General who would have as part of his or her remit the types of tools needed to manage a group of important people such as those or does he think it works okay the way it is because Governments come and go?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.306" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#J03200"><p>Those in government are the people who can hold Secretaries General to account as things stand.  It is a complicated question.  As I set out in the piece we gave the committee on the Government's accountability thesis, Secretaries General are generally Accounting Officers in their own right.</p><p>As the Chairman will know, the legislation and rules about that are very specific.  They are not updatable.  Under the Public Service Management Act 1997, Secretaries General are given, in their own right, responsibility for the day-to-day management of Departments so that Ministers do not have to be called to account any time somebody breaks their arm in a Government building.  There are ranges of responsibility that are not communal but that are held solely by the Secretaries General.  As the head of the office or Department, the Secretary General has those responsibilities.</p><p> With regard to the collective responsibilities, that is really a matter for Government.  It is not the only way it could be done but it is the situation as it now stands.  I have not seen a clearly articulated alternative vision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#K00200"><p>Has Mr. Moloney looked at any vision of an alternative to what we have at present?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.309" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#K00300"><p>There have been several looks at how accountability might be rolled out, implemented or given practical form.  We have done that over time and, as we take into account the views of the independent review panel, we will have another opportunity to do so.  However, as the note we provided to the committee points out, it is a very complex set of interwoven responsibilities, most of which are set out in very long-established legislation that really-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#K00400"><p>Most of the responsibility falls to the Minister, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.311" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. David Moloney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#K00500"><p>The Minister for Public Expenditure-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1496" speakername="John McGuinness" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FPJ2022061500002#K00600"><p>I have rarely heard of a Secretary General being asked to resign but I regularly hear calls for Ministers to resign.  Sometimes, when you look at the issue, that may not be appropriate.  Secretaries General are held to account by the Committee of Public Accounts but that is about it.  I do not see anything else.  The Committee of Public Accounts is still in business.  If everything was functioning the way it should, that committee would not be in business because everything would be running so well.</p> <p>  In my time here, I have seen the same types of mistakes repeated over and over again.  That raises a question as to the response of public sector leadership and the Secretaries General as a collective to Departments overspending or causing a negative perception of themselves to develop.  Someone has to take responsibility for that.  If you look at the jobs Ministers are involved in nowadays, between Brussels and dealing with world affairs and home affairs, you will see that they are kept quite busy.  I presume they expect their Departments to take on the challenge of dealing with shortcomings.  That is where I am coming from with regard to sanctions, conditions of employment, accountability and transparency.  We all have to be accountable.  I believe that any Secretary General asked to come before a committee should do so.  That is my view.  Although the work of other committees should not be duplicated, they should come before the various committees of these Houses.  Until such time as there is change in respect of accountability and transparency, it is my view that Secretaries Generals should have to make themselves available.  The Secretaries General across the Departments should be making great efforts to ensure that issues that arise in the context of the reports of the Comptroller and Auditor General are dealt with.  I am just giving Mr. Moloney my tuppence worth on the matter but I would like to see substantial change in that area.</p> <p>  We have come to the end of our discussion on this.  It has been worthwhile and informative.  I thank Mr. Moloney and his two colleagues for their time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2022-06-15a.313" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 3.05 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 22 June 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>