<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.2" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.3" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Richard Bruton, Garret Ahearn, Paul Murphy, Ollie Crowe, Louise O'Reilly, Róisín Garvey, Matt Shanahan, Marie Sherlock. David Stanton.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy Maurice Quinlivan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.4" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#A00100">Online Content Moderation and Reactivation of Economy: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#B00100"><p>I thank the members and the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment for participating in today's meeting in line with the exceptional circumstances with which we must deal given the Covid-19 pandemic.  I remind them that apart from myself and members of the committee secretariat, all members and the witnesses are required to participate remotely, within the Leinster House complex where possible.  Today's meeting involves consideration of two matters that are of particular interest to the committee.  The first concerns the employment rights and health and safety of content moderators.  In addition, with the easing of the restrictions relating to the pandemic, the committee is keen to explore issues relating to the reactivation of the economy following the disruption caused by the Covid 19 pandemic.  I hope we can fully cover both items during our meeting.</p> <p>  To assist the committee in considering these matters, I am pleased to welcome the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment.  He is accompanied by two officials from his Department, Mr. Stephen Curry and Mr. Oliver Gilvarry.  Before we start, I wish to explain some limitations to parliamentary privilege and the practice of the Houses as regards references that may be made to other persons in evidence.  The evidence of witnesses who are physically present or who give evidence from within parliamentary precincts is protected pursuant to both the Constitution and statute by absolute privilege.  This means they have an absolute defence against any defamation action for anything they say at the meeting.  However, they are expected not to abuse this privilege and it is my duty as Chair to ensure this privilege is not abused.  Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks.  It is imperative that they comply with any such directions.  The Minister's opening statement has already been circulated to members.  I now invite the Minister to make his opening statement.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#B00200"><p>I thank the Chairman and committee members for the invitation to discuss the employment of content moderators and the reactivation of the economy in the context of Covid-19.  As the two issues are quite different, I will speak initially about content moderators and then move on to economic issues more generally.</p> <p>  Although it is a new form of work, we can all agree that content moderation plays a vital role in our use of the Internet and in turn in our everyday lives.  It is hard to imagine what the Internet would be like without them.  Content moderators carry out really important work to protect all of us and we need to ensure they are protected properly in their work.  They prevent the wider distribution of explicit and harmful content and I acknowledge there are specific stressors inherent in the type of work they carry out.  I believe it requires appropriate training, competence, ongoing debriefing and supervision within a well-established, safe and healthy system of work.</p> <p>  In late January, following a request from Deputy O'Reilly, I met a group of content moderators and their representatives to hear from them at first hand.  Following the meeting, I wrote to Facebook setting out the concerns raised at the meeting and the company provided a detailed response to my letter.  I believe this has been shared with the committee recently.  There is a strong legislative regime in Ireland to protect all workers regardless of where they work or the type of work they do in terms of their working conditions, including health and safety.  Employers, no matter what sector they are in, have a duty of care towards employees to ensure that a safe working environment is created.  This includes the management of workplace stressors or psychosocial hazards.  As I said, appropriate training must be provided and employers must carry out a risk assessment with a particular focus on potential hazards relating to content moderation work.  Proper risk assessment, along with mitigation measures, is the foundation of all workplace health and safety.  Promoting positive mental health within the workplace is good for the employees and is also a factor in improving overall business performance and productivity.</p> <p>  For this reason, I urge employees to engage in the first instance with their employer to see how their concerns can be resolved at workplace level.  However, any content moderator concerned for his or her health and safety can contact the Health and Safety Authority, HSA, in confidence and can also contact the Workplace Relations Commission, WRC, about broader working conditions.  Where necessary, the resolution mechanisms available from the relevant State agencies can be utilised by both employers and employees.  I am aware that the HSA is addressing matters already raised with it.  As members will appreciate, the HSA is independent in the carrying out of its regulatory function and keeps much of that information confidential.  This includes keeping it from me.    </p> <p>  Moving on to the second topic, which is the reactivation of the economy, I am very hopeful that we can return to something close to normality by late summer.  It has been an extremely long road for everyone - citizens, workers, businesses, friends and family - but I think our patience and resilience have been worth it.  The vaccination programme is picking up momentum administering approximately 270,000 vaccines per week.  Nearly 40% of our adult population has had at least one dose now and we hope to have the vast majority of our adult population vaccinated at least once by the end of June and fully vaccinated by end of September.  Members will be aware that the portal is now open to people in their late 40s to register.  </p> <p>  Within the next two weeks, we expect to be in a position to publish a national economic recovery plan - most likely at the end of May or even 1 June.  The plan will provide certainty for businesses and workers by outlining targeted support for sectors which will continue to be most adversely affected by the pandemic.  It will outline the next steps for the emergency pandemic interventions, including what we will do with the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, and the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, reaffirming the Government&rsquo;s commitment to avoid a cliff edge.  At the same time, we all understand that for financial reasons, there cannot be a long tail either.  I think members will agree that the three main schemes &ndash; the Covid restrictions support scheme, CRSS; EWSS; and PUP - compare favourably with what is on offer in other countries.  Members may be aware that my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Troy, published our proposals for a new small company administrative rescue process, SCARP, last week.  This is a cheaper quicker alternative to examinership and with the help of the committee, we hope to have the Bill enacted before the summer recess.  This could save a lot of businesses in the autumn that are viable but need to restructure to survive.  </p> <p>  The national economic recovery plan will help to drive a jobs-rich recovery, help people return to work and assist sectors that have been and will continue to be disproportionately affected by the pandemic.  I am thinking of tourism and hospitality, the aviation sector, arts and entertainment.  The plan will also set out our ambition not just to return to pre-pandemic Ireland but to build a better "normal" - a more inclusive society that is equipped to meet head on the twin challenges of digital and green.  Last Friday, I published updated guidance on ventilation and antigen testing to reduce the spread of Covid in the workplace and help people get back to work and businesses to open and stay open.  </p> <p>  The updated work safely protocol, which was developed in consultation with unions and employers, is the most up-to-date public health advice for the workplace.  It sets out the measures required to prevent the spread of Covid-19 in the workplace, including information on how to approach the use of antigen testing.  Our advice is still to continue to work from home where possible but this protocol makes sure every workplace has clear and up-to-date guidance.  It gives clear information on how to use antigen testing appropriately in the workplace.  It sets out that these tests should be used as an additional health and safety measure and not as a substitute for any other precautions.  Employers should also consider how they can improve ventilation in workplaces.  Even simple actions like airing rooms or keeping a window open can make a real difference.  Although we intend to vaccinate the vast majority of the adult population by the end of June, the reality is some people cannot or will not take one.  Vaccination is and will remain voluntary so it is important that employers have guidance on how to manage any unvaccinated workers, particularly in customer-facing roles.</p><p>The document gives some information on that but I accept that it will need to be added to in its next iteration.</p><p> I look forward to members' comments and am happy to answer any questions they may have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#C00200"><p>Thank you, T&aacute;naiste.  I now invite members to discuss both issues with the Minister.  I remind them to use the "Raise hand" function if they wish to contribute and to take it down when they are finished speaking.  We have a rota and a system.  The first person who has indicated is Deputy O'Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#C00300"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for his opening statement and for meeting with the content moderators.  I know they found the meeting to be beneficial.  It would be brilliant if one meeting with the T&aacute;naiste or anybody else resolved the issues they have.  It will not.  This is an ongoing issue.  It is one on which the committee heard from the content moderators, in particular one by the name of Isabella Plunkett, last week.  I appreciate that the T&aacute;naiste may not have had a chance to hear what she had to say.  If he did not, I encourage him to have a look back at the proceedings because she talked from first-hand experience. </p> <p>  The T&aacute;naiste will have heard at the meeting from people who have first-hand experience.  We need to look at the way in which these people are working and the work they do.  They are our first line of defence.  However, we have to ask about the level of trauma these people have to suffer in order for social media platforms to be able to function.  Thinking about this logically, if there were a make of car that every time a mechanic fixed he or she broke a finger, we would take it off the road.  I do not know if the T&aacute;naiste has a view as to how viable the business model is if it requires such a level of trauma and if the consequent supports are not put in place to ensure that people have the opportunity to debrief and to decompress after a shift.  Non-disclosure agreements and conditions that prevent workers from telling their spouse or whoever else is at home when they come home in the evening what it is they have been doing all day are archaic.  They have no place in a modern workforce, yet these are the conditions under which these people are working.</p> <p>  I am aware that Facebook wrote back to the T&aacute;naiste and listed the supports in place, but he will be aware that those supports are not available to the content moderators who work for an outsourced platform.  Does he have a view as to whether a similar level of support should be offered to such workers?  I do not think anything could ever mitigate fully what these poor people have to see in the course of their normal work, but does the T&aacute;naiste have a view on a similar level of supports being available for both outsourced and in-house workers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#C00400"><p>I thank the Deputy for her question and for introducing the content moderators to me because it was very interesting to hear what they had to say.  I think we all agree that they do a very difficult job.  Some of the work they do can be done through artificial intelligence and algorithms but only a small amount of it.  I am not a tech person but I suspect that for the foreseeable future we will need a lot of this work to be done by a human being and a human brain.  Of course, behind a human brain are human emotions.  We need people who will police the Internet and take content down.  We all see the stuff that gets through so we can only imagine the stuff that does not get through, what it is like and the impact it may have on people.  The Deputy will be aware that I wrote to Facebook about this.  It replied.  I have not met representatives of the company in recent months but this matter will be on the agenda the next time I meet them and I will take an interest in it.  The HSA has its role and will carry out its functions as it should.</p> <p>  To answer Deputy O'Reilly's question, my sense is that if people being outsourced to a company or a contractor are doing the same work as the directly employed people within that company, such as Facebook, they should get the same psychological supports and backup as the directly employed workers.  Now, maybe they are doing different work, but if they are doing the same work, they should get the same psychological and well-being supports.  Like many members of the committee, I think, I am not against outsourcing.  The Government does it all the time.  Departments do it all the time, and very successfully.  However, it should not be done by an employer as a means of avoiding obligations or potential legal liabilities.  That is all I will say about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#C00500"><p>I understand I will have an opportunity to contribute again later when we might get another chance to discuss the content moderators.</p> <p>  As for the notion that we will spend our summer outdoors, it would, as people say, be a lovely little country if only we could put a roof over it.  Last weekend, Dublin City Council put a fence around an open space where people gather.  I fully respect that the residents have issues with people gathering outside their houses but I am also conscious that the Government advice is to go outside and spend the summer outdoors.  I raised this with the T&aacute;naiste last week on Questions on Promised Legislation.  We need a plan and it has to involve toilets and bins.  We can put any nice names we want on them, but it is toilets and bins that will be needed in order that people can enjoy the summer outdoors.</p> <p>  It was put to me during the week that it is almost as if the Government is saying, "Irish people, you just cannot have nice things."  That should not be the case.  If we are to have any kind of summer at all, we need to spend it outdoors.  We do not know when we will be able to have everybody indoors together.</p> <p>  Will the T&aacute;naiste comment on what happened in Portobello?  I do not want to see that happen in my area.  I want to see residents respected - of course I do - but, for the want of outdoor toilets and bins, an entire area was closed off.  We cannot keep shunting people around and, at the same time, tell them the message is to go outside if, when they go outside, there is nothing there for them except a fence.  Garda&iacute; have to police people trying to get to one area.  That is a waste of their time and a waste of Garda resources.  Somewhere in the city, while garda&iacute; were standing policing a fence, a crime was being committed.  There has to be a plan to marry the two elements because it is not fair to tell people to go outside but not to go to this or that place and then to move them on all the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#C00600"><p>I definitely do not think the solution to these problems is to close off public areas.  I appreciate that the city council had to make the decision it made and I really sympathise with the residents.  The Deputy can imagine what they have experienced.  This was not just outdoor drinking; it was people urinating and defecating near their homes, and I do not think any of us can condone that.  I remember that in my constituency what kept us sane during the pandemic was the Phoenix Park.  I was there nearly every other day.  There was a suggestion at one point that the park was getting too crowded and it might be a good idea to close it.  The Deputy can be absolutely sure that the public representatives in my constituency responded to that very quickly and said the closure of our biggest park and the crowding of everyone into the small greens was not a solution.  That was not going to work at all and, thankfully, the OPW took the decision not to close the park or to restrict numbers into it.</p> <p>  When we talk about an outdoor summer, it will not be outdoors only.  Increasingly, as people get vaccinated, they can meet up indoors.  I still expect we will have indoor dining in July.  The Deputy is totally right about the toilets and bins, and that is the message we are putting across to local authorities.</p> <p>  Next week, we intend to have two memorandums from the Government.  The first will be on the pathway forward regarding international travel, although the new Indian variants are now causing additional concern.  Nonetheless, it will be a pathway towards the restoration of international travel over the next few months.  The second memo is being brought to us by the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, and is all about live events and a whole set of trial and pilot events in June and July - sporting, artistic, musical and cultural, outdoor and indoor - with limited capacity.  We are making those plans and I think that will be good news to people who are dying to see a live event, as I know the Deputy is.  I am too.  It will be of some relief to people working in the sector who have been unable to work and to do their art, essentially, for nearly a year now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#C00700"><p>Yes, but, with respect, other European cities can manage this.  Dublin is a beautiful city.  It is by far and away one of the loveliest places on earth, in my opinion, so why can we not have outdoor spaces that are similar to those available to citizens in cities right across Europe?</p><p>We have many open spaces.  I was really disappointed to see Portobello Plaza closed and to think this might happen to other places, given that we will be spending the summer outdoors.  For those people who will not be dining indoors and who want to stay outdoors, there should be spaces where they can gather, not just places to meet when spending money.  It seems as if those places are disappearing.  We are becoming less and less like other European cities and I do not think that is a good way for us to go.  It comes down to basic facilities such as bins and toilets.  They will make the outdoors much more liveable.  We would like to see some concrete action on that.  I appreciate that the T&aacute;naiste has heard the point but we would like to see more of an instruction being given to local authorities to ensure this is done.</p><p> On the rules regarding indoor dining, I am not a scientist and do not pretend to be, but it makes no sense to me that this is decided purely on the basis of the type of business.  An hotel with a small restaurant and low ceilings will be able to open, whereas a restaurant with high ceilings and good ventilation will not.  The same is true of a pub that has the capacity to put dividers between the tables and so on.  I appreciate that the T&aacute;naiste has met people in the hospitality industry but they are scratching their heads.  If it is going to be based on size, let it be based on size, or if it is going to be based on ventilation, let it be based on ventilation, but that should be based on scientific evidence.  They have not seen evidence and nor have I.</p><p> Will the T&aacute;naiste offer an explanation for the decision, or even some comfort that such businesses will be able to open at the same time provided that they have the facilities?  Nobody wants 100 people to be squashed into a small room with low ceilings.  We are all a bit risk averse at this stage to that kind of scenario.  Nevertheless, a large pub or restaurant with high ceilings and good ventilation is surely as safe as a similar type of venue within an hotel.  I believe it is possible to do it based on size.  It has been based on size or ventilation in other European countries, rather than simply on the type of business that it happens to be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#D00200"><p>As the Deputy will be aware, the decision to open hotels before restaurants was based on public health advice and was in line with the advice from NPHET.  We are often criticised for not following that advice and this is one occasion on which we did so to the letter, except for the fact that hotels are opening a few days earlier than NPHET suggested.  It is for a practical reason, not a scientific reason.  I will be frank with the Deputy about that and I have been with the industry too.</p> <p>  We have never closed hotels' dining rooms.  During level 5, when we were all locked down at home, hotels remained open for essential reasons, such as for people who had to stay there because they had nowhere else to stay, and we never closed their restaurants or dining rooms.  If we were to close them now, we would be closing them for the first time.  This was never a problem before.  The problem now arises only because there is a disparity between the way we are treating hotel restaurants and other restaurants.  If we were to turn around and close them now, however, it would not make sense.  We would be saying that people can be served their meals in their rooms only.  I hope and expect that the gap will be for only a couple of weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#D00300"><p>I am not suggesting there should be a delay in opening hotels and I am aware they have been open throughout the pandemic, providing food and essential provisions for essential workers.  Would it be possible to carry out ventilation tests, as was done with classrooms such that classrooms were not all deemed either okay or not okay? Could tests be provided on the extent to which restaurants might be able to accommodate people?  Could the Government examine that?  About 80% of restaurants cannot provide outdoor dining, so they are very anxious, as the T&aacute;naiste will know.  For those restaurants that might have the facilities, with high ceilings, ventilation and so on, could consideration be given to allowing them to reopen at the same time?  I fully appreciate that hotels have been open throughout and do not suggest they should be closed as some kind of catch-up exercise.  In the case of restaurants that have the facilities, would it be possible to give consideration to what I outlined?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#D00400"><p>Of course it is possible but it would be going against the advice of NPHET.  My priority now, rather than having a complicated set of criteria for a two or three-week period, is to get the decision to allow restaurants and pubs to open indoors.  If they knew they were going to able to do that in the first week or so of July, that two or three-week period might be more acceptable.  I would be concerned that if we came up with a strict regime to allow them to half-open indoors, they might be stuck with that for months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#D00500"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for his attendance and time.  The role of content moderator is very challenging.  Ms Isabella Plunkett told the committee last week of the effect it had had on her personally and how it had started to have serious impacts on her life outside her job.  She described the horrible dreams she has and the anguish it causes her, and stated she has had to take the step of taking antidepressants.  Dealing daily with hate speech, racism, images of child exploitation is not a job that anyone should have to do but, unfortunately, it is necessary.</p> <p>  In my opinion, there is a moral responsibility on Facebook to ensure, at the very least, that content moderators are very well looked after.  Facebook is one of the richest companies in the world, worth almost $1 trillion.  It is clear it can well afford to treat staff equally and ensure proper supports are in place well beyond weekly wellness sessions, and to pay them fairly.  If the T&aacute;naiste gets an opportunity in the coming weeks to view a recording of last week's meeting, I encourage him to do so.  The culture of fear that Ms Plunkett described, with content moderators afraid to speak out due to non-disclosure agreements, is quite frankly sickening.  I strongly urge the Government to take action, meet representatives of Facebook and demand it immediately address the issue.  I welcome the T&aacute;naiste's comments that he intends to meet the company.  If possible, will he outline when he expects that to happen?</p> <p>  Everybody I speak to in hospitality, SMEs or the wider economy acknowledges the substantial and unprecedented supports the Government has put in place while also recognising that despite these supports, thousands of businesses throughout the country remain under significant pressure due to a crisis not of their making.  I have concerns about the debt that businesses are carrying, particularly in the case of SMEs.  The debt warehousing scheme is a very welcome initiative that will improve short-term cash flow for SMEs.  There is no question but that the scheme is very welcome but the timeframe of 12 months is a short period in which to resolve cash flow issues as we emerge from the pandemic, and that needs to be examined.  I appreciate that outstanding liabilities can be paid off following three years at a relatively low interest rate of 3%, but it would save SMEs having to go to financial institutions, where it is difficult to get funding, if the 12-month period could be extended to 24 months.  I would appreciate hearing the T&aacute;naiste's views on that.</p> <p>  The employment wage subsidy scheme is scheduled to run until the end of June.  It has been run at considerable expense to the State but strong consideration needs to be given to extending it until, at the minimum, the end of September and possibly beyond.</p><p>I speak to business owners in Galway city every day.  The scheme is essential for restaurants, hotels and bars, as it gives them the opportunity to rebuild while limiting their expenses.  All members want businesses to survive, rebound from the crisis and develop and grow again.  If we can make the extra investment now, it may prove to be the difference needed for thousands of businesses across the country to get back on their feet and give them the window of opportunity to ensure they can become sustainable before supports are removed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#E00200"><p>I do not have a date in my diary to meet representatives of Facebook again any time soon.  I usually meet them at intervals of six months to a year, as Facebook is a major employer and taxpayer in Ireland.  I am sure a meeting will happen in the next few months.</p> <p>  On tax warehousing, I hear what Senator Crowe is saying.  It would be strange if we were telling businesses to get Government backed low-cost loans when we could just extend tax warehousing.  That might be the most effective thing for them in terms of cash flow.  It is a matter for the Minister for Finance, as the Senator knows, but I know the Minister quite well and we have had a number of conversations on this issue.  No decision will be made until 1 June.  That is all I can say for now.  I understand the point the Senator made and I agree with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#E00300"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for his reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#E00500"><p>I welcome the T&aacute;naiste to the committee.  The meeting we had with the content moderators was harrowing for all of us.  I congratulate Deputy O'Reilly on having brought the matter to our attention and facilitating their meeting with us and with the T&aacute;naiste, whom I thank for meeting them.  Heinous crimes are being committed in the world, in Ireland and elsewhere.  As the T&aacute;naiste said, these crimes often involve child abuse, rape, torture, murder and God knows what else.  Today, we are talking about supporting content moderators.  I do not know how any human being can survive being exposed to this kind of material, all day every day, without becoming seriously damaged, while not receiving intense support.</p> <p>  Facebook could not continue without the work of the moderators.  I think the T&aacute;naiste said that some of this content is getting through in spite of the work of the moderators.  Is there an issue regarding the investigation by police forces, not just in Ireland but all over the world, of crimes committed and their recordings being put online?  There are real victims out there.  I know some of these crimes occur in war zones, countries without governments and failed states, but much of it is probably happening in the so-called developed world.  Perhaps the T&aacute;naiste will use his good offices at European level and beyond to get governments to chase this material down and prosecute those who put it online, inasmuch as this can be done.  That is not to take away from the content of our meeting today, which is to support the content moderators in every way possible, but what is happening behind the scenes is awful.  I think there are 1,900 moderators working full time in Ireland trying to deal with this material.  That shows the vast scale of the horrific stuff that is going on.  It strikes me that it is important to go beyond what is happening here.</p> <p>  On the issue of opening the economy, the announcement made by the T&aacute;naiste yesterday about supports for people in non-rateable businesses working from home is very welcome.  It is a matter on which several people have rang me about from time to time.  The extension of the small business assistance scheme to such people is very welcome.  I told a number of people about this yesterday and they were very pleased because they have been under a lot of pressure.  I know the amount of money involved is small, but it is very welcome.  When does the T&aacute;naiste expect that to be up and running?  The press release stated that it would be shortly but he might let us know when.</p> <p>  Will the T&aacute;naiste comment on the announcement by Aer Lingus yesterday, which affects Cork and Shannon airports?  Aer Lingus has closed its Shannon operations completely.  In Cork there is work taking place on the runway to coincide with the temporary closure of the base there.  It is a concern and I ask the T&aacute;naiste to comment on it.</p> <p> The pandemic has thrown up all kinds of different issues.  Driver theory tests are being cancelled left, right, and centre.  I know it is not the T&aacute;naiste's area, but people need to drive to work and take part in businesses.  It has been put to me that if the theory tests were to be put off until the company running them has the opportunity to get organised, people could start to do the driving lessons first and do the driver theory test afterwards.  As the T&aacute;naiste knows, people must do the theory test first but many people cannot do it and are put out by that.</p> <p>  Another area which is related to this, is about people involved in business and industry needing a small public service vehicle licence.  There was a hiatus for a year during which the requirement was suspended but it now in place again and &euro;2,000 is being sought from self-employed people who are involved in taxi tours, limousine and car hire.  These people tell me they will not have business until May 2022.  They are being asked to pay &euro;2,000 for a licence they cannot use.  This is a business issue which I take the opportunity to bring to the Minister's attention.</p> <p>  Those are the two main points I wanted to raise.  I thank the T&aacute;naiste for the work he is doing during these very challenging times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#E00600"><p>Deputy Stanton makes a good point about the content that is posted online.  There is a criminal justice element to this.  I do not know whether there are protocols that Internet platforms follow and whether they simply take this content down or report it to the authorities in the relevant country.  I will check that because one would think they would have a responsibility in that regard.</p> <p>  The Deputy will be aware that the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, is working on the online safety legislation and the creation of an online safety commissioner, which is long overdue.  There should be a protocol for the platforms to report potentially illegal content to the relevant authorities, but it is the world wide web and that is not easily done.</p> <p>  On the small business assistance scheme for Covid, SBASC, we anticipate that will open for applications on Friday.  However, just in case something goes wrong, I will say that, officially, it will open next week.  If all goes to plan, however, it will open on Friday and will be run through the local authorities.  The closing date for applications will be 21 July, so businesses have a decent amount of time to make their application.  The scheme applies to any business that had a turnover in excess of &euro;50,000 a year and whose turnover has declined by 75% or more.  These businesses can get a grant of &euro;4,000 to help with their costs.  It is no longer limited to rateable premises, so it includes non-rateable premises and people working from home or a hot desk.</p> <p>  Many people would have heard about the needs of wedding planners, photographers, travel counsellors and on-course bookmakers.  They would largely be covered by this scheme.  I recognise there is an issue with very small businesses with a turnover of less than &euro;50,000.  In order to help them out, we are reopening an old scheme called the micro-enterprise assistance scheme.  That will give very small businesses a grant of up to &euro;1,000 to help with their costs.  That will be run through local enterprise offices, LEOs.  Separate from that, the Minister, Deputy Martin, and I are working on something for the events sector, which is still in real difficulty.</p> <p>  What we expect to do from quarter 3, starting in July, is to move away from different sectoral supports to something that is across the board.  We brought in the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, and the Covid restrictions support scheme, CRSS, which are great but had many gaps.  We then created about ten or 20 different schemes to fill those gaps.  Ideally, what we will do from July onwards is to have a single scheme that fits all firms.  However, as we all know, one size does not fill all, so we will probably find we will have the same problem again.  Hopefully, this will not be an issue because businesses will be open and trading.  It should not be as big an issue as it is now in any event.</p> <p>  On Aer Lingus, yesterday's news was extremely unwelcome.</p><p>I met representatives of Aer Lingus in the last couple of weeks.  I was aware that the company planned to do some restructuring but it did not give us any details.  Understandably, it has to give those to its employees first.  The closure of the cabin crew base in Shannon was not expected.  It is down to the pandemic and the fact that people are just not travelling.  It is also down to the restrictions the Government imposed.  It would be remiss of me not to point out that there are many Members of the Oireachtas who still do not believe those restrictions went far enough.  The decision would have been even worse had we gone along with the calls made by some Members.</p><p> Aer Lingus and the other airlines are receiving very substantial support, millions of euro, every week through the wage subsidy scheme.  Airports have also received financial support.  There is no shortage of money going into aviation from government.  I believe it is in the hundreds of millions of euro at this stage.  We have had conversations with airlines about paying them to keep certain strategic routes open but that is not something they are particularly interested in, aside from the fact that this would run into state aid rules and competition rules.  They want to fly their aeroplanes with passengers on them.  They do not want to be paid to fly empty planes.  We are not New Zealand or Qantas.  In the real world, aeroplanes can be moved out of Ireland very easily to places like Manchester.  That is one of the consequences of the very strict travel restrictions we have in Ireland.</p><p> I do not regret imposing those restrictions, by the way.  We have one of the lowest death rates per million population in Europe.  Only Finland and Denmark have seen fewer deaths per million than Ireland, and some of that is down to our very strict travel rules and the fact that we are an island.  However, they have real consequences for real people, including not being able to see families and friends who live abroad and the loss of jobs in tourism and aviation.  The sooner we can get back to flying, the better.  However, we still stand the risk of reseeding the virus into Ireland and bringing in variants and we cannot ignore that risk.  There is real concern around the Indian variants in particular coming from the UK and we have to keep a close eye on that.  </p><p> I will have to pass on the driver test issues and small public service vehicles.  I could give the Deputy an answer but it would probably be wrong.  I will ask the Minister of State, Deputy Hildegarde Naughton, to get in touch with him on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#F00200"><p>I congratulate the T&aacute;naiste, his Department and its agencies for the flexibility and adaptability they have shown.  I particularly welcome the introduction of examinership-lite and the new approach to work, sick pay, the living wage and so on.  We are seeing the Department responding to a changing environment.</p> <p>  Is the use of antigen testing rather than PCR tests before boarding flights in prospect?  A case is being made that it is being done elsewhere.  </p> <p>  We know changes to corporate taxation are coming.  The challenge for Ireland as we come out of this is to build long-term resilience.  That will involve embedding climate and circular resilience, building a sharing economy and building lifelong learning and digital and remote skills.  These are all changes that we need to make.  To what extent is there an effort under way to mobilise the capacity of the Department's agencies to address these longer term structural changes?  It will need agencies and educational institutions to help companies make the shift.  How will that be approached.  There is always the risk that the urgent will squeeze out the important but there is no doubt that we have to change our model and build new sources of competitive advantage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#F00300"><p>On antigen testing for international travel, we all know there are different views.  NPHET and the Chief Medical Officer do not like it, while the chief scientific officer, Professor Ferguson, is a big fan.  The Government is not ruling it out but for now, we have PCR testing for international travel.  We are not ruling out a move to antigen testing but, without rehearsing the arguments, there are advantages and disadvantages.  The obvious advantage is that antigen tests are cheaper and quicker and will pick up people who are in their infectious stage of the virus where they are shedding virus and are transmissible.  On the downside, they miss a lot of positives and negatives and can give false reassurance.  Given that we are making so much progress with the vaccines, I hope we might not need tests at all.  Perhaps we will get to the point where we can say that being fully vaccinated is enough and not require people to have any form of test.  That is where I would like to be but we have to figure that out between now and next week when the Government agrees its proposals on international travel.</p> <p>  On the wider strategic point, in fairness, the agencies and Department are doing as the Deputy described, even though we have been extremely busy firefighting and dealing with the pandemic over the last year.  Since we have not been engaging in many of the normal activities, such as trade missions and travelling around the country attending major events, we have had a bit of time to do some more strategic thinking.  The remote working strategy was a reflection of that.  An artificial intelligence strategy will come out quite soon.  IDA Ireland also has a new strategy.  Like everyone, the Department and its family of agencies have used the downtime created by the pandemic to do some forward thinking and insurance is part of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#F00400"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for his time and his work to date.  Great supports have been provided, in fairness.  My son, who is a student, had a part-time job and he benefited from the PUP which kept him sane.  I thank the T&aacute;naiste for the work on the PUP, which was put in place pretty quickly, so well done.</p> <p>  On Facebook, I have received letters from various people.  I had meetings with members of Foxglove and we raised the issue in the committee.  Given that Facebook does not directly employ these moderators, surely there is an onus on the recruitment agency, the company that employs them, and it should be put under pressure to provide proper services and reports for its employees.  Is that something we can look at?  There is a loophole for Facebook because if it is not directly employing these staff, it is not directly responsible for them.  What are their official employers, the agencies that recruit them, doing to support these young people and their mental health?  These are young people because there are no old people in these jobs.  I am too old to get a job as a moderator.  We will let down our young people if we do not get proper structures and supports in place for these content moderators.  Prevention is better than a cure.  All members feel very strongly about this issue.  I will not go on about it; I just wanted to make the point about the middleman.</p> <p>  On local enterprise offices, LEOs, there are more than 248,000 small businesses in Ireland with fewer than ten employees.  That is a huge number of jobs and they are the heart and soul in much of the country.  These companies are often much more reliable than the bigger guys who might let us down by leaving and setting up in other countries, as happened yesterday.  Small businesses are often high quality family companies that take good care of staff.  We should support them more.  The LEOs have done amazing work throughout the pandemic to keep small businesses afloat.  They are under serious pressure, however, and it is clear from my meetings with them that they would love to have extra staff and supports. </p> <p>  On food producers, we are importing a lot of food that we could produce here.  For example, potatoes and garlic are coming from China, Israel and England.  We have a lot of great land that should be used more for growing food, not only mass producing beef and dairy.  We should strengthen our labelling for food production.  Under the current system, a company can import anything it likes, do something small with it, wrap it up and make it look as though it was made in Ireland.  We need to have stronger labelling for food made in Ireland.  I am aware of this from my sister's business which produces cheese.</p><p> If we strengthened labelling, we would strengthen Irish food producing companies. Also, because of the climate emergency, carbon footprint and all of those things, there has never been a better time to have a huge push to buy Irish.  Back in the 1980s there was a great buy Irish campaign and it is time to have another one.  I say to the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment that a good buy Irish campaign on social media and national media might not be the worst spending that we could do.</p><p>  I cannot emphasise how important Shannon Airport is to the entire region.  The 120 jobs that were lost yesterday are devastating for the families affected.  A lot of those workers have been loyal to Aer Lingus for a long time and it is disappointing to see the lack of loyalty that has been displayed by Aer Lingus to Cork, Shannon or to their staff.  More important is the ripple effect the airport has on a huge region through the generation of many thousands of jobs in the tourism sector.  It is well known that 95% of the people who fly into Dublin go somewhere else and do not spend their money here.  However, the people who come into Shannon and Cork are the people who stay and spend money here.  They keep businesses open and keep people living in rural regions.  If we are serious about regional rebalance I urge the T&aacute;naiste, the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Transport, Deputy Eamon Ryan, to sit around a table because they really need to see how important the Shannon and Cork airports are to a huge area of this country.  We cannot talk about extending runways in Dublin while there are no flights coming out of Shannon Airport.  We need those flights to England to connect us with the rest of the world and I cannot emphasise enough how important that is.  They are essential for our mental health in the region, as well as our economic health and it is important that we are given hope.  I believe that the Taoiseach is meeting some people but the four Ministers need to get their thinking caps on and decide what to do specifically for Shannon Airport as it has zero flights at the moment.  We need Shannon Airport to resume flights and thrive again.  When people come to Ireland, the east coast is great but the west has the Wild Atlantic Way and the most visited spots in Ireland such as the Cliffs of Moher and Adare.  The region is massive and, therefore, it is important that the four Ministers I mentioned have an emergency meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#G00200"><p>If the Senator wants an answer she has only one minute left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#G00300"><p>The Senator is absolutely right about the content moderators.  Whoever the employer is they have a duty of care whether it is Covalen, Facebook or anyone else.  Under the Protection of Employees (Temporary Agency Work) Act 2012, if one is taking on agency workers, one has to give them the same protections as the people who are directly employed by one.  The same basic working conditions certainly apply.</p> <p>  On the LEOs, again I very much agree.  We are scaling them up.  We are staffing them up.  They have an extra &euro;5 million in their budget this year and we have extended their remit.  They are now responsible for everything ranging from flood relief to businesses to all the new schemes that we have set up.  I do want to keep scaling them up over the next couple of years but I want to do so in a way that is manageable.  Sometimes one can scale up an agency or public body too quickly, ask them to do too much too soon and then things fall over.  So I want to be able to scale up but to do it right.</p> <p>  On the labelling, I am a big fan of Tola cheese, as the Senator knows, and I hope that company is going well.  As labelling is an EU matter under the Single Market, we do not have full control over how things are labelled and how they are not but we have input into the EU.  There are things that producers can do voluntarily but in terms of what the law is around labelling that is a Single Market issue and it is done at a European level.  It is something, however, in which I certainly have an interest as trade Minister.</p> <p>  Finally on Shannon, as the Senator will be aware, the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, is going to meet Aer Lingus today.  He is going to ask them to defer their decision to close the cabin crew base at least until Aer Lingus sees the Government's plan for aviation, which will be out next week.  What the company is saying, and said in its letter to me on the redundancies, is that it is not just about the pandemic and the travel restrictions.  The airline is also saying that the base has been inefficient for quite some time even before the pandemic.  I think that needs to be explored with it because we would like to see the decision deferred.  If the decision goes ahead, we are going to want to talk to airlines about how we can incentivise them to return.  Airlines are very nimble and bases that are closed one month can often be re-opened the next year and we have seen that particularly with Ryanair.  I know that when I was the Minister responsible for tourism - long, long ago - removing the travel tax really helped to get new routes into the country and frequency scaled up.  The travel tax is now gone but we are going to examine what incentives we can put in place to encourage airlines to return and routes to return.  The Ministers, Deputies Donohue and Eamon Ryan, and I actually spoke about that yesterday just after the Cabinet meeting.  We have started that initial discussion already but all those things will only work when people are allowed to fly and that is the bottom line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#G00400"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for coming to our hearing today.</p> <p>  As previous speakers have said, last week we heard powerful testimony from Ms Isabella Plunkett on her work for Facebook as a content moderator, and particularly about the culture of fear that is perpetrated within the company with workers being forced to sign non-disclosure agreements.  I must record my alarm that the company in question happens to be a subsidiary of a company that is in receipt of very significant State contracts.</p> <p>  With regard to what the Government can do on this, I seek the T&aacute;naiste's view of non-disclosure agreements, the withholding of those from workers and whether they should be published.  Also, should content moderation be regulated as hazardous activity?  Should content moderation be recognised in the health and safety regulation of this country? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#G00500"><p>As regards non-disclosure agreements, I am strongly of the view that anyone who signs a non-disclosure agreement should be allowed to keep a copy of the agreement.  I cannot imagine why anyone would be expected to sign any sort of agreement yet not have it.  How do you know you are actually adhering to the agreement yourself if you only get to read the thing once?  If they are not giving a copy of it, that is outrageous.  Any person of course should have a copy of any agreement that he or she ever signs.</p> <p>  It is important to say that non-disclosure agreements cannot be used to prevent content moderators from raising issues of concern about their working conditions or their health and safety concerns.  Non-disclosure agreements tend to be about confidentiality and not breaching confidentiality.  They cannot be used to stop people from raising legitimate concerns about their legal rights and entitlements or health and safety conditions.  Again, without knowing what is in these agreements it is hard to comment on them in any detail.</p> <p>  As for the issue the Senator has raised around health and safety regulation, I will give it some thought.  That is the first time it was raised with me as a possibility that we could reform our health and safety laws in that regard.  We always have to be willing to update our laws as the world of work is changing all the time.  That is something to which I will give some thought and on which I will consult the HSA.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#G00600"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for that.</p> <p>  In respect of the second part of the T&aacute;naiste's contribution this morning, when he very much wore the hat of the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, I welcome the prospect of the national economic plan being published soon.  Obviously he is aware of the serious concerns that were articulated by some organisations in the retail and hospitality sectors on the ability to take back staff and to have a sufficient supply of staff for reopening.  Certainly our Sunday newspapers and a lot of radio airtime have been given over to the issue in recent days.  What is going to be done for these sectors?  What are the issues with these sectors that they cannot get staff?  Is it pay or skills?  Is it time that we had a proper joint labour committee for the retail and hospitality sectors to enable us to talk through those issues?  Some of the issues arise because the pay rate is the national minimum wage or barely above it, so there are difficulties in attracting workers back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00100"><p>Let us see if they cannot get staff.  We are in a very different place now than we were when we did the reopening last summer.  I remember hearing last summer lots of anecdotal evidence from employers saying they could not get people back to work because the difference in what they were getting from the pandemic unemployment payment and what they would get for working 30 or 40 hours a week.  Essentially, it would not be enough to encourage them to come back to work.  In the end, however, I did not see very many shops or restaurants that could not reopen.</p> <p>  I am not actually convinced yet that people will not go back to work.  We are seeing the number of people on the pandemic unemployment payment falling fast.  This needs to be assessed in a few weeks' time.  There will always be a small number of people who, for whatever reason, do not accept their job back.  I think, however, the majority will.  It is probably too soon to come to any conclusions about that yet.  Let us see where we stand in terms of the numbers on the pandemic unemployment payment in July and August.  We will have a better read then.  We could be down to maybe 100,000 people.  That is a better base from which to understand this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00200"><p>What is the T&aacute;naiste's position on the joint labour committee for the retail sector or for the hospitality sector?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00300"><p>There is a process as to how they can be established.  That is all set out in law.  They are being challenged in the Supreme Court and we will have to see the outcome of that case.  I hope it will be that these stand up constitutionally and legally.  In that case, we can have more of them.</p> <p>  I would like to see them exist in the meat sector, for example, which is an area of ongoing concern.  There are also plans for them in childcare and we have a successful one in construction.  Much of this will depend on what happens in the Supreme Court and as to whether these stack up constitutionally.</p> <p>  I believe in the voluntarist system.  It is better that we have a system where employers, unions and employees agree to these arrangements rather than having them imposed.  If the State were to do anything, I would rather see it raise the floor for everyone rather than for certain sectors and not others.  Whether it is the living wage or sick pay, I want to do it for everyone and not different sectors.  I do not see why that would not be good public policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00400"><p>We want it for every sector but some employers are hostile to ever engaging with worker representatives, particularly in the hospitality sector.</p> <p>  Youth unemployment is the single greatest legacy issue arising from the pandemic.  There has been no reference to it in the contributions so far.  There are no easy answers as to what the Government can do.  It has to act, however.  We know that last December when the economy opened up, the unemployment rate was at 53% for those aged between 15 and 24 years.  There will be no going back to normal for a long time, particularly for young workers.  What are the T&aacute;naiste's thoughts on that?</p> <p>  We now have a situation where workers in certain sectors are forced to take unpaid internships in order to get a start in their chosen career.  Does the T&aacute;naiste believe this is acceptable?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00500"><p>There are a lot of things there that I could talk about at length but time is limited.</p> <p>  There can be no doubt that the pandemic has affected different people in different ways.  It has affected men differently to women and younger people differently to older people.  Older people have borne the brunt in terms of death and illness from the pandemic.  Young people have borne the brunt in terms of the economic impact, losing jobs, loss of income and the loss of the opportunities to do the things that younger people want to do which is to meet friends and find a life partner.  All those things have been horribly interrupted in the past year.</p> <p>  I do not like the idea of saying men are more affected than women or older people more affected than younger people.  When one examines it, different groups are affected in different ways.  Even when it comes to gender, men are more likely to have died from Covid and twice as likely to have ended up in ICU.  Women have been more adversely affected by domestic violence, mental health issues and the burden of caring.  It is absolutely the case that young people have been affected in a particular way.  It is an economic way as well as other ways.</p> <p>  The figure around youth unemployment is often misleading.  When people hear of 50% or 60% youth unemployment, they think that means that 50% or 60% of all young people are unemployed.  That is not the case at all.  When somebody is in education or training, they are not counted.  The actual youth unemployment rate is 22%.  I accept that is very high and is about double the average for the whole population.  However, probably the best statistic is the loss of employment.  The numbers employed who are young is down about 14%.  The numbers employed who are middle aged or older is down about 6%.  That would give a more accurate reflection as to what has happened.  It is because young people are disproportionately employed in areas like retail, construction and hospitality which are closed.  Construction is back open while retail and hospitality will reopen.  That will deal with most of the problem but by no means all of it.  That is why we need to do more.</p> <p>  As to what we can do, some of it is around better terms and conditions like the move to the living wage.  One has to have a job, of course, before one gets that.  That is why we need to make sure we do it right.  Education and training opportunities are another area.  I am proud that we have more people from more diverse backgrounds in third level and further education than ever before in the history of the State.  That has been as a result of the great work done by the past two Governments, one of which included the Senator's own party.  We need that to continue.  These are the angles we will go on.  Getting the economy back open is how most people will get their jobs back.  That will bring about the biggest fall in youth unemployment, as well as a focus on education and training, and ensuring people have opportunities.</p> <p>  The unpaid internships need to be examined.  I have done it myself and I have had unpaid interns, as the Senator might have too.  I found it beneficial.  There is a big difference, however, between doing something for a few weeks and unpaid labour for an entire year.  We probably need some regulation in this area but I have not quite had a chance to examine it yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00600"><p>On the previous decision made by IDA Ireland to employ a consultant in Israel, does the T&aacute;naiste think that it is still appropriate to go ahead with this, considering the situation facing the Palestinians and the role of the Israeli state in terms of apartheid conditions, pogroms within the borders of Israel, ethnic cleansing in East Jerusalem and bombs raining down on Gaza being responsible for the deaths of over 200 people?  At this stage, surely we should not be sending the kind of signal that would be sent by extending IDA Ireland to Israel.  Instead, we should be doing the very opposite in terms of the signal that we send internationally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00700"><p>I understand that IDA Ireland has hired a consultant to assist with its work in Israel.  That is not a political decision.  It is not one that crossed my desk or I signed off on.  IDA Ireland has its own legal authority in these areas.  It was done for good reasons because we have a significant trading relationship with Israel.</p> <p>  My general approach to these things is that we should continue to engage with states.  Sometimes we have trade boycotts.  However, as the Deputy knows himself, there are many states with which we could cut off links that people do not talk about enough.  Israel tends to be the focus of campaigns for boycotts around trading links.  There are many other countries, however, that have serious questions to answer such as Venezuela, Cuba and even some countries in eastern Europe.  For reasons I do not understand, people seem to be silent about these.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00800"><p>Right now bombs are raining down on Gaza and children are being-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#H00900"><p>I understand where the Deputy is coming from and I support what he is saying.  However, the T&aacute;naiste is here on two different issues.  Will the Deputy limit himself to those issues?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00100"><p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs has previously stated in written answers to parliamentary questions that IDA Ireland operates under the aegis of the T&aacute;naiste, so he has responsibility here and can make a political statement about whether he agrees with IDA Ireland expanding its operations into Israel at this time.</p> <p>  On Facebook's content moderators, the T&aacute;naiste made the point that non-disclosure agreements, NDAs, cannot be used to prevent workers from speaking up about their working conditions and so on.  I agree with that as both a formal legal position and a moral position.  However, we heard last week that that is precisely what is happening.  The existence of the NDAs, which the workers do not know the exact contents of, is held over them to prevent them from speaking out, talking to unions and so on.  Would the T&aacute;naiste agree that NDAs should be published so that everybody can see what is involved and so that there is full transparency?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00200"><p>The workers who have signed the NDAs should be given copies of them.  As they are agreements the workers have signed, it would then be up to them to decide whether they want to publish details of them.  I would like to see it.  There are reasons NDAs exist.  They are often good reasons relating to protecting people's privacy and confidentiality.  I have worked in jobs in the area of medicine where there were rules around these issues for good reasons.  I would not like to think that NDAs are being used to impose a chilling effect on workers or for them to feel that they are silenced and cannot raise concerns about their rights, entitlements and health and safety.  The short answer to the question is that I would like to see them but it would not be for them to be published publicly.  When an agreement is signed between two parties, it is for them to decide whether to publish them.  I would like to see the content.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00300"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste.  A general point that was raised about the conditions facing content moderators was, in effect, the two-tier workforce, with those who work directly for Facebook and have access to proper psychiatric counselling and so on and those who work for various outsourcing companies, such as Covalen and others, who do not have access to that, to wellness coaches and so on.  There are two groups of workers who are being treated in discrete ways as a result of being employed in two different ways.  Would the T&aacute;naiste agree that all of the workers doing the same work should be brought in-house to Facebook so that they have a direct relationship with Facebook and it can be held responsible for their terms and conditions and so on?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00400"><p>Not necessarily.  It is quite common in business and in the public sector to have core-flex arrangements, with core workers who are needed all the time, then you can flex up or down depending on needs that arise.  That is often done through agencies or outsourcing arrangements.  That should be their purpose.  Their purpose should not be to deny people doing the same work the same standards of protection when it comes to their health and safety and well-being.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00500"><p>That is precisely what it has done.  I have a final question to give the Minister a chance to clarify an earlier remark he made about Covid deaths.  He said that Ireland had the third lowest number of Covid deaths in the EU and mentioned Finland and Denmark as being lower.  I checked those statistics and it seems that Cyprus, Malta, Estonia and the Netherlands all have lower rates of death, which still puts us in the lower half, at seventh lowest rather than third lowest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00600"><p>Where did the Deputy check?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00700"><p>I checked <i>statista.com</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00800"><p>Word of honour says otherwise but we can check it out.  Everyone counts statistics differently, as the Deputy knows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J00900"><p>We are tragically in the top 50 countries in the world with regard to the number of deaths.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01000"><p>We record them all.  The Deputy will understand that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01100"><p>Sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01200"><p>The Deputy will understand that in a country such as India, where my father comes from, people who die from Covid do not get &euro;200 Covid tests.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1628" speakername="Paul Murphy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01300"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01400"><p>Before we move on to the second round, I want to raise the issue of Shannon Airport.  The announcement yesterday was catastrophic for the reason.  The regional balance we talk about will be in tatters if Shannon is not protected.  The T&aacute;naiste said that the Minister is meeting with Aer Lingus today.  There needs to be a better Government intervention.  The T&aacute;naiste said that there was a problem in the regional airports before the pandemic.  I understand that 87% of flights were going from Dublin Airport before the pandemic.  We all understand where we are with the pandemic but we need a plan when we come out of the pandemic for the regional airports.  The Shannon-Heathrow route is crucial for families who live in the mid-west with family abroad and it is also crucial for the foreign direct investment companies that we were lucky enough to attract to the Limerick, Shannon and mid-west region.  This cannot just be left to one Minister.  I am concerned about the Minister with responsibility for aviation policy.  Is his plan not to intervene?  I ask the T&aacute;naiste and Taoiseach to personally intervene in this.  I cannot emphasise how important that is, especially the Aer Lingus Shannon to Heathrow route.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01500"><p>I will do that.  I have met the company in the past couple of weeks.  I will get involved again as Minister with responsibility for enterprise.  It is part of my responsibility, in my mind, to make sure that we have good business connectivity from the mid-west to Britain, Europe and America.  The same goes for Cork and other airports.  I will get involved in this aviation issue and am involved in it already.  It would be remiss of me not to point out that Aer Lingus, in its statement, called out our strict travel restrictions as a reason for this base being closed.  There are parties in the D&aacute;il which thought we should have much stricter restrictions.  I understand that it is still the policy of many parties in the D&aacute;il to have even stricter travel restrictions than we have now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01600"><p>I understand that we have a better plan for the economy coming out of the pandemic.  We might have dodged that bullet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#J01700"><p>On the issue of connectivity, the T&aacute;naiste may be aware of this, but just in case, the route from Dublin Airport to Los Angeles was lost during the economic crash.  We could be here all day talking about how that happened and who is responsible, but it was lost in any event and it took eight years to get it back.  The issue of connectivity is centrally connected to the issue of jobs.  The T&aacute;naiste and I represent neighbouring constituencies.  Dublin Airport is located in my constituency and it is right beside the Taoiseach's constituency.  We know how important the aviation jobs are.  I echo the issues that were raised today with regard to the need for a plan.  There needs to be a real sense of urgency about this because what could be lost in the space of a couple of months could take years to be recovered.  There is a genuine fear.  It is not just about the jobs, although they are so important, it is also about connectivity.  I do not want to go through it but wanted to put it into the T&aacute;naiste's head that when a route is lost, you lose it quickly and get it back really slowly.  Anyone involved in aviation could tell you that.</p> <p>  I will go back to the issue of content moderators.  The discussion that we are having is interesting and welcome because this is a new type of work.  It is hazardous work, a point which was made previously.  It is a type of work that just did not exist when I was young.  It requires its own set of guidelines.  A joint labour committee may be an interesting way to approach it and there may be other ways.  Separate to it being something new, exotic and interesting, we have the issue of these non-disclosure agreements.  Fionnuala N&iacute; Bhr&oacute;g&aacute;in from the Communication Workers Union, which does brilliant work in this space along with Foxglove, cited the chilling effect that these non-disclosure agreements have.  Your boss might give you an agreement, with two minutes to read and sign it, and it might be 80 pages long.</p><p>You sign it because, quite frankly, you have looked at the news and you see the level of youth unemployment coming at you and you think, Jesus I need this job, so you sign the contract.  It is taken from you and then used against you.  You do not have a copy of it, but all you know is that you are constantly prevented from raising issues and having that contract held over you.  It is used as a tool against workers.</p><p> It appears this is not a breach of employment law, and my read of it is that it is not, although employees are entitled to information, but it should be because it is being used against them.  Fionnuala N&iacute; Bhr&oacute;g&aacute;in used the phrase "the chilling effect".  What that means in practice is that workers are afraid to raise concerns.  I fully appreciate that the Health and Safety Authority, HSA, exists, and in the course of my other work I had dealings with the HSA.  I know there is voluntarist machinery available that people can use, but the Minister must accept these people exist in an area that is somewhat outside of the normal industrial relations sphere and these agreements are being used to keep the workers in a situation whereby they are afraid to get organised, come together and challenge their employer.</p><p> This is linked to the next issue I want to raise with the Minister, which is youth unemployment.  We know the people who suffered the most during the economic crash, as in, for the longest, and I am not making a hierarchy of people who were battered by what was done to the economy but in terms of the sustained impact, youth unemployment took the longest to recover.  Is the Minister amenable to working on a cross-party basis to ensure that NDAs can be nullified?  We very often do that although people never see it happening.  There is a role for NDAs in some very discrete instances, but the indiscriminate use of them as a mechanism to control workers is not good and it should not be happening.</p><p> Will there be a dedicated section on youth unemployment in the national economic recovery plan?  All of the unemployment that will arise out of the pandemic will be tough to deal with, but we must learn the lesson from the previous crash in that youth unemployment was sustained at a higher rate for longer than in other age groups.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00200"><p>I do not know how the LA route was lost.  Deputy O'Reilly might fill me in privately some time.  I imagine there is a story to tell there.  I do know how it was regained because it was regained when I was Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  It was a mixture of the travel tax, route incentives, a growing economy, a marketing budget for Tourism Ireland and fifth freedom rights.  I am sure we can get it back with a similar mix when the time comes.</p> <p>  On the non-disclosure agreements, I cannot understand the concept of asking somebody to sign an agreement and then not allowing them to have a copy of it.  I will check up on the law in that regard.  If it is not illegal, it probably should be.  I just do not understand the concept as to why somebody would be asked to sign an agreement and they are somehow supposed to memorise it.  Even if you want somebody to adhere to an agreement he or she signs, would it not make sense for that person to have a copy of it so that person can remember what he or she agreed to?  There is something very odd and suspicious about people not being able to see an agreement they signed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1467" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00300"><p>It is exploitation.  It is not that hard to understand.  It is workers having this used as a tool against them to exploit them.  It keeps the union away from them.  We could be here all day talking about the right to organise and union recognition, so let us not go down that road.  I understand completely what it is that motivates a company to do it.  This tool is working very well because the workers were initially terrified of getting organised.  Thankfully, now they are working with the union, which is a very good and positive step.  The situation is designed to ensure the chilling effect is felt by the workers and the impact of that is they will put their head down, do their work and not raise concerns.  We need workers who will raise concerns, especially in this area because of the mental health effects and the hazardous nature of the work they are doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00400"><p>I think perhaps we will have some employment legislation coming through in this session to deal with some issues the Deputy will be familiar with on the Zalewski judgment.  Perhaps there is an opportunity to make an amendment to employment law in the coming months or this year to make sure employees are entitled to a copy of any agreement they have signed.  I do not see who in the House could be against that.</p> <p>  In response to the question on the national economic recovery plan, there will be sections both on youth unemployment also a section on gender equality and how that must be part of the economic recovery as well because there has probably been a widening of gender inequality in an economic sense during the pandemic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00500"><p>I do not think it is appropriate for the Chair of an Oireachtas committee to criticise a senior Minister when he is not at the meeting.</p> <p>  I welcome the T&aacute;naiste's comments on the return of indoor dining in early July.  It is vital that happens as soon as it is safe to do so.  Will the T&aacute;naiste confirm this will happen if more than 80% of the population have been vaccinated by the end of June?</p> <p>  I will briefly make two other points.  In 13 days' time hotels and restaurants with outdoor dining will be back trading, as far as the T&aacute;naiste is aware.  When will the Department issue the guidelines for this, because it takes some time to get set up and to organise a range of issues?  We need to get the information urgently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00600"><p>I am sorry but what guideline is the Deputy talking about?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00700"><p>The guidelines the Department will issue for the reopening of the hospitality sector on outdoor dining and hotels.</p> <p>  I spoke to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform yesterday about the wage subsidy scheme.  As a person involved in business myself, I tried to outline how vital it is.  I welcome the T&aacute;naiste's positive comments and I would greatly appreciate if he could speak to the Minister for Finance.  I will leave it at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00800"><p>Unfortunately, I cannot confirm or deny anything about July at this stage, but it is certainly our hope and intention to allow indoor dining to resume, we hope in early July, and some mass events as well.  As always, there are four factors.  It is not just the vaccines but also case numbers, which seem to be rising a bit again, the situation in hospitals, which is continuing to improve, and then issues concerning variants.  We do have a concern about the Indian variant.  There is some evidence in the UK of increased transmission and increased hospitalisations as a result of that.  We will see how that develops in the coming weeks.</p> <p>  I believe it is F&aacute;ilte Ireland that draws up the guidelines on outdoor dining and drinking.  It will not be done by us, but we will have an input.  I do not have a date for them, unfortunately, but I appreciate that people need to see them soon in order that they can plan ahead.  To give the Senator a rough idea, it is going to be seated dining only with 1 m or 1.5 m between tables and no more than six at a table.  The six people can come from any number of households.  There will be no rule about a maximum of 15.  If an establishment has the space, then it has the space.  There will not be a requirement to buy a substantial meal.  That will be gone.  We do not anticipate that there will be a limit on the amount of time people can stay.  It will be a lot more practical than what existed before, but that is not finalised yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K00900"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#K01000"><p>I wish to follow up on what many speakers said about our meeting last week with Facebook and the contribution from Isabella Plunkett about her experience in recent years working for Facebook.  Many of the questions that have been asked today should be asked of Facebook.  Chairman, could we invite in Facebook to ask those questions directly because their employment is really a matter between Facebook and the employees?  Based on some of what the T&aacute;naiste said in his contribution at the start of the meeting, it will be a difficult meeting with Facebook.  It emerged at this morning's meeting of the Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment that Twitter plans to take a legal challenge to the online safety laws.</p><p>That just shows the challenge we have with some social media companies.  I do not expect the T&aacute;naiste to comment on the matter, given that the announcement was made only in the past hour.  Twitter stated that one of the reasons it is taking the legal challenge is that it will set a precedent across the world, which seems to be a strange argument.</p><p> On Shannon Airport, the T&aacute;naiste stated that a number of political parties pushed for stronger measures.  I have seen that in my county, Tipperary, where two political parties, and one party leader, pushed for stronger measures, whereas now they are calling for answers in regard to why Aer Lingus has taken this step.  Has the T&aacute;naiste spoken to Aer Lingus?  Have we got any reassurance regarding the strategic routes, particularly that from Shannon Airport to Heathrow?  I think that route is up for review in about one year's time.  Have we any reassurances the routes will remain?  It is a significant concern for the general public in the mid-west.</p><p> On the new scheme the T&aacute;naiste announced this week, namely, the small business assistance scheme, I am surprised it has not been raised more often during the meeting, although my colleague, Deputy Stanton, mentioned it.  This is something that the Members of both Houses have been calling for over the past nine months.  They have asked whether something could be done for businesses that are not rateable premises.  It is very welcome that we are doing it.  While it is small money, it will be very significant.  I am delighted that it will, I hope, be open for people to apply on Friday or if not then, early next week.  Is the grant a straight &euro;4,000 or do businesses have to show what fixed costs they have?</p><p> The closing date for the first round was 21 April.  I am aware of a number of businesses in County Tipperary - I am sure there are many throughout the country - that did not apply for the first round.  They were essentially closed in recent months and, for one reason or another, thought they could not apply until after they began reopening, which occurred after the closing date for applications.  Is there any measure the Department provided last summer, such as the restart grant, whereby businesses could apply for the first restart grant when they apply for the new grant?  Is there any way in which businesses might be able to apply for the first small business assistance scheme at the same time that they apply for the second one?  The closing date was 21 April and if businesses are reopening, it would give those that for whatever reason might not have applied for the first round the opportunity to apply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#L00200"><p>I reiterate that the Minister for Transport is meeting representatives from Aer Lingus today and I cannot pre-empt the outcome of that meeting.  It is fair to say that while the Minister is very aware of the impact aviation has on the environment in terms of emissions, he is also aware of the essential nature of aviation for an island nation.  He is certainly not anti-airline or anything like that.</p> <p>  To my mind, the crucial routes from Shannon Airport are to Heathrow, the east coast of the US and another EU hub.  That hub was going to be either Paris or Frankfurt and we got the former, which was great, but then along came the pandemic and we lost pretty much everything.  It is a very worrying situation.  Again, Ireland is not Australia or New Zealand; it is very different.  Airlines do not want to be paid to stay on the ground in Europe.  They do not want to be paid to run routes on which there are no passengers.  They will just move the aeroplanes, and that is how the single European sky works.  Unfortunately, that could happen to us and that is why we will need a large and attractive incentive package to get airlines and their routes back.  We can do that only when passengers are allowed and able to travel, and we are just not at that point at the moment for public health reasons.</p> <p>  I am always worried about giving information about grant schemes because there are now so many that I tend to mix them up.  My recollection is that it is a straight grant of &euro;4,000.  An applicant does not have to demonstrate particular fixed costs.  We are not going to ask for insurance bills, utility bills or whatever, but applicants will have to show that their turnover is down 75% or more and that they had a turnover of &euro;50,0000 or more, and they have to commit to reopening or staying open.</p> <p>  As for missing the application deadline, to be honest there is not an awful lot we can do about that.  People miss application deadlines all the time and we cannot just reopen them all the time.  Nevertheless, there are sometimes cases, particularly humanitarian ones, where somebody may have missed the deadline for very good reason, but just not having applied, not thinking it was necessary to apply or not getting around to it would not be enough.  We will consider a bit of flexibility in certain circumstances if there are overwhelming compassionate reasons but that is limited.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#L00300"><p>On staff returning to work, a previous speaker mentioned the PUP.  It is welcome that there will not be a cliff edge but rather a gradual easing of supports.  There has been a change even in the past two weeks.  The number of people receiving the PUP in County Tipperary on 4 May was more than 18,000, whereas it has now decreased to 9,000.  It has halved already and that is without the hospitality industry having yet reopened.</p> <p>  One issue I have come across with staff and management relates to when people will be returning to work in a normal work environment.  Companies are eager to get people back to work but staff are not as eager to return.  Businesses seek guidance and the guidance remains that working from home is preferable, but the issue of antigen testing is tied in with that.  How can we encourage companies that might not be fully sure about antigen testing to use it or to see it as an option to get staff back to work?  Obviously, there are differences of opinion on all sides and that applies to the workplace as well.  Some companies will view antigen testing as very positive, while others will be unsure about it.  How can the Government encourage companies that are unsure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#L00400"><p>We are encouraging workplaces to adopt antigen testing and many workplaces are doing so, such as in retail, construction and manufacturing.  Many employers are using it.  We issued new guidance on the issue on Friday last to give employers the strength of a Government document, with the harp on it, that gives them guidance on what or what not to do.  We always say it should be voluntary and staff should not be required to take an antigen test.  It should be done right, using tests approved by the European Commission in particular, and it should be seen only as an additional health and safety measure, not a substitute for getting a PCR test if a person has symptoms.  Similarly, it is not a substitute for social distancing, mask-wearing or any of those measures.</p> <p>  I genuinely encourage employers to take this up because if it is viewed as an additional health and safety measure, it will pick up some cases that might otherwise have been missed, and had those cases not been picked up, they might have caused an outbreak.  It is in employers' interest to have antigen testing in their workplaces.  They can offset it as a business expense against tax and it is not a benefit-in-kind for their employees, so they cannot be taxed on it.  It is not a health benefit in that sense but rather a health and safety measure.  I re-emphasise that if somebody has symptoms, he or she needs to self-isolate and get a PCR test.  Antigen tests are not a substitute for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#L00500"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste.  For someone with so much going on, he is fairly good at answering questions on the hop.  I am amazed at some of the questions members ask him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#L00600"><p>It causes terrible trouble for my officials and advisers afterwards when they have to go around correcting everything I got wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#L00700"><p>I will try to keep it general.  On tradespeople and apprenticeships, we will need a huge number of tradespeople if we are serious about the move towards building, with Rebuilding Ireland, and retrofitting homes.  I worry about the lack of tradespeople.  I spoke to a builder recently who informed me that tradespeople are becoming known as "grey sites" because they all have grey hair.  I recently visited a school, and not one of the children put up their hand when I asked who wanted to be a tradesperson.  We need to do some serious work on this.  We need to make apprenticeships more attractive.  I wish I had been told to marry a tradesman when I was in school because tradespeople are the ones who keep everything on the road.</p><p>I do not know whether we need to issue a PR statement or something around the importance of tradesmen.  They are literally keeping everything we do together, whether it is buildings, transport or whatever.  Where would we be without tradesmen?  I do not know whether they are valued as much as they ought to be and I think we need to do something around that.  We lost a good few tradespeople in the previous recession.  Some of them are in Australia or Canada or such places.  It may be time to consider calling them back, as was done for nurses and doctors.  We will have a shortage of tradespeople to do the work we want done.  We want to get houses built and retrofitted.  I ask the T&aacute;naiste to think about that and consider what can be done.  The apprenticeship model must include time in college so that even people from rural areas who want to become a tradesperson get time experiencing college life and living away from home and that kind of thing.  The job itself has changed in many ways.  I am going to move away from apprenticeships and the importance of tradesmen.  I should say tradespeople.  I have female friends who are carpenters and so on but I was reared saying tradesmen.  However, we have to consider tradespeople if we are serious about what we want to do.</p><p> An issue I wish to raise with the T&aacute;naiste relates to the public realm and how space is shared, particularly in the context of the food and hospitality sector.  There is a need for local authorities to create outdoor spaces, not necessarily outdoor dining but outdoor seating and other outdoor spaces such that if a person wishes to sit down and eat something, whether he or she bought it from a restaurant with seating or a restaurant without seating or whatever, he or she can do so.  We really need to consider the public realm.  I think that will not be done properly unless there are urban designers or urban architects in local authorities.  I mean no offence to road engineers and technicians and quantity surveyors.  They are brilliant at their jobs but this task is not part of their profession.  We really need to look at that issue because we want to become like the rest of Europe, where it is normal for villages and towns to have beautiful, safe and aesthetically pleasing places to hang out.  We get the same amount of rainfall as Copenhagen and Amsterdam.  People speak about the weather a lot but it is not as bad as many people think.  We need to consider that.  It will not work if we do not get proper urban designers.  We cannot leave it on the shoulders of people who have been trained as road engineers.  That is really important if we want to get outdoor everything right, which we do because, as a nation, we went outdoors and realised it is bloody amazing.  It is really important to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00200"><p>If the Senator wants her questions to be answered, she should bear in mind that she only has one minute left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00300"><p>If we are serious about regional rebalancing and jobs in rural Ireland, the issue of rural broadband must be addressed.  I know the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan, wants to try to speed up the roll-out of rural broadband from seven years to five years.  I believe that with the help of the T&aacute;naiste, we might get it done even faster than that.  It is so important.  Even five years seems like a ridiculous amount of time to have to wait.  I know it takes time for it to be physically rolled out but I cannot over-emphasise how important it is to get broadband into rural Ireland.  I worked from home for the past 14 years.  Members would not believe the stress I had.  At one stage I had to hold my laptop above my head.  The digital hubs are brilliant and have a significant part to play.  Even if one works from home, one needs to go to somewhere to meet people.  Digital hubs are amazing and good work has been done on them by the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys.  If the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, wants to try to speed up the roll-out of rural broadband, the more Ministers who can get involved in making that happen, the better.  It is key to everything happening in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00400"><p>The Senator's time is up.  She has not left any time for the T&aacute;naiste to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00500"><p>Damn.  Sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00600"><p>I tried to warn her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00700"><p>Did you?  Sorry; I missed that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00800"><p>I call Deputy Bruton, who has five minutes.  I apologise for the short amount of time allocated to each member.  As a result of the pandemic, we have to limit the duration of meetings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M00900"><p>I will try to take less than five minutes.  There will just be one chance to reset the compass in terms of climate and the circular economy and that is as we start to reopen.  In practical terms, will this happen?  Will there be audits of enterprise to assess preparedness and setting milestones?  Will more people commit to plastic pledges and 2030 climate pledges?  How will we drive it on?  I will take one example, that of the food sector.  It wastes 1 million tonnes of food each year.  That is equivalent to 3 million tonnes of carbon.  That is one year of the ten-year reduction if we could get cracking on that.  Two thirds of the plastic used is not recyclable.  We could really strengthen Origin Green by having better sourcing and identification of the way production is happening.  How is it going to be driven on in practice?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01000"><p>That is a good question.  It is something I would like to discuss in more detail with the Deputy because I have been having those thoughts myself.  One small thing we are doing now is we have opened up the green enterprise fund which the Deputy has probably heard about.  It is approximately &euro;10 million that will fund businesses to do exactly the things he mentioned, such as audits of their energy use, waste and kind of how they operate, in order to reduce waste, energy use and emissions.  That is only a drop in the ocean and a small start because industry accounts for 13% of all emissions and we need to cut them basically by half while still expanding and employing more people.  That is an enormous challenge and probably an issue to which the committee could devote a whole session.  Is that a lazy answer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1549" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01100"><p>I am happy to get involved in any such discussions.  It is not just about looking at energy and waste.  The reality is the choice of materials in construction, for example, can have a significant impact in terms of whether they lock up carbon or generate carbon emissions.  There is a need for micro-thinking to start happening at sectoral level within the agencies that are in charge of them.  I will leave it at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01200"><p>The Deputy's advice is very welcome on this area.  We decided on 51% and we mean it but, therefore, industry has to make its contribution and that is going to be a real challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01300"><p>As there are three minutes remaining, I will bring in Deputy Stanton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01400"><p>I thank the Chairman.  I will be very brief.  I assume that all members are getting emails from constituents - I certainly am - who are concerned about the emergency legislation that is to be renewed again on 9 June.  They are calling for reviews of this and so forth.  We are moving out of restrictions and lockdown thanks to the work of all involved.  I am wondering whether the Emergency Measures in the Public Interest (Covid-19) Act 2020 will be renewed on 9 June as scheduled.  That has an impact on employment, jobs and so forth.</p> <p>  The other thing that has been missing all along is the issue of interpretation.  A query was received yesterday about whether drive-in cinemas are allowed at the moment.  To me, drive-in cinemas are quite safe.  One sits in one's car looking at the big screen and not interacting with anyone.  However, the Garda has interpreted them as not being possible under the current restrictions.  We need to have a debate about how we move forward from here and open up the economy, especially under the various pieces of emergency legislation that were passed by the Houses and that all members want to see rescinded as soon as possible.  That is a very broad issue, but it is a very fundamental and important one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1474" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01500"><p>The sooner we can repeal that legislation, the better, in my view.  If the Deputy had told me two years ago that we would live in a country where it was illegal to leave or enter the State for non-essential reasons, that one could not have visitors to one's house or could not meet outside with more than 15 people, I would have thought he was absolutely bonkers.  What has happened in the past year or two is unprecedented.  We overuse that term but what has happened in the past year really is unprecedented.  We want to go to a new normal and build back better, as people say, but one thing I definitely do not want to keep on the Statute Book for any longer than is necessary is this draconian legislation.  Unfortunately, it is still necessary.  We are not out of the woods yet and that is why we will have to extend it.  There will be proper debate on that in the D&aacute;il and I encourage Deputies to speak freely on this issue.  They should not feel that they are against public health or something if they raise these concerns.  Civil liberties matter.  Concerns about civil liberties have almost disappeared in the past year or so and that bothers me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1509" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2021051900002#M01600"><p>That concludes our consideration of these matters.  I thank all present, especially the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Varadkar, for assisting the committee in its consideration of the matter.  His attendance is much appreciated.  The meeting is now adjourned.  I thank everyone for participating in the meeting under these difficult circumstances resulting from Covid-19.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.93" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 11.30 a.m. sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.94" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Health</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.95" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Colm Burke, Frances Black, Cathal Crowe, Martin Conway. David Cullinane, Bernard J. Durkan, Neasa Hourigan, Gino Kenny, John Lahart, Róisín Shortall.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy Seán Crowe sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.96" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#A00200"><p>Before we commence our formal proceedings this morning, I must address a housekeeping issue.  The draft minutes for our meetings of 11 and 12 May were circulated earlier.  Are they agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.98" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#A00300">Ventilation and Covid-19: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#A00400"><p>I welcome the witnesses.  Both are members of the expert advisory group on ventilation and Covid-19, and will present on the role of ventilation in achieving better health outcomes in tackling the Covid-19 virus.  I welcome Ms Orla Hegarty, associate professor at the school of architecture, planning and environmental policy at UCD, and Mr. Simon Jones, commercial director, Aereco Limited.</p> <p>  Before we hear their opening statements, I must point out to our witnesses that there is uncertainty as to whether parliamentary privilege applies to evidence given from a location outside the parliamentary precincts of Leinster House.  Therefore, if witnesses are directed by me to cease giving evidence on a particular matter, they must respect that direction.</p> <p>  I ask Ms Hegarty to make her opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#A00500"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to attend this session.  I am an architect and academic at the UCD school of architecture, planning and environmental policy.  My expertise is the science of prevention because although the virus is biological, the pandemic, which spreads from one person to another, is highly environmental.  Buildings are key to suppressing the pandemic.  Prevention is about managing people and managing air.  Vaccines alone cannot end this.  They need the support of a parallel prevention plan.</p> <p>  Looking at buildings in Ireland, we see the following.  More than half of the people who died were infected in just 0.03% of buildings.  Over half of the cases in workplace outbreaks have been in just 150 buildings.  Infection in overcrowded private homes is twice the rate of uncrowded homes.  One in four school buildings has had a Covid-19 index case in the past four months.</p> <p>  The problem is infected air.  We now understand that risk of transmission is predominantly indoors and very specific to certain buildings and indoor air conditions.  These conditions are preventable, and this knowledge is key to stopping infections and to opening buildings at low risk.  Most transmission is not from hands touching surfaces, it is from inhaling infected air.  Masks are the only protection at close range.  Outdoors, the virus is diluted and blown away.  However, in buildings and vehicles, it can build up, fill a space, linger for hours and infect many people.  Viral particles in the air behave a little like smoke and must be cleared out.</p> <p>  Many countries are achieving low-risk social and economic activity using prevention policies that manage people and their air.  These strategies include the following: providing public health information; reducing occupancy, that is, the number of people; limiting certain activities; setting indoor air standards; measuring unsafe, stale air; improving ventilation and filtration; and, sometimes, doing structural or engineering works to buildings.</p> <p>  Indoor air can be measured and managed.  This week, international researchers said &ldquo;preventing respiratory infection, like reducing waterborne or food-borne disease, is a tractable problem&rdquo;.  Indoor spread is measurable and controllable.  They warn that. &ldquo;For decades, the focus of architects and building engineers was on thermal comfort ... initial investment cost, energy use, and ... performance ... [and] infection control was neglected.&rdquo;  This was not always the case.  Ireland regulated overcrowding in bedrooms to prevent TB.  Before the modern era of energy efficiency and airtightness, architecture and public health were very closely aligned and that is why ventilation is regulated.  However, the balance has shifted away from disease prevention as the current regulations aim only to &ldquo;provide adequate ventilation while limiting energy use and avoiding occupant discomfort&rdquo;.  One hundred years ago, Chicago suppressed the 1918 pandemic with targeted measures, including building inspectors who signed off on ventilation as a condition of trading.  The city of Chicago reopened within six weeks.  There was no second wave and no vaccine.</p> <p>  With regard to the focus on what is high risk, international evidence points very clearly to which buildings and activities are high risk and where to target resources.  There is a significant body of research from theoretical and experimental sciences and building case studies.  Super-spread events, where many people are infected at once, indicate the particular environmental conditions of spread.  This means that targeted suppression can be very effective, as seen in Japan and other places.</p> <p>  There is a need to target the clusters.  Covid-19 has very particular characteristics.  Most people do not spread the virus to anyone else.  It is said to be &ldquo;highly over-dispersed&rdquo;, meaning spread is not a factor of average contacts.  Suppressing the pandemic, therefore, is less about rules for people and more about rules for places.  This is an opportunity to target interventions because most infected individuals do not contribute to the expansion of an epidemic, so the effective reproduction number could be drastically reduced by preventing relatively rare super-spread events.  These super-spread conditions can arise in any enclosed space with two people or many.  Indoor risk is about the building, its management and operation, the number of people and the activity.  There are strong seasonal factors because indoor air quality changes with the weather, the season and the operation of the building.  Infection risk indoors can be reduced by 50% with increased airflow, and by almost 90% with airflow, filtration and wearing masks.  Although data in Ireland are limited, the patterns of Covid spread are very similar to other countries, so public health measures can be targeted to have the most impact.</p> <p>  I will now look at the high-risk areas.  With regard to vehicles, high levels of ventilation and filtration are critically important in cars, vans, buses and aircraft.  An outbreak on an aircraft into Dublin last summer resulted in 13 cases on the aeroplane and 59 cases in total, across six HSE regions.</p> <p>  With regard to housing, infection rates are double in overcrowded private homes, according to the CSO data.  A significant number of infections happen within households, and rates are higher in households with children.  Inadequate space in institutional and shared housing is high risk, such as in dormitories, hostels and emergency homeless accommodation.  Direct provision centres have had 82 outbreaks with an average of ten cases each.  Traveller and Roma housing have had 423 outbreaks with an average of 12 cases.</p> <p>  With regard to schools and childcare, more than one in four schools has had a Covid index case since February and, in total, there have been almost 2,500 cases linked to 579 outbreaks in schools.  Last week alone, there were 61 outbreaks in schools, which was 20% of all outbreaks.  Of 633 cases linked to outbreaks last week, more than one third, or 36%, were in schools and childcare facilities.  There have been almost 2,000 close contact cases in childcare and after-school facilities since last July and 342 outbreaks in approximately 900 childcare buildings, that is, more than one third of childcare facilities have had an outbreak.</p><p>In hospitals, nursing homes and residential care, 55% of the people who died from Covid-19 in Ireland, were infected in fewer than 0.03% of all buildings.  A mere 667 buildings accounted for the infections that led to more than half of the deaths.  There have been 600 outbreaks in 581 nursing homes, but it is very uneven.  In Kildare, 87% of all nursing home deaths were in just a quarter of the buildings and that needs further investigation.  Inadequate ventilation is linked to poor respiratory health in older people.</p><p> More than half of all infections in workplace outbreaks were in meat and food plants.  There were nearly 3,500 cases in outbreaks with an average of more than 40 cases per building in those.  There have been 96 outbreaks in construction.  One meat plant alone had an outbreak with 226 cases.  One construction site outbreak had 148 cases.</p><p> I will deal with indoor dining, bars, gyms, places of assembly.  Some places have significantly higher risks, particularly where people are indoors in close proximity for long periods of time and without masks, such as in restaurants, pubs, theatres, cinemas, hotels, and entertainment and sports venues.  An outbreak in a caf&eacute; in Cork resulted in 57 cases.  At an extreme level, one breach in hotel quarantine in Australia directly resulted in 18,000 infections, 800 deaths and a 112-day lockdown.  Breaches in buildings can have a very significant impact.</p><p> Certain activities have higher risks, including exercise in gyms and for sports, singing in choirs and at religious events, and shouting, because they generate aerosols and involve deep breathing.  A recent outbreak in a gym in Canada resulted in 480 cases and it spread to 49 workplaces.</p><p> This knowledge provides an opportunity for more sure-footed policies.  Eliminating unsafe conditions protects everyone, including children, people with compromised immunity and those not vaccinated.  It also mitigates the risk of variants, and of super-spread events.  Vaccines alone cannot provide enough headroom for reopening.  A prevention plan is needed.</p><p> Safe indoor air has many measurable benefits for health and well-being.  It mitigates all respiratory illness, including flu, and future-proofs for another pandemic.  Aside from all these benefits, good indoor air quality is a legal requirement of workplace health and safety.</p><p> This understanding of transmission and prevention has significant implications, and indicates a need for fundamental review of some incorrect assumptions in public health policy; public health information; reopening plans; sectoral rules; tracking and tracing procedures; epidemiological modelling; and building standards, inspection and enforcement.  To ensure that policy is consistent and scientifically up to date, an active multidisciplinary approach is needed.  It needs collaboration and engagement across disciplines including biomedical, epidemiological, environmental, sociological and other sciences.</p><p> Further analysis of these patterns of spread and investigation of buildings is needed.  There must be a risk-based approach to target interventions and effectively use limited resources.  If this virus were in water or food, the response would be to take samples, investigate the source and eliminate the problem.  So it must be with infected air.</p><p> This is a third way that steers a scientific course between lockdown and uncontrolled spread.  However, it requires a paradigm shift so that public health policy is evidence based and responsive to new knowledge.  There needs to be a shift in perception that we cannot afford the cost of control, because the economic costs of infections can be enormous and may well exceed costs of containment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.102" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#B00200"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to attend this session today.  Over the past 150 years the link between science, the development of interventions, and organisation of public authorities has increased the success and public understanding of public health.  It is time for ventilation and its impact on air quality to be seen through a similar lens.</p> <p>  We spend up to 90% of our time indoors and this pandemic is a disease of buildings.  Regardless of where we see the balance between fomite, close or long-range transmission, the impact on health of our indoor environment has been thrust into focus.</p> <p>  Ventilation is a critical factor in reducing the risk of long-range airborne transmission, particularly in enclosed spaces.  Often simple strategies that ensure adequate ventilation can help to reduce the spread of Covid-19 in many settings, including homes, schools, workplaces, public buildings and vehicles.  Moreover, these strategies can also reduce the risk of superspreading events where many people become infected at the same time.  It is an important part of a layered strategy to reduce transmission and should, of course, be used in conjunction with other measures.</p> <p>  As the science and our understanding of this disease has developed, ventilation is increasingly recognised as a critical factor in this multi-layered approach.  While it is an important component of any building, ventilation sits within a rapidly changing landscape.  The climate emergency is driving changes in regulations and fundamentally how our buildings are being asked to perform.  We are about to undertake a wholesale upgrade of our existing building stock that will have dramatic impacts on the performance of every building we occupy.  Our lifestyles and how we spend our time indoors continue to change.  Technology is rapidly evolving, giving us more insight into how our buildings perform and how we manage them.  The science related to indoor air quality continues to evolve and its impact on our health and well-being deepen.</p> <p>  Ventilation in buildings and how it impacts our health, in this case Covid-19, is not a field of absolutes.  We must not let perfection be the enemy of the good.  We already know many of our buildings do not perform as intended.  We all have experience of them.  Poor indoor air quality already costs us every day.</p> <p>  According to the EPA, 300 cases of lung cancer per year in Ireland can be linked to radon in our homes and workplaces.  According to the Asthma Society of Ireland, 380,000 people currently live with asthma in Ireland, a disease we know is significantly exacerbated by poor indoor environments, such as damp and dusty homes.  Every four minutes someone is admitted to hospital with asthma.  This disease alone costs the State &euro;472 million per year.</p> <p>  Ventilation impacts in a very real way our health and well-being, the learning outcomes of our children in school, lost days at work, lost rent and income to landlords and the State through disrepair and vacant properties as result of condensation and damp, and in other ways.  The pandemic has brought into stark perspective the impacts ventilation can have in disease control.</p> <p>  It is time for a significant shift in how we, as a society and State, view the air we breathe and start to value it the same way we value the water we drink and the food we consume.  The role of ventilation in fighting this pandemic and the additional benefits it brings must be brought further forward in our strategies and communication.</p> <p>  We need to mobilise professionals and provide signposts and advice for every building owner to access consistent and technically correct information on ventilation - information that is already available.  This would enable them to work with and get the best out of what they have and develop strategies to improve their buildings over time, not just for Covid-19 now and into next winter but for all the other benefits it brings.</p> <p>  We need better enforcement of regulations on ventilation in our new buildings and the development of better standards and guidance for our existing ones.</p> <p>  Ventilation in buildings needs to be at the centre of not just this pandemic but in everything we do in buildings.  It is a subject matter that has an impact on all Departments, including the Departments of Education, Health, and Environment, Climate and Communications.  The dividends of getting this right will repay our effort many times over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#B00300"><p>I thank Ms Hegarty and Mr. Jones for their presentations on the topic.  I agree that we expect water to be treated and the principle of treating our air makes common sense.</p><p>I have travelled by train to Dublin all of the time during this pandemic and part of the requirement of Irish Rail is that the windows are left open.  That is done for a clear reason.  The principle of how air is treated is very important.  I understand that in the building we are in now, unfortunately because of the pandemic we cannot use the committee rooms where our engagement with the witnesses would normally happen.  My understanding is that at least one company approached Leinster House last August seeking to carry out a ventilation exercise in the committee rooms and the Chambers.  As an institution, we want to see people getting back to work but we should be leading by example.  It is regrettable that the Houses of the Oireachtas did not engage more with this principle and use the Oireachtas as an example of how people can return to work safely.</p><p> I am interested in hearing our witnesses' views on the industry standards and the quality and perhaps Ms Hegarty might respond .  There is obviously a difference between ventilation and filtration.  High efficiency particulate air filter, HEPA, filtration is seen as the Rolls-Royce model of equipment that would do what we all want to see in terms of clean air.  Where are we as a country in embracing this?  Are we very much behind the curve?  Is there a European model?  I believe that Germany is particularly ahead when it comes to this, that there are air ventilation systems in the Bundestag and that most schools and public buildings in Germany have very clean and properly ventilated air.  Is there a better example than the German one in Europe?  Ms Hegarty might talk to us about that.  Can she also reflect on how far behind we are as a country in this area of protecting public health?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.105" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Conway for his question.  The most important thing we need to get across today is that much of this can be dealt with by way of clear public health information and good guidance.  We live in a temperate climate.  We are not the United States of America, where there is a great deal of air conditioning.  Most of our buildings are naturally ventilated so that people can improve things dramatically by just understanding the risks here in buildings and vehicles.  Most of our buildings are small ones with openable windows.  In particular, in the seasons when we are not heating or not having to heat a great deal, this can be addressed very easily at little or no cost.</p> <p>  In the winter season, we definitely need to start monitoring air because people are closing up buildings and there is a high risk of infection.  In our larger buildings, we have mechanical or other systems and people need technical advice.  We are talking in particular here about places like shops that are using wall and ceiling-mounted air conditioning units.  These are very dangerous because they are not bringing in fresh air but are recirculating cool dry air and they have been connected with outbreaks where they are blowing air around the room.  Again, this is an area where advice could help.</p> <p>  Larger buildings that have mechanical ventilation systems are often switched to recirculate the air to save energy.  If that is the case they need to be checked and may need upgrades on filtration or on equipment.  There are separate risks there.  </p> <p>The Senator mentioned HEPA filtration.  This involves very low technology portable filtration fans that people can buy, sometimes for &euro;100 or a little bit more for a classroom, that would be very suitable for places like nursing homes and childcare settings where perhaps people cannot wear masks or where there is a concern about vulnerable children or older people being in draughts or uncomfortable conditions.  These are plug-in portable fans that can be very effective.  Even from where we are now, there are very simple strategies that can be used in many places, with advice.</p> <p>  We also need to be very careful where people are selling systems at present, which may not be effective, are not regulated and which could possibly produce harmful by-products that are dangerous to health.  There is an unregulated area at present in which systems are being advertised, sold and installed without being proven to be effective or giving a benefit and which may be very expensive.  This is a technical area which needs to be resolved.</p> <p>  On the question of Germany, it has been dealing with this and has put forward an investment of several hundred million euro in order to improve schools and public buildings.  Monitoring air can be a first step.  This can be done very cheaply and carbon dioxide monitors are small and portable at a price of between &euro;100 and &euro;200.  They can be fitted to classrooms, office buildings and shops very easily.  They are light and can be moved around.  Spain is using these quite extensively in schools, as are other countries. </p> <p>  There are many low technology solutions and advice that can be taken at very little cost.  There will obviously be larger buildings that need specific targeted interventions where they have been identified as risk areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00300"><p>I am aware that Ms Hegarty is part of the expert advisory group.  Does she believe that the Government is taking this issue seriously?  Ms Hegarty stated that this is very much an unregulated area.  The first thing we need to do, therefore, is to introduce regulations to make the testing and monitoring of air part of what we do, in the same way that we test and monitor water.</p> <p>  On the systems that are being used, clearly it is worrying if there are some that are not up to scratch.  Many people have engaged with and purchased equipment motivated by the right reasons.  Clearly then, a job of work has to be done to bring in some sort of regulation and approved recognition for systems, standards and so on.  Does Ms Hegarty believe that this work is now being taken seriously and is being done?  As a committee, should we be making recommendations to the Government in this area?  What is her advice be to us on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.107" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00400"><p>I cannot obviously speak for the expert committee but I can speak personally on that point.  I do not feel that the response has been adequate or that the public health message has been clear.  The vast majority of people to whom I speak do not know why it is important and if they have heard the word ventilation, they do not understand why it is significant.  Many of the policy and sectoral documents advocate improving ventilation if appropriate or if possible.  They do not explain that it is absolutely critically key as a first defence.  There are also a number of other flaws across this issue.</p> <p>  One is that sectoral guidance is left to the sectors to write.  Whether it is sports, construction, childcare, nursing homes, shops, hairdressers or dentists, the sectors are writing their own guidance and a scientific review is not being done on whether that is consistent, correct or up to date.  A significant number of documents out there are scientifically incorrect and out of date.  People are doing their best and what they think is appropriate but are doing the wrong things.  This needs a more co-ordinated approach and needs to align with epidemiological modelling, which is to understand the changes in how we model the spread of disease because this is not a disease of averages.  Very targeted interventions could be much more effective than blanket restrictions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00500"><p>From where does Ms Hegarty believe this response should be led?  Should it be from public health, from NPHET or is there a particular Department that should take the lead on this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00600"><p>That is an answer for the governance structure of where this response fits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00700"><p>Looking at the international situation, is there any model on this level that we can look at that we could adopt here?  If it is already working successfully in other countries, is there a particular model that Ms Hegarty would recommend?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.111" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#C00800"><p>Some countries have scientific review boards that are multidisciplinary.  That would make a considerable difference.  Obviously the focus of NPHET is on hospital buildings and on mitigating risk there.  Hospitals are only 86 of our 2.5 million buildings.  The focus in hospitals is different to the focus on what is happening in the community.  It is also important to note that hospital buildings generally, particularly the newer buildings, are built to a very high standard of ventilation.</p><p>Even within that, we do not have rules within the hospital sector that will protect staff in terms of higher quality personal protective equipment, PPE, for those staff still working behind Perspex screens in some places without masks.  Again, that is not a protection.  A suite of measures are needed, especially within sectors.  There needs to be consistency and the measures should be based on scientific principles rather than what is convenient in a given sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00200"><p>I will ask a quick question first.  Are both Mr. Jones and Ms Hegarty on the expert group?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00300"><p>They are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.115" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00400"><p>Was that question addressed to me?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00500"><p>Yes, I am asking generally.  There are two witnesses, Mr. Jones and Ms Hegarty.  Are they both on the expert group?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.117" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00600"><p>We are, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00700"><p>When was the last time the group met?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00800"><p>It was within the past ten days or two weeks.  I do not have the exact date, but it was within the past week or so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D00900"><p>I am looking at the Government website.  Initially, when the expert group started to meet, the minutes and reports of the meetings were published online.  There are minutes of the meetings of 2 February, 5 February and 8 February.  Then it stops and no minutes or reports are published on the website.  Why is that the case?  I assume the group has met several times since then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01000"><p>I think we have met on 11 occasions.  The reporting of the group moved from the National Public Health Emergency Team to the senior officials group in Government.  The group is no longer reporting to NPHET.  That would have changed in March, although I do not have the exact date in front of me - it may have been in April.  I understand the reports produced by NPHET will be published but I do not think they are on the website at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01100"><p>Both witnesses raised the importance of public education, ensuring transparency and making sure the information gets out.  I hear what Ms Hegarty said about the group originally reporting to NPHET but now reporting to the senior officials group that was set up to manage Covid-19.  If the minutes of the meetings are not being published, we cannot see what is being discussed or what recommendations are being made.  Is this something the group has raised?  Were the members of the group aware that the minutes of the meetings stopped being published on 8 February?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.123" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01200"><p>The internal workings of the group are that our minutes are recorded in any event.  We understand the HSE website is slow to publish minutes generally.  It takes some time to get them up.  As such, the reports have not been published yet.  Our understanding is that the plan is to do so.</p> <p>  On a certain date we stopped reporting to NPHET and moved across to the senior officials group.  At that point, public reporting of reports and minutes ceased.  That does not mean those reports and minutes are not kept on record within the group.  They would be available to be published somewhere if that was the decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01300"><p>I accept that.  My point is broader.  I am not saying it directly to this group because it is not the responsibility of the group to ensure the reports and minutes are published.  I accept that minutes are taken and records are kept.  However, it is important that they are made public so that we can learn from them as well.  For the purposes of preparing for this meeting I logged on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01400"><p>There is a problem with the sound and picture.  You are too near to the device, Deputy Cullinane.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01500"><p>I am some distance from my phone now.  I will repeat the point.  I have no difficulty with the witnesses.  I am saying that in terms of process, public education and access to information it would be better if the minutes of the meetings were published so that we could see them.  For the purposes of preparing for this session, I was able to see the minutes for 2 February, 5 February and 8 February.  Then it stopped.  Is that something the group could take up with the HSE?  Can they ensure that the information on whatever meetings that have taken place since then is made publicly available?  Both witnesses have made a strong contention that there is a lack of awareness and education in respect of ventilation.  If an expert group is in place, I imagine it would be beneficial to the expert group and the witnesses that what has been discussed is made publicly available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01600"><p>I would not disagree with that.  It is something I know our chairperson has raised.  We can follow up externally again and ask the question again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01700"><p>To follow up on a question asked by the previous speaker on international evidence and best practice, where do we rate as a state or country in Europe in respect of the overall management of air quality?  I know we are putting a focus on this because of Covid-19.  The witnesses expressed the view that air management and air quality was a greater issue than Covid.  Obviously, in a pandemic it becomes a major issue to better manage air quality and prevent the spread of this virus.  However, it has wider implications for the health of people and in other areas.  In terms of the overall management of air quality where do we rank in Europe?  Are there data?  Have studies been done on how we rank?  Is it correct to assume the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications has overall responsibility for the management of air quality?  Has each Department responsibility in law to publish air management or air quality plans?  Is there an obligation on each Department to manage this in their buildings and so on?  Is that a requirement of each Department at this point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.129" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#D01800"><p>I will address the question on data first.  It is difficult to measure buildings.  We have buildings in use that are 200 or 300 years old.  We have buildings that have been adapted over time.  We have new buildings and some that have energy upgrades.  People have used them in different ways.  Sometimes they are used in a more crowded way than they were designed for or for a different purpose.  It is difficult to make comparisons.</p> <p>  We do not have ventilation regulated centrally in any way in Europe.  Each country regulates its standards.  Obviously, there is the factor of the local climate and other conditions.</p> <p>  Some other countries are doing far better in the pandemic response, especially Asian countries that have adopted this approach right from the beginning.  Countries like Vietnam, Taiwan, Singapore, Japan and China have responded with a clear message on ventilation as prevention.  They did this from the beginning of the pandemic.  Western countries, especially English-speaking western countries, have been especially slow and, I would say, resistant to adopting this as part of the pandemic response.  We can see the outcomes in comparing cases and deaths across the two different regions.</p> <p>  Who is responsible?  Responsibility is scattered.  The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage has standards for new buildings.  As we know, we have self-certification of new buildings, so certifying compliance is in the control of the developer or owner and not necessarily picked up anywhere independently.  Having standards and performance are two different things.  We can have an issue with the people who operate the building not knowing how it should be considered and so they may block up vents or overpopulate rooms.  The remit of the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage stops at construction.  The Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland has some responsibility in respect of air quality standards.  The Health and Safety Authority has a role under workplace health and safety.  Then again, not every building is a workplace.  There is inconsistency and there has not been a focus on this.  Building regulation standards only tend to change in response to an event.  If there is a structural collapse, a fire or some other emergency, we tend to react and have new regulations.  We have not had an issue with air quality since the tuberculosis era.</p> <p>  We have drifted into a medical response to issues, whereby we medicate and treat the illness rather than prevent it.  We have probably had 50 years of this, building from the oil crisis.  We have not had the experience of SARS or other pandemics that some other countries have had in more recent years.  Now is the time to react to this event and take it seriously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00100"><p>You are on mute and your time is up, Deputy Cullinane, unless you have one more point you want to make.  You are still on mute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1615" speakername="David Cullinane" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00200"><p>No.  I will leave it at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00300"><p>I thank our witnesses for those very interesting documents and presentations.  This issue has major implications.  I am interested in the application of ventilation.  I visited a lot of schools in my constituency prior to Christmas and the way in which the age of the building influenced how the school managed ventilation was really interesting.  With the ultra-modern, state-of-the-art buildings, big and bright and with a huge amount of natural light, which is really healthy, and quite open indoor plaza spaces, I got a sense that they were very well ventilated from a design and engineering point of view.  In the schools that were 30 or 40 years old the ventilation consisted of wide open entrance doors, windows open in every classroom, cold classrooms and children and teachers wearing warmer clothes.  That is simply unsustainable.  As we move forward now, particularly into retail and hospitality spaces, the role of ventilation is critical, whether or not it is with a view to dealing with a further pandemic at some stage down the road.  We know indoors is a no-no, but what have we learned about the obvious hospitality activities of eating and drinking and how we can apply those lessons to those areas?  What kind of advice are the witnesses now in a position to give?  What are we learning?  What is the halfway house or even the quarter-way house between fully open-air, which is almost but not completely impossible in the Irish context, and indoors, which is impossible in the context of a pandemic?  What kinds of lessons have we learned?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00400"><p>As for schools, the age of the school building obviously has an impact.  A lot of older schools built before perhaps the 1970s were designed with the memory of TB still alive.  They have good cross-ventilation, higher ceilings and more space.  A lot of that has been squeezed down and engineered out, I think, and some of those older buildings may have had retrofits involving sealed windows and partitions and other things, which have made them more dangerous.  What the schools did between August and Christmas was very commendable in that they were really the only ones to take this seriously in the autumn.  However, in the absence of any way of measuring safe air quality, the schools probably over-ventilated in a lot of cases, that is, they opened all the windows and the classrooms were very cold and uncomfortable because school management did not know when to stop.  If we provide CO2 monitoring in schools, we can find a happy balance because we can assess in real time whether risk conditions are rising.  Then we can open the windows for 15 minutes or take the class outside for 15 minutes, prevent risk and keep people comfortable.  That is the only option for next winter because children will not be vaccinated, so the schools need a plan for autumn and it needs to start immediately to be in place by winter.  The nursing homes probably fit in that category as well.</p> <p>  As for retail and hospitality, all buildings can be made safe.  Once we start measuring, we can target the risks.  Clearly, many buildings are low-risk because, otherwise, the pandemic would be even worse.  The issue, therefore, is how we find the conditions that are dangerous and deal with them.  This is not perceptible to humans.  I was in a large building yesterday with a CO2 monitor.  It felt reasonably comfortable at all times, yet when I looked at my CO2 monitor the reading went from safe to unsafe within five minutes in a different part of the building.  That would not have been perceptible to anybody not carrying a monitor to check air conditions.  As humans, we cannot guess at this, no more than we can guess at safe water.  We need to start monitoring.  People do not stay very long in retail environments and they wear masks, so the key issue in retail is to keep the numbers low, keep the air moving and protect the staff, particularly those who are there for longer periods and perhaps using back areas, storerooms and break rooms where they take off masks.  They can be the danger areas.</p> <p>  Hospitality is probably the most challenging sector, but that is not to say it cannot be dealt with.  It is the most challenging because people sit close together across a table, breathe the same air, tend to stay a long time and do not wear masks and a lot of buildings have been adapted and changed over the years and tables can be very close together.  Every building needs to be looked at differently and individually within a framework of good advice on the spacing of tables, particularly filtration and localised filtration to tables, which may be a good option for restaurants.  That is the HEPA filtration we spoke about earlier.  It basically comprises just a fan and a filter which cleans virus particles and other particles from the air continuously while people are in the room.  Then it is a matter of taking particular care of staff, back areas, toilets and cold rooms.  The means by which people travel to hospitality environments can be as high-risk as the actual building they enter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00500"><p>This is really interesting stuff.  How would Ms Hegarty see it being put on a structured, formal basis in terms of feeding into any future plans in the autumn and the winter?  That is the first matter.</p> <p>  My second point is about public transport: trams, the DART, trains and buses.  They are back up to 50% capacity now.  What kinds of data does Ms Hegarty have on that?</p> <p>  An obvious area which was connected with antigen testing recently is stadiums.  Are there any data on the air quality in the stands of a GAA, rugby or soccer ground?  Has the expert advisory group come up with any advices in that regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00600"><p>I do not have specifics in that regard.  On public transport, I suppose each transport operator would have to do some level of assessment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00700"><p>Have they done so, does Ms Hegarty know?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00800"><p>Not that I am aware of.  I have seen signage on some public transport about open windows but I think that when people do not understand why windows should be left open, they may close them again.  I know-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E00900"><p>I am sorry for interrupting Ms Hegarty.  It is just to feed into what she says.  I see all the windows open.  I just feel that that stems from perhaps not a particularly scientific approach.  How can we assist public transport companies towards best practice in this regard?  They cannot be faulted because we are learning all the time, but how could they be assisted with this?  What technology could we put at their disposal?  In other words, how could we make public transport reasonably reassuring for the public in greater numbers - or can we at all - in terms of air quality?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E01000"><p>There are a number of things.  The first is to improve airflow such that if vehicles have systems installed they are on full fresh air and not recirculating air that could have virus in it and in order that there is a good throughput of air all the time, that occupancy is managed such that there is no overcrowding and that people wear good masks, not lightweight ones.  The general position in places such as Taiwan and now Austria is that everybody wears a higher standard of mask and does not have a haphazard view of masks.  There are two things-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E01100"><p>This is the mask I am wearing today.  These are the ones we can buy in all our shops.  Is this a good-quality mask?  This is what everybody is wearing besides the cloth ones.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E01200"><p>The surgical masks people are wearing are effectively designed for protection from droplets in hospitals.  For protection from aerosol particles, that is, the very fine, lighter particles, which is what we are talking about, N95 or higher protection masks are recommended.  Some countries have moved to those, and the examples of that are in Asia, specifically Taiwan.  The masks are being provided by the Taiwanese Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E01300"><p>My mask is a surgical mask, is it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#E01400"><p>Yes.  The blue paper-like masks are surgical masks.  The two issues with masks are filtration, that is, the material used, and fit.  Surgical masks are often not a very good fit in that there are gaps around the edges which make them ineffective against aerosol particles.  As I was saying, the Taiwanese Government mass-procured all their masks, people there are provided with a certain number of masks at very low cost every two weeks and everybody wears a very good mask.  Some parts of Europe have required such masks on public transport or in retail or other establishments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00100"><p>Is that something Ms Hegarty recommends?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.145" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00200"><p>Yes, we should be moving towards higher grade masks, particularly in settings like public transport or more crowded environments.  In Japan, there is sort of silence rule on public transport because infected people put less of the virus into the air if they are not speaking or shouting.  We should give people the simple advice that not speaking or speaking in a very low voice can reduce risks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00300"><p>Is NPHET aware of Ms Hegarty's recommendation?  I believe in masks but there are still conflicting reports as to their efficacy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.147" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00400"><p>I am not an expert on occupational health.  The advice I am giving is based on the information I have gathered from speaking to other people, including aerosol physicists and people who work in occupational health.  That is the point I am making about it being a multidisciplinary issue.  It is very important that all of these people are around the table for our risk assessment to balance everything.  In the early stages last year, there were concerns about supplies and procurement.  There were concerns about people buying up supplies which would not then be available to people in the hospitals.  Those things have changed over the course of the year.  Similarly, in making these kinds of decisions, there must be a balance between risk and availability.  This may involve equipment, masks and the settings in which people are.  We must also consider whether cheaper and easier mitigations are available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00500"><p>When Ms Hegarty recommends-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00600"><p>I am sorry but Deputy Lahart has gone over his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1572" speakername="John Lahart" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00700"><p>Have I gone over?  Okay.  That is fine.  I did not get a warning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00800"><p>Mr. Jones was looking to come in.  I ask him to be quick as we need to move on to the next questioner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.152" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F00900"><p>I will be very quick.  There were two questions as people reached for an understanding of how we implement this.  The reality is this is very complex to do.  We have to get down to basics.  Good public information and awareness about the benefits of ventilation will go a very long way in getting people to be aware of their surroundings.  I look on the screen in front of me and see that every single person is in a different environment right now.  We can learn a lot from the world of retrofitting.  We need bespoke solutions for each individual room and building.  That is the hard reality.  There is no easy road with regard to ventilation in existing buildings.  One needs professionals, people who are capable of assessing risk and people who understand health and safety at work.  People need to go into spaces, look at them and understand how to get the best out of those buildings.  It goes back to the idea of perfection being the enemy of the good.  We can look for the perfect solution for every building but the reality is that we have to start somewhere.  The best place to start is with awareness.  We have to get people to understand and be cognisant of the air they breathe.  We can start to develop advice and tools over time to enable people to get the best out of what they have and, eventually, develop strategies to improve those buildings over time.  That is the point I wanted to make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01000"><p>I thank both our guests for their presentations.  The case they have made makes absolute sense.  Sometimes straightforward, common-sense things are overlooked and a more complicated approach to things is taken.  It is incredible that, after 15 months of a pandemic, Mr. Jones still has to tell us that we need to get down to basics.  One has to ask why we have not been dealing with those basics up to now.</p> <p>  I have a question for Mr. Jones.  With regard to the expert advisory group on which both of our guests serve, given the level of expertise within that group, has it produced-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.154" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01100"><p>I am sorry.  There was a bleep and I missed the last words of the Deputy's question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01200"><p>I asked whether the expert group has produced a report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.156" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01300"><p>Yes, we have produced two reports so far.  The first outlined the details of the actions of the expert group.  The second looked in more detail at the best advice available at the moment.  A point which has been made here a couple of times is that good advice is already available right across the sector.  We have seen such advice from American Society of Heating, Refrigerating and Air-Conditioning Engineers, ASHRAE, from the Chartered Institution of Building Services Engineers, CIBSE, and from the Federation of European Heating, Ventilation and Air Conditioning Associations, REHVA.  Many international organisations are already producing very good advice.  From a solutions perspective, the expert group is not reinventing the wheel.  A lot of that information is already available.  That is being reported.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01400"><p>I have been interested in ventilation for some time but I also listen very carefully to the public health advice given at a political level or by NPHET.  One rarely hears ventilation being mentioned.  I am curious as to why that is the case.  Has the group made recommendations in the reports it has produced?  To whom did those reports go?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.158" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01500"><p>To answer the first part of the Deputy's question, people's awareness of ventilation and the discussion of ventilation have always been problems.  It is an invisible thing, a natural thing we do every second of the day without thinking about it.  Even getting people to be cognisant of the air we breathe is very difficult indeed.  This pandemic has certainly brought that into focus but issues of indoor air quality and poor health are slow burners.  They are not as dramatic as the pandemic so we do not see it.  I apologise; what was the second part of the Deputy's question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01600"><p>Did the group make recommendations and to whom did any such recommendations go?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.160" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01700"><p>Yes, we did make some recommendations.  Most of them are in line with the Health Protection Surveillance Centre, HPSC, documents and other advice that was out there.  The advice in the first two reports went to NPHET.  It sat with NPHET.  Since then, we have reported to the civil servant group.  We have moved away from reports and towards letters to the civil servant group.  These letters are more specific to given sectors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01800"><p>It is my understanding that neither of the reports and none of those letters have been published.  Is that the case?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.162" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F01900"><p>Yes, that is correct.  It is my understanding that he HSE plans to publish the first two reports of the expert group.  I also understand that the sector-specific reports or letters to the civil servant group are not to be reported anywhere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F02000"><p>Perhaps this committee can play a role in getting access to those letters and recommendations and publishing them.  It seems crazy to have an expert group looking at this area, making recommendations and advising the Government when no one is hearing about it.  That just does not make any sense at all.  It is something the committee should take up.</p> <p>  I am very short on time.  May I ask Ms Hegarty what are the short-term immediate solutions for household ventilation?  She said that one can deal with 50% of the problem by improving airflow.  With regard to improving air filtration, what kind of costs are we talking about in this regard in either a domestic setting, a school setting or a small business?  I am thinking of the hairdressers and retail outlets opening up this week or last week.  What are they doing about that?  Have they had any direction or guidance from any State agency as regards what they should do about ventilation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.164" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#F02100"><p>As I understand it, the work safety protocol was reissued last week.  This does mention ventilation.  I have been reading quite a lot of sectoral guidance since May of last year when the construction industry produced its first set of advice.  These documents come across as official guidance and people in the sector are taking them as official because they have yellow covers and an official <i>imprimatur</i>.  They are often highly inconsistent and unscientific however.  Other than the work safety protocol, I do not know of any clear advice for anybody opening a shop or small business.  I believe many people mean well but are not doing the right things.  In some cases, they may be making the situation worse.  It is really important that a clear message goes out.<br/><br/>With regard to households, again I suspect that a lot of infection was happening in cars, as well as in homes.  When people are told not to meet or that two households can meet together, the risk does not relate to whether two or three households are involved but to the air conditions in the room.</p><p>It is the equivalent of inviting a smoker into one's home.  How would someone deal with that situation?  How would it be worse if there were ten people in the room and two of them were smoking?  People must understand the logic of that.  It can be very dangerous in a car with two people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1567" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00200"><p>Why is Dr. Hegarty's advice falling on deaf ears on the part of NPHET and the Government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00300"><p>There has been a resistance to understanding how the virus transmits by aerosol.  There has been a strong belief in some quarters that this is not how it transmits but the science now tells us otherwise.  Second, there has been no joined-up thinking between the expert groups in that they operate independently and do not collaborate so people in different disciplines use different terminology and possibly have mistaken beliefs sometimes.  I have come across people who assume that improving ventilation means that we put engineering and equipment into every building and that this is not feasible.  That is not what this is about.</p> <p>  The word "ventilation" has been seen as another add-on beyond distancing, masks and hand washing instead of being seen as core to everything.  Thinking of it as ventilation, it has not translated into "this is about how we use buildings."  It is much more than ventilation.  It is about how people move around in buildings, how many people are in the building, how long they stay for, whether they are wearing masks and whether they are more vulnerable.  A targeted approach that picks out the really high-risk areas would be much more effective than a lockdown.  It would involve an incremental approach involving prevention, particularly schools, childcare, nursing homes and indoor dining and hospitality, over the next few months while the weather is good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1559" speakername="Neasa Hourigan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00400"><p>I will concentrate on how we arrive at the building standards we have and implement, and how we implement and enforce them.  We are talking about quite a broad spectrum of typologies.  Things like hepa filtration and single-room occupancy have been issues in hospital settings for at least a decade.  Businesses and schools are a different consideration than homes.  I know there has been some research in Ireland on the very poor ventilation quality in our homes.  While this may not necessarily speak to Covid transmission, it certainly speaks to the level of asthma we have.</p> <p>  Regarding how we arrive at our building standards, the original Building Control Act provided for a Building Regulations Advisory Board where experts would have joined together to advise the Department about what is appropriate.  That seems to have been disbanded.  Do the witnesses think a mechanism like that would have been useful in the past year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00500"><p>The Building Regulations Advisory Board is there in statute.  It was disbanded in about 2012 and has not been in operation since.  This is a major failing because individual buildings are being reviewed in isolation when they are all connected.  In the case of the new build-to-rent apartment standards, I do not believe there was due consideration of the impact of taking out cross ventilation, lowering ceiling heights so there was less volume, making spaces smaller and removing lobbies to corridors so that there was more of a risk, as we have seen in buildings with long corridors such as the quarantine hotels in Australia, of pressure build up in rooms with long corridors where there are heavy fire doors and one gets airflow conditions that cannot be predicted.  This has caused cross contamination in quarantine hotels in Australia.  Daylight standards have been reduced, balconies have been taken out, which means it is difficult to purge ventilate a room, and more people are sharing lifts than is probably appropriate for public health.  An independent building regulation advisory board that works openly and transparently with a lot of high-level expertise would be very helpful because often a change is made in one area without recognition of the impact and these things are all connected through architecture, be they climate change, the pandemic, cost saving or daylight.  The lack of an open board or possibly a mechanism for those kinds of discussions has been detrimental.  It would be good to see that resumed.</p> <p>  To answer the question about ventilation, we have had improving energy performance requirements over the past ten or 15 years driven by the energy performance and buildings directive from Europe but the ventilation standards have been very slow to catch up in parallel with that.  Ironically, some of our newer buildings that are more airtight may be higher risk for Covid than some of our older buildings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.170" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00600"><p>It is worth making the point that this is a problem across Europe and that at a European level, they are trying to look towards the independent inspection of standard ventilation systems in homes.  Ireland is leading the way here.  In our latest revision of building regulations under Part F, we need an independent validator or inspector of ventilation systems in all new homes.  That is to be applauded.  We are the first country in Europe to go that far in saying that all new buildings need to be inspected by somebody independent.  This is definitely to be welcomed.  Unfortunately, this falls down a bit because the t's and i's have not been crossed and dotted and there is no central database where that information is held and can be audited.  As of today, we do not know how many homes have been inspected and we certainly do not know how many of them have passed or failed.  The devil is in the detail with that kind of stuff that really adds power to those regulations.  In some ways, our ventilation regulations are pretty good and are certainly in line with many other countries.  What is key is inspection, policing and making sure the supply chain is delivering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1559" speakername="Neasa Hourigan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00700"><p>That brings me on to my next question because as the witnesses know, there was a commitment in the Safe As Houses report and the programme for Government to end the self certification of buildings in general, which would improve the situation greatly.</p> <p>  I wish to address the construction products regulations declaration of performance.  We have talked about ventilation systems.  I know a lot of the discussion is about simply opening windows and making people aware.  We will be dealing with more and more mechanical items, particularly in newer buildings where there is an airtightness requirement.  As far as I am aware, there has never been a conviction for proprietary building materials that are incorrect or badly certified.  Is that a concern?  I think Ms Hegarty mentioned that there are products on the market that are not fully compliant or do what they say on the tin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.172" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#G00800"><p>My concern is that there is confusion.  What I have spoken about here is hepa filtration - a very basic fan and filter that people can run very safely just drawing the air through it while they are in a room, be it a cr&egrave;che or bedroom.  This is advisable everywhere and could be a good solution for many buildings and businesses.  Other systems are available.  There are very specialist systems to do with UV light, which may have some specialist installations and are sometimes used in hospitals and other specialist locations, that may have applications in other buildings here but require specialist independent advice and installation.  There are other systems on sale in Ireland that use light, ionisation and other systems that have not been regulated for this purpose and may not be effective.  Some systems produce by-products like ozone, which is damaging to the lungs.  People are selling systems that do this.  They are also selling systems that operate when the room is empty, which is of limited use.</p><p>If you are going to bring people into a restaurant for the evening, for example, using these systems before people arrive is of very limited benefit.  Airing the place well before people arrive and having filtration around the room would be very effective and safe.  Using some kind of other system may be an expensive option and may not be effective.  It is important that advice coming from the Government be very clear so that people who are struggling in their businesses and well intended are given good advice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1565" speakername="Gino Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00200"><p>I thank Ms Hegarty and Mr. Jones for this fascinating debate on ventilation.  How long does Ms Hegarty think we will be wearing masks in settings, particularly public transport and workplaces?  The guidelines for the lockdown will be eased in time but could we still be wearing masks on public transport in a couple of years' time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.175" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00300"><p>I do not know that it is possible to answer that because there are a lot of unknowns with this disease and there are a lot of unknowns over the next few months, especially with variants.  We need to be very cautious opening, in risk assessment terms, with a small percentage of the population vaccinated.</p> <p>  Masks are by far the best protection we have.  The highest risk is close to somebody who is infected.  Another strange characteristic of this disease is that most of the people who get infected are infected by somebody who does not know that they are ill.  You are infected by somebody who is either pre-symptomatic or asymptomatic.  He or she is not showing symptoms.  That is why it has been so difficult to tackle this disease around the world.  Other illnesses may have something that demonstrates symptoms and people stay at home, but not with this one.</p> <p>  Masks are by far our best defence because they do two things.  They stop somebody who may be infected putting virus into the air and they protect the other person who is breathing.  They are also cheap, low-tech, manageable and visible.  Unlike some other places where they are removing mask restrictions, we should be very careful about rowing back on that because people have been very compliant here with wearing masks.  Wearing masks might be more of an issue in specialist settings.  Clearly, people in Asia wearing masks on public transport as a matter of course has been very effective.</p> <p>  Somebody asked about entertainment and hospitality.  A trial was run at a concert in Germany last summer where people were put in very good quality masks and very good ventilation was put in the building.  They found they were both effective mitigation measures for a large crowd gathering for a concert.  Some of this may come down to what mitigation measures people are willing to accept to have more social contact.  There is a balance here rather than going back to the way things were.  It is about adapting to things that will work so that we can have social and economic activity, in the main, by targeting specific areas and accepting mitigation measures that are effective but yet allow us to do most of what we want to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1565" speakername="Gino Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00400"><p>On supermarkets in particular, because they were one of the retail settings that happened to close during the pandemic, and shopping centres have been closed to a lesser degree, how well ventilated are supermarkets and shopping centres? There are certain shopping centres - I am not going to name the company - that do not have any windows whatsoever.  How well-ventilated and safe are these places, particularly if people congregate there?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.177" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00500"><p>We do not know in the absence of data.  I did some spot checks in supermarkets using a CO2 monitor and, with a little bit of effort, most of them would be relatively safe.  Some of the concerns about people being infected in supermarkets is because the people are not going anywhere else, but that does not mean that they were not in another unsafe setting, maybe on transport or in their own home, that they did not realise was unsafe.</p> <p>  In terms of workers in supermarkets, I would have a concern that in some places people are still working behind Perspex, which is not safe, and that they are sharing break rooms and toilets where they are not aware of the dangers of spread caused by just going on a break with another staff member or going to changing rooms.  We notice very clearly a classroom or a supermarket and less so the back areas of locker rooms, staffrooms, toilets, lifts and corridors where the risk might actually be because there are pockets of dead air, somebody has passed through earlier and somebody comes through later and moves into the same space.  We need a more joined-up approach more broadly than just the supermarket.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.178" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00600"><p>Large city centre buildings, shopping centres and supermarkets are highly engineered environments.  The relative safety or not of those environments should be quite easily determinable because they have big mechanical ventilation systems where you can set how much fresh air those buildings get.  If they are not capable of delivering that, then that is an engineering problem but it should be a determinable risk.  I would be confident if they were inspected and those involved worked with the available advice that is out there, those buildings should be able to be made relatively safe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1565" speakername="Gino Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00700"><p>My last question is on Ms Hegarty's statement where she said concerning the number of deaths that people "were infected in fewer than 0.03% of all buildings", which equated to 667 buildings.  As we know, half of the deaths that took place in the South of Ireland were in nursing homes.  How much of a factor was the lack of ventilation in residential nursing settings?  How can we remedy the situation in the future?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.180" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#H00800"><p>We do not have records on the air quality in any of these buildings at any given time.  All we can do is look at the patterns of spread, the speed of spread and the fact some buildings are much more highly impacted than others.  They are all clues that this virus is airborne and has lingered in the air.  I have also looked pretty closely at some of the other nursing home outbreaks in the Netherlands and especially in Canada and the same patterns are there of very rapid spread.</p> <p>  The conditions in nursing homes are quite particular and this is the reason we have had the problem.  They tend to be underventilated because people are looking to keep warm. The operators are largely private and they look to save money on energy.  Nursing homes are often in converted or subdivided buildings that maybe, when they were changed, ventilation was not considered properly or vents were blocked up.  The people who are there are more vulnerable.</p> <p>  The climate makes a considerable impact.  I did not get into it today but the spread of the initial phase of the pandemic was in very particular climate conditions across North America, Europe, Iran, Wuhan and Japan where the air temperature was between 5&deg; and 11&deg; Celsius outside with low absolute humidity.  There was a very strong pattern to that.  In those particular climate conditions, which would be typical of Ireland in heating season, if you bring that air indoors and heat it to 20&deg; for comfort, it is incredibly dry, and dry low humidity air is connected also with a higher risk of Covid in indoor air conditions.  So you have a perfect storm of overheated buildings, underventilated very dry air, people who are most susceptible and certain buildings.  Unlike in homes where people have showers and there is cooking, which puts moisture in the air, that does not happen in nursing homes.  There is a low occupancy and those activities are not happening close to patients, so you probably had people whose noses and throats dried out, and mucus is a person's first protection against this.  For a whole series of reasons it is quite explainable what happened in nursing homes.  More and more evidence shows, to my mind and certainly from speaking to people working in lots of different disciplines ranging from medicine to physics and chemistry, there is an alignment that plausibly explains why the areas were at risk and, more importantly, how we can prevent it happening again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00100"><p>This is an issue in which I have a special interest because I happen to suffer from a sinus condition.  My sinuses are particularly irritated by dust and particles of all descriptions.  It is of the utmost importance to address the needs identified.  It is necessary to avail of technology in every way possible, particularly in the context of hospital wards, nursing homes, public transport, taxis and cars.  To what extent have the delegates managed to monitor the quality of available technology, whether it involves a backpack-type installation that can be carried around and placed in a room when required or is part of the building?  To what extent do these appliances do what they are supposed to do?  In other words, do they trap all particulate matter, some or 90%?  How effective is the technology?  Does it prevent the spread of viruses such as Covid?  To what extent has it been possible to test this, if such tests have been carried out?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.182" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00200"><p>There is a hierarchy of control in ventilation.  The first phase involves removing the pollutant in the first instance, which requires the replacement of stale air with air that is typically from outdoors.  If that outdoor air is not safe enough, filtered outdoor air is used.  That is the first defence.  The second is when polluted air cannot be removed wholesale from a space.  In that case, recirculation through filtering of the space is the next solution.  This is where we start to talk about HEPA filters, be they portable or part of the building.  Where air is recirculated, the pollutants are passed through effective filters to deal with them.  The next phase is to deactivate the substance one is seeking to prevent from entering.  This is where we start to talk about technology such as UV lights, which can kill viruses.</p> <p>  All these technologies, in the right circumstances and appropriately used, have been able to show complete effectiveness at removing pollutants from spaces but they have to be appropriately specified.  One has to understand what one is trying to achieve with them in the given space.  A good example is HEPA filter recirculation through portable devices.  Those devices can typically remove close to 100% of viruses in a single air pass.  While they are very effective, their ability to be effective in a space depends on how much air they are capable of moving in a given period.  Therefore, they have to be appropriately sized and located in the right spots, and so it goes.  The simple answer to the Deputy's question is that these technologies are capable of dealing with almost every issue we face, be it Covid or another pollutant, in these spaces; the challenge is using them appropriately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00300"><p>Is the measurement in microns?  To what extent has evidence been produced?  Has it been made available to the witnesses?</p> <p>  I am aware that there is an efficacy rate of almost 100%.  To the extent that technology is of the quality required to remove 100% of viruses, it is possible not to have draughts, including for schools, without having draughts.  We all had air conditioning in the form of draughts in our houses 40 or 50 years ago but that has changed over time.  I will outline an experience I had in Europe some years ago.  When I went back to my hotel, I never looked at the air conditioning and went to bed, woke up in the middle of the night gasping for breath, presuming I was suffering from various terminal illnesses that were going to change my life, and almost panicked.  I had to look around in the dark for the switches to turn them on.  I could not believe the difference when the tension went.  It had never happened to me before.  I went back to sleep and everything was rosy and perfect.  As a result of my experience, I realise that there is a need for some kind of standard.  This could apply to aircraft also.  I see no reason in the world why it could not apply with 100% effectiveness.</p> <p>  Depending on the size of the equipment and the size of the building or dwelling in which it is used, it can work with 100% effectiveness and clean the air of viruses, which is the vital issue at this stage.  What essential examination of the devices has taken place?  What evaluation of the cost has taken place?  Could Mr Jones point us in an appropriate direction in addition to having the committee taking it upon itself to talk to the Government and set up a structure that deals with this kind of thing as a matter of urgency?  Incidentally, I am totally supportive of the initiative.  It is a great idea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.184" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00400"><p>It is important to remember that there are no absolutes; nothing is 100% perfect.  Even if a device is capable of removing 99.9% of viruses in a single air pass, its ability to be effective in a space depends on whether it is appropriately sized.  A recent study showed that four or five HEPA filters are needed in a single classroom of a particular size to deliver effective control.  The first port of call should always be fresh air, or fresh outside air.  Another point to remember is that if air is being recirculated, one may be removing particulates and viruses but one is not dealing with other pollutants.  While dealing with one problem, another can build up, such as humidity, VOCs, chemicals in the air, and other pollutants or gases.  That is why I say there is a hierarchy.  We try to deal with ventilation with a view to removing pollutants in the first place, replacing them with fresh outside air.  If that is not enough, we start to look to other technologies.  The challenge is determining when fresh outside air is not enough and there is a need to supplement it.  If organisations such as schools are to invest in HEPA filters, how do they know they are at a point at which they need to do so?  The devices are not cheap for a school.  If a school has 20 or 30 classrooms and two or three HEPA filters are needed per classroom, a big investment will be required.  How does the school know it is in a position to need those types of products?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00500"><p>How big would the investment be for the school, airline company or building?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00600"><p>The Deputy is out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1584" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00700"><p>I will return to the matter at some point.  I did not get an answer on whether measurements are in microns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1519" speakername="Cathal Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#J00800"><p>I am present in Leinster House.  I thank Ms Hegarty and Mr. Jones for attending our meeting this morning.  I have read their statements with interest.  We have had an interesting discussion, yet part of me believes it is one we should have had months ago.  We very much feel we are facing the final furlong of the Covid crisis.  Maybe the witnesses share this view.  Covid will still be here after the crisis but we feel we are in the final stage of getting people vaccinated and restoring normality to the country.  The discussion we are having today would probably have been very much worthwhile last autumn or early last winter when people were more inclined to be indoors and we were facing the peak Covid period.</p> <p>  I have several points for the witnesses.</p><p>Their statements have convinced me.  Ventilation is something I was interested in anyway.  Is some of what they are saying at odds with a policy direction that the Government has pursued in recent years, namely, retrofitting homes and building energy rating, BER, certification?  There is a rush among anyone who wants to sell a house at the moment to get to a C, a B or, better again, an A grade and there are incentives to those building homes to put in mitigating measures such as insulation etc.  One now sees very few homes with chimneys, which traditionally were the source of ventilation in Ireland before the more modern systems, as they created updrafts.  In my house, if the fire is lighting the sitting room door will slam in because of the updraft it creates.  That is not a feature in many Irish homes being built nowadays and it certainly is not a feature in apartments.  I will put that question to Mr. Jones, as it is the kind of technology he deals with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.190" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00200"><p>The answer is quite simple.  Had I been asked that question maybe even five years ago I would have said that yes, many of the practices and policies were at odds with what we are discussing today but I really do not think that is the case now.  Ventilation and indoor environmental quality is very much aligned with the goals of the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, SEAI, and the plan for retrofitting our buildings.  It is a core tenet of it.  Certainly under the deep retrofit programmes carried out, there is quite extensive auditing of ventilation systems.  It was one of the first organisations to take up this independent validating of ventilation systems as part of that programme.  While it may not be perfect, it is certainly moving in the right direction and there is no reason for it to be at odds.  One of the key selling points for improving our building stock is the improvement to the indoor environment.  That is one of the core tenets of the SEAI's approach to selling retrofitting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1519" speakername="Cathal Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00300"><p>I thank Mr. Jones.  I have two questions for Ms Hegarty.  One is on HEPA filtration in aircraft.  There is a debate under way at the moment and we are at the cusp of international air travel resuming.  From everything I have read, HEPA filtration in aircraft claims to be 99.7% effective, yet there is a caveat that it depends on whether the air you are breathing in has actually gone through the filtration system.  If it is from the passenger in front or behind, it is a different story.  Does Ms Hegarty believe international air travel, with its extensive network of HEPA filtration, is safe?</p> <p>  Many pubs in Ireland have massive air filtration systems in their ceilings.  They were probably brought in before the smoking ban.  Many have become obsolete yet they are massive pieces of infrastructure bolted onto the ceilings of pubs which have not been used in many years because of the smoking ban and most places do not using them any more.  Do those systems have a function?  Might they be upgraded or repurposed when pubs reopen so that it will be safe when people are congregating and drinking indoors?  I ask because it will not always be possible for everyone to always be outside, going by what Irish weather is like.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.192" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00400"><p>To finish Deputy Durkan's question first, CO2 is measured at parts per million and 800 is considered to be what we are aiming for.</p> <p>  To comment on schools, one in four of our population goes to school every morning.  They will not be vaccinated for the autumn.  When people speak about a return to normality, one quarter of the population will not have protection and will be vulnerable for the rest of this year.  In my view, whatever money needs to be spent on schools is money well spent because it will keep the rest of society open, as well as keeping education and the economy open.  It is critically important that there be a plan for schools over the summer in order that they can operate comfortably and safely for next winter.  The discussion about population protection with vaccination rates at 80% refers to 80% of adults.  That is, at best, 60% of the population.  Regardless of the vaccination programme over the next number of months, a prevention plan in ventilation is critically needed.  Vaccination on its own will not allow things to reopen; it is mathematically not possible.  </p> <p>  On BER certificates, I completely concur with Mr. Jones on the regulations in place now.  However there is a very weak link in terms of compliance and enforcement because the sector is still left to regulate itself.  This is too important to be left to the sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1519" speakername="Cathal Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00500"><p>Forgive me, we only have one minute on this.  Will Ms Hegarty answer the question about the pubs?  I am sorry to cut across.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.194" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00600"><p>On pubs, that is why we measure it.  Some pubs may have great systems, and let us find out where they are so we can open them.</p> <p>  On aircraft, there has been a lot of different information.  It depends on the age of the plane, the number of people in it and how good the system is.  It seems that some of the risk is when it is parked at the gate, when it is taxiing and when people are getting on through air bridges.  It appears that unsafe air conditions can arise there rather than in mid-flight.  We need more information.  In principle, were people to be wearing good quality masks on aeroplanes and were there independently verified ventilation and filtration, it would be possible to engineer a relatively safe solution if the industry was minded to do that.    </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00700"><p>I thank the witnesses for their attendance and for their fantastic presentations, which were so concise and detailed.  They were fascinating and it something I was not aware of.  I appreciate their highlighting the importance of eliminating infected air with good ventilation.</p> <p>  At this stage of the pandemic, when everyone is exhausted after lockdown and after a long, tough winter, many people seem to have lost hope.  The reopening of society and reconnection with community is incredibly important now but based on what we have heard today, it seems that we as a health committee need to start planning around the implementation of ventilation systems that will operate as we come out of the summer into the winter once again.  This information is extremely important and I totally agree about schools.  It is critical at this point.  We need to focus long and hard on how we will protect young people and children.  In her opening statement, Ms Hegarty rightly stated "Vaccines alone cannot provide enough headroom for reopening", and I fully agree with her in this regard.  </p> <p>  I have a couple of questions and I ask the witnesses to forgive me if I am repeating some of them as I lost the line earlier and could not hear some of the meeting.  To follow up on Deputy Durkan's question on the cost for schools, do the witnesses have any idea about that?  I think it needs to be made a top priority.  What would the witnesses like us, as a committee, to do to support them in the work they are doing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.196" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#K00800"><p>On cost, as a very first measure, for less than &euro;1 million every school could have one CO2 meter that could be moved around.  There are about 4,000 schools so it would be well within that cost.  That would also raise awareness as a first step and identify dead areas and hot spots.  If every classroom needed a monitor, which is probably where we need to move, it would be considerably more because there are probably tens of thousands of classrooms.  There is a balance of identifying risk and areas that need to be watched.  Even with a change of wind direction, conditions in a classroom can go from low to high risk pretty easily, so it needs active monitoring.</p><p>As for filtration, some classrooms are well designed for cross-ventilation and may be relatively low risk, but others may have smaller spaces for special needs education, childcare or early years education where people might not be wearing masks and filtration would be a better option.  The exercise would need to be done on how that money was spent.  Germany is spending a lot of money on this area, as are American schools.</p><p> We do not have as big a challenge as many other places because we have a mild climate and we naturally ventilate our buildings.  In America most of the schools are mechanically ventilated.  We have an easier problem to fix or maybe we have buildings that are more responsive to be able to deal with high-risk situations quickly.  Measuring is part of it.  I do not have an assessment of the cost for every school.  Basic information could probably go a very long way.  </p><p> Regarding supporting the work, I will speak personally because I cannot speak for the group.  It would be very beneficial if there was a forum for multidisciplinary engagement.  As things stand, the people dealing with behavioural science, the people dealing with the medical side, the people calculating the epidemiological projections and the people dealing with ventilation all work in isolation.  There is no sharing of knowledge or information that would help people to refine what they are doing to use the resources more strategically.  </p><p> The key point in all of this is that we do not need to prevent every case to stop a pandemic.  We do not need to deal with every building.  We just need to do enough to get the R-nought below 1.  Very strategic activity in places where people gather in large numbers, on public transport and in particular high-risk settings such as meat plants, could have a very substantial impact overall.  It is not a case of spending money on every building or changing everybody's home.  It is about advising people how to live more safely so that they can make strategic decisions that are safer.  It is the cumulative effort of that, along with targeted measures somewhere else.  It is just a proactive approach, using what we have and using it wisely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.198" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00200"><p>Most of the benefits of improving ventilation and awareness of ventilation fall in the lap of health.  Almost no resources, whether that is time or money, are allocated to improving ventilation and creating awareness of the impacts of ventilation on health.  This does not just apply to the pandemic.  It applies beyond the pandemic to health in general, as I pointed out in my opening statement.  Money spent improving awareness and outcomes through ventilation for this pandemic has other benefits too.  Getting this right will pay us dividends well beyond the pandemic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00300"><p>I believe it would save lives.  The committee might need to consider publishing a report, as we did with the report on vitamin D we produced a few months ago, to highlight the importance of this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1523" speakername="Colm Burke" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00400"><p>I thank both witnesses for their presentations and contributions.  We have many older buildings which are providing vital services.  I am on the board of a hospital that was initially built in 1741.  While it has undergone considerable adaptation, it is still an old building.  Likewise, many of our public facilities are old buildings.  If the witnesses were doing a national plan on this issue, what areas would they prioritise to get the changes that are required for filtration and air ventilation?</p> <p>  Unfortunately, many people contracted Covid in the past year in nursing homes and community hospitals.  What major changes need to be made in those facilities?  Should we set a timeline for each of those facilities to reach the required standard?  What level of investment is required to get that done?  Nursing homes are normally kept very warm and there is not a sense that fresh air is circulating in the place.  Is that an area we should now be prioritising?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.201" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00500"><p>I will answer the questions in reverse order.  Nursing homes, community hospitals, long-term care facilities and that kind of institutional housing, including direct provision and other similar locations, really need to be considered in the same way as schools should be for the autumn.  This is a new disease and vaccination is also new.  The duration of immunity is unknown, particularly in older populations and among people who might have a low response to vaccination.  I would definitely have a concern about nursing homes, care homes and community hospitals.  There could be a further problem in the autumn.  In the same way that schools need to be preparing now, those buildings should be considered as representing an upcoming risk in the autumn.</p> <p>  As Mr. Jones has said, there are international standards that we can plug into if they are adopted.  In particular, we cannot assume that an engineer or an architect will be available to every business and building owner.  People need to be able to pick up and read simple advice to allow them to make careful decisions, whether that is turning off a unit in a hairdressing salon or opening a back door in a shop, restaurant or wherever.  Beyond the technical advice, it is very important that practical guidance is given to people about some of this.  </p> <p>  The Deputy spoke about older buildings.  There are only 86 hospital buildings.  It is well within the resources available to look at each of those buildings and carry out an assessment of where the risk areas are.  The entire building may not have a problem; there may be pockets of risk.  In the short term, simple implementation measures could be made even within days in some cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1523" speakername="Colm Burke" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00600"><p>Is Ms Hegarty saying that because of the way nursing homes and community facilities were constructed, we did not make provision for adequate ventilation?  Does major work now need to be done to those nursing homes, even though many of them are less than 20 years old?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.203" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00700"><p>I do not think we can know without assessing them.  However, the regulations we have are very generalised for natural ventilation.  Even design performance may not reflect the actual performance.  How they perform on paper may not be what happens in reality.  What happens this morning may be compliant, but with a change of wind direction, a very still day, somebody not opening a window or somebody blocking a vent this afternoon, it could become very non-compliant.  It is impossible to say where the problem is.</p> <p>  As we also have a system of self-certification, it is impossible to know who signed off on that building and whether they did a careful assessment, whether they gave good advice to the people who are running the building or whether a subsequent change was made without any professional input, for example, changing doors, adding partitions, doubling up on rooms or something else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1523" speakername="Colm Burke" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00800"><p>Who has responsibility for inspection?  What level of change do we require on inspection of buildings to ensure they are compliant with the regulations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.205" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#L00900"><p>I believe Deputy Hourigan referred to the Safe as Houses report and the very broad concerns about whether our building control system is resourced and fit for purpose.</p><p>The Food Safety Authority of Ireland has strong powers related to food safety, to close businesses if there is a danger to public health, to do inspections and which operates independently with a defined remit.  We do not have anything like that in the building sector.  We have a system whereby owners and developers hire people to sign off on buildings and, in the main, they are not independently verified.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.207" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#M00200"><p>Many of the buildings the Deputy asked about in his opening question are larger public buildings.  They are well managed and covered by the likes of the Office of Public Works, OPW, the Health and Safety Authority, HSA, the HSE, the Department, and HIQA.  They all have structures above them and within them that are capable of resourcing the kind of advice and help that they need.  A colleague of ours in the UK, as part of the Scientific Advisory Group for Emergencies, SAGE, coined the term this week that the success of this summer will come down to three "Vs", namely, vaccines, variants and ventilation.  That is a pertinent point at the moment, in that what will make or break us for the next two quarters will be how successful we are with vaccines, how variants impact on that and how we deal with our buildings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1523" speakername="Colm Burke" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#M00300"><p>Do buildings that are currently being built under current regulations now need to be reviewed to make sure that they can be adapted appropriately?  Is it the case that any building that is under construction should be immediately looked at to put in the adaptations required?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.209" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Simon Jones" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#M00400"><p>All new buildings come under regulations.  We have started to introduce terminology within regulations around matters such as capacity, recognising that it is not okay to just meet minimum requirements for ventilation and that there needs to be some flexibility inherent within buildings.  That is very welcome.  Regulators in the UK are currently revising their ventilation regulations.  They have looked at them again in light of Covid.  We have had a commitment from building standards authorities in Ireland that, in the next revision, they will be cognisant of disease control in regulations for buildings.  The thing to be aware of when talking about regulations is that we are typically talking about flow rate, which is the amount of air moving in buildings.  There is sometimes quite a difference from what we would call background ventilation, to maintain reasonable levels of general air quality, and the volumes of air that we are looking to move to limit risks of infection.  We need to be in a space where our buildings are capable of doing both.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.210" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#M00500"><p>It is broader than building regulations, which are to do with measuring the air flow and volume of air.  We need to look at our apartment and hotel regulations, as well as at other settings.  I have particular concern about the reduced standards for apartment sizes that were brought in about three years ago, which do not have cross-ventilation or balconies and have up to 20% less volume of air than they would have had previously.  We need to be concerned about the deregulation of standards.  It merits a review in light of the pandemic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#M00600"><p>I have a couple of questions and comments myself.  Ms Hegarty spoke about how Chicago suppressed the 1918 pandemic with targeted measures, including building inspectors who signed off on ventilation as a condition of trading, and the city reopened within six weeks.  Here we are 100 years later and we are almost starting again, going by some of the evidence that was given today.  There was some mention of the situation in Australia.  We are aware of the strict quarantines involved there.  Regarding the Irish quarantine, I am conscious that we are taking away people's liberties because of the health concerns.  Are the witnesses aware of particular criteria, especially related to ventilation, in some of the hotels selected so far?  Has that come into consideration when a hotel is assessed?  We have all stayed in hotels where, for instance, the windows did not open, so one relied primarily on the air conditioning and so on.  Are the witnesses aware of that as an issue?  Regarding the strict approach taken in Australia, the witnesses have mentioned the fire doors, and how that trapped the air within that corridor.  Do the witnesses have any recommendations for that?</p> <p>  I do not know what the witnesses' experience of most aeroplanes is, but many of them are fairly dirty, and filthy in some cases.  It is a while since I have been on a plane.  After getting off a plane, you usually have a cold or something else a couple of days later.  It is down to people sneezing or coughing on the planes and down to the ventilation systems.  The witnesses said there had to be an independent verification system.  Maybe they will expand on that.</p> <p>  The figures at the start of Ms Hegarty's opening statement state that half of the people who died were infected in 0.3% of the buildings.  Over half of workplace outbreaks have been in just 150 buildings.  One in four school buildings have been affected.  It has been mentioned that we are at the end of the road with Covid.  I do not think so if we are talking about one in four school buildings having a Covid-19 index case in the last four months.  Would the witnesses accept that we need to be much more targeted, especially in those 150 buildings?  I imagine that if I knew where those 150 buildings were, I would be a bit wary of going in and out of them.  I presume some are hospitals and nursing homes.  Do the witnesses think it would be helpful for people to be able to make those judgments?  Do they think there should be some sort of targeted intervention now, at this stage, when we are rolling out the vaccine?  I do not think this is going away any time soon and we may face another wave.  If we have buildings where there is a particular problem, should there be some sort of focus on those buildings?</p> <p>  The witnesses mentioned the schools.  It makes sense to have some sort of supports for those schools from the Department, especially where there is overcrowding in the classroom and for the old buildings.  Do the witnesses have recommendations for some sort of fund for schools?  They mentioned the carbon dioxide meter.  Is that a minimum that they are saying should be introduced in schools?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.212" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#M00700"><p>Carbon dioxide monitoring in schools is a cheap, quick, easy way, and would pay for itself with energy savings because people will not have to overventilate and sit in the cold.  They will be able to ventilate adequately for the risk, so they will save on heating bills.  The Chairman mentioned testing in Chicago.  I recently noticed that San Francisco has posters in windows of business premises where they have had an independent inspection.  Somebody has come out and given advice.  It is not just about inspecting the building but about public confidence to go back to enter those businesses again.  They have posters in the windows to state that the building was inspected on a certain date, which system they are using, or if the door has to be open, the filter has to be on, or whatever the requirements are.  There is really good public health information.</p> <p>  Regarding the quarantine hotels, we have a lot of information from Australia and New Zealand about risk factors there, very strongly indicating that traditional hotels with rooms off long corridors with air conditioning are a bad idea for disease spread.  It is not a minor risk.  The outbreak in Victoria was purely down to a hotel breach and 800 people died as a result of that breach.  Perth recently had a five-day shutdown following a hotel quarantine breach.</p><p>They are now looking more broadly at non-city centre locations akin to low-rise buildings or even caravan parks, that type of setting, for their permanent quarantine facilities in Australia.  It also means one takes away the risk of city centre staff members living in overcrowded conditions themselves whereby outbreaks can spread or who perhaps have a second job or use public transport.  Outside city locations seem to be better, as do hotels with opening windows and not air-conditioned hotels.  It is getting away from that corridor model.  We have plenty of advice from Australia that could be adopted here from what they have learned.  Can the Chair remind me of the final point? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#N00200"><p>It was on aeroplanes and the point you made about the verification there as well.  Is there something more that can be done?  Again, there is a fear that as soon as people get the green light, a lot of them will jump on planes to get some sunshine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.215" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Orla Hegarty" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#N00300"><p>There are serious concerns about aircraft because obviously one can open a window on a bus but on a plane, one cannot.  It comes down to the operation of that individual aircraft.  Is it serious enough that there needs to be independent monitoring?  I suppose that is a political decision.  Data would help in all of this.  The HSE is gathering data from every outbreak.  They know which schools, cr&egrave;ches and hospitals have had outbreaks but those data are not available.  Anything I have quoted today is from publicly available sources.  I do not have access to any more but there is a lot more available.  I think we have to start using those data, rather than having them in a filing cabinet somewhere.  That is how risk assessment could be done and how targeted interventions could be done.  They have data about cases related to travel, quarantine, hotels, schools, childcare facilities and nursing homes.  If it is a case of inspecting buildings, clearly that is an indication of where to start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1571" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2021051900002#N00400"><p>The committee appreciates the witnesses' coming in this morning.  We certainly will look for the reports mentioned in the witness statements.  It would be useful for the committee to get copies of those reports.  The suggestion that we try to produce a report on this issue is useful.  If there is anything else that the witnesses feel they have not had a chance to expand on this morning, we would appreciate it were they to send it in writing to the committee.  It was a useful intervention this morning.  A lot of information was provided that hopefully people will take on board in their own lives, particularly those at home.  There is a responsibility on school authorities and the Department of Education to follow up on some of the statements made this morning.</p> <p>  That concludes our business for today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-05-19a.217" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 11.33 a.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 26 May 2021.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>