<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Transport, Tourism and Sport</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 12:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Ruth Coppinger, Senator Mark Daly, Deputy Imelda Munster, Senator Frank Feighan, Deputy Catherine Murphy, Senator John O'Mahony, Deputy Kevin O'Keeffe, Senator Pádraig Ó Céidigh. Deputy Noel Rock, Deputy Robert Troy,</p><p>In attendance: Deputies Michael Harty, Michael Healy-Rae and Jonathan O'Brien</p><p>DEPUTY FERGUS O'DOWD IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Attendance list to be confirmed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.5" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#B00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#B00200"><p>Before we commence, I remind members to turn off their mobile phones as they interfere with the recording equipment.  I propose we now got into private session.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.7" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 12.39 p.m. and resumed in public session at 1.39 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.8" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#O00100">Governance and Funding of Football Association of Ireland: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#O00200"><p>Before we commence, I again remind members to turn off their mobile phones as they interfere with the recording equipment.</p><p>The purpose of today's meeting is to consider all issues related to governance of, and funding to, the Football Association of Ireland, FAI.  I welcome the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, the Minister of State, Deputy Brendan Griffin, and officials from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport: Mr. Kenneth Spratt, assistant secretary, Mr. Peter Hogan, principal officer, and Ms Betty Griffin, assistant principal officer.  From Sport Ireland, I welcome Mr. John Treacy, chief executive, Mr. Kieran Mulvey, chairman, Ms Mary Dorgan, chair of the audit and risk committee and board member, and Mr. Colm McGinty, director of strategic programmes.<br/><br/>I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  <br/><br/>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/><br/>The Minister, Minister of State and Mr. John Treacy will make opening statements, and after that there will be a period of questions and answers of ten minutes for each member.  I will tell members when nine minutes have elapsed.  I presume because we are taking the Minister, his Department and Sport Ireland together, that members will direct their questions at whomever the appropriate person is.  The interaction will then take place.  I call the Minister to make his opening presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#P00200"><p>I am joined today by the Minister of State, Deputy Brendan Griffin, who will also make an opening statement.  I thank the committee for its tireless work on this matter and for the light it has shone on serious issues within the FAI.  Investigative journalists have also played a commendable role, particularly Mark Tighe, whom I wish to thank.  I apologise to the committee for failing to provide my opening statement in advance as requested.  As I am sure members will appreciate, this has been a very fluid situation, including significant developments as late as this morning, which would have overtaken any script provided earlier.</p> <p>  I regret that there has been a cloud over Irish sport, especially Irish soccer, since 17 March, St. Patrick's Day, when news broke about the loan of &euro;100,000 to the FAI by its then chief executive, John Delaney.  On 19 March, we wrote to Sport Ireland, directing it to engage with the FAI to clarify matters of concern.  Since then, there has been intensive activity between the FAI, Sport Ireland and my Department.  The decision of the board of Sport Ireland to withhold and suspend funding to the FAI was an extraordinary moment for Irish sport.  I do not have to remind the committee of the scale and reach of the FAI.  This is an organisation with more than 200 employees, and an annual turnover of close to &euro;60 million.  It is also an organisation with several thousand clubs, the national governing body, NGB, for the most popular team sport in Ireland by participation rate.  While it may not be among our native sports, soccer is a sport which is at the heart of Irish life and culture.</p> <p>  It would be remiss of me not to mention the importance of due process and natural justice when dealing with these matters.  While members of the committee are unfettered, the response by the officials of my Department, Sport Ireland, the Minister of State, and by me must be considered and appropriate.  Having said that, I watched the FAI's engagement with the committee and I have monitored developments since then.  Last week's appearance and events over the weekend have been very disappointing.  Yesterday's announcement that the former CEO had voluntarily stepped aside pending an independent investigation fell far short of expectations.</p><p>While it is the case that due process is hugely important, the committee will not be surprised that I have become increasingly concerned with these developments.  Here we have a clear case of the FAI admitting it failed to abide by the conditions for receipt of State funding.  We had a shambolic appearance by the FAI at this committee last week at which even the most basic questions, for whatever reasons, went unanswered.  Concerns remain around a financial transaction, basic levels of corporate governance, the creation of the new executive vice president role, issues of a substantial nature being considered by the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement and other developments which would suggest that all is far from well.<br/><br/>The Minister of State, Deputy Griffin, and I have made our serious concerns known.  We have impressed upon Sport Ireland the need for root and branch reform of corporate governance.  Over the weekend, I also spoke publicly about the need for strong corporate governance as a precondition for ongoing State funding, including capital works.  As late as last night, we reiterated to Sport Ireland the need for regime change.<br/><br/>As a result of the ongoing pressure, I am pleased to confirm to the committee that in the past few hours, the FAI has written to me, indicating decisive action is being taken.  I will now read the FAI&rsquo;s letter into the record of the meeting:</p><blockquote>Dear Minister,<br /><br />I would like to first of all apologise to you and your colleagues for any embarrassment caused through the association&rsquo;s engagement with the Oireachtas committee in relation to recent controversies.  I can assure you no disrespect was intended by me or the association in relation to our engagement at the committee.  Whilst I am acutely aware that our &ldquo;response&rdquo; to date has caused considerable frustration and has not appeased public demands for action, I have a responsibility to ensure that we act legally and follow due process in relation to both employment matters and our engagement with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement.<br /><br />Since the controversies first arose, the board of the association formed a sub-committee to progress all issues involved and this sub-committee has been working hard to try to ensure all matters are fully investigated and that progress is made.  The need to reform governance structures is recognised and it is intended that we will put in place both structures and processes that meet best practice from both a corporate and sporting body perspective.  We have already taken significant action in this regard.<br /><br />We have commissioned Mazars to undertake an in-depth review of all the matters of concern.  This is a fully independent exercise which will be carried out to the highest professional standards and will be forensic in its approach.  We are pursuing all steps, with legal advice, in relation to ensuring that all matters that arise from this review are actioned as appropriate.<br /><br />The processes that have been put in place are significant and will have far-reaching effect.  They will, of necessity, however, take some time, having due regard to the need for detailed examination and to respect the rights of all individuals who may be involved.<br /><br />In relation to the board structure, we have engaged with Sport Ireland in relation to both the membership of and terms of reference for a new governance group which will, among other issues, bring forward proposals for the restructuring of the board and other governance requirements.<br /><br />We have asked that this group commence work immediately and bring forward recommendations as speedily as possible.  It is our intention that recommendations in relation to restructuring the board will be brought to the membership for their consideration and adoption at our annual general meeting in July (or at an extraordinary general meeting, if the work of the group facilitates an earlier date).  At that point, when a new structure has been put in place, it is the intention that the existing board will step down to allow for a new board to be constituted in the best interests of football.<br /><br />It is our considered view that it is imperative that the board would be allowed to facilitate the management of these processes to conclusion and this will address, in a very real way, all of the concerns that have been raised in recent weeks.  It also provides that this resolution is managed in conformity with UEFA and FIFA statutes regarding governance.<br /><br />In the interest of all players, coaches, volunteers, fans, employees, sponsors and Government stakeholders, we are utterly committed to ensuring that the FAI moves to a position where trust and confidence is restored.  I hope that this letter will provide some assurance in that regard.<br /><br />Yours sincerely,<br /><br />Donal Conway,<br /><br />President [of the FAI]</blockquote><p> I welcome the fact that the Football Association of Ireland is engaging with Sport Ireland in a process and that they have now indicated that the board will step down.  I believe that an emergency general meeting should be called before the July date as soon as the active investigations have been concluded to facilitate a transition to a new board by way of transparent elections.  Given the ever growing lack of public confidence in the FAI, this move is to be welcomed and it is hopefully the first step on the road to rebuilding trust in this important national governing body of sport.</p><p> Considering the issues over which most of this board has presided, and the fact of those issues being obvious even before the various investigations have started, it is clearly time for a regime change.  As regards Government funding, I welcome the swift and decisive action of the board of Sport Ireland to suspend and withhold the funding.  I can add that there will be no further Government funding for the FAI until we see real change and reform in the association's corporate governance and until we have received credible answers.  With regard to future allocations under the sports capital programme and the large scale sport infrastructure fund, I will be closely monitoring developments on corporate governance and the conditions that must be met before Sport Ireland's funding to the association is reinstated.  In this regard, no new capital payments will be made by my Department to the FAI until I am satisfied with the new measures put in place.</p><p> I am pleased that the FAI will work with Mazars to overhaul the association's governance.  It is well known that I have great difficulty with organisations conducting internal reviews and investigations so I welcome the invitation by the FAI to Sport Ireland to input to the terms of reference of the Mazars exercise.  I trust that the FAI will continue to liaise with Sport Ireland throughout this challenging process and in implementing any changes recommended therein.</p><p> As Minister, I have responsibility for a considerable number of appointments to State boards and I am well aware of the importance of appointing individuals with a broad range of skills and experience, especially financial and legal expertise in this context.  The FAI should take meaningful steps to improve the process for the election of its board and implement any recommendations with regard to the appointment of independent directors.</p><p> As we have heard, Irish football includes a broad range of stakeholders extending far beyond the FAI headquarters at the National Sports Campus.  On the new board it would be appropriate to include representatives of the players - male and female - supporters, coaches, volunteers and leagues.</p><p> It has been abundantly clear in recent weeks that there is an immense frustration throughout grassroots soccer in Ireland.  We have seen protests at recent international matches and at League of Ireland fixtures.  Every committee member has received a vast number of letters and emails from volunteers and supporters across the country who are furious with the leadership of the association and the way it has responded to the recent controversy.  Many have highlighted other issues that are important for the future of soccer in Ireland, such as youth development, participation of women and girls as well as the challenges faced by League of Ireland clubs.  It is now time to convene a stakeholders' forum to allow representatives from every level of football in Ireland, including the international teams, the schoolboy leagues, the local community clubs and those playing in the League of Ireland Premier Division, to come together to shape the future for their association and their sport.  This is quite the crisis for the FAI but it is also an opportunity to develop an inclusive vision for the development of soccer in Ireland.  The Minister of State with responsibility for sport, Deputy Griffin, and I will facilitate that long overdue conversation.  I would welcome the committee's observations and any questions committee members have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#R00200"><p>Thank you, Minister.  Before I call the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Brendan Griffin, I think it is appropriate that I would welcome the regime change in the FAI to which you referred in your letter.  It is important.  It is also important that the Minister would hold a stakeholders' forum that is as broad and as representative as possible to ensure what everyone wants, which is the best soccer teams at local, regional, national and international level that we can possibly have.</p><p>That is very positive news.  I invite the Minister of State, Deputy Griffin, to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1318" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#S00200"><p>I am a long-standing supporter of Irish soccer and of the teams that have represented our country on the world stage.  The current situation is extraordinary.  There has been friction for a long time in the Football Association of Ireland and many have been critical of the association's leadership.  The League of Ireland has had particular challenges and there have been calls for more investment from the association and more support for clubs and players.  At the same time, great progress has been made in respect of grassroots soccer.  The inclusive nature of Irish soccer is remarkable, with teams and competitions for all regardless of gender, level of ability, ethnicity, socioeconomic background or age.  I have been greatly impressed by the ambition of the FAI to hold international competitions, including next year's UEFA Euro 2020 games at the Aviva Stadium.</p><p>As the Minister said, the questions being asked by members of this committee and Sport Ireland are being asked by soccer supporters throughout the country.  We understand that individuals are entitled to be treated fairly and to due process.  Nobody wishes to see a trial by media of people who have worked hard for their sport over many years.  However, I am incredibly disappointed by the lack of answers from the FAI.  As the members will be aware, those of us elected to D&aacute;il and Seanad &Eacute;ireann have a responsibility to the people of Ireland to ensure that public funds are used wisely and carefully to deliver real outcomes across all programmes.  When discussing an organisation such as the FAI, whose public funding represents a modest proportion of its total income, there are limits to what we can do.  I share the frustration of members of the committee.  Nobody who witnessed last Wednesday's meeting with the representatives of the FAI could feel differently.  </p><p>There is an obligation on the Government to use any levers of influence it has to ensure that the FAI provides Sport Ireland, its members and all supporters of Irish soccer with a full explanation of the circumstances of the 2017 loan and with assurances that failures in oversight and governance have been addressed.  The Department's sports capital programme is one such lever.  The vast majority of capital grants go directly to sports clubs and organisations throughout the country.  There is no suggestion that we would penalise local soccer clubs for issues in their national association.  However, national governing bodies of sport may also apply and the FAI has been directly allocated a total of &euro;130,000 under the programme since 2016.  All payments under the sports capital programme are made retrospectively following receipt of, <i>inter alia</i>, proof of payment of the relevant invoices and a signed certificate of compliance with the terms and conditions of the programme.</p><p>The national sports policy, which we published last July, provided for a large scale sport infrastructure fund, LSSIF, with at least &euro;100 million available over the coming years.  The fund was launched in November 2018 and closes for applications tomorrow.  It is confined to national governing bodies of sport and local authorities, all of which received letters inviting them to make applications.  The new fund has generated great interest and I expect it will take a number of months to have all applications assessed by our officials and recommendations made on allocations.  As the Minister indicated, no new capital payments will be made by our Department to the FAI until we are satisfied that it has given us a full and complete account of the 2017 loan, we have seen the outcome of the governance review, meaningful change has been implemented on the basis of the findings of that review and until all other relevant conditions have been complied with.  The sports capital programmes are a very important resource for the Irish sporting sector and I am sure this will also be true of the new large scale sport infrastructure fund.  In the interests of fairness to all applicants we must insist that the FAI addresses these serious concerns before any payments to that organisation can be considered.</p><p>Finally, I remind the FAI and its board that there are further risks for the association if it fails to address satisfactorily the questions and concerns which have been outlined.  If we conclude after a due process that there are lingering doubts about governance and that appropriate recommendations for improvement are not being implemented, the risks for the FAI would be considerable.  As matters stand, the FAI board has problems and it has time to address them.  I hope it uses that time wisely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#S00300"><p>I will shortly ask Mr. John Treacy, chief executive of Sport Ireland, to make his opening statement.</p><p>The people outside these Houses might not be aware that it has come to our notice that proper books of accounts are not being kept by the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, and that form H4 was filed in the Companies Registration Office yesterday with an effective date of 12 April.  That will inform people watching or listening to these proceedings of exactly what is going on.  I ask Mr. John Treacy to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#T00200"><p>I thank the Chairman.  I am joined today by my colleagues, Kieran Mulvey, chairman, Mary Dorgan, who is chair of our audit and risk committee, and Colm McGinty, director of strategic programmes.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland appeared before this committee on Wednesday, 3 April, where we gave a comprehensive account of our dealings with the Football Association of Ireland, including our funding to the organisation and the control mechanisms and management arrangements relating to this grant funding.  Today, we will take the opportunity to provide the committee with an update on developments since Sport Ireland last appeared, including the significant decision of the board of Sport Ireland to suspend and withhold funding to the FAI.</p> <p>  Before continuing, I would like to give Sport Ireland's view on the meeting of the committee with representatives of the FAI on Tuesday last.  Sport Ireland had the expectation that the FAI would engage with this committee in an open and transparent manner on all relevant issues and answer the committee's key questions as directly and straightforwardly as possible.  The FAI delegation chose not to answer important questions, which was extremely disappointing.  Nevertheless, through the committee hearing, Sport Ireland learned some information that we did not previously know from correspondence and meetings with the FAI.  This new information gives an insight into the corporate governance practices in operation within the FAI.</p> <p>  We now understand the following.  Not only was Sport Ireland not notified of a material deterioration in the FAI financial position in 2017, it appears that the board of the FAI was similarly not notified.  That such a serious financial situation existed and was not reported to the FAI board is concerning from an internal financial control and general governance perspective.</p> <p>  The events of 2017, as described by the FAI, give rise to serious concerns on the FAI board's application of its governance and oversight role as required under Sport Ireland's terms and conditions of grant approval.  As a State body that invests substantial funds in the FAI, Sport Ireland is also very concerned about the FAI's adherence to appropriate internal financial and management control procedures during this period.</p> <p>  Following the meeting of 3 April of this committee, Sport Ireland again wrote to the president of the FAI on 4 April seeking a response on behalf of the board of the FAI.  A copy of this letter has been provided to the committee.  On the afternoon of Friday, 5 April, I received a call from the president of the FAI seeking a meeting with them that evening.  Sport Ireland agreed and a constructive meeting with the president and two members of the board of the FAI took place at Sport Ireland offices that evening, with Sport Ireland represented by the chairman, myself as the chief executive, and Colm McGinty.</p> <p>  At that meeting, the president of the FAI provided to Sport Ireland a written response to our letter of 4 April.  A copy of this letter has also been provided to the committee.  At the meeting, the contents of the letter were discussed at length and the following actions agreed: the outcome of the Grant Thornton ongoing internal review of the association's book will be provided to Sport Ireland; the terms of reference of the review by Mazars will be provided to Sport Ireland once they are finalised; Sport Ireland will be consulted by Mazars as part of the review process; Mazars' full and final report will be provided to us in a timely manner; the review by consultants Jonathan Hall Associates will be provided to Sport Ireland; and the FAI will discuss the composition of the new governance review group with Sport Ireland.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland issued a formal response to this letter on Thursday, 11 April.  A copy of this letter has been provided to the committee.</p> <p>  As outlined to the committee on 3 April, the Sport Ireland Act confers considerable authority in Sport Ireland.  That is reinforced by our responsibility in investing substantial amounts of public funding into sport.  As a statutory agency, we seek to develop strong sporting organisations and recognise the considerable public interest in a successful Irish sports sector.  That said, we are also mindful of the limits of Sport Ireland's legal powers and we respect the autonomy of the national governing bodies of sport.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland is responsible for the investment of public money in sport and, subsequently, oversight and accountability of this investment.</p><p>All procedures and interactions with the national governing bodies reflect this responsibility.</p><p> At our meeting on Tuesday, 9 April, the board of Sport Ireland unanimously made the decision to suspend and withhold funding to the FAI.  This decision followed a lengthy discussion by the board on the &euro;100,000 loan and related matters.  The suspension and withholding of funding to the NGB is not a decision that the board of Sport Ireland takes lightly.  It is typically an intervention of last resort, and is only ever used very reluctantly.  Sport Ireland is acutely aware that this action causes uncertainty and disruption to the delivery of very important strategic programmes.  However, Sport Ireland is ultimately responsible for the security and accountability of approximately &euro;2.9 million in public funding invested in the FAI.</p><p> In the course of the board&rsquo;s discussion, it was noted that in the FAI&rsquo;s written opening statement submitted to this committee ahead of last week&rsquo;s hearing, the association acknowledged that clause 4.3 of the further reporting section of Sport Ireland&rsquo;s terms and conditions of grant approval was not met.  This relates to 2017, whereby the FAI did not notify Sport Ireland of any material deterioration in its financial position.  Notwithstanding some positive steps taken by the FAI in the preceding days, it has been acknowledged by the association that it was in breach of clause 4.3.  For the committee&rsquo;s reference, clause 4.3 states: "In addition each organisation undertakes to notify Sport Ireland in writing without delay in the event of any material deterioration in its financial position or of any other matter which may jeopardise the organisation&rsquo;s overall financial viability and/or its ability to comply with its commitments in the Approved Submission, and thereafter to provide Sport Ireland with such information and documentation as Sport Ireland may request in connection with the relevant matter and any steps being taken to rectify it."</p><p> In light of this clear acknowledgement, the board of Sport Ireland made the decision to suspend and withhold funding to the FAI in accordance with clause 1.1 of Sport Ireland's terms and conditions of grant approval.  In making this significant decision, the board of Sport Ireland is aware that 50% of the youth field sport funding has been paid to the FAI in 2019.  The next payment to the FAI is due in the third quarter of this year.  The board of Sport Ireland, in its deliberations to suspend and withhold funding outlined above, was of the clear view that this interim period should be used by the FAI to take whatever actions are required to enable Sport Ireland to restore funding.</p><p> On the limited number of occasions in the past when Sport Ireland has had concerns about governance and financial controls and has acted to suspend and withhold funding to a sporting body, I will outline the process followed.  First, an audit of the sporting body&rsquo;s governance and financial control is undertaken.  Second, a liaison process is established with the sporting body to closely monitor, verify and support the NGB's implementation of the audit recommendations to verify compliance with the terms and conditions of grant approval.  Third, the liaison process is overseen by Sport Ireland&rsquo;s audit and risk committee, with periodic updates and recommendations made to the board.  Fourth, grant funding is withheld until sufficient progress has been made on implementing the audit recommendations, and governance and financial control issues have been progressed.  Fifth, once progress is made on implementing the audit recommendations, and assurance is received of the effectiveness of governance and financial controls, staggered payments are generally made to the NGB in question.</p><p> Sport Ireland will follow this established process with the FAI, as it has in the past with other NGBs when similar situations have arisen.  Sport Ireland's audit and risk committee will meet on 18 April and will discuss the specific requirements, from a governance and financial control perspective that will be required of the FAI.  The audit and risk committee is also scheduled to meet again in May and will review FAI progress.  The executive of Sport Ireland, with the oversight of our audit and risk committee and the board, will continue to liaise with and meet with the FAI to progress all important matters.</p><p>The board of Sport Ireland has agreed to review the decision when it is satisfied that the FAI has addressed its current governance and financial issues.  Important steps in that regard include but are not limited to the completion of the Mazars review and adoption of its recommendations by the FAI, as well as the completion of the Grant Thornton review and adoption of corrective actions by the FAI.</p><p> Depending on what emerges from the Mazars and Grant Thornton reviews, we will also consider a full audit of the FAI by Sport Ireland&rsquo;s appointed auditors, as per Sport Ireland&rsquo;s terms and conditions of grant approval.  Last night we agreed with the FAI that a full audit would be carried out.  The scope will be defined by Sport Ireland&rsquo;s audit and risk committee.  It will be set with reference to our satisfaction with the scope and findings of the Mazars review.  In the light of the acknowledgement by the FAI that there was a breach of the terms and conditions, the audit will be as broad and extensive as necessary to satisfy Sport Ireland that the FAI is compliant with our terms and conditions of grant approval, including that its internal financial controls and management, as well as its general governance, are of sufficient standard in order to restore funding.  The specific mechanisms to satisfy Sport Ireland on the effectiveness of the FAI&rsquo;s governance and systems of internal financial control will be proportionate to the significant level of Sport Ireland;s investment in the organisation.  Our specific requirements will be informed by the response of the FAI during the liaison process.</p><p> Sport Ireland is also cognisant of the FAI&rsquo;s engagement with the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement in its particular inquiries which we understand are substantial.  We will continue to observe this process closely and with keen interest.</p><p> On the next steps to be taken, Sport Ireland has accepted the FAI&rsquo;s offer of engagement on the composition of its new governance review group, to include a majority of external members, as well as to assist in identifying its external chairperson.  Sport Ireland has identified a potential candidate, Aidan Horan, a director of the Institute of Public Administration.  It has been agreed with the FAI that he will take up the role.  The terms of reference of the group will be agreed with Sport Ireland and finalised by the group once it is established.</p><p> Noting the FAI board&rsquo;s ability to appoint an independent person-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00200"><p>I apologise for interrupting, but does the committee have this information on the external chairperson?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00300"><p>Is this additional information not contained in the opening statement?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.24" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00400"><p>We had a meeting with the FAI last night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00500"><p>We have not been given this information.  This is different from the statement submitted to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.26" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00600"><p>It is just that one little piece of information.  We had a meeting with the FAI last night which finished at 7 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1329" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00700"><p>With respect for the members, we would like to receive copies of the additional content Mr. Treacy has given.  Will his staff arrange for that to be done?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.28" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Treacy" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TTJ2019041600002#V00800"><p>Yes.</p> <p>  Noting the FAI board&rsquo;s ability to appoint an independent person to the sub-committee which is examining these matters, Sport Ireland will also nominate a person with relevant experience to sit on the committee.</p> <p>  In the light of our role as a development agency, Sport Ireland will also seek to expedite the level of additional governance support, training and assistance which can be provided for all national governing bodies, NGBs.  It will include a chairpersons network to bring together NGB chairpersons for the consideration and discussion of topics of mutual interest, to share ideas and learning, as well as to inform the development of good public governance.  This is in accordance with actions already identified and being progressed in the Government&rsquo;s national sports policy.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland is aware that the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, as well as the Minister of State, will also have additional questions for and requirements to make of the FAI.  Sport Ireland has no role in the sports capital programme beyond what applies to the provision of large-scale national projects on the Sport Ireland Campus.  In that regard, it will liaise with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport before any decision is taken to restore funding to the FAI.</p> <p>  The board of Sport Ireland has agreed to keep the FAI&rsquo;s progress in dealing with all relevant issues under review at each and every board meeting.  Sport Ireland will continue to provide non-financial assistance and guidance for the FAI which may be helpful in advancing matters.</p> <p>  Sport Ireland with representatives of the FAI last night.  An update on the meeting will be given to the committee today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-04-16a.29" nospeaker="true" time="12:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>