<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Education and Social Protection</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy James Bannon, Senator Marie Moloney, Deputy Ray Butler, Senator Hildegarde Naughton, Deputy Jim Daly, Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell. Deputy Derek Keating, Deputy Aengus Ã“ Snodaigh, Deputy Willie O'Dea, Deputy Brendan Ryan,</p><p>DEPUTY JOANNA TUFFY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.4" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 1.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.5" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700003#B00100">Review of Vote 37: Minister for Social Protection</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700003#B00200"><p>We will now discuss expenditure at the Department of Social Protection.  I wish to draw the attention of the Minister and her officials to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(l) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  The opening statement submitted to the committee will be published on the committee website after this meeting.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  Once again, I ask that everyone puts his or her mobile phone in aeroplane mode or switches it off completely.</p><p>  The purpose of today's meeting is to conduct a mid-year review of the position regarding expenditure in the Department of Social Protection for 2014, with a particular focus on performance and output related data and also to consider the Department's proposals for 2015.  It is intended that this mid-year review will become an annual feature of the joint committee's ongoing scrutiny of expenditure.  I welcome the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton and her officials.  </p><p>  A timetable for today's meeting has been circulated which allows for a brief opening statement by the Minister to be followed by a discussion of each programme in the Estimate.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  I now invite the Minister to make a brief opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700003#B00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and members of this committee for the invitation extended to me to appear before the committee to consider further the social protection Vote for 2014, to review the mid-year position and to look ahead to budget 2015.  My officials have provided members with briefing material which I hope will assist us in our deliberations today.  I propose to give a brief overview of some of the structural reforms to the Department since I became Minister and to quickly go through the key points in the briefing in order to inform and begin our discussions.  I welcome the views of members and and look forward to their engagement and our discussion.</p> <p>The service traditionally provided by the Department of Social Protection in providing income supports has continued and, despite the need to stabilise Government finances, the welfare system continues to play a very positive role in protecting those who need our support.  I will return to this aspect later.  One of my main priorities since becoming Minister has been to transform the Department from the passive benefits provider of old to one that is actively assisting jobseekers to return to work, including engagement with employers to help them get the employees they need.</p><p> Under Pathways to Work, the Government has set out a comprehensive reform of the State's approach to helping unemployed jobseekers return to work.  Since its launch, the programme of work has seen the roll-out of 44 Intreo one-stop-shop centres throughout the country; the introduction of group engagement whereby all new jobseekers are briefed on the services available to them; the profiling of every client on the live register to help prioritise and direct interventions; the introduction of a case management system whereby jobseekers receive scheduled one-to-one interviews with case officers based on their profile; the introduction of a social contract of rights and responsibilities between jobseekers and the State through the record of mutual commitment; the creation of an employer engagement unit in the Department to start the process of building effective relationships with employers; and the formation of the labour market council.</p><p> Signs of economic recovery are becoming tangible.  The most recent live register figures published by the CSO show that unemployment continues to decline, with the standardised unemployment rate falling to 11.2% in August from a crisis peak of 15.1% in early 2012.  These statistics, together with the latest quarterly national household survey and the end of August Exchequer figures indicate that as the economy is strengthening, our jobs market thankfully is recovering.  The number of people at work has increased by more than 75,000 since the recovery began in 2012.</p><p> While we are beginning to see a positive turn in our domestic economy, it is important and necessary that we help those who have been hit by the recession get back on the ladder of recovery as quickly as possible.  Since the lowest point of the jobs crisis, long-term unemployment has fallen from 9.5% to 6.8%.  These positive trends are very welcome and in line with the Government's Pathways to Work objectives.  The Government has greater ambition for those citizens who are unfortunate enough to be unemployed.</p><p> In addition to deep-rooted reforms, I have prioritised efforts to combat social welfare fraud.  The vast majority of people on social welfare are claiming only the entitlement due to them.  As such, it is essential that we respect the majority - and taxpayers and PRSI payers who fund the system - and maintain public confidence in the system by vigorously tackling any fraudulent activity within the social welfare system.</p><p> I have spoken to the committee previously about the public services card.  We have also begun the phased introduction of the public services card with key security features, including a biometric standard photo and signature, which will be used to authenticate identity of individuals.  As of last week, we have issued in excess of 910,000 cards, of which 240,000 are the free travel variant, mainly to our retired citizens.  These new cards will enable individuals to gain access to public services more efficiently and with a minimum duplication of effort while at the same time preserving their privacy to the maximum extent possible.  They will also play a crucial role in eliminating fraud in the social welfare system.</p><p> The clearance of backlogs in all areas continues to be a major priority in the Department.  Considerable progress has been made in recent years in this regard.  It is worth noting that the number of pending claims, that is, claims being processed, has almost halved since the end of 2010, falling from more than 118,000 to just under 62,000 at the end of July last, a drop of 56,000.  This has been achieved, as members are aware, through a combination of updating IT systems, introducing significant processing efficiencies and a quicker and more responsive service to our customers in the face of increased claim loads in recent years.  I thank the staff and management of the Department for the huge effort they put into this and their great enthusiasm for getting better service to people who use the Department's services.</p><p> The number of appeals in hand has also fallen dramatically.  The number continues to decline from more than 20,000 at the start of 2013 to under 14,800 at the start of 2014, and I am happy to say it has further reduced to just over 10,000 on 1 September 2014.</p><p> I return to our consideration of the 2014 Revised Estimates.  Table 1.1 on page 6 of the briefing shows departmental expenditure by the various programmes we operate.  Table 1.3 shows that 80% of expenditure is incurred by a relatively small number of schemes.</p><p> Other than expenditure on child benefit, respite care grant and domiciliary care allowance, members may wish to note that the expenditure outlined in this table relates to the cost of the weekly rates of payment for the recipients involved.  It does not include the cost of supplementary benefits, such as the free travel, fuel allowance and the household benefits package.</p><p> As everybody knows, Ireland has had to stabilise its Government's finances over recent years.  As I mentioned, it is sometimes forgotten in this context that the welfare system continues to play a key role in our society, and I have ensured that the necessary resources have been made available where required.  This is very evident in the overall expenditure in two important areas, namely, that devoted to carers and pensioners since 2010.  I draw members' attention to the very significant rise in both spend and numbers, notwithstanding the pressure the country has been under.</p><p> Total expenditure by the Department on carers has increased from just under &euro;752 million in 2010 to almost &euro;806 million in 2014.  This is an increase of &euro;53.9 million or 7.2%.  The overall number of caring recipients has increased from just over 76,000 in 2010 to almost 84,000 recipients in 2014.  This is an increase of 7,815 people in receipt of carer payments, an increase of 10.3%, notwithstanding the acute financial crisis of which we are all aware.</p><p> Likewise, the 2014 Estimates provided for expenditure of &euro;6.5 billion for pensions, up from &euro;5.9 billion in 2010, an increase of more than &euro;600 million or 10.3%, which is a really big level of increase.  The number of pensioners funded from the Department's pension programme has increased from 494,000 in 2010 to in excess of 587,000 in 2014, an increase of 93,000 or 18.9%.  We have prioritised those payments to the additional number of pensioners coming through at an average of almost &euro;200 million a year to provide for almost 100,000 additional pensioners.  We have a democratic dividend in Ireland in terms of more older people retiring and living longer, and we have a demographic bonus relating to the numbers of young children and our very strong population growth.  Of course, these demographic pressures result in extra money being paid and I am happy to say I have been able to prioritise and provide for that.</p> <p>The Department will spend &euro;19.6 billion this year on a wide range of schemes and services.  At the end of June more than 1.44 million persons were in receipt of a weekly payment in respect of almost 2.3 million beneficiaries, as well as a further 607,000 families in receipt of a monthly child benefit payment in respect of more than 1 million children.  The scale of the numbers alone means that our payments and services impact on the lives of almost everybody in the State in one way or another.  Social transfers play a pivotal role in alleviating poverty and cushioning people from the worst effects of rising unemployment and falling incomes.  They are essential in supporting well-being and reducing inequalities through the redistribution of income, therefore helping to promote social solidarity in society.  In addition, the importance of welfare spending as a key tool in stabilising demand in the economy is recognised both at home and abroad.</p><p> I held a pre-budget forum on Friday, 4 July last in Dublin Castle.  It was attended by 37 voluntary and community groups.  The purpose of the annual forum is to provide such organisations with an opportunity to have an input into the budget process.  I value such meetings enormously.  This year&rsquo;s forum included a number of workshops on specific themes such as children and families, illness and disability, poverty and social inclusion and housing supports.</p><p> In terms of budget 2015, the Government made a number of commitments in the Statement of Government Priorities 2014-2016 which I concluded with an Taoiseach in the context of the formation of the new Cabinet in July.  I wish to draw the attention of members to three elements of the agreement which reflect on social welfare commitments.  The first is to increase the household benefits package by &euro;100, in part to compensate older people and other vulnerable groups for the introduction of water charges.  It is a water support payment which we estimate will cost approximately &euro;42 million, which will extend to people aged over 70, carers, families who receive a domiciliary care allowance in respect of a child with special needs and also people with disabilities who are on a disability payment.  It goes to some of the most important groups in society.  I estimate the payment will go to about 410,000 households.</p><p> We have committed to the full retention of the free travel scheme.  It was never in doubt, but I know people raised concerns earlier in the summer.  We have committed to introducing measures to assist low-income families by improving the system of child income supports such that those moving from welfare to work will retain payments for children to ensure that people are better off in work.  That is a fundamental reform.  People might wish to ask about it but I have told Deputies previously that we have significantly increased the amount of money we spend on family income supplement, FIS.  As of now, expenditure on it is approximately &euro;280 million for this year but it will be higher next year.  For families with children it will be an additional support which will increase the incentive for people with children to go back to work.</p><p> On foot of the latter commitment I have asked the Department to bring forward options to smooth the transition from welfare to work and to ensure that families are encouraged and able to avail of an employment opportunity.  The work is nearing completion.  The specific aim is to provide an additional incentive for families who are long-term unemployed to move from a social welfare payment into employment, including, importantly, self employment.  The working family dividend scheme will allow such individuals to retain a portion of their previous social welfare payment which relates to their children, the QCI, for a period after they leave the welfare system.  I look forward to progressing the scheme in the forthcoming budget.</p><p> Overall, &euro;19.6 billion was allocated to the Department for 2014.  Department of Social Protection expenditure in the year to date is very close to that target.  Recent Exchequer returns indicate that Ireland&rsquo;s financial position continues to improve.  However, it is too early to say what the precise implications are for budget 2015, but the latest returns indicate another positive step forward.  We have four more months of returns and it is clear that the September returns in the context of the budget date will be particularly important.  When account is taken of once-off factors in 2013, the Exchequer deficit is nearly &euro;2.4 billion better than last year.  That represents real progress in stabilising the finances.  I am conscious that almost everyone in the country has contributed to us getting to that point from where we were following 2008.  However, we need to be cautious at this stage as 40% of total tax revenues are received in the last four months of the year.</p><p> My colleagues and I will give detailed consideration to the coming budget over the next few weeks.  Our priority is to meet our deficit target of 3%.  The emerging economic and Exchequer data mean that we now have a somewhat more positive environment over the next few years in making budgetary decisions than this Government faced in its first three years.  I caution against expectations of a so-called giveaway budget along the lines of the Celtic tiger years.  The key achievement of the Government has been to stabilise the nation's finances, to increase employment and to achieve economic growth.  This endeavour is well under way and we can look forward to reaping the benefits in a sustainable way in years to come.  I hope the briefing gives committee members a good overview of the Department's expenditure in 2014 and the challenges and opportunities ahead in 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700005#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  We will now consider the Revised Estimate and also proposed expenditure and performance for 2014 for each programme.  We have an order in which committee members speak.  It is Fianna F&aacute;il, Sinn F&eacute;in, the Technical Group, the Government and then Deputies and Senators in the order in which they raise their hands, followed by non-committee Members.  First, we will consider the pensions programme.  I refer members to page 13 of the Department's brief and to page 5 of the committee secretariat's notes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700005#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister for her presentation.  We were talking in the first session about pensions.  I note that the figure for expenditure on pensions is &euro;6.5 billion, which represents one in three euro spent on the social welfare budget.  That is considerable expenditure.  I will not delay the committee because I see that we have only about 20 minutes to discuss the matter.  The position is that if one looks at the figures as a whole, it is obvious that this is the area in which one will face increased liabilities in the years to come, due as the Minister pointed out, to demography.  The Department estimates that the pensions bill will increase by up to &euro;1 billion in the next five years due to an increased number of recipients.  The Minister will be aware that there are various suggestions as to how the matter should be addressed.  For example, there is an OECD report.  There is also a report from Social Justice Ireland on a universal pension scheme and there is a Department of Social Protection document dating back to 2010.  Various other proposals also exist.  What is the position on the reports as we face into this huge demographic crisis, where according to the figures, the ratio of people earning to people not earning is going to reduce substantially by 2050?  What, if any, action has been taken on the reports and what action is it proposed to take?</p> <p>When one is facing a crisis like this, one of the obvious partial solutions is to encourage people to provide for themselves, buy their own pensions and, therefore, take themselves off being dependent on the State.  What specific proposals do we have to encourage people to provide for themselves?</p><p> I note the bereavement grant is part of this subhead.  The savings made on the abolition of the bereavement grant are approximately &euro;21 million.  When we were discussing this in the D&aacute;il, the Minister informed me and other Members that people who needed assistance with funeral payments could have access to the burial grant, which is means-tested.  It existed side by side with the bereavement grant in the past.  I know of many cases in which many people had to avail of both grants because the bereavement grant only went a small way towards covering the costs of a funeral.  What additional provision has been made to that budget, out of which the burial grant is paid?  Is it paid out of supplementary welfare payments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00200"><p>No, it comes from exceptional needs payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00300"><p>If I read these figures correctly, the exceptional needs payment provision has actually been reduced by &euro;2.5 million, despite the abolition of the bereavement grant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00400"><p>No, not in that area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00500"><p>Has that budget been increased then?  If so, by how much?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00600"><p>The big challenge for the State, as Deputy O&rsquo;Dea said, is to ensure the Social Insurance Fund is large enough to deal with an increasingly ageing population.  Yesterday, I attended an Age Action conference at which representatives of all parties were questioned on various issues by an audience of pensioners.  The Minister would do well to speak with her party colleague, Councillor Mary Freehill, who attended and got an absolute roasting from the audience.  There is a large level of anger among pensioners.  It is not about the pension payment level itself but the other cuts and charges that have been introduced over the past several years, such as water charges.  If these continue, they suggest the rates for the State contributory and non-contributory pension should be increased to make up the shortfall, particularly as they are on a fixed income.  From what the Minister has said, it does not seem that an increase in the pension rates has even been looked at.  Is that correct?</p><p>  Will the Minister give an impact assessment of budget 2015?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00700"><p>I thank the Minister for this briefing on her Vote.</p><p>  When we think of pensions, we think of people who are over 66.  There are quite a number of people on pensions under that age such as those on widow&rsquo;s or widower&rsquo;s pensions.  Has the abolition of the transition pension been factored into the figures presented for this Vote?  Did we cut off our nose to spite our face by abolishing that pension?  If people could retire at 65 under the transition pension arrangements, automatically jobs would be created for others, taking them off social welfare.  What savings were made by abolishing the transition pension?  Are there any proposals such as tax incentives to encourage people to take out private pensions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700006#E00800"><p>I commissioned the OECD, Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development, to prepare a report on introducing a supplementary pension scheme which would be developed along the lines of the successful schemes in Australia and New Zealand.  On occasion, I have described it as a shamrock or Celtic saver.  It would allow people to save money in a safe way to generate an additional pension, over and above the State contributory or non-contributory pension.  The State contributory pension is among the best paid in Europe.  Nonetheless, if one retires on that pension alone, it can be a very tight management exercise.  As a society, notwithstanding the difficulties we have been through, we have prioritised continuing to spend on pensions to a very high degree.</p><p>  The OECD reported last April and its key recommendation was to improve the adequacy of pensions by increasing coverage to the funded part of the pension system through a universal mandatory or quasi-mandatory employment-based pension scheme.  In line with this recommendation, as well as the programme for Government and the recent 2014 to 2016 restatement of priorities which the Taoiseach and I drew up in July, the Government will agree during 2015 to a roadmap and timeline for the introduction of a new universal supplementary pension savings scheme.  I am delighted to re-affirm this as it was not widely broadcast at the time.  The decision has been taken in response to adequacy and sustainability challenges to the pensions system.  This has been an increasing concern, as Deputy O&rsquo;Dea said, in recent years.</p> <p>I gave some statistics earlier.  In the period since 1995, supplementary income coverage has remained at only approximately 50% and this figure needs to improve significantly.  It is an issue for atypical workers who are in and out of the workforce.  It is also an issue for women in particular, and for quite a lot of self-employed people, particularly in very small operations.  Significant improvement of this figure is an important national goal.</p><p> The State pension is and will continue to be a key social welfare payment.  It is the fundamental basis for the Irish pension system.  It is a very valuable benefit.  While, thankfully, people live longer and healthier lives, the cost to the State and the individual of supporting this longer life is increasing incrementally.  I gave the committee some figures earlier.  Approximately 17,000 additional pensioners come into receipt of the State pension every year.  The over 65 year old population is projected to increase from 11% of the total population in 2010 to 15% as soon as 2020.  Sometimes when I hear people speaking at conferences about this they speak about 2040 and 2050, but a year-on-year increase in the number of retired people is with us at present, and those who retire live longer.  At present there are 5.3 people of working age for every pensioner and this ratio is expected to decrease to approximately 2:1 by 2060.  This is in line with almost every other European country.</p><p> Given the changing demographics and the incrementally upward pressure of pension provision and State finances, there is a need to provide a long-term savings habit and mechanism by individuals to supplement income from the State pension for those who will otherwise not be in a position to enjoy standards of living in retirement similar to those in pre-retirement.  Development of the roadmap for a universal pension involves detailed consideration of policy and operational parameters.  It includes co-operation across a range of Government Departments and engagement of all sectoral interests.  I am happy to say much work is ongoing in the Department.  This will involve major IT input.  There are major considerations for the pensions industry in Ireland and I have spoken at a number of conferences on the very detailed technical issue.  I am happy that now in particular, with the recovery taking hold and with the agreement in July, we will be in a position to progress this significantly.  In countries which have done this successfully it took a number of years and was built up a very gradual period of time.  This is very much what I envisage happening in the Irish system.  When incomes of people in employment have been so tight it has been difficult to envisage them making additional savings for their retirement and I am looking forward to the development of this in the economy.</p><p> On the related question of funeral expenses and how we support people, I am glad to have an opportunity to speak about the number of supports in place.  We make a direct cash payment of &euro;6,000 to a widow, widower or surviving partner with a child or children on the death of his or her spouse or partner.  This is a very important payment and goes to the person and family directly bereaved.  At the time of the changes to the bereavement grant I stated I wanted to emphasise support for the direct survivors of the person.  In some cases estates are left to far more distant relatives.  I would like the limited funding we have to be concentrated on the direct family and children of the person who died.  In the case of the death of someone on a retirement pension we continue to pay the retirement pension for a period of six weeks after the individual's death.  These are the two significant payments we make.</p><p> With regard to the exceptional needs payment, we have provided &euro;31.3 million in 2014 and more than 68,500 special needs payment were made to the end of August 2014 for a variety of needs.  With the development of the new Intreo offices the Department has consolidated community welfare services to people in need of special needs payments in all of our new offices.  We also have a telephone system available and, if it is required, we will get officials to call directly to the person's house.</p><p> I cannot give the committee the detail on this.  Last year &euro;4.398 million was spent on supporting the cost of burials.  I do not have the 2014 data yet but I will try to get the information for the Deputy and we will have it at the end of the year.  We must collate it in detail from community welfare officers throughout the country.  They are significant supports for people with requirements for financial support for funeral costs.  My colleague in the Labour Party parliamentary party, Deputy Eamonn Maloney, has drawn attention to this.  The burial costs charged, particularly in the Dublin area, have risen by extraordinary lengths.  Deputy Maloney tabled a Private Members' Bill to restrict some of the costs related to the opening of graves.  People such as Deputy Keating and I know that some of the cemetery companies charges, even to place a small urn with the ashes of a beloved one in an existing family grave, are extraordinarily high.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700007#F00200"><p>I will take supplementary questions but I would like to move on to the other items and I ask committee members to keep it short.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700007#F00300"><p>With regard to the bereavement grant, community welfare officers used to deduct the amount of bereavement grant from the burial grant.  It was obligatory to apply for the bereavement grant before an application for a burial grant was processed and the amount was then deducted.  Now that the bereavement grant is gone they can give the full amount.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700007#F00400"><p>This is an important point and I thank Senator Moloney.</p><p>  The key point is that funerals, particularly in the Dublin area, are extraordinarily expensive.  Thankfully this trend has not been as extreme outside of Dublin.  Recently somebody was telling me about the cost of placing a small urn containing the ashes of a loved one in a family grave.  The family members thought they would be able to place it themselves but they were not and the amount they were charged was staggering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700007#F00500"><p>Thankfully it is a bit cheaper to die in Limerick but it is still quite expensive.  With regard to the burial grant, the Minister stated that in certain circumstances there is a direct cash grant of &euro;6,000 and a continuous payment for six weeks to the surviving pensioner.  My point is both of these benefits existed previously in conjunction with the bereavement grant  The Minister stated the Government has abolished the bereavement grant but these two other grants were not abolished.  As far as the exceptional needs payment is concerned, I have found that in practice it is true to say the bereavement grant would have been deducted from the general level of the exceptional needs grant.</p> <p>However, in terms of the community welfare officer deciding that somebody is entitled to &euro;1,200, in the past if they got a bereavement grant they deducted the &euro;800 and the bill that fell on the community welfare officer was &euro;400.  The bill that will have to be met now by the community welfare officer is, in theory anyway, &euro;1,200.  The bottom of page 25 of the brief clearly states that expenditure on the exceptional needs payment scheme will be reduced by &euro;2.1 million in 2014 so the fund out of which all those extra payments are paid is basically reduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00200"><p>The Deputy will understand that as people on the live register go back to work, the actual level of claims on some of the Department's payment schemes has been falling.  I am happy to say that unless the Deputy has personal experience as a representative of individual constituents who have had issues, we have not received any complaints.  On the contrary, I am personally aware of important and considered support given by our community welfare services around the country to families who have suffered a bereavement.  It must be remembered that this payment is going to the directly bereaved family, which is very important, as opposed to it going to inheritors who may be distant relations.  If people need the support with funeral costs, as Minister I am saying they will get it.  This is something the Department has done since the development of a modern social welfare system in the early 1950s.  If the Deputy has a problem, please let me know because I know the community welfare service is extremely considerate in regard to bereaved families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister.  There are a few cases I will bring to her attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1079" speakername="Ray Butler" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00400"><p>I want to follow up on what the Minister has just said because in recent months we have been dealing with the community welfare officer.  In one case they had not got any money and &euro;6,000 was granted for the funeral expenses.  In another case they had &euro;3,500 and the balance was sent to the undertaker.  It is working very well and the community welfare officers are doing a great job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00500"><p>We will move on to the working age employment supports programme.  I refer members to page 19 of the Department's brief and page 6 of the committee secretariat notes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00600"><p>I have some brief questions.  One of the items we are dealing with is lone parents allowance.  The Minister has said, and I agree with her, that her objective is an active system where people are activated to go out to work, when the work is available, rather than staying at home and relying on welfare.  One of the means by which savings have been got in regard to lone parents is the reduction in the income disregard.  In other words, we are reducing the amount of money one can earn while still getting one's full lone parent allowance.  Effectively, it means that because of the changes made, if somebody in receipt of lone parents allowance, which is means tested, goes out to work, they will now get less because the income disregard has fallen.  I cannot understand how the prospect of getting less money than one was getting previously will encourage people to go out to work.</p><p>  I note that &euro;29.1 million has been saved as a result of the standardisation of the reduction in the maternity benefit payment.  I note also that the Minister, Deputy Noonan, introduced tax on maternity benefit in the budget.  Would the Minister have the figure for the projected yield from that change made by the Minister for Finance?  In other words, would she know what is likely to be the tax collected in the year on maternity benefit?</p><p>  We have had many discussions here, in which Deputy Butler among others has featured strongly, on the prospect of illness benefit and jobseeker's benefit, in other words, contribution-related payments for the self-employed.  Where are we on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1062" speakername="James Bannon" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00700"><p>Regarding the part of the Minister's opening statement dealing with combating fraud, what is the timescale for the complete roll-out of the public services card to all persons?  Also, is the issuing of the cards being undertaken in-house by an Irish company or outsourced?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00800"><p>Before the Minister replies, strictly speaking that does not come under the area we are discussing but if the Minister wants to speak to it she may do so.  Is Deputy Keating's question a general one but relating to this issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1012" speakername="Derek Keating" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G00900"><p>It is related to the Minister's report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01000"><p>We are taking it programme by programme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1012" speakername="Derek Keating" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01100"><p>That is fine.  I will await my turn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01200"><p>I call Deputy Daly on work-related income supports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01300"><p>It is still a difficulty for some employers to compete with the welfare system.  I asked 12 random employers in the town I represent in my constituency last week if they found it difficult to compete and they said they had difficulty this summer.  We had a great season and west Cork was thriving but employers find it very difficult to get people into the workplace.  Unfortunately, there are still queues outside what we traditionally call the dole office.  When we examine the issue in more detail, obviously it is not the headline welfare rates that are the problem but the black market economy coupled with people who are happy to take their benefits and work two or three days for cash.  What is the Minister's view on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01400"><p>I have a number of questions.  The figures for farm assist are significantly reduced.  Can the Minister indicate the reason for that?  Are farmers doing a good deal better this year than other years?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01500"><p>I was at a farm last night and they were doing very well, and they were delighted with-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700008#G01600"><p>Some farms are doing better but other farms will not have done as well.  That is the nature of farming but it is a substantial drop in a year in terms of farm assist.</p><p>  On the redundancy and insolvency section, which I believe falls under the working age income supports, RTE ran a story about the recovery of redundancy debt and suggested that in 2011, for instance, only a very small portion of the &euro;300 million outstanding was recovered; it had the figure at 4% or 5%.  It has increased since then but upwards of &euro;200 million or &euro;300 million, which is a substantial amount, is outstanding to the State.  If that was in any other field the State would have a programme through which to recover it.  The criticism in the RTE programme was that the Department did not have a strategy by which to pursue this recovery.  Part of the reason for that is because employers were allowed state that they had an inability to pay but that inability to pay was never fully investigated.  That is money the State should be pursuing as rigorously as it pursues those wrongfully claiming allowances.</p><p>  I am concerned about lone parents as all research continues to show that they are a section of our society experiencing major disadvantage and poverty yet we have seen a significant fall in spending on lone parents to a level of 11.8%.  That is the equivalent of a fall in spending of &euro;115 million.</p> <p>Is the Minister concerned about the impact this is having on those lone parents in particular?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700009#H00200"><p>There are a number of questions.  I will take Deputy Bannon's question on the public services card first.  I understand the company which does the work is a subsidiary or part of De La Rue.  It is based in Bray.  I am aware that there are some external inputs into the software systems, but I can get the Deputy more detail.  Significantly, it is an Irish operation.  It has gone quite well so far.  In November, we will reach 1 million cards.</p><p>  The cards have hugely increased security.  The use of the biometric photo means that when someone gets a card, their photograph is automatically matched with all of the photographs on the major database.  For instance, on a weekly basis the Department gets matching photos where someone has turned up, say, in the Athlone office, who on a biometric basis has an exact facial resemblance to someone who has been in the Longford office, and that has been a significant assistance in deterring fraud.</p><p>  The printing is done in Bray, and there is a Dutch company which has been involved in the technology software side of it.  It is to airport standards of biometric identity and it has been helpful in limiting cases of multiple identity fraud which is a problem for all social welfare systems around the world.</p><p>  In response to the comments of Deputies O'Dea and &Oacute; Snodaigh on lone parents, when I became Minister I decided that we should be as ambitious for lone parents to work as we are for anybody else who is out of the workforce.  The key way back for considerable numbers of lone parents, particularly the young, is to engage in education.  Happily, a significant number of lone parents do so.  In the countries that have successful support systems for lone parents and good outcomes for the children, getting lone parents into education and training and then back to work, which may take a protracted period of time, is the way to do it.  Therefore, in the structure we have devised, lone parents will move, after their youngest child is seven, to a transitional transition-to-work lone parent payment, and that will continue for another seven years.  To date, the system is operating well.</p><p>  As I stated earlier, in terms of the agreement in July with the Taoiseach, we are introducing further targeted supports.  This also addresses Deputy Daly's point that some employers state they still feel that drawing lone parents back to work can be difficult.  In my experience, it is difficult in two particular areas - where someone has children because he or she is getting the qualified child increase, QCI, which is &euro;30 a week, and where there may be problems for those who are on rent supplement.  The move to the housing assistance payment, HAP, via the local authorities, which is being piloted in Limerick, should also solve the latter employment trap.  In terms of the working family dividend, that will apply whether it is a lone parent or somebody who is in a relationship, whether cohabitation or marriage.  We are making good progress there.</p><p>  One should note that lone parents qualify for family income supplement, FIS.  Many lone parents who go to work are opting to go on FIS, which is an attractive top-up for somebody who is leaving social welfare, either completely or on a partial basis to take up part-time work.  Deputy Bannon will be aware that I gave significant allocations, last year and the previous year, to the Department of Children and Youth Affairs for further supports in child care because in all my discussions with lone parent groups and parents in relationships, the cost of child care is a significant factor.  I allocated &euro;14 million to assist in both aftercare and community care services, and the Department of Children and Youth Affairs has been working to expand that system.</p><p>  Through our facilitators in all of the Intreo offices, including the offices in Limerick which Deputy O'Dea visited with me, we have employment officers who will specifically look at the needs of lone parents and seek particularly to help them.  I appreciate the point that it is a big change, but I believe that change is working positively.</p><p>  I am particularly happy that there is a strong emphasis on education.  We also have expanded and improved significantly the training provided, for instance, to those who participate in community employment, CE, and who undertake child care.  Quite a number of those who take on child care in CE are lone parents.  Many might be older women who have partially reared their families and are interested in taking up a new career in their late 30s or in their 40s.  We are ensuring that participants are trained to FETAC level 5.  That has been positive.</p><p>  In respect of farm assist, I can confirm the numbers are dropping.  The payments have dropped by &euro;7.85 million.  That is a reduction of 7.9%.  In general, the current trends in farming and the weather last year and this year probably had some impact on that.  On farm assist, as with the self-employed, as I stated in Wexford in recent days, we in the Department are flexible.  If a farmer or fisherman or someone who is self-employed experiences a catastrophic fall or collapse in income because the business has gone to the wall, as happened during the economic collapse, we are able to provide a service in real time to him or her.  Before I became Minister, such a person had to go and get two or three years' accounts, which is expensive.  If one does not have any money, it is difficult to pay an accountant to sort out one's accounts.  We are now doing it in real time based on the person's income as he or she goes into the office.  As a consequence, I am happy to say the situation that existed in 2011, where many who had previously been self-employed had no access to social welfare, has been changed.  I would be interested to hear from members if they have any problems in this regard.  We are now able to meet the requirements of almost everybody, including farmers and fishermen.  That has been confirmed by the Mangan advisory group which took a look at this at my request because I was anxious, because it is becoming so significant, that those in self-employment who lost their business would not be ineligible.  The entitlement is subject to means testing but the system is now working favourably.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700009#H00300"><p>Was Deputy Daly's question answered?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700009#H00400"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700009#H00500"><p>I am sorry.  On the redundancy debt, I heard that slightly peculiar RTE report.  We took over the redundancy debt from the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation because, although I do not want to continuously harp back to the awful events in 2008 and afterwards, there was a considerable backlog.</p> <p>The Deputy may have known people - I certainly did - who had worked in construction and whose construction employer went bust.  In some cases, they all but disappeared and there was a waiting period of significant duration.  I personally dealt with cases in which the waiting period was up to two years and this Government inherited a large number of such cases.  The Deputy may criticise me for this but as Minister, I decided to focus on those who were waiting on their redundancy payments in what I found to be an inheritance from the previous Government.  It was because the crash was so huge and rapid and because the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment frankly was not geared up to deal with the kind of demands that emerged.  The then Government decided - in my view wisely - to try to transfer the administration of the scheme to the Department of Social Protection.  I prioritised paying those who were due redundancy payments or insolvency payments or both.  Second, the Department's staff worked flat out and created a new information technology platform.  The Deputy will remember the prolonged dispute concerning the sit-in at Vita Cortex.  Once an agreement had been reached there and the employers had put in the appropriate redundancy payments and applications, the Department was able to pay the people involved who were in benefit within a very short time.  That was when the new computer system went live and the Department has concentrated on getting the system up to date.</p><p> In addition, as one of the savings it undertook, the Department reduced the actual refunds that were paid over a period of time.  It was in respect of refunds that the arrears arose in past times and the saving to the State in this regard was &euro;117.5 million.  This is what I found a bit odd about the RTE report, as actually there has been a significant saving in this area, as well as a huge improvement of the service.  For instance, if a redundancy is announced anywhere in the country nowadays - happily they are less frequent - social welfare staff will go into that place of employment, set up an office and get the details of the staff.  There have been small problems with British-based companies because the British redundancy rules and social welfare system are different from ours and sometimes, where the receivership is being handled from the United Kingdom, there may be a slight communications pause.  I remember that in the case of a number of those computer shops which also went bang during the recession, there again were long delays for some of the workers involved.  However, the system at present is working very well.</p><p> In respect of debts, one should remember the Department has taken over a lot of this from the former Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment and it does not write off debts unless that is strictly in line with Comptroller and Auditor General requirements.  The Department pursues employers and members will recall the legislation was changed recently to enable the Department to pursue debt, in that where the employer subsequently recovers and is collecting some other Government support, the Department can deduct any outstanding debt.  The Department has made great progress in the recovery of outstanding debts over the past few years from individuals and other sources.  Over the period since the legislation was changed, I believe the debt recovery amount is running close to &euro;300 million in respect of overpayments, frauds and so on.  As I stated, I found the RTE report to be a bit unusual.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00200"><p>Deputy Daly's question was about-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00300"><p>It related to the black market.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00400"><p>When the Department introduces the return-to-work dividend for families, whereby they will be able to hold onto some of those social welfare payments in respect of children, I hope this will be a significant incentive for people to return to work.  The other point pertains to the Department's employment service and if the Deputy has specific examples, I ask him to pass them to the Department's managers on the ground, because we have a contract arrangement.  We have a social contract with people who are unemployed, whereby those who are at work and who pay taxes and PRSI, as well as businesses, are supporting a good social welfare system on the understanding that when work is available, those who are in receipt of jobseeker's payments will make themselves available.  Moreover, the Department will help them in getting ready to be able to do that work successfully.  They do not really have an option of turning down a serious job prospect.  That is not acceptable and if people refuse to co-operate, the Department can and does operate sanctions.  It can reduce payments to them and has done so in approximately 3,000 cases thus far.  For the most part, however, people want to go back to work and this is not really a big problem for the Department.  Consequently, if the Deputy has specific examples, he might talk to the local managers in west Cork, which would be really helpful to the Department.  Alternatively, he should pass them on to me and I will take it up.</p><p>  Another point is that as we develop a culture of people going back to work, more people will expect to go back.  JobsPlus has been something of a runaway success and almost 3,000 people are on that scheme, whereas the Department's target for this year was 2,000 participants.  In this initiative, the Department pays employers to take on people who have been unemployed for one year or two years.  In the case of those who had been unemployed for one year, there is a cashback payment of slightly more than &euro;300 for each month in which the employer employs the person.  If the person has been unemployed for more than two years, there is a cashback payment of &euro;418 for each month in which people are employed, for up to two years.  This has been very popular and the Department has been obliged to expand the scheme.  Moreover, 60% to 70% of the people taken on have been unemployed for more than two years.  This initiative is based on measures of which I am aware in countries such as Austria and Germany in which one incentivises both the unemployed person and the employer and with this, one can make sure that people who are on the live register have a real chance to benefit from the increased availability of employment.  This is critical for Ireland's as a country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00500"><p>There are a couple of supplementary questions and I would like to bring in people who have not yet spoken.  I call Senator Moloney and then-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00600"><p>I am sorry to be obliged to go back over this but had the Chairman allowed me in, I could have directed the question and the Minister could then have answered them in one go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00700"><p>The Senator did not indicate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00800"><p>I did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J00900"><p>Senator, I did not see you until after everybody had asked their questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J01000"><p>No, sorry, the clerk wrote down my name.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J01100"><p>No, after I went back to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J01200"><p>No, it was not.  Anyway, I am not getting into that argument.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J01300"><p>Senator, you have come in a lot of times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700010#J01400"><p>I had a good discussion with the T&aacute;naiste in Wexford this week on the working family dividend, if that is going to be its official name.  I raised some important matters with the T&aacute;naiste on which she will revert to me but it is important that the joint committee speaks on it and is informed about it as well.  The first point was that this dividend should not interfere with the family income supplement, that is, it would be disregarded in line with the family income supplement.  Second, it should not interfere with the medical card for those who were returning to work.  While I acknowledge the T&aacute;naiste probably cannot give answers today, I ask her to take it on board when she is contemplating this initiative.  Another important point concerns separated parents who have joint custody.  What will happen in that case, as many people are separated and have joint custody?  Who will get this dividend for people returning to work?  Will it be the mother  or the father?  It it will be important for the T&aacute;naiste to take on board this point when considering the dividend.</p><p>  In her briefing to the joint committee, the T&aacute;naiste noted there is an additional incentive for families who are long-term unemployed to move from a social welfare payment into employment, including self-employment.  While we discussed this during the week, she was unable to advise on the position in respect of self-employment and I would appreciate it, were it possible to give an update in this regard.</p> <p>Will the Minister advise the committee what she means by long-term unemployed?  Is she saying somebody on jobseeker's benefit cannot avail of this?  Is that person considered short-term unemployed?  What does the Department consider to be long-term unemployed?  Are we talking about one year, two years or about people on jobseeker's allowance?  </p><p> The other issue relates to child care.  We will not get people back to work until we have proper, affordable and secure child care in place.  The Department of Social Protection and the Department of Children and Youth Affairs should work in tandem with the Department of Education and Skills because much of the child care should be provided in schools - after school care - because if one comes from a rural area, like I do, and one's town is ten to 15 miles away from the school one's child attends, one cannot get from one's job to the school to pick up one's child and take him or her to the child care centre.  If it was provided in the school, it would be very convenient for everybody.  Many schools have put preschool facilities in place which could be used for after-school child care.  Will the Minister work with the Department of education and Skills on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00200"><p>I would like to call two members who have not spoken.  Even though this might be slightly off the topic, I would like to be fair to the members concerned.  I have Deputy Butler's name but I want to call two members who have not spoken at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1079" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00300"><p>I spoke because I had to butt in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00400"><p>I know.  I have to chair this meeting as fairly as I can by taking all things into account, and I am doing that.  Several members have spoken more than once but some have not spoken at all.  I ask Deputy Keating to make-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1079" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00500"><p>I spoke on a separate issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00600"><p>I will bring Deputy Butler-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1079" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00700"><p>I did not speak in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00800"><p>Deputy Butler is listed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1012" speakername="Derek Keating" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K00900"><p>I join with the Chairman and the committee in welcoming and thanking the Minister.  Having listened to the debate over the past hour or so, it occurs to me that most fair-minded people could not have envisaged the Minister producing such a very positive report even three years ago, when one considers the mounting challenges the Minister faced in one of the most difficult jobs in government.  I am delighted the Minister included in her report a commitment to free travel.  As she said, there was considerable speculation and a bit of a frenzy a while ago that free travel would be eliminated, so this is a very welcome inclusion in the Minister's report.</p><p>  The Minister touched briefly on the whole area of combatting fraud.  She has made a very significant effort, with considerable success in that whole area.  What more can we do, or can the Minister give us a greater insight into what we can do?  We hear so many stories about non-Irish people flying into the country, availing of social welfare in one form or another, including child benefit, and then leaving.  How much of a handle has the Minister on that, or can she give us an insight into what more she has in mind?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01000"><p>I also thank the Minister for her excellent briefing today.  My question relates to a different subject, namely, carers.  It is estimated that the care given in the home each year comes to approximately &euro;4 billion.  It understandable that given the move away from institutional-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01100"><p>That is a more general issue, so I will not allow the Minister to answer until we get to that programme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01200"><p>I will pose the question now, but I understand that.</p><p>  It is understandable that given the move away from institutional care for cost, psychological and other reasons, the State should encourage care to be given in the home.  I understand the constraints and realise the Minister is inundated with requests at this time of the year in regard to increased spending.  I refer, in particular, to the Carers Association's submission to the Department and would like to hear the Minister's views on its request to formally acknowledge the half rate carer's grant as a core payment and on the respite grant. The Carers Association made a submission asking that the respite grant be paid twice yearly because it pointed out that the annual payment means that those who lose a loved one during the year would miss out on the June payment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01300"><p>We are going through this programme-by-programme, so the Minister will have to reply later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01400"><p>I understand that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01500"><p>To be fair to Senator Naughten, she spoke for the shortest amount of time of any member who has contributed so far, so I think I have allowed her a bit of leeway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1079" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01600"><p>I agree with the Minister that the JobsPlus scheme has been excellent.  Many business people and companies are accessing JobsPlus through my office, naturally enough being the local Deputy and having a direct line.  It has been very successful.</p><p>  I thank Deputy O'Dea for bringing up the issue of the self-employed.  The Mangan report proposed that instead of having the S class stamp, we bring in a new stamp at 5.5%.  ISME has come back with a report to us.  Everybody is in favour of bringing in a new stamp.  The elephant in the room is whether it would be voluntary or mandatory.  We have spoken to the Minister for Finance and the Minister has spoken to people in her Department.  We could introduce it in stages.  Currently, a self-employed person pays 4%.  We could introduce it for the first couple of years at 4.25%.  I would like the findings of the Mangan report implemented because we are going down the road of talking about pensions for self-employed people.  This is a huge area where we do not have social security, or social cover, for the self-employed.  This would bring in disability and sick pay for the first time for self-employed people.</p><p>  Now is the time to do this.  We are at a low base.  There are 340,000 self-employed people in this country.  The figure is rising and will continue to rise, given the economic forecasts projected for the next couple of years.  We propose that we look at this.  The only way it will work is if it is mandatory rather than voluntary.  </p><p>  The Minister has done great work in this area and she has lowered the threshold levels.  She has been excellent and has really helped self-employed people over the past couple of years but we need to push on with the findings of the Mangan report and put this stamp in place now.  We do not want to go back to the past and to what happened with self-employed people and the horrific stories and the horrific crash self-employed people in this country experienced. </p><p> Let us put this new stamp in place.  There is no reason not to do so as everybody wants it.  We just need somebody to step up to the plate and to say this is the way it will be.  Some 4.25% for the first couple of years would only be a 0.25% rise, which is very small.  We know retail businesses and other businesses are starting to come right.  This is only 0.25%, so why give it in revenue or income tax when one can put a little bit aside to ensure one's family has security at the end of the day and that there will be money coming into one's house?  Will the Minister push this with the other Ministers in Cabinet?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700011#K01700"><p>Further to the question I asked earlier, I would be the first to be very proud of the achievements of the Department to date in becoming an active Department, in trying to deal with unemployment and in actively engaging in the myriad of programmes it has.  In fairness, the Department has been transformed from being just a cheque issuing one to one which actively engages.</p><p>  The Minister referred to people on the ground.  The people in west Cork, including Mr. Sean Murphy and his team, are superb.  I get great support from those kinds of people with employers who are frustrated trying to get employees.  In the past week, I interviewed 12 random employers ranging from employers employing four to six people to 150 people and asked them what was their biggest concern ahead of the budget and what they would like me, as their representative, to feed into it.  Ten out of 12 of them raised the issue of trying to get people off the dole and trying to get them to work.  I do not think the issue is that welfare benefits are too generous.  The issue I am trying to get at here is simply the black market combined with welfare.  I wrote to the Economic Management Council expressing my concerns about this.  The Taoiseach passed this on to the Minister in the past day or two days, so I appreciate she might not have seen this but, hopefully, it will be discussed by it.</p> <p>There is an issue with which the Department of Social Protection will have to grapple which is that benefits cannot be looked at in isolation.  They must be coupled with the black market economy where people are working two or three days a week for cash and retaining their benefits in full.  It does not pay them to go into the workplace for &euro;360 or &euro;370 a week, the minimum wage jobs that are available, of which there are many and which are proving to be a difficulty for employers.  I hope in the run-up to the budget and in the submissions with which we are dealing that the Minister would take on board that particular problem of the combination of welfare and the black market.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00300"><p>I strongly support the recommendations in the Mangan report, which was raised by Deputy O'Dea, Deputy Butler and others.  Deputy Butler in particular has on a number of occasions at the committee strongly supported the extension of invalidity and permanent disability benefits to the self-employed.  I have seen some organisations representing the self-employed criticising the proposal - Deputy Butler knows who I mean - and I think they are tremendously short-sighted.  Where a medium-sized to larger firm is doing very well, it is relatively easy for the proprietors to pay for and invest in private pension benefits and schemes, which are very attractive from a tax point of view, as well as paying very hefty premiums for income maintenance in the event of illness.  That is generally way beyond the capacity of self-employed people operating on a small scale.  The social welfare system offers extraordinary value for money to self-employed people.  They pay 4% contributions, which is a very low rate of contribution.  For somebody in employment, the rate between them and the employer is 14.75%, so there is a very big gap.  I certainly think that as the economy recovers and as people come to retirement age and as retirement age looms, and it is only then, unfortunately, when they tend to become exercised about the issue, it will make even more sense, but it has to be on a funded basis.</p><p>  Ita Mangan, chairperson of the advisory group on tax and social welfare, has been asked in the committee and in other public venues about mandatory or voluntary contributions.  She and others with a great deal of experience in social welfare have said that there cannot in practice be a voluntary social welfare insurance scheme because what is being done from an insurance point of view is that a significantly large population is being covered in the hope that the number of claimants is a relatively small proportion of that population.  It has to be self-financing over a period of time.  The more we have a social welfare system where the financial resources flowing into it are adequate to meet the demands on and expectations of that system, the more sustainable the system will be.  That has always been a goal of mine.  It is a debate that continues.</p><p>  I am delighted to hear that Deputy Daly has been having a conversation with the Minister for Finance.  In the context of the extraordinary pressures that have been on the economy in recent years, I can understand that it is difficult to enter into fresh commitments.  The time is approaching when we can move forward and I am happy that a lot of work has been done in the Department.  This work has major IT implications and we have staff specifically looking at those.  As with all new systems in large-scale welfare or health areas, getting the IT simple and easy for people to use and ensuring it is absolutely reliable is the cornerstone.  The Department's senior staff, including the deputy secretary, have been involved - I think it is called the business management system - and I have learned to respect them, because the long-term planning of every element is critical.  I remember in earlier years, along with Deputy O'Dea and with Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh, taking a decision in respect of the Longford office and the carers' payments and so on that were coming from there.  I advised moving to much better quality IT platforms and I remember advising Deputies at the time that it would result in some delays.  In fact, the outcomes have been well worth it.  However, the same applies with moving over to a supplementary pension savings system.  It has to be very well organised and I am pleased that the deputy secretary, Anne Vaughan, who is present, has been very involved in guiding the business preparation for that.</p><p>  In relation to carers, Senator Naughton asked about the potential-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00400"><p>Could the Minister please wait until we get to that programme, which we should do very soon?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00500"><p>Okay, fine.  What other ones am I to do now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00600"><p>Any of the ones that were related to this particular programme, which is the working one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00700"><p>Does the fraud issue come within this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00800"><p>I suppose it does, because it covers all things.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700012#L00900"><p>The compliance on anti-fraud strategy that I launched earlier this year is a rolled out programme for 2014 to 2018, and if anybody wants a detailed copy, it is on the website or we can send it.  Under the additional measures in the strategy, I want to move to using what has become a very fashionable term - big data.  This means using predictive analytical techniques to enhance the identification of areas of the Department's activities, or individuals or locations, where there is a particular risk of fraud, therefore targeting investigations specifically at high risk areas.  Particularly at the request of the Committee of Public Accounts and the Comptroller and Auditor General, we carry out surveys on a phased basis of all the operational headings we have been discussing.  These are standard surveys of a population of 1,000 chosen at random following normal sampling techniques.  I expect that predictive analytical techniques will help the Department to reduce fraud.  Fraudsters are becoming more sophisticated all the time.  While the development of online systems has been a boon, it has also been a boon for people who engage in fraud.  Using predictive analytics and modelling the risk profiles are going to be very important.</p><p>  We are also enhancing debt recovery through a new debt management system which we will have live by the end of 2014.  This is another IT platform that we have been building.  On Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's point in this regard, the precise amount we recovered in 2013 was &euro;70.7 million, and the informal figures I have seen for this year are a little more than that.  These are very significant recoveries, and they have pretty much doubled since we adopted the new techniques.</p><p>  The other matter about which I have spoken at some length and which it has taken some time to implement is the secondment of 20 garda&iacute; to the Department's special investigations unit.  These officers will increase specifically the investigative capacity of the Department to prevent, detect and deter social welfare fraud.  There has been significant interest on the part of serving members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in working with the Department.  I am delighted by that, and we expect to have them in place in the next month or two.</p> <p> There was also a reference by Deputy Daly with regard to ports and airports.  I am happy to say that with the support of both the D&aacute;il and the Seanad, we changed that legislation two years ago so that social welfare officers at airports can question somebody if they believe that this person has been entering and re-entering the country in order to claim social welfare.  There have been a number of cases that were very widely reported by the media around the country, and I think the message has gone out that Ireland is not a soft touch.  There have been Irish people who went to work abroad and continued to claim, and there have also been people who immigrated to this country, then returned home and continued to claim illegally.  In some of these cases we found that people have had multiple claims because not only have they been claiming wrongly, but they have also been involved in identity fraud.  Again, some of those cases have been reported in the media.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M00200"><p>And on the black market question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M00300"><p>We make a point through the special investigation units, SIU, of tackling areas like street markets and street traders to check that control savings represent the value of prevented expenditure.  We have done a huge number of "feet on the street" campaigns.  That involves visiting industrial estates and calling to see that the people on the premises are registered for tax and insurance purposes.  We do that on construction sites and at street fairs and markets.  We also do it in general where, for instance, somebody's lifestyle and spending capacity seems to be entirely out of sync with somebody who is living on a social welfare payment.  For an honest trader or businessperson, it is galling to be undercut by people who are engaging in fraud.  That is not acceptable and if Deputy Daly can give us the names of any employees or employers affected by this, we will follow it up in a discreet manner.  We receive a very significant number of tip-offs and contacts from members of the public.  While some are misunderstandings, a significant number represent valuable information which is followed up by our SIU.  The Taoiseach has met a number of staff from the SIU.  He had a meeting with them last year in Government Buildings.  He also had an opportunity to talk one-on-one with myself and with senior staff from the Department about the things that could be done to improve the Department's detection and elimination of fraud risk.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M00400"><p>I would like to remind members that we have just over half an hour left.  Although we could spend hours speaking on this topic, we have six programmes and we have only moved through three at this stage.  I will give members a choice.  We could move on to the other programmes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M00700"><p>Or sit here and not get answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M00800"><p>That is not fair, Senator Moloney.  I am simply putting it to members that we have very little time and there is a limit to how much time I can spend on questions and answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01100"><p>It is a very simple question to the Minister and her officials as to what they consider the term "long-term unemployed" to mean.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01200"><p>Senator, please speak through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01300"><p>Through the Chair, it was a very simple question and I expect an answer.  I asked a question earlier to which I did not get an answer, but I let it be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01400"><p>Can the Minister answer the Senator's question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01500"><p>The official definition in Ireland of long-term unemployment for statistical and other purposes is anyone who has been unemployed for more than one year.  For Senator Moloney's benefit, I would point out that in my view, in most modern economies anyone who is unemployed for more than six months falls off a ledge in regard to the willingness by employers to give them serious consideration.  In America, employers speak about a "gap".  Employers and HR departments tend to look much less favourably on candidates who have a gap of more than six months on their CV than on candidates who have only recently become unemployed.  This is a major problem because huge numbers of people became unemployed through no fault of their own, and if six months becomes one year, then two years, their chances of returning to work become progressively slimmer.  This is why the education, training and work experience the Department of Social Protection provides are so important in getting people back on track and into work.</p><p>  I understand that there are to be statements of sympathy to the House on the death of former Taoiseach, Albert Reynolds.  Would it be possible to find out when this will occur, as I am offering sympathy on behalf of the Labour Party, and am thus under a time constraint.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01600"><p>If that is the case, we would have to reconvene the meeting at another time.  We will make inquiries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01700"><p>Will we have the opportunity to meet on another day to finish the other items?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01800"><p>We can, but we will first ascertain the situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M01900"><p>Subject to the Minister's availability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02000"><p>And subject to the agreement of all the members.  However, I would remind members that even if there is a second meeting not all questions can be answered, unfortunately, so members must prioritise questions.  If members are agreeable, we can move straight to the Illness, Disability and Carers programme.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02100"><p>We have only half an hour left anyway, despite events in the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02200"><p>I am prepared to stay, I just had that one query.  I understand the clerk will ascertain the position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02300"><p>My understanding is that we must be out of here by 3.30pm in any event.  We will have to adjourn then and come back another day.</p><p>  The wage subsidy scheme is part of the working age employment supports.  This scheme is designed to increase employment for people with disabilities.  Some &euro;10.9 million has been allocated to it.  The rate of unemployment among people with disabilities is far higher than the overall average rate.  Does the Minister have any statistics to hand on the rate of unemployment among people with disabilities?</p><p>  Does the Minister have details of the number of those who are receiving partial capacity benefit and the review of this benefit?  How much money has been allocated to the Youth Guarantee scheme for this year?  On the Gateway scheme, under which people must compulsorily take up a position which will pay them &euro;20 a week more than social welfare-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02400"><p>It is going very well, it is very popular.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02500"><p>There are 620 people on this scheme at the moment.  Were there many refusals to take part in the scheme and what sanctions, if any, were imposed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700013#M02600"><p>On the wage subsidy for people with a disability, in 2014, 1308 people received this to June 2014.  In total in 2013, 1100 people received the subsidy and in 2012, 1000 received it.  In 2011, 916 received it, and in 2010, 833 people received it.</p> <p>There are now 812 employers, to the end of June, involved in the scheme.  The situation is improving but nowhere near the rate of improvement that I, personally, would like to see. </p><p> We also have the disability activation programme in the BMW region which has been under way for the past two years.  I secured funding from the European Union for a pilot programme relating to people with a disability.  The programme particularly involves very interesting work among organisations working with young adults with a disability.  It has been an enormous help in generating public support in towns and areas and among local employers.  The work ranges from retail to hospitality and other services.  If it is difficult for an unemployed person who is fully able bodied to find work then it is even more difficult for somebody with a disability.</p><p> As people will know, in the education system we are now mainstreaming young people with a disability right up to leaving certificate level which I think is a great achievement for this country.  A small number of young people proceed to further education and third level and when they emerge they have another step to go to secure employment.  The numbers are increasing but I would like to see them increase much more.</p><p> We took over the employability services and we have done a lot of additional work.  I want to take the opportunity to say that we coach and mentor the person with a disability and we do the same work with the employer and the employer's human resources department.  One of the difficulties can be a lack of appreciation of the needs of the person with the disability and a lack of knowledge on the part of both the would-be employee and would-be employer of what precisely the needs are.  We have small capital grants as well as the wage subsidy.  The current budget for this year is &euro;10.85 million and to date, that is to the end of June, we have spent over &euro;6 million.</p><p> I have spoken here before about the European Youth Guarantee.  Our funding proposals are with the European Union.  We have engaged very extensively with the European Union on the youth employment initiative which is the vehicle the European Union uses specifically for people under 25 years of age.  Within the Department this is being used to part fund some of the activities within the Youth Guarantee.  </p><p> The Department proposes to claim &euro;41.4 million European Social Fund and &euro;35 million from the youth employment initiative over the period 2014-20, under the relevant operational programmes.  These claims will be submitted under arrangements with the Department of Education and Skills which is the certifying authority for these programmes for the EU in Ireland.</p><p> Let me outline the schemes which will be covered and the range of almost all of our activation schemes such as T&uacute;s, JobBridge, JobsPlus and the back to work enterprise allowance.  Expenditure relating to clients on these schemes, who are under 25 years of age, will be claimed for both the ESF and the youth employment initiative.  That means for every &euro;300 of eligible expenditure, &euro;100 of ESF and &euro;100 of the youth employment initiative will be refunded by the European Commission.</p><p> Obviously the administration and paperwork required for European funding is extremely challenging.  We have got most of ours done and completed but all of the countries have to go through the same process.  We are early movers on the whole thing.  We also got the OECD to look at what we were doing and there has been significant support.  A very successful pilot has been under way for some period in Ballymun.</p><p> In terms of our contact with employers and the Labour Market Council, we have had numbers of employers, such as Diageo, specifically working with ourselves and local educational institutions to provide FETAC level training in retail and hospitality.  There are also a number of the supermarkets on the retail side and they are taking on young people who are under 22 years for the main part, and subsequently employing quite a lot of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00200"><p>I remind the Minister that statements will take place at 4.54 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00300"><p>I can stay then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00400"><p>We can resume the meeting in the morning but at that stage we would just talk about administration and so on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00500"><p>I will try to get through it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00600"><p>We agreed the timetable at the beginning of the meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00700"><p>Are we dealing with illness and carers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00800"><p>We agreed a timetable at the beginning of this meeting which would have us out of here at 3.30 p.m.  We can still do this but that is up to members.  We can come back tomorrow if people prefer but we have until 3.30 p.m.  Do members agree to move on to illness and disability?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N00900"><p>I had already indicated.  I can assure the Chairman that my question will be very brief as the Minister knows my position on JobBridge and other initiatives.  What is next year's target for JobsPlus in terms of numbers?  It has been a successful programme and is one of the schemes that we should encourage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N01000"><p>Is that the Deputy's question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N01100"><p>That is my question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N01200"><p>I have a slightly complicated answer.  We originally had an allocation of 2,000 for this year.  As the Deputy will know, we only launched the scheme this time last year and it takes time for any scheme, in terms of word of mouth and spreading the news, to penetrate.  It has been so popular that we raised the allocation of 2,000 places for this year to 2,400 earlier in the year.  We have now exceeded that figure.  We are slightly under 3,000 and I anticipate at least that figure, plus.</p><p>  We have a very flexible allocation.  Let us look at JobsPlus and T&uacute;s.  At any one time there are about 7,700 people on a monthly basis on T&uacute;s and at any one time there are somewhere around 6,500 people undertaking JobBridge.  I anticipate that over the next year or two, the JobsPlus scheme will move strongly.  We have moved from a standing start this time last year to 3,000 places now.  I would anticipate a similar demand for both the JobBridge and T&uacute;s programmes, which are very popular.</p><p>  Deputy O'Dea asked about Gateway.  We have a significant number of counties where county managers and their staff have initiated the Gateway scheme, together with local councils.  As I speak there are 782 people participating in Gateway, which I am happy to say.  </p><p>  Deputy Jim Daly is here.  Gateway is essentially the same as the community employment scheme except that it is offered by county councils.  Gateway has the same terms and conditions - 19 hours and an extra &euro;20-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N01300"><p>There is no specific training budget so it is not the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N01400"><p>It depends on capacity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700014#N01500"><p>The demand for the scheme is very strong.  After the floods in Limerick, young family men in St. Mary's Park asked me if they could go on a scheme.  They did so because they wanted to help with the work in Limerick after the disastrous floods last year.  In this instance Sinn F&eacute;in should wake up and smell the coffee.  There is a huge pent up demand for people, particularly former construction workers.  Many of them are in relatively isolated areas.  They are either on their own in a house or are in a more isolated rural area.  These people want to get involved.  The scheme is a pathway back to work, like lots of other pathways.</p> <p>It is exactly the same as the social employment schemes initiated in the 1980s and the community employment schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00200"><p>It is not exactly the same as community employment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00300"><p>I am disappointed -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00400"><p>If the Minister even read her own documentation on the conditions tied to it, she would see that it is not exactly the same as community employment schemes across the country.  If it was, I would support it.  The difference is that the training budget is not included.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00500"><p>In Cork county more than 100 people are anxious to take up this opportunity.  I understand that some people in parties who wear badges about being left wing and for working people oppose this.  I do not know whether the Deputy's party is involved in that particular county.  I am not going to enter that discussion but, for heaven's sake, give people a chance to get back to work.  That is what it is about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00600"><p>I have no problem with that.  I would encourage it if it was a proper scheme.  It is not a proper scheme, it is a scam.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00700"><p>I asked a specific question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00800"><p>It is not an employment scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O00900"><p>Please speak through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01000"><p>What is the training budget?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01100"><p>I will answer the Deputy if he gives me an opportunity to do so.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government has sanctioned 150 acting-up allowances for existing local authority staff to support the supervision of Gateway.  That has been agreed with the trade unions and management in the county councils.  I do not know if the Deputy's party colleagues are aware of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01200"><p>I am aware of it and I know exactly where they are coming from.  They are not additional staff; they are diverted from other work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01300"><p>There is Lotto funding worth millions of euro for training grants for participants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01400"><p>Through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01500"><p>It is not available for these schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01600"><p>Sorry, from the dormant accounts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01700"><p>The Department has provided &euro;2 million for health and safety training, for specific tasks and for personal protective equipment.  Can the Deputy open his eyes and go out to visit some of the fine work that has been done by people who would otherwise be sitting at home?  When the local authorities begin to recruit again, which I am sure will happen before too long given the way in which the recovery is proceeding, the people who have gained valuable experience through Gateway will be in a good position to apply for these jobs and be seriously interviewed for them, unless the Deputy's party has a problem with people who have been long-term unemployed getting back to work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01800"><p>By the time they come around there will have been the six-month gap that the T&aacute;naiste mentioned earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O01900"><p>Deputy O'Dea had a specific question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02000"><p>Some 61 people are due to start this week and Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh wants to stop them.  I think he is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02100"><p>I do not want to stop them.  I want to encourage them by making sure they have proper jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/994" speakername="Jim Daly" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02200"><p>The Deputy's party wants to stop them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02300"><p>No, I want them to have proper jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02400"><p>I want to bring in Deputy O'Dea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02500"><p>I refer to the question I asked initially.  I do not doubt that a number of people who are unemployed want to get on the scheme but my understanding is that people are selected for and sent on the scheme by the Department and that sanctions are imposed if a person refuses to go on a scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02700"><p>Have there been instances of refusals or sanctions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02800"><p>I will get the exact figures for the Deputy.  The scheme also allows local authorities to take on people who approach them, provided that they qualify, namely, they have been unemployed for the requisite period.  A number of Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il Deputies have reported that people approached them to seek to go on schemes.  We provide for that but there is also an element of random selection.  The reason for this is very simple.  Sometimes when people are called to a random selection, they are too busy to make time to drop down to their local Intreo offices.  If they are that occupied we need to find out why.  Sometimes they have even left the jurisdiction.  The random selection is very helpful.  Some people who are randomly selected, particularly in respect of T&uacute;s, are delighted to be invited because they have never seen themselves as being able to work in their local community and do something valuable.  The random selection is helpful.</p><p>  According to figures from the middle of July, the data collected in respect of the 6,430 jobseekers who were selected to date for Gateway indicate that six jobseekers were subject to sanctions resulting in the temporary disallowance of up to a maximum of nine weeks of jobseeker's payments.  A further 80 jobseekers' claims have been closed following engagements between officials and jobseekers.  In some of these cases a different payment was deemed more appropriate to the individual's circumstances and processes are ongoing in a number of cases which are not represented.  If we make contact with somebody through our activation process and he or she does not respond, we follow that up.  In some cases there are good reasons for this.  The individuals concerned may be ill, for example.  However, we want a response from them and, as people show up to collect payments, I see no reason they cannot show up to discuss an opportunity.</p><p>  In regard to these opportunities, approximately 10,000 people are in receipt of enterprise allowances and 20,000 are on the back-to-education allowance.  There is a huge flow of people in and out of these allowances.  In respect of the numbers on JobBridge and T&uacute;s, to date more than 32,000 people have been on JobBridge schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O02900"><p>I will stop the T&aacute;naiste there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03000"><p>If people do not show up, we call them back and if they do not have a reasonable explanation -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03100"><p>Members agreed a time limit of 20 minutes for this subject.  As we have spent more than 20 minutes discussing it, we will proceed to deal with illness, disability and carer's allowances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03200"><p>Did the Minister receive the submission prepared recently by the Carers Association and how does she intend to respond to it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03300"><p>Senator Naughton also raised that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03400"><p>It arose in the context of the pre-budget forum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03500"><p>The submission contained a number of practical suggestions, some of which would not cost much.  Some of them would even save money for the Department in the long term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700015#O03600"><p>With regard to the carer's allowance, I ask the T&aacute;naiste to give her commitment to retain the half-rate carer's allowance in the forthcoming budget.  With regard to the disability allowance, problems arise in the processing of applications.  If the application is refused on medical grounds, the appeal can take up to ten to 12 months.  If the applicant wins the appeal, he or she may have to wait months for means testing because it was not carried out in the first instance.</p><p>  I am also encountering problems involving people who are very sick but are finding it difficult to access invalidity pensions when the two-year period for illness benefit expires.  They cannot return to work because their GPs will not allow them to do so but they have nowhere to turn to because the medical officer is saying they are fit for alternative work, which is not quite true.</p><p>  The third issue I wish to raise may seem minor but it is a big issue to some people.  When one applies for illness benefit, the only choice on the form is in regard to whether it should be paid to the employer or into a bank account.</p> <p>However, there is certainly no facility to go through the post offices, which we are trying to keep alive and kicking.  Perhaps the Department could examine that in order to give people a choice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00200"><p>As regards the number of appeals on disability, at the beginning of 2013 there were over 4,000 appeals on hand.  By the beginning of 2014, a year later, that figure had gone down to just over 3,000.  That was a fall of 1,000.  I am happy to say that as of 1 September, the number has dropped to 1,700.</p><p>  We operate an open-ended repeat review system.  We have been looking at the letter that is sent out and people have a legal right to enter an appeal.  Very often, as Senators know, they will come to a public representative after they have lodged an appeal.  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh and I have discussed this matter on a number of occasions.  They would be much better off getting better medical evidence on their condition.  There are a lot of new Deputies in the House this session, so I keep telling people to leave the appeal until the last minute.</p><p>  We have a facility, particularly in a serious case, to withdraw the appeal if the amount of evidence that has become available is more significant.  The office does that regularly.  It should be remembered that the appeals process is a legal one.  It is like planning appeals - once one goes into that process one is better off having pre-planning discussions so that one has cleared out all of the difficulties and one knows the mind of the local authority on planning.  Similarly, I would strongly suggest to members of the joint committee to get that additional information that may make the difference for people to lodge an appeal.  Some doctors, even though they may be much loved by their patients, do not give very detailed information that sufficiently supports the claim a person is making.  That is the factual situation. </p><p>  I am delighted to say that the number of appeals on hand has fallen dramatically.  However, if it is a question of introducing fresh information that the Senator experienced in this area, as I know she has, I would seek to withdraw the appeal and have a fresh review instead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00300"><p>The Appeals Office is quite good at returning it for a review without having to withdraw it, so that works as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00400"><p>Yes.  That is because we have improved the platforms and have really invested in technology at the Appeals Office.  In the context of the recession, there was a vast increase in the number of applications and appeals.  If one meets an application at an early stage and it is not successful, I would advise members to seek to obtain more appropriate and stronger evidence to support the application, rather than having to go into the appeals process which, by its nature as a legal procedure, tends to be a bit longer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00500"><p>I have a quick query on that because people seem to be constantly seeking advice on appeals.  In the event of additional information becoming available, do they send it to the appeals office or the review office?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00600"><p>Staff are aware - and the legend is - that if one withholds some of the stronger medical information until the appeal it will help the case.  I think that goes back to a period when the times were a lot longer.  My personal recommendation is that if one has the evidence and one is still in the application process or review - we allow multiple reviews which very few social welfare systems do - one should use it when it becomes available and, if possible, avoid having to go into the appeals system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00700"><p>What I and other Deputies have found is that sometimes the appeal is lodged and that is when there is a delay in obtaining medical information.  There is a huge problem in getting letters from consultants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P00900"><p>It could be two months down the road in the appeals process at that stage, so does a person give the information to the appeals office or back to the Department?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01000"><p>As with the domiciliary care allowance, we looked at it and significantly reduced the waiting times.  We also ran a number of information seminars for Deputies and their staff.  If the Deputy feels that would be helpful, given the IT changes and other reforms in the Department, I would be happy to arrange that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01100"><p>I would appreciate it.  We can look at that in the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01200"><p>Would the committee let me know through the Chairperson?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01300"><p>Yes, we will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01400"><p>We will arrange it in the AV room.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01500"><p>I suggest that members should ask any outstanding questions now so that we can finish our business today.  I am sure people have many questions at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01600"><p>I have three brief outstanding questions.  The report of the child and family income supplement advisory group recommended dramatic changes in child benefit.  Where are we with that?  Second, has the Minister taken any decision on the rent supplement caps?  Third, would the Minister consider a suggestion that the names of people who receive rent supplement from the State, that is landlords, should be published?  It is taxpayers' money so I suggest the recipients' names should be published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01700"><p>I have two brief questions.  One concerns the Children's Rights Alliance which made a specific appeal about the habitual residency condition concerning child benefit.  The CRA said the State was out of touch with Article 2 of the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, which deals with non-discriminatory aspects.  I ask the Minister to examine that matter.</p><p>  Has any consideration been given to increasing the PRSI rate on high wages - that is, the portion over &euro;100,000?  We are out of sync with other countries in that regard.  Such a move would significantly increase the social insurance fund and that would allow some recovery for the fund.  </p><p>  I have a lot of other questions but I will table them as parliamentary questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01800"><p>I will probably put the Minister on the spot in saying this but I hope she will not allow herself to be pressurised into making cuts in her Department to supplement other Departments.  Social welfare has taken enough hits, so the Minister should avoid any more.  If she is in a position at some stage to reverse cuts, she should do so.  I never want to go back to a position where there were giveaways prior to elections because that is what got the country into this mess.  At some stage, however, when we have a surplus, we might consider restoring the free telephone allowance for carers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700016#P01900"><p>On the child and family income supplement, following the large amount of detailed, informative and good work that the Mangan group has undertaken, we have arrived at a general agreement to support families with children and, in particular, the activation of proposals.</p> <p>We are maintaining the child benefit system.  What we have significantly increased levels of funding this year and last for family income supplement as people go back to work.  My proposal is to continue that policy and as I said earlier to have the additional payment to families with children who have been unemployed.  That work is ongoing.  Senator Moloney raised a number of valid questions and we will take them into consideration as the work on the scheme is being planned.  That is the reform path.</p><p> Child benefit payments are a significant payment to families, many of whom are in the age cohort of those who are troubled by mortgage debt.  Cash flow is very important to the budget of those families, particularly those with two or more children.  Child benefit is paid to families irrespective of whether they are in work or out of work and is paid directly to the caring parent.  I propose to continue with the child benefit payment structure.  A very important feature of the payment is that the cash flow is getting to the children.</p><p> We have revised the family income supplement scheme.  It is now working in a much faster and better way than was the case before the improvements to IT.  I hope the qualified child increase changes, whereby people will retain a portion of them over a period of time as a working family dividend, will be attractive.  I am conscious of the fact that we have roughly 80,000 people on the live register.  In the main these are men who lost their jobs during the construction collapse or lost jobs in areas related to construction and many of those men are in family relationships with children.  I hope that this will be a significant assistance to that group of people, as we see the construction industry slowly but surely increasing its activity levels.  </p><p> We are reviewing the rent caps at present.  On previous occasions I spoke to Deputies O'Dea and &Oacute; Snodaigh about the emergency protocol which came officially into force during June.  That has worked very well.  At this point, more than 100 cases that we know about have been addressed and sorted out in relation to rent increases by landlords.  A number of parliamentary questions have been tabled on this topic, but the outcome is working very well.  I know that Deputy O'Dea on a previous occasion spoke about it being extended to Limerick.  I understand the community welfare officers in Limerick are pretty much available to apply the same system.  There has not been anything like the number of cases there as in Dublin but again, there is an intervention to support a family with a difficulty with their landlord.</p><p> As I have said, the way to address this difficulty in the short or medium-term is to increase the housing supply.  We have had extensive discussions with Dublin City Council on ending the policy of boarding up vacant houses and putting the contents of the house or the apartment in a skip.  If we can bring those apartments and houses back into the available housing stock for families, it will assist a significant number of people over the remainder of this year and the first half of the next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700017#Q00200"><p>On the issue of the free telephone allowance for carers, the Minister probably cannot answer that now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700017#Q00300"><p>I am not in a position to answer that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700017#Q00400"><p>I would imagine not but I am only raising it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700017#Q00500"><p>My lips are sealed as regards the budget, with the exception of the agreement that the Taoiseach and I reached in public.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2014091700017#Q00600"><p>I thank everybody and if members are happy that will conclude our discussion.  I propose with the agreement of members to deal with the private business of this meeting at our meeting next week.  We will possibly meet a little earlier on Wednesday, 24 September.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.183" nospeaker="true" time="15:15:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 3.35 p.m. until 1 p.m. on Wednesday, 24 September 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.184" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.185" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Alan Farrell, Senator Martin Conway, Deputy SeÃ¡n Kenny, Senator Denis O'Donovan, Deputy PÃ¡draig Mac Lochlainn, Senator Katherine Zappone. Deputy Finian McGrath,</p><p>In attendance: Deputies Jerry Buttimer and SeÃ¡n Ã“ FearghaÃ­l.</p><p>DEPUTY DAVID STANTON IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.186" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700002#A00100">National Disability Authority: Chairperson Designate</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Deputies Anne Ferris and Marcella Corcoran Kennedy and Senator Ivana Bacik.</p><p>  The purpose of the meeting is to have an engagement with Ms Helen Guinan, the chairperson designate of the National Disability Authority.  On behalf of the joint committee, I thank Ms Guinan for appearing before us.  Members look forward to hearing from and engaging with her in this session.  We will first hear a short opening statement from Ms Guinan followed by questions from members.  </p><p>  I draw Ms Guinan's attention to the fact that witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give this committee.  If, however, a witness is directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and the witness continues to so do, the witness is entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of his or her evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  </p><p>  Members are reminded that under salient rulings of the Chair, they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official by name in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I invite Mr. Guinan to make her opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.188" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700002#A00300"><p>I am honoured to be nominated by the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, as chairperson designate of the National Disability Authority.  I am looking forward to the challenge and the opportunity to oversee the important work the authority does as the independent statutory advisory body to the Minister on disability policy and practice and in promoting universal design.</p><p>  I have spent many years working with or on behalf of children and young adults with intellectual, physical and sensory disabilities.  I recently retired from my post as principal of St. Paul&rsquo;s special school in Cork.  I have been closely involved over many years in policy development and implementation at national level with a number of organisations, including the National Council for Curriculum and Assessment, National Council for Special Education and National Federation of Voluntary Bodies.  I greatly enjoyed the opportunity to gain a national and international perspective on advancements and improvements for persons with disabilities.  My grounding as a teacher and principal in a busy school meant I always had an eye on the practical implementation of the policies and strategies in question.</p><p>  As principal of a large school for students with highly complex needs, my priorities were to lead, encourage, counsel and guide the immediate and wider school community towards providing the highest standard of education and care for our students.  Parents and families were a central part of that community, which also included the invaluable work of multidisciplinary team members. </p><p>  The National Disability Authority, under the National Disability Authority Act 1999, is an independent public body whose principal function is to provide evidence based information and advice to government on policy and practice relevant to the lives of persons with disabilities.  The authority is in a unique position in that it sits independently of the disability sector, Departments and State agencies.  It is not a charity or service provider, nor is it a representative or campaigning organisation.  It has, therefore, a critical role to be an independent adviser.  It has a duty to ensure that the information and advice it delivers to the Minister for Justice and Equality, other Ministers and officials are informed by robust evidence, research and knowledge of the lived experience of persons with disabilities and an understanding of the policy context. </p><p>  While the overarching role of the National Disability Authority is to provide advice, other functions include providing advice on co-ordination of services to people with disabilities, undertaking or commissioning research and developing standards and guidelines as well as monitoring their implementation.  The authority has an important role as an honest broker, working with the relevant stakeholders to identify realistic and achievable actions to progress the inclusion agenda in line with national strategies and international conventions.</p><p>  The National Disability Authority also has the highly interesting role of promoting universal design, which refers to the design of places, products, services, information, communications and information technology in order that they can be readily accessed, used or understood by people, regardless of their age, size, ability or disability.  I am conscious that other countries are keen to follow the operation of the centre for excellence in universal design and that the centre is playing a key role in standards development at national and international levels.</p><p>  The National Disability Authority's strategic plan sets out the main areas of work in which it is engaged.  Key goals include the provision of guidance on the implementation of the national disability strategy, which covers all persons with disabilities and most policy areas.  Disability needs to be embedded into all mainstream policy and mainstream services.  While we are at an early stage of this journey, the national disability strategy can provide the means of driving this forward.  Another key area of work is in supporting the implementation of the significant change programme in disability services aimed at putting the person at the centre of the service and supporting people with disabilities to live ordinary lives in ordinary places.  People with disabilities need to be enabled to choose where and how they live in order that they can participate to their full potential in the community alongside everyone else.  A further key goal of the National Disability Authority is to work on a ten-year comprehensive employment strategy.  Such a strategy could deliver real change in the lives of those who have or acquire a disability.  Other major areas of work include the provision of advice on ratifying and implementing the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities and promoting universal design.</p><p>  The board of the National Disability Authority, which I have been asked to chair, has a majority of people with disabilities, their representatives, families or carers.  This will ensure our work is guided by people's real, lived experience of disability.  As with all State bodies, the board is subject to the highest standards of ethics and of governance, including the code of practice on the governance of State bodies and public procurement rules.</p> <p>I look forward to chairing the board and providing strategic direction to the executive as the National Disability Authority, NDA, plays its role in guiding policy and practice that can enable people with disabilities in Ireland to participate in Irish society as equal citizens.   My years of experience in motivating people from a wide range of backgrounds and experience to work collaboratively towards excellent service development and provision will be useful in my role as chair of the National Disability Authority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00200"><p>That was very interesting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00300"><p>I welcome Ms Guinan before the committee and wish her well in her work with the National Disability Authority, NDA.  I have some questions on the points raised in the submission.  Perhaps I am showing my bias as an ex-principal but when I saw that Ms Guinan has been a teacher in a busy special school, I thought it was good to see somebody dealing with the practical implementation of policies on the ground.  Mistakes have been made when people were appointed who may not necessarily have had experience on the ground.  I welcome Ms Guinan's appointment.  In her submission, the witness mentioned parents and families as a central part of the community in the school.  Will that be a strong focus in the NDA and its future outlook?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.192" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00400"><p>Yes, although I should qualify that answer by saying I have not yet taken up the role.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00500"><p>Is it Ms Guinan's vision?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.194" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00600"><p>Yes, it would always be part of that.  Families are a central part of everything that happens.  When something happens to a person with disabilities, there are repercussions throughout a family and even in a community.  They form a central part of the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00700"><p>In her submission Ms Guinan also makes the point that disability needs to be embedded in all mainstream policy and services.  Have we moved on with the mainstreaming process compared with ten or 15 years ago or have we remained static?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.196" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00800"><p>We have certainly moved on.  The supports needed in the mainstreaming process are critical; it is one area where much work still needs to be done.  It is all very well to say that mainstreaming is necessary - as it absolutely is - but unless supports are there, it can become really difficult for people delivering any service to accommodate particularly severe needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B00900"><p>We are discussing and designing policies and services and I mentioned earlier the parents and families of children or young adults with disabilities.  Will they play a vital role in the development of the general national disability strategy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.198" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01000"><p>That is a strength of the National Disability Authority as it can speak to everybody involved.  It must consider everybody's opinion and not just one particular group over another.  It must be an informed and research-based process.  There would be a balance of the real, lived experience with the international and national research.  There is a place for everything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01100"><p>Ms Guinan also mentioned that the authority is responsible for advising on ratifying and implementing the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  There is ongoing debate among legislators and disability groups about ratification, as many want to ratify the convention.  Some argue that it would be better to put the services in place first and then ratify it.  What is Ms Guinan's advice or what is best international practice?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.200" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01200"><p>There is a division among countries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01300"><p>There is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.202" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01400"><p>I would not be qualified to make a judgment on that just yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01500"><p>These are early days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.204" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01600"><p>These are early days for me anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01700"><p>I strongly advise that we ratify this and get on as much as possible.  We already have some elements in place, which is good.  Importantly, Ms Guinan indicated that the board of the NDA has a majority of people with disabilities, their representatives, families and carers.  I welcome this important step.  That is not the case for many organisations dealing with disability or service organisations.  I urge that this point be considered in a national disability strategy, especially if it takes in mainstreaming or including people.  We recently witnessed a row at the Central Remedial Clinic at Clontarf.  It has a brilliant new board but there is a lack of people with disabilities on that board.  I welcome that the NDA has a majority of such people, and although that is refreshing, we must up our game with the issue.  I urge the NDA to focus on that as a broad policy issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.206" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01800"><p>I will bring that back with me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B01900"><p>As Members we are being lobbied by the carer representative associations about cutbacks in recent years.  In fairness to all Members, regardless of political perspectives, we have much empathy with carers.  They do heroic work while giving love, support and sustenance to their dependants.  We want to get to a position where these carers can be fully supported.  Leaving aside empathy and support, the reality is that carers save the State a fortune in money.  What is Ms Guinan's vision of how carers in families will be supported by the disability authority?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.208" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B02000"><p>As I have not started in the role yet, I do not have an intimate knowledge of it.  All I can do is say that I will bring back that keen observation.  That issue is close to everybody's heart.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B02100"><p>Another issue is the mobility allowance and the motorised transport grant.  Both of those schemes were suspended because the Ombudsman found them to act outside the law with regard to equality legislation because they were not available to elderly people.  When the Department considered the matter, the estimate to deal with it came to approximately &euro;500 million and that would not be economically sustainable.  The issue has dragged on for quite a while.  I have a particular interest as the committee which I chair, dealing with public oversight, works with the Ombudsman.  We have brought in a previous Secretary General of the Department of Health on a number of occasions, as well as Ministers.  Will Ms Guinan seek to take an active interest in the matter, as it seems these are lost schemes for those who wish to avail of them?.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.210" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B02200"><p>Yes.  I thank the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1054" speakername="Se&aacute;n &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700003#B02300"><p>I thank Ms Guinan for her presentation, which was clear and concise.  I have no doubt she will be appointed to the role and we wish her well.  All of us value the work by the NDA, which fulfils a vital role in advising the Minister on the disability area.  I have a question which relates to Ms Guinan's area of expertise, as I know she has worked in special education.  Throughout the country there is a growing desire on the part of parents to achieve inclusion for children with disabilities, and inclusion and integration is important for parents of children with special needs and for the broader school community, as it can learn just as much from the process.</p><p>  It appears that within the Department of Education and Skills there is no strategic plan at all for the provision of educational opportunities.  Within schools I have seen preschool provision but no primary places in the same building.  I have seen towns where primary schools have provided specialised units but post-primary schools have no provision and, much more importantly, no plan for any provision.</p> <p>Given the investment made over the years at primary level, many of those children are progressing to post-primary level, as we would wish.  We will see people criss-cross the country seeking school places that are not available in local communities.  These children should be able to attend school locally with their siblings, friends and neighbours.  Education does not feature prominently in the opening statement made by the National Disability Authority, NDA, but this may be due to bias arising from where that organisation is coming from.  Significant work must be done in the area of education to compel the Department of Education and Skills to implement a strategic plan for the provision of integrated services in existing schools as this is not occurring at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.213" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00200"><p>The National Disability Authority has a representative on the board of the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, and I am a council member.  I know the NCSE is working very hard with the Department of Education and Skills on the provision of services for and the inclusion of children with disabilities.  Much work is being done on this and the NDA is feeding into the process.  I am keen to keep an eye on this area as I agree that gaps exist, though they are being identified.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1021" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kenny" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00300"><p>I thank Ms Guinan for her opening statement and I wish her every success in her new role.  I have some questions on access to services for people with disabilities.  I am a member of the Committee on Transport and Communications and my interests therefore overlap.  Some public bus service operators still do not provide wheelchair access.  Safety is an issue for people with disabilities and an incident this summer in Raheny, where I live, comes to mind.  An elderly blind woman went to the DART station, stumbled off the platform in front of a train and was killed.  This was a tragedy and, though it was the kind of thing that can happen, it raises the question of the safety of people with visual impairment and physical disabilities.  Perhaps the National Disability Authority could address these matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00400"><p>I congratulate Ms Guinan on her pending appointment.  Knowing her CV I do not doubt she will do a very good job.  The Government has asked the NDA to create a ten-year employment strategy, and I think the best thing for a person with a disability is a job that allows him or her to contribute to society, pay taxes and feel equal.  Is the creation and implementation of an employment strategy important to the NDA?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.216" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00500"><p>Yes, it is important to the NDA.  Having spoken to the director of the National Disability Authority, I am aware the employment strategy is very high on the agenda.  Much work is being done under the national disability strategy to move the ten-year employment strategy forward.  The need for and importance of the strategy is recognised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00600"><p>I suggest the committee invite Ms Guinan to return in a year to give an update on progress on the ten-year employment strategy and the other work that will be done by her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00700"><p>It might be appropriate to link that invitation to the publication of the National Disability Authority's annual report as it will give us a document to focus on.  When is the annual report due?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.219" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00800"><p>The board will meet at the end of this month.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C00900"><p>In that case Ms Guinan may be back here before she knows it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01000"><p>I thank Ms Guinan for the presentation and I congratulate her and wish her the best.  I am delighted to see that she has a background in education and experience at the coalface.  In my family life, in the past year and a half, I have begun to deal with the issue of coping with disability and I can see very clearly how far we have to go on priorities in the strategic plan.  Ms Guinan mentioned the disability strategy, living independently in the community and universal design of the environment.  Progress on universal design of the environment will impact significantly on whether we can progress the notion of living independently in the community.  The concepts are very much connected.  Can Ms Guinan comment further on universal design?  Does a centre operate to produce standards and so on?  Are efforts being made to reach out to industry and those working in this area on the matter of universal design?  In my experience technology relating to sight loss is way behind and I hope the industries in this area are working towards improvements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.222" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01100"><p>It is my understanding that efforts are being made to reach out to architects, building designers, product designers and so on.  People now come to the National Disability Authority and the universal design centre seeking information, and this is a measure of the respect that exists for the advice given.  On one level this is wonderful, but it presents challenges for the future relating to retirements that are forthcoming and the skills sets involved.  This must be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01200"><p>How many people are working in the universal design centre?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.224" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01300"><p>I am not sure because I am referring to the work of both the National Disability Authority and the universal design centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01400"><p>I would like this committee to be briefed by the people who work in the universal design centre to learn more of the work they do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01500"><p>I support that suggestion because I was asked to launch the tourism toolkit that was produced.  Many representatives from the hotel industry attended the event at the Guinness Storehouse and I was very impressed by what they were trying to achieve.  Much of it was common sense but sometimes common sense must be tabulated and disseminated to be acted upon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.227" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01600"><p>I know that they are achieving international fame and I look forward to learning more about this aspect of things.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01700"><p>Perhaps Ms Guinan could arrange a briefing note to be sent on this to give the committee some information beforehand.</p><p>  Autism is an issue about which Ms Guinan probably knows more than me.  It seems an increasing number of children are presenting with the condition.  Does the NDA have plans for an autism strategy similar to that in Scotland?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.229" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700004#C01800"><p>It is a question of reaching a balance between the specific needs of a person with autism and the wide range of needs across the spectrum.</p> <p>If mainstream is to accommodate the needs of people with disabilities it must look at the specific needs and generally be able to accommodate all needs, however severe or mild, and work towards not excluding anybody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00200"><p>The strategy in Scotland is from cradle to grave, right through to housing, employment and all other services.  I do no know what work has been done by the authority in that area but we would be interested to find that out because it is an issue we are all presented with many times.  As Deputy &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l said, and I agree with him, the issue of second level schools not having ASD centres and so on and that children have to travel by bus far away from their home place are not what we want.  Another issue which is of interest is that some schools will have centres but others refuse to have anything to do with it.  We need to encourage all second level schools to play their part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.232" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00300"><p>There is also the issue of the inclusion, apart from special classes, of children into the mainstream classes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00400"><p>Integration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.234" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00500"><p>-----and the supports that needs to be in place for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00600"><p>That is not only for autism but Down's syndrome and all similar conditions.  Will the Disability Act 2005, the EPSEN Act 2004 and the sectoral plans be part of the progress report that Ms Guinan will present to us in a few weeks' time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.236" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00700"><p>I will know more about that next Monday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00800"><p>As the EPSEN Act has not been fully implemented yet, perhaps the witness would look at that.  How long is Ms Guinan's tenure of office?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.238" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D00900"><p>I understand it is three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01000"><p>If Ms Guinan were to appear before the committee in three years what would she like to tell the committee she had achieved?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.240" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01100"><p>I would hope, if the country is out of the recession, that the needs of people with disabilities would be to the forefront in that recovery and that it will mean, as Senator Conway said, the employment of such people will not be forgotten, that all services would put a cross-sectoral support in place and that various sectors would work together collaboratively under the national disability strategy.  There is a framework for it and it is matter of getting everybody to pull together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01200"><p>My final question is on mental health issues.  Does Ms Guinan see herself taking a huge interest in that whole area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.242" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01300"><p>I am looking forward to learning more about that area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01400"><p>We have two invitations for Ms Guinan.  One is to come in with her CEO to speak about the annual report following its publication and also to give a briefing on the Centre for Excellence in Universal Design to enable us find out a little more about the work being done there.  Are there any further points or questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01500"><p>May I ask one quick question?  I have listened to an interesting debate between the Chairman and Ms Guinan on autism and education.  I am concerned at something that has been happening in the past seven or eight years.  If a school in a community is really good about including children with disabilities and there is another mainstream school about two miles away, there is a huge move for all the children with disabilities to go to the former school because it has the resources and the proper equipment, while the more academic children go to the other school.  Part of Ms Guinan's brief is to advise the Minister on mainstreaming and bringing us all together.  That is happening in some parts of the country and I am concerned about it.  It is like a division in some schools.</p><p>  The more academic children will want to go to college and the children with special needs are in another school down the road.  I am concerned about that issue in the long term.  Perhaps Ms Guinan would think about this in terms of advising the Minister as there could be more division in society, particularly at second level.  The position is better at primary level.   As soon as the word gets out that a school has an autistic unit or a unit for children with Down's syndrome, another school in the area has all the children who are getting As and Bs in the junior certificate examination.  I am concerned about the division and would ask Ms Guinan to keep an eye on this in the next couple of years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.245" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01600"><p>The work started by the then Minister, Deputy Quinn, on admissions and enrolment policy will have an impact whereby schools will not be able to refuse admission and the barriers will be removed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1017" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01700"><p>A mix is always good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01800"><p>Deputy Buttimer wishes to come in on that point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D01900"><p>May I make a brief point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D02000"><p>Yes, the Deputy is welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D02100"><p>I thank the Chairman and members.  I congratulate Ms Helen Guinan on her appointment.  I know her and commend her to the committee.  In her job in Cork in the COPE Foundation she worked as a principal and as a school teacher.  As a person she brings tremendous value to the role to which she has been appointed.  Members will find in Helen somebody who has a vision and an interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D02200"><p>I join Deputy Buttimer in echoing those comments as I am sure all my colleagues do.  We were very impressed with Ms Guinan's presentation, her dedication and enthusiasm for the role.  I wish her well and thank her for appearing before the committee.  We hope to engage with her again in the not too distant future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.252" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Guinan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D02300"><p>I thank the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014091700005#D02400"><p>The committee will notify the Minister that it has had this engagement with Ms Guinan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.254" nospeaker="true" time="14:20:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 2.36 p.m. and adjourned at 3.03 p.m. until 11 a.m. on Wednesday, 24 September 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.255" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.256" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 16:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett, Senator Mary M. White.* Deputy SeÃ¡n Kenny, Deputy Michael P. Kitt, Deputy Michael Healy-Rae, Deputy Aengus Ã“ Snodaigh,</p><p>* In the absence of Senator Ned O'Sullivan.</p><p>DEPUTY PÃDRAIG MAC LOCHLAINN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.257" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 4.17 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.258" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700003#B00100">Redressing the Imbalance Report: Free Legal Advice Centres</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700003#B00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Senators Harte, &Oacute; Clochartaigh and O'Keeffe.  I remind everyone present, including members of the committee, media personnel and those in the Visitors Gallery to ensure their mobile phones and BlackBerry devices are turned off completely, or switched to flight or safe mode, because they interfere with the sound system, even if they are in silent mode.  We are pleased to welcome Ms Noeline Blackwell, who is the director general of the Free Legal Advice Centres, and Mr. Paul Joyce, who is a senior policy analyst with the organisation.  They are here to make a presentation on a recent report, Redressing the Imbalance, which was published by the Free Legal Advice Centres.  I thank them for forwarding their presentation to the joint committee.  It has been circulated to the members of the committee.  As many of them will be aware, FLAC is an independent human rights organisation that seeks to promote equal access to justice and eliminate discrimination in all its forms.  Its work involves providing information and advice to the public and carrying out research and public advocacy.</p> <p>The report, Redressing the Imbalance, is an in-depth study which analyses the legal protections offered by the State to people availing of credit from banks, hire purchase companies, credit unions and other finance suppliers.  Many members of the committee are familiar with the Free Legal Advice Centres.  They are eager to hear the presentation and engage with the representatives.<br/>Before we commence, I must inform the witnesses that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they are to give this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given.  They are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  I invite Ms Blackwell and Mr. Joyce to make their presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.261" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700004#C00200"><p>I thank the Chairman and the members of the committee for inviting us to come here today.  As the Chairman suggested, the Free Legal Advice Centres are known as an organisation that provides advice and information.  Our work on debt has probably also been to the fore in recent times.  Many questions relating to credit are associated with the work we do to protect those with consumer debt.  The work we did over a long period of time on questions like how credit gets given in the first place, whether the protections given to consumers are adequate to protect their human rights and whether adequate redress systems are in place led to the publication of the substantial report we are discussing today.  My colleague, Mr. Paul Joyce, who is FLAC's senior policy analyst, is the main author of the report in question.  After he has made a presentation on the report, we will try to assist the members of the committee by clarifying matters of interest to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.262" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700004#C00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and the members.  I will be brief.  A five-page briefing note has been given to the committee.  I think a discussion would be far more useful.  Perhaps it would be much more interesting from the perspective of members.  As Ms Blackwell has said, this report is about two things.  It is about the kind of protection that exists for consumers of financial services at the point at which they draw down credit.  It is also about the systems of complaint and redress that are available for people who are unhappy about the conduct of financial service providers.</p><p>  The first part of the report looks at the origins of the EU consumer credit directives.  It suggests that they did not really do us any favours during the boom time, in terms of curbing irresponsible lending practices.  It looks at the poor transposition of those directives into Irish law.  In the course of the interviews we conducted with representatives of the Central Bank, they admitted that the bank does not really police the consumer credit legislation.  They prefer to police compliance with their own codes.  That, of course, leads us to another problem, which is the legally binding nature - or otherwise - of Central Bank codes.  It is of interest that these codes are neither primary nor secondary legislation and are not laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  Therefore, the Members of the Oireachtas essentially have no say in how they are put together.  As the committee will be aware, the code of conduct on mortgage arrears is of particular importance at the moment in the context of the alternative repayment arrangements that are supposed to be put in place to avoid home repossession.</p><p>  I would like to summarise the first section of the report.  We are saying we do not want another boom and bust fiasco.  During the boom time, we were really missing proper regulation of credit checking and of assessment of capacity to service agreements.  Interest rates were not regulated properly.  We needed to have more control over sub-prime lenders.  We accept that credit institutions are self-policing at the moment, but that might not always be the case.  If we are to avoid a recurrence of the same situation, we need really strong rules about responsible lending and borrowing and proper information across the board for all forms of credit.  We note in our submission that the hire purchase area is growing at the moment.  A person is entitled to enter into a hire purchase agreement.  Hire purchase companies are not regulated by the Central Bank.  The consumer protection code does not apply to hire purchase.  There is no obligation on a hire purchase lender to assess capacity to afford the agreement in the first place.</p><p>  We looked at the operations and procedures of the Financial Services Ombudsman's bureau.  We also looked at the legislation that underpins that office, which was established on a statutory basis.  In the course of doing this, we interviewed a number of users of the services of the FSO - people who had made complaints, etc.  We had supported some of them, through advice or otherwise.  We also interviewed a number of money advisers with the Money Advice and Budgeting Service who had assisted clients with their complaints to the FSO.  Given that this report runs to over 200 pages, it is very hard to summarise it to any great extent, but I would like to mention some issues that came out of the analysis of the FSO.  One of the messages that came clearly across was that there is a strong inequality of arms between the consumer complainant and the responding regulated financial service provider.  Those who responded to our interviews stated that this was not helped by the formality of the procedures, such as the exchange of submissions.  Many people felt that they were weighed down by a welter of technical detail when all they really wanted to do was articulate their complaints and try to obtain some form of redress.</p><p>  There are many statistics in the report.  It is clear that many complaints disappear off the horizon with no explanation.  Many settlements take place before an investigation takes place.  It is clear that the Financial Services Ombudsman does not really know the reason for this and has not inquired into it to any great extent.  The success rate is quite low.  Just 10% of the complaints that proceed to a full investigation are fully upheld.  Another 17% are partially upheld.  In 2012, three out of every four complaints made that went to a full investigation ended in failure.  It seems that the amount of money awarded as compensation in cases of success is on the decline.  We are not against the notion of an FSO - on the contrary, it is a good idea to have a free alternative dispute resolution service - but we are seriously calling into question how well that service is performing its functions.</p><p>  The report finds that there are problems with the legislation that established the Financial Services Ombudsman.  We think it should be reviewed and the six-year rule should be reformed.  The level of mediated cases is low.  The impression we got strongly from the FSO was that the institutions are basically using that bureau as an accelerated complaints mechanism from their own complaints procedures.  The aspect of this matter that probably concerns us most of all is that the avenue of appeal for a complainant who is unhappy with the outcome of his or her complaint is to the High Court.  We believe this is fundamentally inaccessible and unfair.  It exposes the complainant to the serious risk of legal costs.  It is clear from decisions of the High Court that the appeal is not a full appeal - it is actually a review to see whether the FSO committed any serious error in coming to its decision.  Many people do not understand that it is not a rehearing of all the basic facts.  We are saying that the Circuit Court would be much more appropriate.  We are also saying that the FSO should not necessarily be the respondent to all the appeals that take place.  It appears from the 2012 figures that the vast majority of appeals to the High Court are from consumers, surprisingly.  We believe the FSO could spend more time on developing the expertise of its office, rather than spending so much time defending appeals in the High Court.  That is a short summary of a lengthy piece of work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700004#C00400"><p>I thank Mr. Joyce for the outstanding work he has put into this report.  I invite the members of the committee to ask some questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700004#C00500"><p>I thank the witnesses for the introduction and for the work they have done on this document.  I enthusiastically support the thrust of what FLAC is trying to do.  I would like to ask about how we might rectify the problems that exist.  I have recently come across quite a few cases, involving the Financial Services Ombudsman and other bodies, in which the "inequality of arms" alluded to by Mr. Joyce has been a feature.  I refer to cases in which people are in dispute with organisations that have substantial legal resources.</p> <p>I have had cases where people are dealing with educational institutions and other big institutions that have lots of resources to stymie one's effort to make a complaint or to challenge certain decisions.  How can we rectify that imbalance so that the playing field is a bit more level for the ordinary citizen in pursuing a complaint or challenging a decision?  I am curious to hear a response in that regard as the situation appears to be very difficult.</p><p> Many cases are intractable because the people involved feel they have been wronged.  When I look at the cases in question, on the face of it that appears to be the case, but people just cannot get a proper hearing because those whom they are up against have the resources to make life difficult at every twist and turn given the high-powered legal resources at their disposal.  It is impossible for people to take a case and they end up literally pulling their hair out.</p><p> Is Mr. Joyce saying that if people do not get the result they want from the Financial Services Ombudsman that there are other places of recourse such as the Circuit Court?  Is he saying that people could make an application to the Circuit Court and have a judge hear the full facts of the case, which would be easier than going to the High Court?  Is that an easier option to take?  Will it be doable for people?  When I come across such cases I do not even know where to begin to advise people what to do next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.266" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700005#D00200"><p>It is clear that financial services is a tricky area as the provider has a lot more knowledge and expertise than the consumer.  The attitude the Financial Services Ombudsman tends to adopt is that the office has to be an honest broker and cannot favour either side, even though often the complainant sees the ombudsman as a consumer champion, which the office clearly is not.  There is nowhere specific that one can go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700005#D00300"><p>Why does Mr. Joyce say the Financial Services Ombudsman clearly is not a consumer champion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.268" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700005#D00400"><p>That is the strong view of the office.  It is a creation of statute and cannot take sides.  It is an independent office.  There is no specific service consumer complainants can access to prepare their complaints.  In some cases money advisers from MABS can help.  In other instances we have helped.  There is a patchwork of organisations here and there but there is no dedicated place where one can go to help formulate one&rsquo;s complaint.  That would be a help to start with, because obviously if a complaint gets off on the wrong foot and one does not make the appropriate submissions and word things carefully it can affect the complaint.</p><p>  That is one concrete thing that could be done.  There is also no database of decisions available.  If a consumer wants to make a complaint about a particular issue one should be able to log on to a part of the website and see how similar issues might have been treated previously to help one formulate one&rsquo;s arguments.  An appeal to the Circuit Court is not ideal but it is preferable to a limited appeal to the High Court where the risk of substantial legal costs is high.</p><p>  As I am sure Deputy Boyd Barrett knows, our organisation also works very much to reform the civil legal aid system.  We are also of the view that people should be able to apply for and receive civil legal aid in appropriate cases for appeals to the Circuit Court.  In addition, we say the appeal to the Circuit Court should follow the normal fashion of appeals.  Although the decision is made by the ombudsman, the appeal should be against the financial service provider.  That would normally be the case, for example, with unfair dismissal cases.  What happens at the moment is the Financial Services Ombudsman acts as the respondent to appeals and comes into the High Court to defend the office's decision.  That is unnecessary in many instances.</p><p>  There is a fundamental problem of expertise on the part of the institution.  In a lot of cases people felt they were being thrown a lot of technical paperwork which was obscuring their complaint.  A number of people felt that an oral hearing where they could be in the room and address questions to the people they dealt with and have somebody listen to the case would address their complaint much more comprehensively and they would feel much more vindicated rather than going through a paper process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.269" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700005#D00500"><p>Deputy Boyd Barrett is absolutely correct about the whole business of inequality and the feeling that one is up against a big, powerful organisation.  That is a real problem of the legal aid system in general.  The legal aid system could give assistance in the Circuit Court but because of delays and the rest of it, may not and is prohibited by law from giving assistance in a complaint to the ombudsman.  If I go to the Legal Aid Board - the State-funded legal aid service - and say I want help in bringing my case to the ombudsman it cannot give me representation.</p><p>  The ombudsman system is probably much better than having to go into court on day one.  It is free and it is supposed to be utterly independent.  The blocks are in how one gets there, exactly as Mr. Joyce outlined.  The independence of the ombudsman disappears when he goes into the High Court and goes on-side against the consumer who is bringing the appeal, which has been our invariable experience.  The appeal is not against the company that made the decision in the first place; it is taken against the company and the ombudsman.  The ombudsman fights the case so one risks losing and paying two sets of costs.  That is an entirely impractical system for most people who cannot be assured of success at the far end of it.</p><p>  We also have exactly the same problem in relation to people trying to negotiate with their banks.  At a different stage we spoke at a different committee about the imbalance of power where people are not supported by any State assistance or bank assistance unless they are lucky enough to be with MABS or an advocacy agency, which is very hit and miss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.270" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700005#D00600"><p>I have one further short point.  The Central Bank&rsquo;s consumer protection code obliges all regulated financial service providers to have a complaints mechanism within the organisation which one can access.  The wording of the code is curious.  It suggests that a regulated financial services provider must attempt to resolve a complaint within 40 days.  Practically speaking, a lot of the complaints are not resolved within that eight week period and take substantially longer.  From the evidence we saw, many people give up hope before they even get to the ombudsman because they feel stonewalled by the provider itself.  If a case is strung out then people will eventually give up rather than follow through.  Something must be done to monitor the code to ensure the timelines are shorter and they are strictly adhered to, as at the moment that is not properly monitored.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700005#D00700"><p>This is an area of interest because a number of people have contacted me and I have tried to help them put together a complaint where a service has not been delivered.  PayPal is one of the companies that is very difficult to deal with.  If one&rsquo;s account is affected, due to no fault of one's own, through fraud at another end, one cannot access PayPal in any shape or form.  People try to get an appeals mechanism in place.  Reference was made to companies attempting to resolve cases within 40 days.  In the case of PayPal and probably other companies a reply is made outlining an initial finding and stating that more time is required.  When the complainant offers more time that is usually the last he or she hears about the case, as in the two cases with which I am familiar.  The consequence is that someone with an online business has his or her account suspended.  There must be a way to ensure that such consumers can complain properly or appeal to the Financial Services Ombudsman if the complaints system is not working.</p><p>  Reference was made to a number of areas in which legislation must be tightened up.  The committee could help to encourage the Minister for Finance to look at that.</p> <p>As individuals we can see if we can try to ensure that where there are faults in financial legislation, as we have highlighted today, we can examine them.  This should happen particularly with regard to consumer protection, which is vital.  I was elected in 2002 and it struck me at the time that a credit company operated in my area, and I complained about the 195% interest being charged.  There was a different regulator at the time and when I inquired about this, I was told that although it came within its remit, there was no entitlement to restrict interest rates charged by companies.  The regulator would have ensured they operated legally nonetheless.  No institution should be entitled, with a licence from the State, to charge exorbitant annual percentage rates over 30%.  Some of these companies charge over 200%.  Given where we have come from and the indebtedness of our society, the issue must be addressed.</p><p> It is useful for others to raise this matter, as the more voices we hear, the more this side of financial regulation will be used to limit what interest can be charged.  Institutions should not be able to get away with some of the costs not just in interest rates, but also in collection rates.  If a company is forced to reduce interest rates, it may increase collection rates to make up the 200% rate.  Some of these operations have little more than signs and one could have difficulty in accessing the company or complaining about a lack of service given to a consumer.  I will look with interest at how this is received and whether we could get the Minister for Finance, in particular, to take on board these issues.  Valid questions and proposals have been raised, and they relate to some of the problems that led us to the current crisis.  There was a lack of regulation and oversight, and the more of this available to a consumer, the less likely we will end up with people struggling.  Part of our job is to ensure all ombudsmen have the required tools to deliver for the consumer and citizen, so we should take this report on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.273" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00200"><p>As the Deputy noted, the interest rate charged by moneylenders is horrendous.  It is a particularly pertinent point, as every Deputy knows, especially when other forms of credit are so limited right now, including credit union loans and other normal low-cost credit forms.  With regard to legislation, some of the points are net and could be dealt with reasonably easily.  For example, the business of hire purchase companies not being regulated seems to be an amazing oversight, especially when every third advertisement is now about hire purchase.  It seems to be a worrying trend that the protection for consumers for one of the few forms of credit available currently is simply not good enough but could be fixed very simply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.274" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00300"><p>The point about the cost of credit is valid.  As Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh has indicated, these are mainly licensed moneylenders; they would apply for a licence and state on the application what they intend to charge.  If the State grants the licence, they can charge whatever is permitted in the licence.  There is a question regarding the cost of credit being too high but Deputies will know that some people would use moneylenders routinely as their only source of credit.  It can be a difficult question.  The annual percentage rates are far too high.</p><p>  The report also identifies that during the boom years, particularly from 2004 onwards, many sub-prime lenders - both mortgage and personal lenders - entered the market.  There is an illustration of an agreement which we dealt with on page 7.  I will spare the committee the details but it was a top-up loan, which licensed moneylenders are not allowed to charge for.  It involved a credit institution from outside the country which came in by "passporting" on its banking licence.  It offered a personal loan over seven years at an outrageous rate of interest, topped up the loan and loaned the borrower money for payment protection insurance, which was prepaid for the full duration of the agreement.  It was absolutely scandalous and the cost of the credit was outrageous.</p><p>  Such cases went by without any regulation.  The institution was a credit body for the purposes of the consumer credit legislation and it could do as it wished.  There is a gap in consumer credit legislation that means credit institutions do not have to get a licence to charge over 23% annual percentage rate, although moneylenders do.  That is a simple change that could be made to the legislation tomorrow.  During the course of the boom, certain business names of certain banks were offering credit agreements at over 23% annual percentage rate, and not just banks coming in from outside.</p><p>  The report details that sub-prime lenders were authorised by statutory instrument to be housing lenders for the purposes of the consumer credit legislation, with no other controls placed upon them.  They are responsible, although not alone, for many of the difficult arrears cases.  They became retail credit firms in 2008.  This is what is being proposed for the unregulated entities which have bought loans from others, and Deputies are aware of the consultation which has just finished with the Department of Finance.  Legislation is due from that.  We just do not seem to get there on time and we seem to be behind all the time in putting in place necessary protection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00400"><p>I was going to raise the hire purchase issue, as finance companies are not regulated.  FLAC has raised the matter with the Central Bank and the Department of Finance but has there been a response?  Perhaps this was dealt with before I arrived.  What are their duties in this respect?  During the summer there was much debate about life assurance and I heard it being discussed quite a bit on the "Liveline" programme.  Terms were changed regarding the amount of premia that would have to be paid in order to maintain insurance levels; in some cases if premia were not raised, the cover decreased.</p><p>  I have a question about FLAC offices, particularly in Galway city, where a very fine service is run.  There is an issue with resources and staffing.  Perhaps the witnesses do not want to deal with that but I would appreciate if they could tell me something.  I am fully supportive of the work but there have been some complaints at policing committees I attended that sometimes people get too much free legal aid.  For example, repeat offenders may get free legal aid on a number of occasions, and this is not the way to go when tackling crime.  I am somewhat outside the issue being discussed today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00500"><p>Yes, although I am giving some poetic licence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00600"><p>Perhaps there can be some comment as the issue will arise again, I am sure.  I thank the Chairman for his leniency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00700"><p>If Deputy Kitt were in the Chair in the D&aacute;il, he would not give such latitude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.279" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700006#E00800"><p>With the hire purchase issue, one is entitled to a hire purchase in writing and in full.  Sometimes it is not provided but as I mentioned, the area is not being properly policed by the Central Bank.</p> <p>However, the lender is not obliged to do the proper due diligence on the borrower's income, other credit agreements, capacity to service the agreement and so on.</p><p> During the boom hire service was a major source of over-indebtedness and they are quite technical agreements.  For a start, the person does not own the vehicle until he or she makes the final payment, which many people did not understand.  Some people sold on vehicles with disastrous consequences.  It is an area where the maximum information and protection is necessary.  Given that the entities are not regulated, even some garages have started to go on solo runs and do their own HP because they have seen the possibility of doing so.  Normally they were credit intermediaries acting for institutions.</p><p> We have raised this.  We have had meetings with representatives of the Central Bank and had meetings in the Department of Finance.  Nobody is saying it is a bad idea to regulate them.  It just seems to take a huge amount of time to get around to doing what people seem to accept should be done.  The technical explanation is that hire purchase is not credit, according to the Central Bank.  Of course it is credit because people are paying in instalments usually over 60 months with an interest payment.  It is a rental so it is a bit of a subtle distinction, but it is not a distinction that stands up in practical terms.</p><p> Our feeling is that when something needs to be remedied quickly and it is of consequence for financial institutions, it tends to be done.  When it is a consumer issue, it tends to take a long time.  Nobody has come back and said there is a good reason for not doing this, but it still has not happened.</p><p> Was Deputy Kitt's question on life assurance related to mortgages or just life assurance policies generally?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00200"><p>I think that people might not have read the life assurance small print.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.282" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00300"><p>Those are the terms and conditions.  Financial agreements are generally pre-drafted on behalf of the institution in question.  There is a considerable amount of small print and people enter into these agreements without fully understanding what they involve.  The National Consumer Agency has been quite helpful in providing information on its website and so on, but people do not always have access to the Internet.  There is a set of regulations, the European Communities (Unfair Terms in Consumer Contracts) Regulations, which can be used by consumers to point to unfair pre-drafted terms in contracts.  That is something that might be looked at and the National Consumer Agency is quite active in that regard.  People can seek to have an order made that a term in an agreement is unfair because it is deliberately imbalanced against the interests of the consumer.</p><p>  There is also an issue relating to life assurance and mortgage arrears because people are entering into rescheduled agreements and either their mortgage protection has lapsed or they have not readjusted their mortgage protection policies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.283" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00400"><p>On the question of us and the Legal Aid Board, we do not set out to be confusing but we are confusing.  We are the free legal advice centres and we only have one office in Dublin, and Mr. Joyce and I comprise about a fifth of the staff.  The State-funded Legal Aid Board is what provides the general State representation.  That is a fully State-funded body.  We have huge admiration for all the lawyers who work in that, but we are not them.  We give a volunteer service in citizens' information centres in evening clinics as well as in NUIG.</p><p>  We know that the State-funded Legal Aid Board cannot deal with this area - if I want to draw it back into this area a bit - or any other area as well as it would like because its demand has doubled over the period of the recession.  It has had reduced resources and employment frameworks which limit the number of people who can do it.  As a result, our concern, as a small voluntary non-governmental organisation seeking equal access to justice, is that in this area as well as in others people are not able to access the information they need at the time they need it in order to resolve their own affairs.  Returning to what Deputy Boyd Barrett said at one stage, people then build up huge unnecessary disputes sometimes where proper access to legal aid and representation would give them a better outcome.</p><p>  Returning to the Ombudsman, if people could get to the Ombudsman in an informed way so that they knew what they were doing when they brought their complaint and could understand the process they were going through, they would be likely to have more faith in it, provided the resolution was one they could depend on.  That is not the case at the moment but it is fixable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00500"><p>There is no database of decisions by the Financial Services Ombudsman.  How can we, as legislators, be aware of the scale of the problem if we do not have the necessary statistics?  For example, how can we identify if there is a problem in the hire purchase area or with personal loans?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.285" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00600"><p>The Ombudsman publishes biannual reviews and publishes an annual report and occasional case studies.  On the website, ironically, there is a list of the High Court appeals, but there is no database of decisions broken down by category to give an indication of where there may be problems.  Decisions are published from time to time but as case studies, so there is no reliable database in place.  This is not the only area with issues of access to social justice; we have pointed out the social welfare appeals office.</p><p>  To be fair, we have had some engagement with the FSO since the report was published and it is looking at some of the issues.  It is considering rejigging its website and improving certain elements of it, but it was not particularly keen on developing a database.  Obviously, there is a fair amount of work involved, but given that there are 7,000 to 10,000 complaints a year, people are entitled to guidance as to how to frame a complaint.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.286" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00700"><p>While the Ombudsman would claim it is not bound by all its previous decisions, how can we know there is consistent decision making within it without that information?  There is a model which is not totally satisfactory but now works in the immigration area.  The Office of the Refugee Appeals Tribunal has a database it can make available to people.  If I am looking for the tribunal's decisions on a specific issue, I can ask it for that.  I will not see everything on its website, but if I have a particular concern, I can see it.  That is a model that has been adapted and used, and seems to be satisfactory without being too top-heavy on cost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00800"><p>People think of the Ombudsman as the impartial judge based on its translation from its Nordic origins.  It is an independent arbiter that looks at the complaints, gives the body that is being complained about a chance to respond and then adjudicates and makes a recommendation.  I know the witnesses have a number of recommendations in the report on the Financial Services Ombudsman.  Would they prefer that to the existing model?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.288" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700007#F00900"><p>I believe the Ombudsman would say that is the model that exists right now in being independent and not taking sides.  It should evaluate the evidence and make a recommendation which can be subject to appeal.  That is fine in theory, but in practice because the consumer is coming from a position of much less knowledge, that creates of itself an imbalance.  We need to consider ways to ensure that the consumer complainant is more empowered and that the procedures adopted by the FSO are less formal and less weighed down in paperwork which the complainant finds difficult to understand.</p><p>  Some of the respondents made complaints on their own behalf.  One person, who was very experienced in financial matters, found the system very difficult to navigate.  He said at interview, "I can only imagine what it is like for people who are not familiar with this kind of stuff".  The area of financial services is complicated and the consumer definitely needs assistance from the outset.  It would make a big difference if there was a dedicated place for them to go to get assistance to formulate the complaint.</p><p>  There should be more oral hearings.</p> <p>A number of the respondents said: "I really wanted to express how frustrated I was with how the institution dealt with me, how I was stonewalled, how I was not getting answers, how I was sent from Billy to Jack and I did not get that opportunity."  The Financial Services Ombudsman was saying that if we have to have oral hearings in every case, it will affect our throughput of cases and so on, but again an oral hearing is an access to justice issue, the opportunity to articulate one's complaint.  I think it is about improving the service.  In principle it is fine, but in practice it needs a great deal of improvement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.290" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00200"><p>At the far end the ombudsman makes the decision and then stays out of any appeal.  The ombudsman has adjudicated at that stage.  We find it difficult to understand why the office of the ombudsman needs to go into most appeals.  They might need to go into the odd one as an expert to explain some rationale, but for the most part that detracts enormously from the perception of their independence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.291" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00300"><p>To add to that, what is provided for in the legislation is that the ombudsman may be a party to the High Court appeal.  In our view it should not be an appeal to the High Court.  What has happened in practice is that the ombudsman is the respondent in every High Court appeal and we have been involved in a few ourselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00400"><p>As the witnesses from FLAC may know, the context of its presentation today is that we are working on one of our public petitions that is challenging the secrecy of the Central Bank's financial regulator and the issue of accountability around the process and the outcome.  Does FLAC have a perspective on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.293" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00500"><p>That is an interesting topic.  I have had a quick read through the recent discussion of 9 July.  The administrative sanctions programme which was referred to fairly frequently throughout the submission that was made to the joint committee is the Central Bank's way of dealing with financial service providers who may breach standards and so on.  Our experience would be similar.  The process takes place behind closed doors, where the provider can opt for a settlement.  The focus seems to be on settlements rather than on prosecutions of any kind.  There is some material in the report, in which representatives of the Central Bank say that is the most cost effective way of doing this.  Our overall impression would be that in the realm of financial services, different standards apply, that the financial service industry is unduly protected and, on the other hand, the consumer has fewer rights than they might have in other areas.  We have had experience of writing to the Central Bank looking for details of how it arrived at sanctioning certain bank charges.  It is very difficult to get information.  Members may be aware of the famous section 33AK of the Central Bank Act 1942 is constantly referred to and it seems there is a kind of shield of confidentiality over everything.</p><p>  As the petitioner at the recent meeting of the joint committee said, that is understandable for prudential issues and there are certain issue that have to remain confidential, but it seems to be a kind of confidentiality shield across the board, which is way over the top in our view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.294" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Noeline Blackwell" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00600"><p>A personal bugbear of mine is that the Central Bank's strategic plan specifically names the strengthening of consumer protection, that is, the protection of consumers of financial services, as one of its high level goals.  It seems to us that this is interpreted from the side of bankers looking at how they perceive consumers should be protected in financial services rather than from a consumer perspective, even to the point of outsourcing its own information function to the National Consumer Agency.  It always seems extraordinary that one goes to the Central Bank and one cannot get an answer.  One will be directed elsewhere, either to the National Consumer Agency or to the Financial Services Ombudsman.  That strategic plan the Central Bank has developed is until next year.  One of the things we would like to see the Central Bank doing is being more relevant to consumers.  The Central Bank has an advisory panel but consumers seem to be always viewed from the perspective of bankers.  We would like to see others ask the Central Bank how it would look to the consumer perspective and consumer rights when developing its next plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.295" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Joyce" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00700"><p>Let me give a brief example.  If tomorrow morning I wanted to log on to the Central Bank's website because I want to apply for a personal loan and I want to choose between the terms offered by different lenders, there is no one place that I can go to find out what default interest rate bank A charges on personal loans as opposed to another bank or what kind of charge is made for direct debits missed and so on between bank A and that bank.  The reason that information is not there is ostensibly because of confidentiality.  That is not confidential information.  That information should be in the public domain to enable people who are availing of financial services to make a choice between one provider and another.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014091700008#G00800"><p>On behalf of the joint committee I thank Ms Blackwell and Mr. Joyce for attending today's meeting and for engaging in a most interesting and wide-ranging discussion.  We are very grateful to both of them for taking the time to meet the committee and we will take account of the exchanges in our deliberations.  We will publish a report and of course we will have to deliberate on the petition at a later stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.297" nospeaker="true" time="16:45:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 5.05 p.m. and adjourned at 5.20 p.m.until 4 p.m. on Wednesday, 24 September 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.298" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Transport and Communications</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.299" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 11:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Timmy Dooley, Senator Sean D. Barrett. Deputy Tom Fleming, Deputy Brendan Griffin, Deputy Helen McEntee, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan,</p><p>In attendance: Senator Maurice Cummins.</p><p>DEPUTY JOHN O'MAHONY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.300" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 12.10 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.301" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700003#J00100">Port of Waterford Company: Chairman Designate</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700003#J00200"><p>The purpose of this meeting is to engage with Mr. Des Whelan, chairperson designate of the Port of Waterford Company in order to discuss the approach he proposes to take when appointed to the role and his views on the challenges facing the port.  Members will be aware of the Government decision of May 2011 which put new arrangements in place for the appointment of persons to State boards and bodies.  The committee welcomes the opportunity to meet the chairperson designate in public session to hear his views.  I trust this provides greater transparency to the process of appointments to State boards and bodies.<br/>On behalf of the committee I welcome Mr. Des Whelan.  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  However, if you are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and you continue to so do, you are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of the evidence.  You are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and you are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, you should not criticise or make charges against any persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Any submission or opening statement you have submitted to the committee will be published on the committee's website.  Members are reminded of a long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House, or any official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/>I call on Mr. Whelan to make his opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.303" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Des Whelan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700003#J00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for the opportunity to address the committee on how I envisage the Port of Waterford progressing during my chairmanship over the next five years.</p><p>  I will begin by running through some of my experiences in business as a director and chairman of some businesses.  I have been in business in Waterford for 36 years.  I operated a local radio station for a decade and then won a licence in 1989 to broadcast to Waterford city and county.  I have been doing that for the past 25 years and that is what takes up most of my time.  I am the managing director of WLR.  We celebrated 25 years broadcasting, as members of the committee probably know - the committee had a reception not so long ago for the industry here.  When the industry was very young I was involved in setting up the advertising services and the independent news sector for the broadcasting industry.  I was an original founding shareholder in Newstalk.</p><p>  At the start of 2000 I was involved in a number of licence applications and I was eventually successful in putting together a consortium and establishing a company to win Ireland's first regional broadcast licence for Beat 102-103.  I am also a founding shareholder and chairman of Radio Nova in Dublin and chairman of Red FM in Cork.</p><p>  My day job is very much about running WLR and I have a great interest and passion for things in Waterford.  For the past three years I have been a director of the Waterford Treasures museums in the heart of the Viking Triangle, which is playing a very important role in the rejuvenation of the city.</p> <p>I am also chairman of the organising committee of the Waterford Viking marathon.  Waterford was previously the only city in Ireland that did not host a marathon.  This work was part of my day-job running Waterford Local Radio, WLR, and the marathon has been held successfully for the past three years.</p><p> I was part of the marketing committee when Waterford hosted the tall ships in 2005 and I chaired the overall organising committee when the tall ships returned in 2011.  This was deemed by most to be a success, attracted the largest ever crowds to the city and generated a major economic boost.  I had great support in this from everyone involved.  I have a great passion for the sea and Ireland's maritime sector - I do some boating and hold a coastal skipper certificate.</p><p> One might wonder how a person involved in the broadcasting sector has ended up as chairman designate of a port.  I have some background experience in this area.  My father was a cattle dealer in the south east for many years and shipped cattle to the UK every two weeks.  My first job was on the quayside loading cattle onto ships in the 1960s, which I remember fondly.</p><p> I realise it is an honour and a considerable responsibility to be asked to chair the Port of Waterford company.  I gave the offer much thought before accepting it.  This is not something I take lightly and I appreciate the challenges that lie ahead.  I hope that my experience, the experience of the board and the commitment of the management and staff of the company will bring prosperity to the port.</p><p> Waterford is 1,100 years old this year and it has a wonderful history starting from the Vikings who came up the river in longboats.  Many trade routes were established between Waterford and great European and American ports over the centuries.  As the country's oldest city, Waterford has a tremendous maritime tradition.  Waterford Harbour Commissioners was established in 1816 and in 1999 the Port of Waterford became a commercial semi-State company.  In the 1990s it was noted that the city quays were too confined for modern shipping and the port moved four miles down river to Belview, County Kilkenny.  The Port of Waterford is the fourth largest port in the Republic of Ireland and has Ireland's most modern port infrastructure.  It is recognised as a port of national significance in the national ports policy of 2013.  The Port of Waterford is a superb facility that has world-class road access and it is one of only two Irish ports with a direct rail link - it is also the closest Irish port to continental Europe.  This starting point offers great opportunities to grow traffic through the port.  In addition to its excellent location, there is a substantial development zone at Belview that will allow the port to expand its services and accommodate growth from companies that benefit from the location.</p><p> The port at Belview can cater for ships of up to 4,000 tonnes and 190 m in length.  Ships carrying loads of up to 20,000 tonnes are common and ships with a draft of up to 9 m can be catered for either side of high tide.  The port is currently served by a twice-weekly container vessel service to Rotterdam, via Dublin and Cork.</p><p> Waterford Port has the full support of Kilkenny County Council and Waterford City and County Council, along with other key public and private sector stakeholders.  There is no doubt that a thriving port can facilitate economic recovery in the south east while benefitting from increased overseas trade.  The Port of Waterford depends on imports and exports and, like many businesses in the south east, it was severely affected by the recession.  Turnover peaked in 2008 at &euro;12 million and revenues are now at half that figure.  Waterford port made a loss from 2009 to 2012 but following a major restructuring, which saw staff numbers reduced from 49 to 27, the port made a profit of over &euro;900,000 in 2013.  This compares to a loss of &euro;1.2 million in 2012.</p> <p>Tonnage through the port of Waterford in 2013 amounted to 1,430,000 tonnes and the port&rsquo;s share of the bulk market in Ireland increased last year to 3%.</p><p> The port does face many challenges.  It carries a substantial pension deficit, which now stands at &euro;7.2 million.  That has reduced over the past three years from &euro;10.9 million.  Following the storms of last January and February, dredging costs will be doubled for 2014 and 2015.  The port must also replace its current CEO, Stan McIlvenny, who retires in 2015 and it is to be hoped that the remuneration package will allow a high-quality successor to be secured.  </p><p> At national level, there is reason for some cautious optimism about the future of the ports sector as economic recovery takes hold.  For instance, Irish shipping and port activity rose by 4% in the first quarter of 2014 when compared to last year, according to the latest data from the Irish Maritime Development Office.  The IMDO also reports that container traffic grew by 6% over the same period.  While I have yet to chair a board meeting, I have been impressed by the positive attitude and culture of the workforce in the port.  Corporate governance is excellent as are the health and safety standards in operation.  </p><p> I must acknowledge the work of former chairman, Michael Flynn, and his board and the hard work of the CEO and his team.  Anybody in business will understand the hard graft and effort that it takes to reduce company size during difficult times.  The port now has a much lower cost base and a committed, hard working and well organised management and staff.   Much of the hard work is done and the port is geared for growth.  As the economy improves, it will be the new board&rsquo;s priority to get further container services to the port and in particular a feeder service to Rotterdam, and to make those south-east businesses and transport companies using ports at the very least reconsider the attractiveness of using Waterford.  Sales and marketing will be to the forefront of the business and it will be a priority to create new job opportunities as business improves.  The port&rsquo;s excellent location and world class facilities will be a very attractive proposition for the new Glanbia production facility at Belview and the reform of CAP will further increase the port&rsquo;s agribusiness potential.  </p><p> We are also confident that many more relevant businesses will locate at Belview and during my term as chairman I would hope that we can make a concerted effort to tidy up the old North Quays in Waterford and give visitors to the city a better first impression.  This could also help in retaining and developing the port&rsquo;s cruise business which &ndash; while not hugely significant to the port in revenue terms &ndash; is an important part of its contribution to the south-east region as cruise calls are an important driver of tourism revenues.  The Minister's predecessor in the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, has appointed a skilled and experienced board and I look forward to working with the new board and management team to help continue to revitalise the Port of Waterford.  Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700005#L00200"><p>Thank you.  The motto "when you want somebody to do a job, ask a busy person" comes to mind.  Mr. Whelan's CV is very compelling.  I will hand over to the members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700005#L00300"><p>I thank Mr. Whelan for his setting out his stall.  He has a passion for boating, understands the business, lives in the area and is interested in the wider community.  He has demonstrated very clearly why he is being appointed and I wish him well.  At this stage our questioning is almost unnecessary once he has shown he has the credentials to be appointed.  We may invite him back at a later stage to deal with issues as they arise for the port.  He has set out very plainly his skills and experience.  I note he is the son of a cattle dealer.  Coming from a small farm I understand that if he has learned anything from his father he will be well able to deal with the complexities of the business that is Waterford Port.  I wish him well and look forward to seeing him develop that piece of infrastructure to the benefit of the south east.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700006#M00200"><p>I am not a member of this committee, but I thank the Chairman for letting me contribute.  I am passionate about the port of Waterford, being a former chairman and having worked in the port for over 23 years.  I actually had the honour of serving with Mr. Whelan's father on the Waterford Harbour Commission.  It is clear that the port faces major challenges.  Since 2006, it has lost approximately 40% of traffic, and probably a few hundred per cent since the 1990s, when the port was thriving and up to 300,000 TEU, 20 ft. equivalent units, were being shipped in and out.  It saddens me to hear that there are now only two ships a week to Rotterdam.  When I worked in the port, we had five or six ships to Rotterdam, four or five to Newport and one or two per week to Le Havre.  Hopefully we can gradually get back to that situation.</p><p>  As Mr. Whelan has said, the port is ideally situated.  It probably has the best road access in the country.  The rail access, however, is totally under-utilised.  We must start using this means of transport again, because Waterford is one of only two ports in the country with direct rail access under the gantries.  As Mr. Whelan pointed out, cruise ships are another area with great potential for growth, which would be of huge benefit to the tourism sector in the city.  Mr. Whelan has a difficult job; much is done but there remains much to do in coming years, with a new manager in place.  Marketing, and Mr. Whelan's experience in this area, will be key to advancing the port in future years.  As the Chairman has stated, the members of the committee wish Mr. Whelan well, and I am sure he will be invited back after a year or so to report to the committee on his stewardship.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.309" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Des Whelan" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700006#M00300"><p> I need to find out more about how ports operate.  In recent months, I have met all the customers of the port, including those running the cruises, many of the staff, and obviously Stan McIlvenny.  Senator Cummins is quite right about the marketing; it is very important.  The most important thing the port must do is to go out and ask for business.  I would be strong on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1180" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700006#M00400"><p>I wish Mr. Whelan the best of luck.  As Deputy Dooley stated, the committee will most likely invite him in again to the progress being made at the port.  The biggest issue is to secure further services to the port, as Mr. Whelan pointed out, and to get as close to the 2008 figure of &euro;12 million in turnover as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1051" speakername="Brendan Griffin" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700006#M00500"><p>I also wish Mr. Whelan the best in his new role.  There is potential for a round-Ireland cruise, stopping at the various ports around the coast, including Waterford.  Perhaps this is something that Mr. Whelan could keep in mind, along with colleagues from the other ports.  Cruise liners coming in from different parts of Europe are certainly welcome, but we have a beautiful coastline, which could be showcased in an exclusively Irish cruise.  I am not aware of any company that is doing that at the moment, and it is something that could benefit all the ports and coastal areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700006#M00600"><p>As we were reminded by Mr. Whelan, the cruise ships themselves do not generate a great deal of revenue for the port itself, but they are good for the economy of the surrounding area</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700006#M00700"><p>Just a quick observation from the meetings Mr. Whelan has had so far with customers, etc., I note the figures and the challenges that have been pointed out here by members, namely the drop in traffic and turnover since 2006.</p> <p>On the basis of Mr. Whelan's earlier observations, would he say that was more to do with the difficulties in the economy rather than the infrastructure or lack thereof around the port, or was it a combination of both?</p><p>As other speakers noted, we have heard a great deal in recent years about the potential for growth in the cruise ship market and the business that market brings to towns, cities and regions.  Is there a requirement for a significant infrastructural upgrade to facilitate expansion in that regard at Waterford?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.315" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Des Whelan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700007#N00200"><p>There are several factors as to why the port has suffered, the main one being the recession and the associated reduction in business.  Ports like Foynes, Cork and Dublin are very busy and, from what I can see, Waterford did lose contracts to Dublin and elsewhere, which we will have to work to win back.  That will not happen overnight, but we are now in a very competitive position.  Anybody who drives regularly between Waterford and Dublin will be aware of the improvement compared with five or six years ago.  There have been fantastic infrastructural improvements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700007#N00300"><p>Is Mr. Whelan suggesting the improvement in the roads was a disadvantage to Waterford Port?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.317" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Des Whelan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700007#N00400"><p>No, I expect it will be an advantage.  The port has been through a very difficult time and the whole area was hit hard by the recession.  There is potential for growth, but it is a case of going out and looking very hard for the business and doing everything we need to do with industry locally and in the south-east region.  There is already a feeling that business is on the up, with a large volume of inquiries about Belview and the possibility of setting up a feeder service to Rotterdam.  I am confident that will happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700007#N00500"><p>Glanbia is a major industrial player in the south east.  Does it use Belview extensively for all its exports?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.319" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Des Whelan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700007#N00600"><p>Glanbia does use the port but not for all its exports.  The company is currently trialling a new milk production facility which will open in the new year.  The port has tendered for the business associated with that.  Again, however, we are talking about big logistics and the decision may well rest with the transport company that looks after Glanbia's logistics.  I cannot anticipate the outcome of the tender, but we will do all we can to secure the business from Glanbia.</p><p>  Regarding the cruise business, I met last week with representatives of the main agents for cruises coming into Waterford.  Their view is that we could get more of this business.  There were 277 cruise visits to Ireland this year, of which Waterford got only 17.  In 1996, by contrast, there were only 100 such visits to Ireland, but Waterford got 24 of them.  We certainly can do more to improve our performance.  Tidying up the North Quays is an important step as we seek to bring as many of those cruise ships as possible into the city.  The agents to whom I spoke argued that there is particular potential in trying to develop visits from European cruises, in a context where almost all of the 17 ships that came to Waterford this year were American.  The cruise market is booming in Europe and there is scope to encourage more of them to visit Ireland.  We will be working with everybody involved to ensure that happens.</p><p>  People want the port to be successful and to emerge as a driving force in the economy in Waterford.</p> <p>It needs to be seen as that as well.  There is a lot of work to do but I am confident.  The Minister made a point of meeting all the board members individually.  I have been impressed.  I think we will be a good team and will get things done.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.321" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014091700008#O00200"><p>I thank Mr. Whelan for his presentation.  We wish him well on his new appointment.  We thank him for coming in to engage with us.  We look forward to engaging with him in the future.</p><p>  We will send a copy of the Official Report for today&rsquo;s discussion to the Minister for his information.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-17a.322" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 12.35 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>