<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.2" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.3" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 15:25</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 15:25</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Seanadóirí / Senators Jackie Cahill, Paul Daly, Marcella Corcoran Kennedy, Michelle Mulherin. Martin Kenny, Willie Penrose.</p><p>* In éagmais / In the absence of Senator Anthony Lawlor.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy Pat Deering sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.4" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#G00200"><p>Before we begin, I remind members to ensure their mobile telephones are turned off.  Apologies have been received from Deputy Charlie McConalogue and Senator Rose Conway-Walsh.  I propose that we go into private session to deal with some housekeeping matters before proceeding to the main business of the meeting.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.6" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 3.30 p.m. and resumed in public session at 3.40 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.7" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#J00100">Food Democracy: Trócaire</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#J00200"><p>Before we begin, I remind members, witnesses and those in the Visitors Gallery to ensure their mobile phones are completely turned off as they interfere with the broadcasting system.  We are here to discuss the Tr&oacute;caire policy paper, Food Democracy: Feeding The World Sustainably.  From Tr&oacute;caire, I welcome Mr. Michael O'Brien, policy adviser; Ms Olive Moore, head of programmes; Mr. Joshua Aijuka, programme manager, sustainable farming systems, PELUM Uganda.  I thank the witnesses for attending today to discuss Tr&oacute;caire's policy paper, which has been received by the committee.</p> <p>  Witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  </p> <p>  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p> <p>  I invite Mr. O'Brien to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.9" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Michael O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#J00300"><p>I will hand over to Ms Moore, who is head of programmes at Tr&oacute;caire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.10" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Olive Moore" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#J00400"><p>I thank the committee for inviting Tr&oacute;caire and PELUM, one of our partners from Uganda, to address it today.  This invite follows on from the publication of Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s policy report, Food Democracy: Feeding the World Sustainably.  This report was published to coincide with last October&rsquo;s conference, Transformation Pathways for Developing Country Agriculture, which was organised by the Irish Forum for International Agricultural Development, IFIAD.  Tr&oacute;caire is an IFIAD steering committee member and we were very pleased that the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine opened the conference.</p> <p>  I will introduce Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s strategic plan and outline the context that informs our approach to work on agriculture and food.  Mr. Joshua Aijuka from PELUM Uganda will then speak about its work on agroecology and evidence of its social equity and the resilience-building properties of agroecology.  However, despite the huge potential of agroecological approaches, the policy enabling environment to support agroecology is still weak, and Mr. O'Brien from Tr&oacute;caire will close with recommendations for the committee to consider.</p> <p>  Tr&oacute;caire's aim is to encourage Ireland, through its engagement with the Rome-based food agencies - FAO, IFAD and the WFP - and through its overseas development assistance programme, to increase and deepen its engagement and support for agroecology.  Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s vision is for a just and peaceful world where people's dignity is ensured and rights are respected, where basic needs are met and resources are shared equitably, where people have control over their own lives and where those in power act for the common good.  Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s current strategic plan pursues this vision by prioritising three key areas of work - women's empowerment; humanitarian preparedness and response; and resource rights.</p> <p>  Under resource rights, we address the sustainable use and management of natural resources.  In 2018, we had programmes in ten countries - Democratic Republic of Congo, Guatemala, Kenya, Malawi, Nicaragua, Pakistan, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Uganda and Zimbabwe.  These programmes supported poor rural households to become more nutrition secure and have better economic, social and environmental futures through maintaining and enhancing the natural resource base on which they depend.  In the macro environment in which we live today, the number of people living in hunger is again rising and, globally, a disproportionate number of those affected are small-scale family farmers.</p><p>These small-scale farmers continue to deliver up to three quarters of food consumed in a large part of the developing world but they are doing so on a declining share of farmland.  The rapid urbanisation that is happening is accompanied by insufficient non-agricultural work.  The degradation of the resource base is undermining the resilience of farmers who are trying to deal with climate change and related extreme weather patterns.  Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s agricultural and food interventions are concerned with identifying the agriculture and food approaches that are best placed to reconcile responses to the multiple and interconnected challenges of food security, nutritional adequacy, environmental protection and social equity.  At a time of increasing hunger and malnutrition, land degradation, rapid urbanisation, climate crisis and unprecedented levels of biodiversity loss, there is an urgent need to reframe agricultural and food policies to ensure they are adequate for tackling poverty and hunger, increasing small-scale farmers' resilience to climate change and promoting biodiversity.</p><p> Based on Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s country programme experience and the growing compendium of research that examines these and related issues, our interventions are increasingly based on agroecological approaches.  We are here today to talk about such approaches.  In essence, agroecology is about agroecosystems mimicking the biodiversity and functioning of natural ecosystems.  Such agricultural systems can be productive, pest-resistant, nutrient-conserving and resilient to shocks and stresses.  Agroecological practices include integrating trees with livestock and crops, producing food from forests, growing several crops together in one plot and using locally adapted and genetically diverse crops and livestock.  These practices combine local indigenous knowledge with modern ecological science to generate good yields and multifunctional benefits.  The adoption of agroecological practice is growing across Tr&oacute;caire's programme countries.  It is being documented that a wider diversity of food types is being grown by households.  We are particularly pleased to be joined today by Mr. Joshua Aijuka from our Ugandan partner, PELUM Uganda.  Last year, 17 new communities in Uganda mapped their wild food resources and made plans for their protection.  Thousands of additional households in Uganda are accessing water for food production through rainwater harvesting and solar systems.  All of this is part of our agroecological approaches.  I ask Mr. Aijuka to explain a little more about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.12" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Joshua Aijuka" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#K00200"><p>PELUM Uganda has been working since 1995 to improve the livelihoods of smallholder farmers and the sustainability of rural communities through ecological land use management.  We work collaboratively with like-minded organisations to share skills and knowledge about good practices and techniques, to undertake research and demonstration projects and to advocate for policies that better support small-scale farmers.  PELUM Uganda is part of an association of civil society organisations from 12 countries across eastern, central and southern Africa.  Our current strategic plan focuses on three major areas: sustainable farming systems, with a specific focus on the wide promotion of climate-resilient agroecological systems, farmer-managed seed systems, traditional indigenous and wild foods and local innovations in agriculture; agricultural market development; and advocacy towards policy makers at national level and links to regional and continental processes for an enabling policy environment which supports the rights of smallholder farmers and the advancement of agroecology.</p> <p>  PELUM Uganda is one of five partners that are implementing a five-year project aimed at securing resource rights for smallholder farmers in eastern and northern Uganda.  PELUM Uganda is providing technical capacity support on agroecology to four local implementing partners, which are working with 48,000 smallholder farmers.  The project applies participatory approaches, such as an climate-resilient agroecosystems model and a gender action learning systems methodology to facilitate gender-responsive, inclusive and sustainable management of natural and agricultural ecosystems in the context of climate change.  PELUM Uganda is the new country lead organisation for the ecological organic agriculture initiative and the co-host of the eastern Africa knowledge hub on organic farming.</p> <p>  Agriculture is critical for Uganda's economy and for its population, which is growing quickly.  The majority of the population live in rural areas and are directly dependent on agriculture for their livelihoods.  Agriculture employs approximately 69% of the labour force, 77% of whom are women and most of whom reside in rural areas.  Specific challenges are having a negative impact on the performance of the sector in terms of production and productivity.  Soil and land degradation is the key challenge in this context.  According to a study by the International Fertiliser Development Centre, Uganda is one of the countries in sub-Saharan Africa with the highest rates of soil degradation, leading to a loss of approximately 12% of our GDP.</p><p> The ambitions to transform the agriculture sector from a largely subsistence to a more commercially oriented agriculture largely fail to recognise the shortcomings of this approach in terms of delivering inclusive socioeconomic development, especially for poor smallholder farmers, or strengthening resilience to the growing challenges related to climate change.  Other negative linkages relate to the practice of commercial agriculture on large aggregated land holdings.  In a context where diverse tenurial systems exist, the potential for unlawful land evictions of vulnerable smallholder farmers and encroachment onto communally held lands and natural ecosystems that offer key ecosystem services for current and future generations represent significant threats in terms of poverty and conflict.  We have provided some cases in the submission.</p><p> There exists an ever-growing evidence base, both globally and nationally, that agroecological production systems deliver a more inclusive and sustainable path to rural agricultural transformation.  A long-term comparative assessment, which was conducted by Misereor in Uganda, revealed that locally adapted means of sustainable farm management offer more viable alternatives for smallholder farmers than conventional industrial farming, which in this case would be the contract outgrower schemes that link with conventional farms to sell produce, and conventional farming.  Farmers who were practising agroecological farming exhibited more resilience to market fluctuations, pest and disease outbreaks and harsh climatic conditions compared with their conventional counterparts.  As a result, smallholder agroecological farmers were more food and nutrition secure through their dietary diversity.  They also had higher incomes because they had to spend less on food since they were growing it, they used family labour and used locally sourced inputs.  They were also spending less on medical care for basic ailments.</p><p> I will hand over to Michael O'Brien to present the conclusions and recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.14" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Michael O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#L00200"><p>In the context of the multidimensional social, economic and environmental challenges faced by small-scale farmers in Uganda and across Tr&oacute;caire programme countries and the potential of agroecological approaches to significantly respond to these challenges, realising this potential requires supportive public policies and investments.  Tr&oacute;caire&rsquo;s report, "Food Democracy: Feeding the World Sustainably", outlines factors that currently impede the widespread adoption of agroecological approaches, while also noting initiatives that could enable the scaling up of agroecological systems.  Support for agroecology is highly compatible with progressing the transformative and sustainable ambition of Agenda 2030 for Sustainable Development and the sustainable development goals.  Sustainable development goal 2.4 specifically seeks to "ensure sustainable food production systems and implement resilient agricultural practices that increase productivity and production, that help maintain ecosystems, that strengthen capacity for adaptation to climate change, extreme weather, drought, flooding and other [natural] disasters and that progressively improve land and soil quality".</p> <p>  There is growing importance in policy discourses from the Food and Agriculture Organization attached to Ireland's new international development policy, A Better World, and to the role agroecology can play in effectively responding to diverse social, economic and environmental challenges, including delivering on the right to adequate food for all, promoting biodiversity, resilience to climate and fiscal shocks and greater social equity.  Just as Ireland took a lead role in ensuring agreement of the sustainable development goals, Tr&oacute;caire believes Ireland is well placed to take similar leadership on sustainable agricultural systems, particularly agroecologically based agricultural and food systems, and welcomes this opportunity to invite the committee to consider the following six recommendations.</p> <p>  The first is to engage the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade with responsibility for the diaspora and international development on the relevance of agroecology in tackling the multiple challenges outlined in sustainable development goal 2.4 and its wider potential to contribute to Agenda 2030 for Sustainable Development.</p> <p>  The second is to inquire from the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade how Ireland is advancing the European Union consensus on development commitment to supporting agroecological practices and actions to reduce post-harvest losses and food waste, as well as to protect soils, conserve water resources, halt, prevent and reverse deforestation and maintain biodiversity and healthy ecosystems.</p><p>The third recommendation is to inquire of the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which leads Ireland&rsquo;s relationship with the UN Rome-based food agencies, how Ireland is actively supporting the Food and Agriculture Organization-led scaling up of the agroecology initiative.</p><p> The fourth is to ask the same Department how Ireland is contributing to an effective policy convergence process and timely conclusion to the Committee on World Food Security high-level panel of experts report on agroecological approaches and other innovations for sustainable agriculture and food systems that enhance food security and nutrition.</p><p> The fifth is to promote the integration of agroecology into research and development strategies with particular reference to the roll-out of the food intervention priority in Ireland&rsquo;s new international development policy, A Better World.</p><p> The sixth is to encourage budget support for agroecological innovations, research and practices in Uganda and other priority partner countries.</p><p> We thank members for their attention and welcome their questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#M00200"><p>The first member to indicate was Deputy Penrose.  He will be followed by Deputies Cahill, Corcoran Kennedy and Martin Kenny in that order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1370" speakername="Willie Penrose" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#M00300"><p>I thank the representatives of Tr&oacute;caire and PELUM for appearing before the committee and giving us a very useful insight into the work that is going on and the importance of the input we can have.  They have contributed to a realisation that we are a significantly wealthy country in terms of what we contribute and highlighted the importance of the international policy development objectives set out in A Better World.</p> <p>  What share of the population of Uganda is involved in agriculture?  Is it subsistence agriculture?  What is the average size of a holding?  I have no doubt that they are small.  Agroecology is something with which members are very familiar.  It involves going back to the old system of working with nature as well ensuring that certain challenges are overcome, such as pests or diseases that are resistant to various products.  On the help that can be given to achieve the acro-ecological practices set out and the actions to reduce various things, where can Ireland take a lead?  What role has Ireland played to date in the wider world structure in that regard?  What can it do to ensure that adequate food mechanisation policy is pursued in those areas?  What level of monetary, physical and technical resource is being given globally to assist in that regard?</p> <p>  Obviously, all present are aware of the natural disasters that have taken place.  What can be done to try to prevent further disasters such as drought or flooding?  How can our mechanical, technical and other expertise be utilised in that regard?  Where can we fit into any programme that the organisations may be designing to achieve very worthy and important objectives?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#M00400"><p>I thank the representatives for their presentations.  Similar to Deputy Penrose, I would like more information on the kind of agriculture in Uganda.  There were frequent references in the presentation by the three delegates to small-scale family farmers.  Is there commercial farming in Uganda or are all farmers there on a small-scale family farm structure?  According to the written statement provided, "the numbers of people living in hunger are again rising, a disproportionate number of whom are small scale family farmers".  Is that because farmers are selling what they produce in order to pay bills?  Unless there is a famine in a country, farmers can usually feed their families at the very least.  Why would family farmers be descending into the hunger trap?</p><p>How much food is produced in Uganda?  How much food does Uganda import?  Has Uganda the economic facility to import food?</p><p> B&oacute;thar is an Irish charitable organisation that regularly delivers heifers to these countries and the animals are greatly prized by the families who receive them.  Has the initiative been expanded to help develop a dairy industry in Uganda that would, in turn, help people to feed themselves?  Are heifers delivered to families on a once-off basis just to enable families to feed themselves?  Has the initiative of donating heifers been expanded to grow the dairy industry?  </p><p> I have a serious lack of knowledge about the agricultural structure in Uganda.  Obviously poverty in the region is extremely worrying.  The objectives are welcome but I would like to hear more background information.  Earlier it was mentioned that 48,000 people are working on various projects.  How many smallholder farmers are there in Uganda?  Is there any commercial farming activity in the country?  If so, what quantity and type of product are produced?  What is the food shortfall in food production that necessitates imports if the country had the wherewithal to purchase food?   </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#N00200"><p>I thank the witnesses for coming here this afternoon and making presentations.</p> <p>  Why do women account for 77% of agricultural employees?  Have many men migrated or are they in other roles in the area?  Why has Uganda the highest rate of soil degradation in sub-Saharan Africa?  Has climate change led to desertification or are other factors at play?</p> <p>  I read the description of agroecology given by the witnesses and, to me, it sounds quite like permaculture.  Is that the style of production being considered?  I am not an expert but please confirm whether my assessment of agroecology is right or wrong.  Please give a specific example of a model that has worked in Uganda, and outline what it was like at the start and where it is now.  </p> <p>  Ireland may be a small island nation but it is a very well developed and rich country that has climate responsibilities.  This meeting is timely as witnesses have told us that  Uganda, as a developing country, has been negatively impacted by the success of the developed world through the production of greenhouse gas emissions and all of the rest.  We must become more aware of our climate responsibilities and it is part of the national conversation at this stage.  That is my observation.  It would be helpful if the witnesses answered my few questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1345" speakername="Martin Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#N00300"><p>I thank all of the witnesses for their interesting presentations.  I was struck by a couple of comments, particularly the document entitled  Transformation Pathways for Developing Country Agriculture, which seem to call for countries to step away from the conventional drive towards a more industrialised-type of agriculture and return to a low-intensity but higher nature type of farming.  That is probably what the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, and other things are trying to make us do in this country as well.  It is ironic that for the last 40 or more years Ireland and many other countries in the developed world have pushed for intensive farming practices and increased production.</p><p>As the economy of a country develops, agriculture becomes less important, fewer people work it, it becomes more mechanised and has fewer people involved, and it becomes more specialised.  Scientists now tell us all of that is to the detriment of nature and ultimately to the farmer as well.  It is about catching that in time.</p><p> I seek clarity on the impact of climate change on Uganda, and Africa in general.  Has there been much of an effect in recent decades?  We are told that most of the impact of climate change is on developing countries and especially Africa.  This is an opportunity to share with us on how significant an impact climate change is having.</p><p> I am also interested to hear about the multinational industries involved such as Bayer, Monsanto and other large companies that work on the basis of selling more of their seeds, fertilisers, sprays and products to farmers.  Some consider it to be an opportunity but others call it a trap.  The farmers become large providers of cash crops, which are susceptible to crashes, and they might have a good income for a number of years and then have nothing for a period.  I am interested in hearing about the inherent instability because the witnesses appear to say they are trying to get away from that and to go in a different direction.  I am interested in the role of multinational companies because we have been told that some of the products that have been banned in the west are still being pushed and are used, especially in Africa and in other countries, and I would like to hear about that.</p><p> When I think of Africa I am struck by its size, which is something very few realise.  Europe, China, and most of America could fit in Africa.  It is enormous and the scale and size of it is something of which most people in other parts of the world are unaware.  I firmly believe that Africa has more than the capacity to feed itself.  It is just poorly organised.  Perhaps there are reasons for that which are not always internal and make sure that is the case.  I would welcome some comment in that regard.</p><p> Reference was made to the sustainable development goals, SDGs, especially 2.4, and I am interested in discussing the issue.  The SDGs are about making sure that everything is done in a sustainable manner, which will look after the humans on the Earth, as well as everything else that is on it.  I often hear the term used - and Bono was criticised for using it - to tell them it is about trade not aid.  Trade is the answer to all of the problems rather than giving aid.  I am interested in the views of the witnesses on that because it may sound like a lovely little clich&eacute; but when one gets down to it, is that the issue?  Is trade the answer, in particular for a continent the size of Africa?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#O00200"><p>I welcome the representatives from Tr&oacute;caire and PELUM Uganda.  I seek clarification on agriculture in Uganda.  Is there a transition at the moment from previous agricultural methods to agroecology or is the agriculture sector in Uganda only beginning to grow now on the back of the stimulus from the new approach?</p> <p>  In order to get a better picture of the land ownership situation in Uganda, are the smallholdings owned by farmers or are they tenants of larger landlords?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.24" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Olive Moore" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#O00300"><p>I thank members for their open engagement and their considered and thoughtful questions.</p><p>I will try to respond to a few of them, and then I will hand over to my colleague, Mr. Aijuka, to talk about the Ugandan experience and to Mr. O'Brien to look at trade and other issues around that.</p><p> Deputy Penrose asked about what we can do, which is a very important question, and first and foremost the Deputy mentioned resources.  One of the commitments made in A Better World was that the Irish Government will meet its commitments to 0.7% around resourcing.  A very practical thing this committee can do is reinforce and support that commitment, and monitor it so that we do reach that 0.7% for our overseas development assistance.</p><p> Second, many of the recommendations that we have for the committee today are around engaging with the Department of Agriculture Food and the Marine and its role within this, and the importance of understanding the policy coherence, that these international development issues are not just issues for the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade or other external-facing Departments, but reach across all of our Government and all our Departments.</p><p> Third is the area of climate, which the Deputy mentioned.  One of the most pertinent and topical issues is understanding the impact of climate change but also understanding that biodiversity meltdown and soil degradation is happening and that the impact is happening in developing countries and here in Ireland today.  One thing that is very current at the moment and which we very much welcome is the recent report from the Joint Committee on Climate Action, as well as the climate action plan that is being discussed and debated by the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and the Environment.  Engaging with that plan is a practical thing we could see this committee doing.</p><p> Deputy Cahill asked why we still have hunger today.  One of the most important points to put home is that there is enough food in the world today to feed the population.  It is not a question of scarcity of food.  There is enough food in the world today to feed the population of Africa, or even a growing population.  The issues around hunger are related to adequacy, accessibility, availability, and sustainability.  What that comes down to, essentially, is politics and power.  It is not necessarily about the food itself but about who has access to that food, who controls decisions around that food and, critically and more importantly today, sustainability in relation to the impact on climate change, biodiversity, and soil degradation.  The issues are far more complex than simply the amount of food, but are to do with who has it and availability around resources.</p><p> Deputy Corcoran Kennedy had a question around 77% of farmers actually being women.  One issue we have seen over the last decade is the increasing feminisation of agriculture and farmers.  Part of that, as the Deputy mentioned, is due to some of these communities coming under immense pressure and a resulting urbanisation trend of people migrating towards cities.  Very often it is the men who migrate and the women who are left alone on the farm.  Regardless of that, a lot of the burden of work on farms does generally fall to women and has always traditionally fallen to women, who are responsible for farming and feeding families.  There are very strong gendered aspects to this, and when we look at vulnerability and the impacts of climate change, it is first and foremost women and children who are feeling this and who we are most concerned about.  We have to keep them in the back of our mind constantly in any approaches we have around this.</p><p> There were questions on some successes we have had.  Increasingly, there is growing evidence around the value of agroecological approaches.  Tr&oacute;caire recently carried out research in Guatemala, for example, where we showed how farmers using agroecological practices realised significantly higher incomes in comparison with their counterparts using semi-conventional systems.  We found that the outcome related to a number of factors, including the attainment of comparable yields in crops such as maize, but without a reliance on expensive artificial inputs.  I was talking recently to some of my colleagues in Zimbabwe about Cyclone Idai, and one of the things we are starting to see and gathering evidence to show is that communities of farmers using agroecological approaches were more resilient to onset floods, cyclones, and so on.  Their crops were stronger, more resilient, and more able to withstand some of these changing weather patterns.  Something we ourselves are working hard on is collecting more evidence and research to show this.  It is not only us.  Other big organisations, such as the Food and Agriculture Organisation of the United Nations, FAO, are far more interested and engaged in this, and indeed my colleague from PELUM can talk a bit more about it.</p><p> On the whole question of climate change and its impact, we are seeing this across the board.  Tr&oacute;caire's concern is mainly with small-scale farmers on the front line of this and are experiencing climate biodiversity meltdown and soil degradation.  These farmers are on the front lines of experiencing the detrimental effects of climate change while at the same time are least responsible for causing it.  It is playing out in many different ways across communities.</p><p>Livelihoods are being eroded, economic migration is being forced on communities, food security is at risk, crops are failing, and weather patterns on which people traditionally relied are now entirely unpredictable.  I have sat with farmers who have told me that the rains have not come and then, when the rains eventually come, they come so heavily that they cause floods and wipe out entire crops.  This leads to families going hungry but also has an impact on families' excess money for healthcare, education for their children, and so on.  It not only affects families and individuals, the whole social fabric of communities is being decimated because these people do not have the resilience to withstand the huge stresses being put on them.  My colleague, Mr. Aijuka, can speak further on the impact of that.  I will hand over to him to address the questions about Uganda, of which there were quite a few.  Mr. O'Brien might also have some further comments to add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Joshua Aijuka" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#Q00200"><p>I thank the committee for this opportunity.  I will start with the part of Uganda that practises agriculture.  This was broadly highlighted.  Uganda is predominantly an agricultural nation.  All of us are born farmers, or most of us at least.  Everyone is linked to farming.  One's parent is a farmer.  Approximately 66% of Ugandans derive their livelihood directly from agriculture, the majority of these being women.  Most of the agriculture in Uganda is family agriculture; it is largely practised by members of the family.  There are also cases of commercial agriculture, which has existed in some regions for quite a long time.  For example, there have been plantations of sugar cane in the eastern part of the country for quite a long time.  It is interesting that the poverty levels in regions in which we have had plantation agriculture are among the highest.  There has also been a lot of pressure on natural ecosystems; wetlands have been destroyed and forests are being cut down and given away.  There are several cases of that right now.  In transforming agriculture and moving it forward, a question arises as to whether this is the approach we need to take.  There is commercial agriculture in Uganda.  The food that is produced is largely consumed at home but some is sold.  That is how the people are able to sustain themselves.</p> <p>  One of the challenges we face is the fact that market prices are not that conducive.  Market prices for, for example, hybrid maize fall when the yield is really good so farmers may not be able to afford to buy seed for the next season.  There are also programmes under which the Government gives out inputs.  For example, right now it is giving out a lot of hybrid maize.  Last year there was an outbreak of fall armyworm which almost ate up the bigger part of the yield.  Farmers who had gone fully into that area of farming could not even get seed to plant for the next season because they had been used to being given seed by the Government for quite a while and had lost the ability to produce their own inputs.  </p> <p>  I will also comment on the issue of women and the situation on the ground.  Why are there more women involved?  The role given to women has always been to provide the food but agriculture is becoming more unpredictable.  Men move out and look for other opportunities but women do not have the opportunity to do so in most cases.  They have to stick around to feed their families.  Climate change is causing an increase in this trend.  As the men go they tend to move into practices that are not environmentally friendly, for example, charcoal burning.  I do not know if this is something with which the committee will be familiar; it is fuel produced using biomass.  The men move into such enterprises, which feed into land degradation trends, because they can no longer rely on agriculture in such uncertain times.</p><p>My colleague has spoken about why degradation is so high.  It is partly because of that.  As a result of the change in patterns, we have missed a couple of seasons.  Traditionally, farmers were used to growing crops in a certain season, but now things have changed considerably.  Rains now intensify all of a sudden.  Heavy downpours cause erosion and destroy crops and sometimes property.  The rate at which the natural cover is being destroyed means there is nothing holding the soil together.  When the rains come, intensive erosion takes its course.</p><p> Deputy Corcoran Kennedy asked whether agroecology is like permaculture.  I would say that permaculture is assisting within agroecology.  It is basically a way of designing a system that mimics nature, in a way.  While there is a very strong relationship between agroecology and permaculture, agroecology is much broader.  It looks not only at the science but also at the social aspects which cause things to be the way they are.  It is about being able to organise farmers into a strong movement that is able to change and influence things and take up its rightful position in the food system.</p><p> I am not sure if I have left out anything.  I will be glad to respond to any further questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Michael O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#R00200"><p>I will make a few comments in response to questions that have been raised.  Deputies Penrose and Corcoran Kennedy both referred to agroecology as something that works with nature.  They sounded somewhat familiar with the concept.  Such familiarity can sometimes generate the idea that agroecology involves going backwards.  We would like to impress on the members of the committee the idea that agroecology, which may sound familiar, is a modern fusion of the best traditional approaches, the best traditional knowledge and the best practitioner knowledge with the best and most advanced ecological science.  That is what agroecology represents.</p> <p>  Ms Moore has spoken about what Ireland can do to support the scaling up and scaling out of agroecology.  In that regard, I draw attention to the recommendations we are making to the committee today.  Some of the international processes which are afoot are being led by the UN food agencies, particularly the UN Food and Agriculture Organization, FAO.  The success of initiatives aimed at scaling up agroecology depends on the demonstration by member countries across the international community of support for such initiatives.  I encourage the committee to ask the relevant Departments how Ireland is supporting the scaling up of agroecology initiatives and the process afoot at the Committee on World Food Security, which is examining agroecological approaches and seeking to make recommendations later this year on the best innovations for sustainable agriculture and food systems.</p> <p>  Deputy Cahill's question about why farm families continue to fall into a hunger trap has been addressed in part by my colleagues.  Developments over several decades can be cited as another part of the reason.  The structural adjustment policies of the 1980s and 1990s, which were led by the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund, had a particularly negative impact on African agriculture, about which we are talking this afternoon.</p><p>Its negative impact was to reorient the focus towards large-scale monocultural export-driven produce, rather than looking at the basis of the livelihoods of the 500 million plus small-scale farming producers.  By small scale, we mean farmers with less than 2 ha.  The majority of those would now have less than 1 ha.  There has been relative neglect as evidenced by the direction taken since the 1990s in response to those structural adjustment policies.  The fiscal commitments that many governments have given have privileged that monocultural export-driven production rather than considering domestic and local markets.  That requires revisiting trade policies and investment policies and looking to trade policies that support access to local markets, competitiveness of small scale farmers in those local, national and regional markets without the same emphasis on international markets.  </p><p> In answer to Deputy Corcoran Kennedy's question about the feminisation of agriculture, another related dimension which raises the importance of agroecology is that although there is very significant migration to urban environments, those urban environments are failing to create the employment opportunities for many of those who go there.  The Food and Agricultural Organization is highlighting that there is not commensurate employment generation and because of that there is a need to consider what forms of agriculture in these societies can really sustain decent livelihoods.  There is opportunity in agroecology, which is more labour intensive than capital intensive, to create quality jobs, on and off-farm, in the rural economy.  </p><p> There was a question about differences or similarities between permaculture and agroecology and, as Mr. Aijuka said, there are significant similarities in respect of specific practices in permaculture, organic farming and agroecology.  There are three distinguishing features of agroecology, the first of which is the co-creation of knowledge, that is, the emphasis on the best of indigenous farmer knowledge fused with the best of ecological scientific knowledge.  The second is the linkages made with local markets, which puts the focus on local markets and circular economies, rather than long-distance value chains focused on meeting the needs of international markets.  The third feature concerns meeting the food and nutritional needs of the households and the local communities. </p><p> Deputy Martin Kenny asked about the sustainable development goals and the relevance of agroecology to those.  I draw the Deputy's attention to the Food and Agricultural Organization's scaling up agroecology initiative, transforming food and agricultural systems in support of the sustainable development goals.  The Food and Agricultural Organization is joining Tr&oacute;caire and PELUM tomorrow in a policy roundtable, to which committee members will have received invitations, that will deal with this specific topic.  It shows that agroecology is relevant to virtually all of the sustainable development goals.  It is also highly relevant to the report that was published last week on biodiversity.  The global assessment report on biodiversity and ecosystem services by the UN Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services, whose status is equivalent to that of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, IPCC, work on climate change and action, the 1.5o report, has underlined the urgency of the biodiversity loss and the threat that represents.</p><p>In terms of the SDGs, it tells us that progress towards achieving 80% of the goals, that is, 35 out of the 44 assessed targets of the goals relating to poverty, hunger, health, water, cities, climate, oceans and land, will not be met if we do not address the biodiversity challenge.  Agroecology is all about diversity, moving away from monoculture and towards a system that builds nutritious, sustainable food systems.  </p><p> I thank the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#T00200"><p>We have addressed all the questions at this stage.  Are members happy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#T00300"><p>With the permission of the Chairman, may I ask two brief question?  I was engaged in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#T00400"><p>I am sorry that I missed the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#T00500"><p>Last week Dr. Sinead McCarthy from Teagasc appeared before the committee on Europe Day.  We discussed food in the context of climate action, carbon emissions and the contention that we need to get more of our protein from plants.  I observed that when one goes into the supermarket and looks for beans, lentils, and pulses, all these products are imported.  Dr. McCarthy acknowledged that growing beans and different plant proteins for human consumption is not ideally suited to our climate or soil.  This would, therefore, necessitate importing such produce, unless there is some other solution.  My understanding is that agricultural land in the tropics and in developing countries is probably more suited to growing this produce.  Is there not a conflict in policy that needs to be addressed?  How is it being teased out?  Some of my colleagues gave the example of the avocado, but what are the number of air miles to bring an avocado to Ireland?  Will the witnesses comment on the interplay between people at subsistence level who are producing food and those in first world countries thinking they are doing well by eating more plant-based protein and how that looks in the round?</p><p>Second, the witnesses from Tr&oacute;caire outlined the work they are doing to improve the situation for many people, but what engagement do they have with African governments?  Do those governments allow Tr&oacute;caire to proceed with its work or do they implement the programme that it suggests or co-fund it?  Do they have national reach and irrigation programmes, and do they make moves to stop deforestation in the manner it is happening in some countries?  To what extent are these governments engaging and accepting Tr&oacute;caire's principles?  It seems that in many African countries, especially in east Africa, the gulf between the wealthy and the poor is widening and even though the continent has more wealth, the poor are poorer than they ever were<font color="#FFFFFF">.</font></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.36" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Olive Moore" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#T00600"><p>I will respond to Senator Mulherin's second question and my colleague will then respond to her first question.</p> <p>  Tr&oacute;caire works through a partnership model.  What that means is that Tr&oacute;caire does not directly implement policy on the ground.  We work through partners such as PELUM Uganda or civil society organisations but also many different and diverse types of organisations, including the church.  Part of that partnership is certainly working with government.  In every country that we work in, we engage with the government.  We are in dialogue with government, both at national level and increasingly at local level in the communities where we work.  In some countries that may include working directly supporting government and delivering services but in many cases it means working alongside government, understanding the work it is doing and seeing where we can fit and how we can complement what it is doing.  Our experience has been mixed from country to country and it can also be mixed within a country from local authority to local authority.  Most recently I travelled to Tigre in northern Ethiopia, met government officials and saw some of the reforestation programmes.</p><p>I saw many of the projects that have been put in place, which were complementary to agroecology and embracing the approaches around it.  Our role is working through our partners and complementing the work of governments in those countries.  It can be mixed because in many of those countries, there are strong vested interests who may be working against some of these programmes and policies inside and outside government and trying to influence government.  A core part of our approach is advocating for the government to influence the role it has and many of our partners, such as PELUM are active in that regard.  I invite Mr. Joshua Aijuka to comment on engaging with the Ugandan government</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.38" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Joshua Aijuka" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#U00200"><p>We have a memorandum of understanding with the line Ministries, including for agriculture and land, and this gives us a good platform for us to engage with government.  We also try to engage with government at local level, trying to ensure that they share the benefit of our experience.  We target the extension services providers on agroecology where we work and we can see a way of mainstreaming agroecology in what we do.  Towards the end of this month, we are organising the national agroecology actors symposium, and together with the Minister for agriculture, the FAO and the Uganda programme, so that we can look for mechanism of how to work together on a large scale in terms of mainstreaming agroecology and the way of work, especially for the government.</p> <p>  This collaboration is always about dialogue and dissent.  In some cases we support government to deliver these services to the people.  In cases where we feel some of the interventions are not that favourable, we are there to sit at the round table and have a discussion on the proposed alternatives.  We always choose dialogue.  We look for solutions together and look at the alternatives and over time we earn the mutual respect to be able to sit around the table and discuss alternatives but in some case, one does not get the change that one wants and then one has to keep pushing.</p> <p>  A question was asked about land holdings and I forgot to respond to it.  In Uganda, approximately 80% of the land is owned communally so that the land is passed on from one generation to the next.  We have some land that is freehold, with title, and that can be sold.  We live in a patriarchal society so men have greater powers in deciding on land use and issues of ownership.  Women have access to the land and can use the land to grow crops, but they cannot transact or do anything of that nature.  That is the system in which we work.  It always poses a challenge where there a majority of smaller farmers move to industrial agriculture as this requires that them to be displaced through unfair land acquisition schemes because a lot of land is needed for industrial agriculture.  These are some of the dynamics we need to look into, in terms of which model to promote, if we are to put the last first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Michael O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#U00300"><p>I thank the Chairman.  I will deal with Senator Mulherin's second question on the importance of more diversified diets, including more plants and vegetables which was discussed at the committee recently.  That rhymes with the international scientific evidence and advice, which is increasingly coming to the fore.  The Senator is probably familiar with the significant debate that has surround the EAT-Lancet commission's report on healthy diets, which calls for more balanced diets.</p><p>Tr&oacute;caire would certainly endorse the importance of more balanced diets for achieving health, nutrition security and food security, as well as social equity and environmental sustainability.</p><p> Globally, alongside the rising number of people in hunger, we see the increasing number who are living with malnutrition, both in developed and developing countries.  In order to address this, we need to look at a transformation in some of what we are doing in the agricultural and food system, and biodiversity is a key dimension.  Having more diverse production, whereby Ireland would be in the position to grow more fruit and vegetables that are suitable for this climate, means we would not need to import so many carrots or onions as they could be grown here.  Similarly, there should be a concentration in developing countries around diverse fruits and vegetables where climatic conditions are conducive in those environments.  Through that, we believe we would be supporting the ecosystems and ecosystem services that are at the very base of ensuring agriculture continues in a healthy condition, both here and globally.  I am talking about those services around provisioning, food security and regulation, and around addressing health and climate regulation, as well as the cultural and spiritual value that is associated with food.  There are also the support services around ensuring that natural habitats are retained and that soils remain healthy.  This is why agroecology is very much coming to the fore as something which ticks all of those boxes. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#V00200"><p>That was not really my question, with respect.  What I am saying is that it became obvious during the discussion that we are not so well suited.  I am talking about the protein we get from plants such as beans, not about fruits and vegetables or anything like that, because the debate is around where we get our protein.  In fact, the doctor from Teagasc outlined that we are well-suited to get protein from dairy and beef with our pasture land and all the rest.  We have some challenges in regard to growing plant-based protein and, in fact, what we find on our supermarket shelves is for the most part imported.  Both the climate and soil conditions are more suitable in other countries, which is particularly obvious in the tropics, where people already have challenges with regard to getting food and nutrition.</p> <p>  It seems like a contradiction that there are some agendas pushing people and telling them they should not eat any meat at all.  I am not saying that is the middle-of-the-road view and I believe everyone would agree on a balanced diet, but there is an inherent contradiction in that regard.  My concern in regard to where Tr&oacute;caire is coming from is that if it is talking about somewhere in east Africa, for example, where mung beans or pinto beans are grown which people are suggesting is what people should be eating but which we cannot grow here, are there not other tensions?  For example, do the people in those areas not need to eat those foods themselves?  In addition, we are importing something quite a distance and while I am not suggesting everything is going to come from east Africa, obviously, this food will be transported some distance whereas local is better.</p> <p>  Is this not a legitimate part of the conversation, aside from all that Mr. O'Brien has discussed about the realities for people in Africa and other places which do not have the disposable consumer society we have, where we are trying to stop ourselves from eating wrong foods, and where there would be a whole different set of problems?  It has to be recognised that we do not grow those crops as well in our country and, therefore, are not as efficient in growing them as these other countries.  In the past, when we were looking for biofuels from certain crops, perhaps from east Africa, that had to be stopped because crops were being imported and people were being displaced from their land to meet the demand of the Western economies to feed into biofuels.</p> <p>  Nobody is arguing about biodiversity, ecosystems and doing it right.  I am just saying this is an issue that does not get covered or discussed, although it has been raised here by Deputy Corcoran Kennedy and me.</p><p>Where the food is to be brought from is not discussed.  If it is to be from Third World or developing countries, which are better suited, there are surely challenges already, with which the delegates are very familiar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1345" speakername="Martin Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#W00200"><p>It almost relates to a point I was making initially on whether the approach should be trade or aid.  How important is trade?  Is it an answer?  It seems from what is being said here that it is not in many cases.  Farmers with only 1 ha or 2 ha of land are not going to be producing a massive amount of product to trade with anyone unless they are operating very collectively and co-operatively.  We are always told that if we could get developing countries to trade better, they would trade their way into prosperity.  I doubt that.  I would like the delegates' view on it.  This is related to Senator Mulherin's point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Michael O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#W00300"><p>I will respond and leave the final comment to Ms Moore.  The questions are related.  On the question on trade, the evidence clearly shows that in the 1960s, many African countries were more food secure than today and were net food exporters.  Today, more countries in Africa are food insecure and are net food importers.  The international trading system, in terms of agricultural livelihoods, has not benefited or worked for the small-scale producer, generally speaking.  That is why, along with the environmental concerns, about which we have become much more aware, and in terms of the need for an effective climate response, there is great merit in linking the farmers in question with their local markets and developing local market opportunities so they can derive an additional income in addition to being food secure.  Local, national and regional markets should be emphasised rather than international markets.</p> <p>  With regard to protein and sourcing that protein, there is a significant challenge.  Diversification of agricultural systems is critical to meeting it.  We are not going to comment specifically on the Irish context, but internationally we are examining supporting the more biodiverse systems in light of their being more economically, socially and environmentally sustainable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Olive Moore" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#W00400"><p>We recognise that there are many complexities and that there is no single solution or answer.  Often, we welcome the fact that many of the solutions being proposed are being debated and discussed.  We are examining options and weighing up the implications.  Tr&oacute;caire's concern, first and foremost, is with small-scale farmers in the developing communities and in the countries where we are working and the impact on them.  This is what we wanted to speak about here today, but we very much welcome an ongoing debate and discussion on understanding the agro-ecological solutions we need and their impacts in the communities and countries in which we work and here in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#W00500"><p>That completes our questions on the topic.  I thank the delegates for their very informative presentation.  We will pass on the transcript of this meeting to the relevant Ministers mentioned in the opening presentation and see what response we get.  I thank Mr. O'Brien, Ms Moore and Mr. Aijuka for their presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.47" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.50 p.m. and resumed at 4.55 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.48" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#X00100">Future of the Beef Sector: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#X00200"><p>We are continuing our discussion on the future of the beef industry.  At our meeting before the Easter recess we learned about the Kepak-Glanbia initiative, the programme that was launched towards the middle of April.  The joint committee considered that the initiative might have a contribution to make in the overall discussion we were having on the future of the beef industry.  With that in mind, we decided to invite representatives of Kepak and Glanbia to come before the committee to discuss the initiative.  I thank them for taking up the invitation we extended to them.  From Glanbia Ireland I welcome Mr. Martin Ryan, head of the beef division, and Mr. Pat O'Keeffe.  From Kepak I welcome Mr. Mick O'Dowd, agri-development manager, and Mr Jonathan Forbes.  As they will be aware, the committee is undertaking this initiative of discussing the future of the beef industry.  The issue is very topical throughout the country and we consider that the committee has a part to play in the discussion.</p> <p>  Witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  </p> <p>  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>I invite Mr. Ryan to make his opening statement.  I understand Mr. O'Dowd will also make a contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#Y00200"><p>I thank the members for inviting us and for the opportunity to contribute to their deliberations on the future of the beef sector.  Both Glanbia Ireland and Kepak are delighted to share details with the committee of our collaborative innovation for calf to beef production, the Twenty20 Beef Club.  Both companies have worked together to develop a solution that will bring certainty for farm families involved in the production of beef calves, in response to trends in the national herd.  This innovation was built with the benefit of Glanbia Ireland's experience in fixed milk price schemes and low-cost finance products, such as MilkFlex and FundEquip, and with Kepak's track record in developing clubs such as the KK club and the Angus producer group.  The Twenty20 Beef Club affords members a guaranteed market for their heifers and steers from the time they enter them in the club through a guaranteed pricing formula that will apply at the time of slaughter.  In addition, it delivers a production blueprint supported by safe and secure high-quality farm inputs and leading edge technical advice.</p> <p>  For Kepak customers and consumers, the Twenty20 Beef Club will provide a secure and predictable supply of high-quality beef with unrivalled input traceability and provenance through the attributes of a closed loop supply chain.  The closed loop assurance includes nutritional products, non-prescription animal health products and fertiliser, sourced and supplied by Glanbia Ireland.  From a consumer perspective, this provides absolute traceability regarding key inputs and is the genesis of our ability to pay a very significant club premium.  The first year of the programme is a pilot phase during which 6,000 calves will be enrolled on Glanbia Ireland and Kepak supplier farms throughout the Republic of Ireland.  Numbers will increase to 20,000 in year 2, with a target of 50,000 from year 3 and subsequent years.</p> <p>  The Twenty20 Beef Club was developed to bring greater certainty and predictability to beef production for all stakeholders in the industry.  Some of the benefits are a guaranteed market for club cattle, a predictable pricing structure, targeted reduction in the age at slaughter, management of nutrition, a technical support programme to assist members achieve output targets, targeted improvement in eating quality and environmental management, an advance payment mechanism to support cashflow, and full and final payment on the day of slaughter.  The primary objective is to create a new end-to-end model for sustainable beef production.  It is anchored in the market.  It is farmer-centric and built on a collaborative partnership between two industry leaders.  This approach enables Kepak to deliver a premium for farmers from the market.</p> <p>  A key feature of the Twenty20 Beef Club offering is that members can benefit from an optional advance payment package of up to &euro;770 per animal to provide cashflow during the animal's lifetime, which offers farmers a more stable income from beef production.  This will be administered and payable upon credit approval by Finance Ireland.  Members have the option of selecting a monthly payment per animal of &euro;25 or &euro;35 per head at an APR of 3.9%.  Payment can be made from month 3 to month 24, and up to 90% of a club member's registered cattle can qualify.  During the pilot phase, the advance payment package is supported by Glanbia Co-op.  It is the intention that this finance package will be available to all credit-approved club members after the pilot stage is completed.</p> <p>  I now hand over to Mr. O'Dowd, who will continue the statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.52" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#Y00300"><p>The Twenty20 Beef Club will be open to dairy farmers, beef finishers or suckler farmers rearing dairy calves sourced from the Glanbia herd and supplying Kepak with finished animals.  Glanbia Ireland and Kepak staff will work together and will provide technical farm support to members as the programme develops.  This will involve leading edge advice on breeding, nutrition, animal health and welfare, grassland management, and slaughter preparation.</p> <p>  A key target for the club is sustainability, with an ambition to become world leading on environmental standards.  It focuses strongly on leveraging science and technology, including genomics, genetic evaluations and greenhouse gas reduction.  Eligible calves will have to have a known sire recorded on the AIMS registration system from 2020.  Stock bulls must be pedigree registered and genotyped.  Some 10% of calves entering the programme must be genotyped to verify breed and parentage.  Dairy farmer members must select bulls with a specified minimum Irish Cattle Breeding Federation, ICBF, dairy beef index.  All members must be approved and fully compliant with Bord Bia's sustainable beef and lamb assurance scheme and, as such, must be verified members of Origin Green.  It targets a reduction in the average age of the cattle at slaughter, which will reduce the environmental footprint of the beef produced.</p><p>Additionally, the nutritional programme will incorporate methane-reducing feed additives that will improve feed conversion efficiency and further reduce methane output.</p><p> The Twenty20 Beef Club targets increasing beef output and sales value per hectare through improved efficiencies on farm.  This focus will increase the proportion of dairy bred cattle meeting market specifications.  The pricing model is anchored in the market and will contain the following components: the average quoted price, AQP, as quoted weekly by all ROI processors; a club premium, ranging from 15 cent to 25 cent depending on the AQP applying in the week in question; a club protocol bonus of 12 cent will be paid on all cattle, regardless of grade, meeting the carcase weight specification of 280-360 kg in the first two years - the objective is to increase the number of cattle meeting market specifications through improved breeding and technical support; a breed bonus, which is currently applicable on angus and Hereford, will still apply for club cattle; and a seasonality bonus will be applicable.  In April and June, it will be 6 cent while in May it will be 10 cent.  At an AQP of &euro;3.75, a Twenty20 Beef Club angus steer slaughtered in April 2021 will qualify for a net price to the farmer of &euro;4.28, while at an AQP of &euro;4, the same animal would earn &euro;4.43 per kg.</p><p> In conclusion, we believe the Twenty20 Beef Club delivers a new model for calf-to-beef production; a guaranteed market for members' cattle; a predictable and guaranteed pricing structure; a production blueprint based on leading-edge technical advice; a model to deliver a reduction in environmental impact whilst increasing output; and a product for which the consumer will be happy to pay a premium.  We believe this collaborative cross-sector approach demonstrates an alternative and progressive approach to delivering a more sustainable future for Irish beef and dairy production.  I thank members very much for the invitation to appear before the committee.  There is more detail on the companies behind this new initiative in the material circulated.  We are happy to answer any questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#Z00200"><p>I am not happy with what is being attempted.  While some of the initiatives are welcome, the overall concept of a closed loop is anti-competitive and it is a bad way for two companies to protect farmers' income.  It is a very slippery slope for farmers to go down.</p> <p>  Is the quality assurance bonus, which farmers get at the moment for selling cattle from quality-assured farms, an addition to the club pricing structure?  There is a reference to the breed bonus.  In the heifer and angus schemes, a bonus is paid, which varies depending on the time of the year.  Does this bonus scheme replace the heifer and angus schemes?  Does it incorporate Friesian cattle?  There is a seasonality bonus but angus and heifer schemes in the past have offered bigger seasonality bonuses than in this case.  There is a base price for typical club cattle.  I have the misfortune of being one of those farmers that finish cattle out of Friesian cows and I can say that R= grade or R- grade are not typical cattle.  If I saw an R on a classification sheet now, I would reckon a mistake had been made in the grading because they are as scarce as hens' teeth.  It is disingenuous to produce a table of R= and R- grade cattle from the dairy herd.</p><p>Do O- grade cattle qualify on this pricing structure?  They do not qualify on the quality assurance scheme.</p><p> How many cattle from the dairy herd killed in 2018 would meet the requirements of this scheme, taking into account weight restrictions, age and grade?  I believe the percentage of Aberdeen angus heifers which get to the carcase weights would be small.  A lot more research needs to be done on sexed semen and it has to be promoted more.  If our beef industry is to survive, it has to progress rapidly.  Teagasc has focused on cross-breeds over the past number of years but this has also put us on a slippery slope and has to be reversed.  The presentation states that the consumer wants this but if we went out on Grafton Street or St. Stephen's Green and asked people if they wanted a closed loop for beef production, they would look at us as if we had two heads.  It is incredible and disingenuous to tell us the consumer wants this and will pay a premium for it.  I have been too long in the business to swallow that.  There is a major crisis in incomes from beef farms.</p><p> There is an insinuation that other mills producing top-quality rations are somewhat inferior to what is produced by Glanbia merchants and Glanbia mills.  I am a board member of another co-operative that has a mill and I brought this up at a board meeting last night.  Last year, farmers were under significant pressure in accessing credit and they ran up large bills but this will tie people into a straitjacket by requiring that they deal with just one merchant.  Farmers have experience of credit being pulled from under them very quickly and to tie a farmer to one supplier is anti-competitive.  I cannot see how anyone could propose it.</p><p> More movement restrictions are also being proposed, with only one being allowed in the life of an animal.  This puts farmers into another straitjacket and reduces the options they have as they try to make a profit out of the industry.  Glanbia will not like me saying this, but for the past couple of years, its price for grain and mill has been consistently behind the average paid by other grain merchants and processors.  It pays a top-up after six months or at year end but this top-up is consistently paid out of our own money, that is, the dividend received by the co-operatives.  It galls me that the largest processor in the country uses our money to keep pace with other competitors.  Now, a scheme has been designed that will force farmers to deal with that business.</p><p> We have to change and our beef industry has to change, and I have been to the forefront saying that what we have at the moment cannot continue.  In the beef industry at the moment the question is not who is losing money, but who is losing the least money.</p><p> I welcome the idea of promoting calf to beef systems.  It is something that is needed.  The straitjacket that farmers are being put into is wrong, however.  As a farmer and a public representative, it is a very slippery slope that Glanbia and Kepak are trying to put farmers on.  At first glance, the club pricing structure looks very attractive, but when we see what is in the marketplace at the moment, it takes a lot of the gloss off it.  At the end of the day, when we would be killing cattle coming from the dairy herd, the percentage that would meet those weight requirements would be very small indeed.  This was announced with a fanfare a couple of weeks ago and I was surprised by the silence from different organisations in response to it.  There was a lack of critical analysis of the scheme.  While having cattle killed at younger ages, trying to have sustainable food production and meeting our climate change targets are all welcome initiatives, a Friesian bullock that is killed at 22 or 23 months of age is just not going to meet those weight limits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.57" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Deputy Jackie Cahill took the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1345" speakername="Martin Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#BB00300"><p>We have been discussing the beef sector for the past couple of months.  It is clearly in a lot of trouble and has a lot of problems.  Anything that has the appearance of a solution or way forward or that could assist the sector will naturally be welcomed.  The type of closed loop system that is proposed is one I know quite well.  I used to work in the mushroom industry years ago.  I had mushroom tunnels and it was very much a closed loop system.  We bought the compost, all the materials, packaging, chemicals and everything from a company and then sold the mushrooms back to the same company, which took the cost of everything out of the final price.  We were very much at the mercy of the company.  There were good times but there were bad times as well.  If we got a bad load of compost, for instance, that produced very low yields, we had great difficulty trying to argue our case.  That is one of the problems with the proposal being put forward here.  Farmers will look at the prices and may think they are getting a bit of a bonus here, along with the possibility of getting money up front.  It is up to &euro;770 or up to 75% of the cattle early on, so the farmer can have a cashflow scenario sorted out.  While that looks attractive, many farmers would be very worried about not having the freedom to buy their input from wherever they want or to sell to whoever they want, and that they would be tied in so restrictively.  That needs to be dealt with.</p> <p>  The system can work but I do not think it will work in the long term.  I do not think it is the solution to the problems we have in the beef industry at present.  It may be part of the solution and may work for some farmers who are tied in to an extent.  It might possibly work for dairy farmers who are also producing beef or are both customers of and suppliers to the two groups that are here.  Other farmers would have serious doubts as to the way forward.  The witnesses have a lot of work to do to convince people that this system can work and that it is the solution that was hailed.  I know nobody would present it as being the ultimate solution and the witnesses are not doing so.  Nothing is the ultimate solution for the beef crisis, unfortunately.  Even the prices the witnesses are talking about, with the bonuses added in, go nowhere near making most beef production into a profitable and prosperous industry.  Even prices of &euro;4.28 to &euro;4.43 per kilo will not cut it in the long term when we look at the amount of investment that has to go in.</p><p>The questions that need to be answered are around that.  We need to know how the farmer can be sure he is going to get the proper return and is not going to be over a barrel when it comes to it.  The witnesses gave some estimated figures, for example, if there are 6,000 animals in year one, the figure would go up to more than 50,000 animals by years four to five.  I would like to see how that is going to work.  It will have to be shown to work very well in year one before anyone is going to stay there.</p><p> As was pointed out by my colleague, there is also the issue of all the other suppliers that have very good relationships with and work well for farmers.  They are in business as well.  Farming in the rural community has a kind of micro-economy of its own, in that the farmer, the miller, the veterinary services and everyone around them all depend on each other and work together.  When two big companies - scale is important in any business - set up what is in effect a closed system and a closed model, many people in the community would see it as pushing everyone else out.</p><p> There is also mention of the inputs and a suggestion that the inputs would all come from within the group.  I see that nutritional inputs are included in that.  I see reference to a reduction in the carbon footprint by introducing feed additives that would produce less methane.  Would the witnesses also be talking about medicines for cattle?  Is that part of it?  I would like to get details in respect of all of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1370" speakername="Willie Penrose" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#CC00200"><p>Anything that brings predictability to the situation in terms of the current concerns of beef farmers has to be welcomed.  It is a contribution to bringing something forward that it is hoped will make an input in the longer term.  People are less likely to be exposed to the vagaries of the market.  I can see where it is coming from.  I would say, however, that the proposal is inspired by Glanbia.  It has tried this before with milk.  It is not the first time Glanbia is venturing into this area.  Kepak may well see a benefit in it and may have explored it with the farming public or those from whom its buy its product.  The issue is the closed loop.  It effectively kills competition.  If this succeeds, other co-ops from the milk area will probably be rushing in to pair up with other competitors.  We will shortly have three or four of the big co-ops with three or four processors.  We all have worries about processors at all levels.  In the Twenty20 club, as far as I can see, for the animal to get the bonus, the calf has to come from a Twenty20 farm, be reared on a Twenty20 farm, and has to get all its ingredients from one source: Glanbia.  I thought prescription medicine was exempted.  All the needs and requirements associated have to be got from Glanbia.  It shuts out any competition, which is of concern.  As Deputy Martin Kenny says, there are relationships built up throughout the whole supply chain that will now be sidelined.</p> <p>  I see the examples there.  I am very much attached to the breed bonus and am glad to see it included.  It is an excellent idea.  I was bemused to see Mr. Goodman Jnr. effectively recognising the importance of breed for market access and penetration.  I am sure Kepak and those companies that know more about market than I will ever learn will tell us that if one does not have a quality product, one will not penetrate the high-price markets.  I look with interest at that.</p><p>Notwithstanding the efforts of Deputy Cahill, who is an excellent farmer and probably produces very good beef, he is correct about Friesians.  I am sure he would produce more of them if he thought he could achieve what was outlined in some of the scenarios.  I am a little taken aback but I cannot contradict the representatives of Kepak and Glanbia.  I believe Glanbia is more interested than Kepak in ensuring that Friesians get recognition in the markets.  I would like that being distilled out.  I cannot see how the average quota prices would be achieved.  If I am wrong about that, Deputy Cahill is making more money that I thought he was, but in any event I do not believe he is.</p><p> In all seriousness, this initiative is a contribution and we cannot pooh-pooh such contributions.  Some beef farmers, many of whom I know well, are almost drowning in fatalism at this time.  Anything that stimulates them to consider various scenarios is to be welcomed.  However, I am concerned about the closed loop aspect.  There is no point in saying it is not a concern when it is.  Representatives of the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission will appear before the committee in a few weeks and we will explore with them if this concept is anti-competitive or if it stands up to scrutiny in terms of an anti-competitive practice.  It is important that would be ironed out and taken out the equation.  This does not involve Kepak very much, rather it more concerns Glanbia.  I note the structure of its company, and Deputy Cahill pointed out that there are GI readings and so on but often the farmers are being rewarded with their own money within that structure.  There point has been raised with us on a number occasions.</p><p> I am sure this initiative will be piloted with 5,000 or 6,000 animals.  Perhaps we will all be proved wrong and our concerns about the closed loop concept will not be vindicated and will be dispelled.  If they are, we will be the first to say we were on the wrong side of the argument.  I have concerns about what I believe are anti-competitive objectives contained within this initiative.  That is the only concern I have about it.  My major concern at this time is the viability of the future of the  beef industry.  Like Senator Paul Daly, I come from a strong beef producing county.  It will be interesting to see how this initiative goes down among the farming population of that county.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#DD00200"><p>I welcome the representatives from Kepak and Glanbia.  I also welcome the initiative.  We all know the crisis facing our beef industry.  It is welcome that somebody is taking an initiative.  This initiative in its fruition is very much in its infancy.  I find it difficult to see how it will take off or be successful or make any solid improvement for beef farmers in the sector.  My reservations are similar to those mentioned by the Chairman and Deputies Penrose and Martin Kenny regarding the closed loop concept.  I do not see the need for such a closed loop.  If this initiative is supposed be to the advantage of the beef sector and the beef farmer, the only winner from the closed loop concept, as documented in the presentation, will be Glanbia.  I can understand why one would want to closely monitor feed inputs with respect to traceability and the turnout of the finished animal but I do not believe the fertiliser spread on the grass that the animal eats has any bearing on the outcome of the quality of the beef, the age at which the animal will be slaughtered or the final carcass weight.  That is purely materialistic and commercially aimed towards Glanbia.</p><p>I would like the representatives to tell us - I doubt that they will - the arrangement they have among themselves behind the scenes.  I cannot see the beef farmer winning.  As Deputy Cahill and the Chairman said, with the greatest inputs of genetics and genomics, there is a vast range of Friesian cross animals, especially heifers, that will not be in the 280 to 360 kg category.  To get the majority of the rest to that point, it will require massive inputs, which is another plus for Glanbia.  Would a farmer who does everything by the book and whose animal, because of its breed, does not make the cut-off point not be far better off paddling his or her own canoe, taking the average quota price and possibly buying his fertiliser and all of his or her inputs a little cheaper elsewhere?  Financially, without the bonuses, he or she may possibly have paid top price for all inputs because he or she does not have any say in the matter and is still only getting what he or she would have got from any other meat processor in the particular week.  In that scenario the farmer will lose and Glanbia will win.  If the farmer does not hit his or her targets - he or she will be advised by Glanbia personnel and employees on what concentrates and their quantities he or she should be using - he or she will probably have massive input costs that he or she might not have had if he or she had been left to make his or her own decisions on inputs.  However, if he or she hits the targets and receives the bonus, I do not believe he or she will be winning because of the extra input costs involved.  Kepak will not be winning either because it will be paying more than any other meat factory in the same meat market for the same animals in the given week.  How are the organisations balancing it between them?  Kepak cannot take all of the hit for the love of Glanbia?  There must be some arrangement behind the scenes in the operation of the Twenty20 club such that one of organisations is funding the other.  I do not know if the representatives are in a position to advise us of that arrangement or give us the information that lies behind the setting up of the club from the two companies&rsquo; perspectives, but I would like to hear it to gauge how they are managing it.</p><p> I was going to mention the point made by Deputy Penrose about the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission as I agree with him.  I would like it to examine the Twenty20 club initiative.  I strongly believe it will find it difficult to consider the initiative to be legal in the Irish agricultural market.  </p><p> It is welcome that the organisations are taking an initiative, but it needs to be done on a larger scale to help to rescue the beef sector.  However, in the context of the closed loop concept, this initiative will not be the answer as there is only one winner.</p><p> I asked two questions.  In the operation of the scheme is there any age limit in the movement of calves?  Will there be a fixed price for a calf or will the organisations have an input into the price between the two farmers performing the transaction?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#EE00200"><p>Based on what the representatives have described, I can see many beef farmers taking up the initiative for the sake of certainty and the prospect of a bonus being paid.  In the presentation I note the description of the Twenty20 Beef Club as being farmer-centric.  However, I share many of the reservations expressed by colleagues.  The organisations are not doing it for the good of their health or out of the goodness of their hearts; rather, they are managing two very successful business concerns.  The reason they can close the loop is they are operating on such a scale.  The reason the club is farmer-centric is farmers do not have the negotiating power of the two organisations.</p><p>It is farmer-centric because it suits and the farmers do not have negotiating power as the witnesses have.  If the witnesses proceed as they propose, I do not begrudge any farmer getting the positives that the witnesses have suggested, but if other companies, such as merchants, are going out of business, and the witnesses are the last ones standing, why would they still be benevolent to farmers, except that they have entered into a contract?  What happens once that expires?  This goes back to the issue of the factories both being big concerns.  They have entered into this undertaking and it seems that they are in a dominant position <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>the other merchants.  We are just having a cursory discussion here but I can see how it could end badly.  If what the witnesses do could ultimately put these other companies which operate and deal with farmers out of the equation, the farmers would then be at their mercy.  That is the kernel of our concerns.  We have many issues with multinational retailers because they are so powerful and the small shop has really changed.  They are very challenged with regard to food, drink and everything else.  All sides have to be looked at.  I am interested in how the witnesses will address the anti-competitive suggestions.  Some of my colleagues have pointed out how regulated feed, fertiliser and such are.  There is an idea that the witnesses are offering something much better.  There is a lot of standardisation.  Leaving people out of the loop is questionable.<br/><br/>I have to leave to attend a division in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#FF00200"><p>I thank the witnesses for attending to help us with our consideration of the circumstances of the beef sector.  What was the motivating factor in establishing the Twenty20 Beef Club between Glanbia and Kepak?  I am curious as to how the name was arrived at or what its significance is.  How do the witnesses respond to the independent merchants who have expressed their concerns about this?  It was alluded to earlier.  There are a number of them around the country.  Two are in my area - Liffey Mills and J. Grennan and Sons.  They are concerned about the impact that this might have on their bottom line, their value in the rural communities that they operate in and the kind of relationships that they have.  They have been clear about their concerns that this may be anti-competitive in that it ties in farmers.  Having said that, I appreciate that nobody is forcing anybody to enter into this.  At the same time, these are the concerns that we are hearing and that need to be addressed.  At a time the price of beef is probably the lowest it has ever been, the timing of this is good to address the temptation that people have to think that this will solve all of their problems.</p> <p>  On the companies involved and the potential advantages that Glanbia Ireland has with regard to the fact that 60% of the shares are owned by Glanbia Co-op, it has been suggested that some shareholders might in some way be disenfranchised by this.  Will the witnesses refer to that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#GG00100"><p>I thank members for the questions and comments.  I will start with Deputy Corcoran Kennedy's question on the programme.  There is a logical flow to it.  Our farmers and supply base, whom we talk to regularly, have repeatedly said that they do not have sight of the future potential of the dairy calf at present.  The quality coming from the dairy herd has declined somewhat with the rush to focus on milk.  Mr. Ryan may address that later.  They have also said that there is no predictability about price.  They start to feed cattle over two years with no predictability about the price that they will get.  They have also highlighted the difficulty of accessing cashflow throughout the production cycle of those animals.</p> <p>  We felt that farmers coming together with our leadership, investing in genetics and raising that standard so that there is a certain threshold that dairy producers have to adhere to will bring more predictability to the performance of that calf.  If that is coupled with a technical support package, then the targeted finishing specification for that animal becomes much more predictable for us as a processor.  As a result of that, we can then bring more certainty to the farmer at the beginning of the production cycle when they register those calves for the programme.  That is the logic of it.  By being able to bring that pricing predictability to the farmer, since Finance Ireland is supporting the programme, the farmer can go to Finance Ireland, and once he or she is credit approved, he or she can get finance for each of those animals and have a cashflow coming through throughout the lifespan of the animal.  We repay that loan to Finance Ireland and pay the balance to the farmer at the end.  That is the logic of it.  The Deputy asked about the name of the programme.  That comes from a 2020 vision and it has been described by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine as visionary and pioneering.  As Deputy Martin Kenny said, it is a solution but not the only solution, which we realise.</p> <p>  As Deputy Cahill said, this represents 50,000 animals after three or four years.  That is our target.  It is less than 3% of the overall kill.  We are not trying to claim that this programme will solve every problem.  We have gone around the country since we launched the programme and run information nights where we have presented for approximately an hour and then fielded questions from an average of 100 farmers at each information night.  The questions have been like some of the questions members have asked.  We have since been inundated with expressions of interest in the programme.  Our target of 6,000 animals in the first year is already oversubscribed.  Farmers obviously feel that it is a solution that can help them.</p> <p>  Deputy Martin Kenny mentioned the mushroom industry.  This is built on the market.  When farmers register calves in the programme, they know that they will always be above the market when they slaughter that animal.  That is guaranteed.  That is why members will see in our brochure and the statement that we made that, in a falling market, we are supporting the price even more because it is rising from 15 cent to 25 cent.</p> <p>  Deputy Cahill mentioned the R grade.  We appreciate that.  We know better than anyone the amount of O grade and P grade cattle that comes from the dairy herd.  We are doing this programme to try to increase that standard.  We are not saying that we will bring every P grade up to an R grade, but through improved genetics and technical support, we fully believe that we will increase the standard.  That is for a small cohort of animals in this programme.</p> <p>  The Deputy also asked if the protocol bonus is replacing the quality pricing system.</p><p>We are saying that because we are investing in it upfront, for the first two years all grades will be entitled to the 12 cent because of our belief that, through the programme, we will raise the standard of production and bring more animals into the category to which this will apply.</p><p> On Senator Paul Daly's question on the arrangement, this is a collaboration between the two of us to try to help.  We are rooted in agriculture.  Our founder had a great link to farming.  Our Kepak farm, which this committee visited last year, is used as a knowledge transfer centre for our supplier base, our customers, and Teagasc-led discussion groups.  We are listening to farmers, more than 1,000 last year, and one of the things they are saying is that they are looking for big companies to come up with solutions.  That is what this is.  This is a solution for the industry.  It is not the complete silver bullet for the industry, but it is a start.  There is absolutely no arrangement between us other than to try to help with a solution, to get more predictability into the system for us, and to bring more predictability to the farmer.  These are the opening comments to some of the questions that have been raised, and I am happy to take more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00200"><p>When Mr. O'Dowd says that all grades qualify for the club protocol bonus, is that if they meet the weight restrictions, or do they all qualify irrespective of that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.70" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00300"><p>No, they qualify within the weight restrictions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00400"><p>They have to meet the weight restrictions to qualify.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.72" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00500"><p>Yes.  Currently the grades, O- or less, would not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00600"><p>If a beast is a P+, does it qualify if it meets the weight criteria?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.74" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00800"><p>It does.  In case Mr. O'Dowd thinks I am being completely negative, I welcome the finance part with the cashflow.  On beef farms, that is a very interesting development and is to be welcomed.  Does Mr. O'Keeffe or Mr. Ryan wish to come in here?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.76" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH00900"><p>I am just confirming that this is the case.  In one of the Vice Chairman's comments in that regard, he mentioned the percentage.  As it stands today, one is looking at somewhere in the 20% area, depending on what part of the country one is in, to meet the specification and to get a quality bonus for a Friesian breed cow, whereas for Angus it is probably 50% and for Hereford it is around 60% in terms of meeting the O= or better.  It is extended for that two-year period to 100% with the objective of pushing to breed better cattle from the dairy herd and to use a much higher percentage of beef sires on the dairy herd.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH01000"><p>We could argue about that for a long time with Mr. Ryan, but with the focus on the solids and everything else on the dairy side, it is going to be very hard to see how confirmation on the beef side is going to be improved dramatically.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.78" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH01100"><p>There is no doubt at all that it is a big challenge.  We are trying to change the percentage of animals, and that will demonstrate to others how value can be increased.  Not everything will be changed overnight.  People will breed replacements continually on the economic breeding index, EBI.  We may need to put more focus within the EBI on the beef value within it, but that is an industry matter.  Given the amount of dairy stock produced today, there is certainly scope to increase the number of beef-sired animals within that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH01200"><p>I have been very critical about the lack of evaluation in the EBI of the beef value of an animal.  That has totally disappeared.  Ten or 15 years, it would have been possible to pick a Friesian sire at our local AI station that would have had significant beef qualities.  Six weeks ago I went through the same brochure.  It was next to impossible to pick a Friesian sire that would add anything to the beef side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.80" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#HH01300"><p>That is correct as it stands today, and that is one of the things we want to set out to try to move.  In the first instance, people will shift towards using more beef sires.  Then we get to a point where sex semen will play a role but an improvement is required in technology.  The next step after that is to try to have a heavier weighting within the EBI on the beef value of the actual dairy offspring, because those animals are transferred to a different farmer.  It is looking at it from an industry value perspective as opposed to within the farm gate.</p><p> On the closed loop piece, as demonstrated by the premium piece, clearly somebody wants it and is prepared to pay for it.  The closed loop to us is certainly fundamental to the programme.  It is definitely the genesis of the ability to pay collectively and deliver that premium over the market piece.  It is a combination of ourselves, the customer and the processor.  It is, substantially, the customer who is making that contribution.  That is what they want.  That is what purchasers, as in major retailers and others, want.</p><p> I had an engagement recently with a company called Eco2 in the UK with regard to what work it is doing on the carbon area in the context of where we are today and the issues in Ireland.  By a mile the greatest level of work it is doing is for retailers in terms of looking to produce what it can sell on the market as a lower carbon footprint beef product.  That is where its heart and soul is today.  The alternative to doing something is to stay where we are.  We definitely want to try to avoid that.</p><p> From a customer perspective, it is infinitely easier for them to audit one supplier than to audit 20, 30 or 40 in the supply chain.  They just find that impossible to do today.  The steps we are taking today form, first and foremost, a potential opportunity to build a block chain within the beef industry here.  That would certainly add value and markets down the road.  Particularly when one goes towards Asia, that is a big requirement in their minds there for the future development of it.</p><p> As Mr. O'Dowd highlighted, the number of cattle, even at 50,000 down the road, is about 2.8% of last year's national kill.  It is a very tiny piece but it is symbolic.  It demonstrates a potential and a different model for people to look at as well.</p><p> On the fertiliser piece, and this is the last piece we considered in this regard, not because fertiliser is different or better than anywhere else because it would be substantially the same, the big challenge with fertiliser, which members will come across in their climate debates and others, is to ensure we use the right kinds of fertilisers to manage carbon footprint.  There is a huge impact from nitrous oxide in that regard where we slowly release nitrogen and so on.</p><p> One of the comments made by Deputy Penrose was to do with prescription medicines.  They are not included.  Our whole focus in this programme is prevention of the use of medicine through vaccination and other approaches.  It is very much about reducing that part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1345" speakername="Martin Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#JJ00300"><p>Are vaccinations included?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.83" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#JJ00400"><p>Absolutely, yes.  We really want to reduce antibiotic use here and improve welfare and health benefits.  That is the best and cheapest way of doing it.</p> <p>  On the price issue that was raised by a good few people, I can assure them we will have a competitive price proposition here, because without it, it does not work for anybody: not for us, not for the farmer, and not for Kepak.  Like some of the other schemes we had, they were all oversubscribed and we never had people pulling out of them because they were set up for them.</p> <p>  Glanbia co-op, as mentioned by the Deputy, is effectively a farmer co-op with a farmer board.  It is run by farmers for farmers.  We might be big but we are not a multinational company operating just-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1350" speakername="Jackie Cahill" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#JJ00500"><p>I do not believe we agree with its decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#JJ00600"><p>No more than the farmer, whether he decides to go in here or not, he is entitled to make his decision.  This is an optional programme that will suit certain people for different reasons, and it is a small percentage of the total market.</p> <p>  Mr. O'Dowd has covered some of the areas, but the important piece was to do with quality and breed.  That is applicable to all of the cattle that qualify on the weight basis during that two-year period rather than the percentages that are there today.</p> <p>  There is no desire or approach around looking at other millers or anything else like that.  We are trying to find a model that will help the value of a dairy calf and help a beef producer get a return on rearing them.  We see that as quite a challenge today.  We are trying to bring some certainty and clarity to that.  It is for a small percentage of the cattle population.  Depending on how it goes, others may follow suit and others may have other initiatives around this.</p><p> A number of the other issues were covered a few times.  There was a question about the age of the calf.  There is no limit regarding what point a calf can move at.  It was one movement at any time in its life.  If a dairy farmer normally keeps his calves for nine months, a year or a year and a half and another farmer finishes it from there, that is not an issue.  There is no restriction around that.</p><p> On the price of the calf, we have no involvement in setting the price.  It is between the farmers.  It is always a challenge to make sure the market has a fair price.  We reckon the fairest way of handling that is through the farmers.  Just as we will send all members of the club the weekly ROI price quoted, what we will do is also send them the prices of calves from the marts to give them an indication of where the price is at.</p><p> That covers most of the key points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Pat O'Keeffe" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#KK00200"><p>On the general comment about the Glanbia schemes, it was mentioned that Glanbia had tried schemes like this previously.  The fixed milk price schemes were launched.  They are voluntary schemes.  We are now on scheme No. 13 and over 20% of the milk in the Glanbia pool is fixed by farmers voluntarily.  If a scheme is not attractive when it is launched, no farmer will sign up.  We have 4,500 farmers and they make independent choices.</p> <p>  Deputy Cahill said he was surprised at the lack of critical analysis.  There was certainly critical analysis at the information meetings we mentioned.  The interesting thing I discovered is that, after the critical analysis, the farmers asked many hard questions about the price of inputs.  To be assured they would be getting value, they signed the form after the meeting.  Ultimately, this is not a short-term programme.  If the farmers perceive that they are not getting value and a return at the end of the programme, they will opt out after a period.  We will be the losers.  Glanbia and Kepak have set out on a journey with ambitious targets, and those targets will not be reached if the programme does not work for farmers.  Farmers will sign up for calves this year in the pilot, and if the pilot works for them, they will continue in the programme.  If it does not, they will move their business elsewhere.</p> <p>  A number of the members mentioned the private merchants.  We operate in 21 counties and in all those counties there are strong, private, independent merchants and other co-operatives competing for farmers' business.  It is to the betterment of farmers that they are there.  They have invested in their business, the dairy herd has expanded, the dairy processors have invested in milk processing capacity and the private merchants have invested.  At every Glanbia council meeting there is comment on the pricing.  There is great competition in the market.  This programme for 6,000 or 20,000 calves will not change the competition that exists across the 21 counties.  We fully respect that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.88" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#KK00300"><p>I wish to add a comment on Deputy Cahill's query about the age of the Friesians.  Obviously, meat is required 12 months of the year, so it is important that there is a range in which animals are slaughtered.  While the upper end will be 30 months, we anticipate that there will be a range operating there, particularly with some heifers coming from suckler farmers at 20 months and some of the Friesians the Deputy mentioned being 27, 28 or 29 months to get them to the required level of finish.</p> <p>  The fodder crisis and credit were mentioned.  Glanbia, being a farmer co-operative, showed its true colours during that period and gave a massive extended credit facility, an extended credit scheme, to farmers, which they will be working off over the next couple of years.  We have been very fair in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.89" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#KK00400"><p>Deputy Cahill also asked if the consumer wants this.  Not all consumers want it.  Consumers are driven by many different things, and as an exporter of 90% of our beef, we are consistently looking for differentiators in the market.  There are consumers who are very driven by the environment and by consistency in eating quality.  We feel we can bring all of the different attributes into it through this.  It was mentioned that there was an insinuation against other merchants.  There absolutely was not.  It is because of the consumer-led drive for additional attributes to the beef that we are trying to bring a product to them, and this is the way we feel we can do it for a cohort of cattle.</p><p>I repeat that this is a small percentage of the overall kill from which we are trying to produce a package that can go to a customer.  That is what is driving it.</p><p> I wish to make another point.  From talking to our supply base - more than 10,000 farmers are supplying us - and from the beginning of our discussions with Glanbia, we wanted to have a solution for the suckler industry as well.  Again, it is not the perfect solution but it is an effort to raise the output from those suckler herds.  For suckler farmers who are prepared to finish their progeny under the programme and to take in a minimum of 25 calves from the dairy herd, all of their progeny are eligible under the pricing structure we have outlined.  We feel it is a start to bringing a solution to that industry as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.91" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Deputy Pat Deering resumed the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#LL00200"><p>Customers were mentioned.  Will the witnesses be supplying their existing customers or have they lined up new customers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.93" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#LL00300"><p>We have been working with a basket of customers across Europe and Asia for this beef.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#LL00400"><p>They are all new customers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.95" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#LL00500"><p>It is a mixture.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1345" speakername="Martin Kenny" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#LL00600"><p>I have been looking at the practices that would be required.  The outline refers to fertiliser, feed and time of weaning.  It is all the good husbandry and best practice we should see happening on the farm.  I assume that advisers will be part of this package.  Will the witnesses contract Teagasc or the like to talk to farmers or will they employ advisers to work with farmers to meet these standards and to check that the standards are being met?  There will be a cost involved in that regard as well and the farmer somehow or other will pay that cost down the line.</p> <p>  My experience of it, and I have been on both sides of it, is that when one is working with a group like this and one has advisers going around working with farmers, what one is talking about is creating specialists.  Glanbia and Kepak want to have a group of specialists who can produce a special product for them and will do that within the group.  Some farmers who are not up to that standard will fall away in time and others will stay.  Farmers have a fear of the feedlot scenario, that the witnesses will have a specialist category that will produce the best of the product they want under their conditions, and that the others will fall aside, will not get the price and ultimately will fall out of the system and fall away from farming.  That concern must be addressed.</p> <p>  As far as I can see, the witnesses are talking about a producer group.  This is a farmers' producer group in all but name.  It is not being organised by the farmers but by Glanbia and Kepak.  The farmers are working to a particular standard, getting a particular price and using particular inputs.  They are basically working in that model.  At present, there is funding available for producer groups.  Has that been examined by the witnesses or by the farmers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#LL00700"><p>I apologise that I had to slip out earlier and perhaps my question was asked, but is there much interest in this initiative at present?  As a Glanbia supplier, any initiative that will help the beef industry must be welcomed.  Obviously, there might be some issues that could be teased out further, but if we carry on as we have been over recent times, we will end up in difficulty.  There is an old saying that if one keeps doing the same thing, one will always get the same result.  We have seen that over time.  The beef industry must change and diversify over the next period so it can be sustainable for the future.  Hence the discussions in that regard in this committee over the past month or six weeks.</p> <p>  For many years I have seen that dairy farmers are more keen to use technology to progress.  Tillage farmers use it to a lesser extent, but dairy farmers are particularly keen to use technology.</p><p>We have seen the results of that technology in recent times.  Do the delegates agree there is a requirement for education in some parts of the beef sector in that regard?  My view is that it should be a key focus of the meat industry to educate, bring farmers along and ensure they have confidence in the future.</p><p> Will the delegates indicate whether there has been much interest in their initiative and if they expect to be able to fill the quota for this year?  Looking to the future, do they intend to sell their message and programme?  If they have filled their quota by the end of the year, will they assess where they are after year one and go from there?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.99" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mick O'Dowd" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#MM00200"><p>The pilot phase quota of 6,000 has already been oversubscribed.  The expression of interest form was for the purpose of expressing interest in the programme for the years 2019 and 2020.  We are well on the way to filling the 2020 quota.  </p> <p>  Deputy Martin Kenny asked some important questions about our objectives.  The club technical team comprises people from Kepak and Glanbia coming together to help and support the farmer, at no extra cost to the latter, throughout the life span of the animals registered with the club.  Our KK club was developed in the late 1990s and is still going strong with more than 50 members.  The club approach is what we have always encouraged and strived for, building loyalty and supporting our farmers throughout the production cycle of their animals.  We see this programme as being very similar.  We hope in year one to have 100 to 150 farm members, with the average number of cattle per farmer likely to be in the region of 50 to 55.  That is the typical number that has come back via the expression of interest form.  On that basis, we expect a club membership in year one of 100, rising towards 1,000 by the time we hit our target of 50,000 animals per year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#MM00300"><p>On the advisory aspect, what is really motivating us to provide a good specialist technical advisory service is the evidence from the profit monitors on the calf to beef programmes which show an enormous difference between average income and the top one third.  There is huge scope for improvement in that regard.  The main reason a person might fall out of beef production is the lack of being able to drive his or her output figure.  With reference to the 513 farms in the profit monitor of the calf to beef programmes in 2017, the difference in output per hectare between the average and the top one third was 362 kg.  The difference in value of output per hectare was &euro;855.  That is an enormous gap which must be closed if people are to produce beef sustainably, which is the objective of the technical team.  A large part of it is driven by good grassland management, more than by anything else.  The objective is to get good lifetime performance from cattle and keep costs under control.  That is the angle from which we are coming and we will have a number of specialist advisers working to that end.  In addition, we have had discussions with some of the Teagasc specialists.  There will be room for their involvement where there are specialist skills that can be used.  We will have workshops and particular farms we will visit to demonstrate those skills.  That is a critical aspect of our work because there is a great deal of low-hanging fruit.  To translate the figures into costs per kilogram of live weight, the difference between the top one third and the average in the calf to beef systems is 50 cent.  It is a serious difference.  Our goal is to ensure all of the available potential is harvested.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#NN00100"><p>I thank the witnesses for attending to give us an insight into the initiative.  I wish them well with it.  This forms part of our ongoing discussion on the future of the beef industry, which I am sure they are following closely.  We will have a number of further engagements in the coming weeks, with representatives of Teagasc, Bord Bia and the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission due to appear before the committee.  We hope to have a report in early June outlining a clear pathway for the future of the beef industry, which is an important sector in agriculture.  It is important that it has a sustainable future.</p> <p>  I again thank Pat O'Keeffe, Martin Ryan, Mick O'Dowd and Jonathan Forbes, for appearing before the committee.  I also thank Mr. Forbes for the hospitality he showed when we visited 18 months or two years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.102" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jonathan Forbes" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#NN00200"><p>The Chairman is welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1268" speakername="Pat Deering" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2019051400002#NN00300"><p>It was a very interesting day out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.104" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 6.05 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 21 May 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.105" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.106" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 15:00</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 15:00</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Seanadóirí / Senators Timmy Dooley, Tim Lombard, James Lawless, Michael McDowell. Eamon Ryan, Bríd Smith, Brian Stanley.</p><p>I láthair / In attendance: Deputies Denis Naughten, Jonathan O'Brien and Éamon Ó Cuív.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy Hildegarde Naughton sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.107" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 3.38 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.108" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#H00200">National Broadband Plan: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#H00300"><p>I welcome the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Bruton and the Minister of State, Deputy Canney, and the departmental officials to discuss the national broadband plan.</p> <p>  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p> <p>  Members should switch off their mobile phones or switch them to airplane mode.  I invite the Minister to make his opening statement. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#H00400"><p>I have provided the committee with a written copy of my statement.  I thank the committee for the opportunity to present this statement.  We have sought to be extremely open on this contract because it is of such importance to the State and we have provided a huge volume of information which I know the committee is anxious to discuss.  This project is core to Project Ireland 2040 and I absolutely believe that the power of digital transformation is such that the Oireachtas should not contemplate 1.1 million people not having access to broadband.</p><p>That would represent a quarter of our population, 1.1 million people, including 68% of farmers, and 540,000 premises.  Having previously been Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and, more recently, Minister for Education and Skills, I am aware of the extent to which the digital transformation is altering how business is done, how lives are led, how education is consumed and, in time, how health will be delivered and the capacity for remote working.  Nobody would dispute that what we are doing here is crucial.</p><p> Twenty years ago, the State sold Telecom &Eacute;ireann, the merits of which decision I will not enter into today.  It meant we have been reliant on the private sector to decide the level of telecommunications service that is delivered.  In the intervening period, the State has stepped back dramatically in terms of provision.  In the decade to 1996, nearly &euro;2 billion was spent by the State on telecommunications infrastructure, a very substantial sum for the time.  In the 20-plus years since, by contrast, just &euro;400 million was spent.  Over the comparable period, we spent &euro;11 billion on the water system and nearly &euro;40 billion on the roads network.  In telecommunications, however, we have relied on the private sector.  The latter is doing a good job for urban dwellers, who will, in time, receive fibre broadband to their premises, but for many households and businesses in rural areas, that is not happening.</p><p> Our decision was to use state aid, as is permitted under EU law, to deliver 146,000 km of fibre and thereby extend the current access to high-speed broadband to cover the 1.1 million people who are excluded.  The evaluation showed very clearly that the most effective way to do this is to use the existing network of poles and ducts, which are privately owned and for which a rental must be paid.  Doing so is much cheaper than building them from scratch.  The total cost of the project is &euro;5 billion to design, build and operate for 25 years.  The State has committed to an upper limit of &euro;3 billion, &euro;350 million of which is VAT.  Of the remainder, &euro;545 million including VAT, or &euro;418 million excluding VAT, is a contingency which will only be drawn upon in very specific conditions, which will be subject to audit where they are due to be paid.  The contingency is capped.</p><p> The private investor is responsible for the remaining &euro;2.4 billion.  It will have to cover that cost partly by its initial equity, partly by its working capital and partly by the user fees it generates or new equity invested over the course of the project.  The initial equity to be invested was confidential under the terms of the negotiations that were conducted.  However, in view of the close interest of Oireachtas Members in this matter, I asked my officials to raise it with the investor, and the latter is happy to disclose the information.  It is investing &euro;175 million in initial equity and &euro;45 million in working capital.  It is important to bear in mind that the company takes the entire risk of building this out.  It is only as it completes the network that it will be paid by the State.  The operator, therefore, carries the risk.  Several commentators have argued that take-up may be much lower than that predicted by the investor.  If that proves to be the case, the risk will be carried entirely by the company.  On the other hand, if the initiative is more successful than projected, the State will realise 60% of the additional profits.  It is a very balanced contract that has been put together.</p><p>The other thing to be said about the network is that this will be a fully regulated company.  It will be required to deliver open access on a wholesale network.  Every retailer will compete over that network.</p><p> The price it can charge to operators is fixed.  In the case of a residential home it is set at &euro;30 per month per subscriber.  This is an entirely regulated business.  The Deputies can do the sums as to the pace at which the build-up of revenue can happen.  In the early years, the revenue is likely to be very small, perhaps no more than &euro;10 million by year 2.  It will build and the expectation is that by the end of the period it will be approximately &euro;150 million.  To put that in context, that is a company operating in a controlled environment.  Eircom today - not 25 years hence - has a turnover of &euro;1.3 billion.  Therefore this is a very small company by comparison.  Essentially the company is taking on the rolling out of an infrastructure to reach those subscribers who would not be otherwise served.  After a very careful evaluation, the State chose this approach of not seeking to own it at the end.  Rather than trying to install the poles, ducts and so on, it is more cost-effective to have that fibre erected on private infrastructure, which is the dominant format now delivering service.</p><p> Not having it revert to the State by year 25 creates an incentive for the investor to continue to invest in upgrading that infrastructure in order that it can earn more revenue and get more people on the network.  We can see that already in that it is committing to deliver not 30 Mbps, but from the outset to have 150 Mbps and by year 10 to have risen to 500 Mbps.  By contrast, if this came back to the State in year 25, with the lifespan of fibre being 25 to 30 years, the incentive would be there to run it down to the point where the State would be left having to carry the cost for the significant upgrade.  It is important to bear that in mind.</p><p> We have evaluated all the alternatives that Opposition Deputies and other commentators have put out there.  This investment was not undertaken without considerable due diligence and evaluation of alternatives in every case from the earliest point in 2015 when the five options on the table were reduced to two options.  Again in 2018 ten different options were evaluated when the cost of this became clear.  More recently in 2019, a series of options were further evaluated.  These evaluations included many of the options people have canvassed such as setting up a new company from scratch, a bit like Irish Water, or using the ESB.  The difficulty with all of these is that they fail on the basis of being more costly or more risky to the State or fail to meet the ambition we set in the first place.  That is the difficulty.  We have carefully looked to see if there are alternatives.  The only alternative that delivers while reducing the cost to the State is by reducing the scale of those who will benefit from this, which the Government has set its face against.</p><p> There has been much interest in whether the ESB should be one.  The ESB originally entered the fray in partnership with Vodafone through SIRO, but then withdrew.  This tendering process obviously has to proceed to its completion.  If this were rejected we could not then give state aid to the ESB to undertake this and we would have to have a fresh procurement process before any economic entity such as the ESB could be granted that.</p><p> I pay credit to the team present today for the work they put in.  Very detailed thought has been put into how the State can be protected in the context of a very significant investment of &euro;2.6 billion in a worst-case scenario, albeit over a 25-year period.  There is a suite of key performance indicators.  If it fails in those, it will face penalties in the short term or even loss of the project.  There are clawbacks in the case of it being more profitable than expected, being sold or the terminal value being higher than was projected.  There are checkpoint reviews on its progress in rolling out the model with viability checks and if it fails those, the State can take back the asset.  There will be a stand-alone board.  Very detailed reporting will be required of not just the financials but also the technical roll-out and the costs of various items.  We will police rigorously with a governance model every item where the State can save.  A contingency of &euro;480 million is included.  In the coming months we will put together a team to strengthen the resources we already have to ride shotgun on the roll-out of that to protect the State.</p><p> While I know this is controversial and there will be many questions, I assure members that when I took up this post, like members, I came in with a sceptical approach and a questioning mind to look afresh at all of these.  I can say hand on heart that I believe this is the best option available to us.  It will deliver this at the least cost and the least risk to the State.  It will ensure that 1.1 million of our citizens have the opportunity to participate equally and fairly in what I believe will be tremendous opportunities created by the digital transformation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#L00200"><p>I am grateful for the invitation to appear before the committee today.  The decision to move ahead with the national broadband plan is of great importance.  Some 1.1 million people are disenfranchised at the moment.  They do not have equality of opportunity or the potential to develop.  Certain small businesses and farmers cannot join the digital age.</p> <p>  As Minister of State with responsibility for our digital strategy, I have put in place many of the plans necessary to prepare for the roll-out of broadband.  We have broadband officers in every county.  They are working to identify what is needed there.  That is a key part of what we are doing now.</p> <p>  The 760 national schools without broadband are not providing education in the way other schools are.  This cannot continue and we need to get on with this.</p> <p>  At the end of the day we need to create equality of opportunity.  I am chairman of the Atlantic economic corridor task force, which is charged with providing economic development as a counterbalance to the overdevelopment on the east coast.  We can only achieve that by ensuring we give every opportunity to everybody.</p> <p>  Some 10,000 people in Dublin do not have access to broadband.  The issue goes across the country.  We have published a map which shows the yellow area.  Some 83% of the land mass has to be covered by broadband.  This is a major project which presents a big challenge for us.  However, we need to do it if we are to move forward and continue to lead in the area of digitalisation of the country.  This is about creating the jobs of the future.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#L00300"><p>I thank the Minister for his presentation.</p><p>Until today, he had indicated there was a commercial impediment to the release of financial data <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>what Granahan McCourt was in a position to commit to.  Will the Minister outline what it was or the advice he had in that regard?<br/><br/>The next element, following that particular train, is that at about 1.45 p.m. today, or maybe closer to 1.50 p.m., the national broadband company issued a statement providing the information the Minister is now giving us and that the Taoiseach gave us during Leaders' Questions today.  How did that come about?  Was the company mindful of what the Minister might say here or about what the Taoiseach was going to say?  Has there been any communication between the Department and the national broadband company?  Did the Minister seek the issuing of the statement?  Has the Department been communicating with the company in that regard?  If so, it seems the Minister is seeking the assistance of the company to dig him out of the political hole he dug for himself last week by giving the status of preferred bidder to the company within two weeks of local and European elections.  Undoubtedly, at the political level some people felt this would be of benefit to some of the Fine Gael candidates on the doorstep.  While that was within the Minister's bailiwick, I would be deeply concerned if he were now attempting to use the company on which he has conferred preferred bidder status, creating a certain liability for the State, to dig him out of the political hole he has fallen into.  I am very interested in hearing where he goes from here.<br/><br/>Prior to the Minister's coming here, I sought in private session the support of the committee to begin an investigation into the national broadband plan and all the aspects that are outstanding.  I hope the committee will meet later this week to address the proposal.  I do not know what our committee will decide but, from our perspective, we will be pushing very strongly for this committee to put together some terms of reference for trying to get to the bottom of what has gone on here for a protracted period.<br/><br/>I am not just being political because we have to be mindful of all the advice the Minister and his Department have received, particularly from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  An effort has been made by some to characterise this as just the concerns of the Secretary General of that Department, but when one goes through the work done in detail, one notes it is not just Mr. Watt but an entire team within the Department that has reached these conclusions.  I am hopeful, on the basis that the Minister has decided to move away from the commercial impediment he talked about in regard to the release of the capital investment of Granahan McCourt, that he will be more comprehensive in his appraisal of the documentation circulated among us and remove some of the redactions or most of the redactions that appear throughout.  While he did a very significant document dump last Wednesday, there is some critical information that would assist me and other members in making basic judgments on the good or otherwise of this proposal.  We will need access to the information, however.  I hope that if this committee initiates an investigation, the Minister will commit to reviewing the documentation that has been redacted and provide us with some clarity on it.  This could be done.  I do not see any commercial impediment.  Since there is only one bidder, I fail to understand why the Government could not or would not make the information available to us.<br/><br/>I noted media reports over the weekend, especially a report in <i>The Sunday Times</i>by the journalist, Justine McCarthy, who made it very clear that there are questions over the financial standing of the remaining bidder, Granahan McCourt.</p><p>My understanding, having read the article, is that there is a certain reliance on a company related to Granahan McCourt.  While "related" may be a broad term, this involves a company owned and controlled by a brother of the principal of Granahan McCourt.  Could the Minister give a detailed explanation as to how that provides the financial standing of the company, recognising that Granahan McCourt itself has disposed of considerable assets in recent times, namely, Enet.  Therefore, if one were to take it on its own standing, it would not have the financial track record to be awarded the contract.  It would be helpful if the Minister could take us through this in more detail.</p><p> The other issue, which perhaps was lost on some in the announcement last week and in the fanfare over what the Department or perhaps the Government sought to dress up as positive, was that the rolling out was going to be delayed very significantly.  Heretofore, the Government had indicated the vast bulk of the 542,000 homes would be passed within a three-year period.  The Department continued to assert that over recent years, yet the announcement on the last occasion suggested it would take up to seven years, notwithstanding the fact that, buried in the detail, was the point that the build company would remain in existence for ten years.  That would raise a red flag for any of us observing the pace of progress on the national broadband plan because every deadline has been missed along the way.  One would be forgiven for seeing the potential for further delays.</p><p> There are also concerns over the way in which the Department extended the contract for the operation of the MANs to Enet prior to its sale to the State-backed infrastructure fund.  All of this happened at a time when Enet was the main bidder and seemed to have lost the support of its then backers within the consortium to win the national broadband plan, namely, SSE and John Laing, which had removed or were removing themselves from the process.  Yet, Enet succeeded in extending contracts with the State for the operation of the MANs and, in doing so, increased its value very significantly.  Enet was then flipped, resulting in a very significant return to Granahan McCourt, allowing it to invest again.  This requires further investigation.  There are also questions to be asked on the Peter Smyth report, which was prepared previously.  When Mr. Smyth reviewed the meeting that took place in New York between the then Minister and Mr. David McCourt, he concluded Mr. Frank McCourt, the principal of another company I talked about that is now being used to bolster the financial position of Granahan McCourt, was in attendance.  At the time and during the Peter Smyth investigation, the necessity for his presence may not have been clear.  The reason he may have been present is now clear or more clear.  Would the Minister consider having Mr. Peter Smyth review his report in light of what we now know?  Maybe that is enough for the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#N00200"><p>There were many questions.  The Minister may go through them in whatever order he wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#N00300"><p>I will go through them.  The Deputy is suggesting the announcement was not positive.  Considering that every Deputy in the House was asking me when it would happen, there was a huge appetite for it.  It is a positive announcement.  It is really important that we set about ensuring there is not a digital divide, as it is described, between people who live in rural areas and those in other parts.</p> <p>  The Deputy asked about the roll-out.  We are being realistic, having done the very detailed due diligence exercise, and we are considering every element of how the fibre will be rolled out and how the poles and ducts will be made available.</p><p>This is a realistic estimate on which we believe we can deliver and to which the contractor has committed.  Hefty penalty clauses are set out should it fail to deliver at the 30%, 60%, and 100% delivery points.  Stringent penalties would have to be paid.  This estimation is therefore not only very realistic, it is also backed up by a detailed contract.  </p><p> With regard to the contract extension in respect of the MANs, I am not briefed to speak about that today but we have provided material to one of the other Oireachtas committees.  That was independently evaluated, the decision was made independently, and the extension was awarded.  I will provide the committee with that information.</p><p> I do not believe there are questions with regard to the report done by Peter Smyth because, as the Deputy knows, he found that the former Minister was not privy to any sensitive information which would have been of benefit to Granahan McCourt, that he did not take any decisions during the process which could have benefitted Granahan McCourt, that he was not in a position to influence changes to tender documents, and that he was not in a position to influence the evaluation of the submissions.  On that basis, Mr. Smyth was satisfied that neither the former Minister nor Mr. McCourt sought to influence the conduct of the tender process.  He went on to say that, because the then Minister, Deputy Naughten, stepped down at that point, he removed the perception that anything was amiss.  I therefore do not believe that there is an issue in that respect.  </p><p> In respect of the reliance on a related company, the detailed terms under which the pre-qualification occurred, and continues to occur, are set out in the documents which are available to the Deputy.  In the assessment of the capacity and experience of the bidder, including minimum threshold requirements, Granahan McCourt relied on the resources of Tetrad Corporation and McCourt Global LLC.  This meant that it was Tetrad and McCourt Global that were assessed from a turnover and financial capacity perspective.  This was appropriate given the scale of the investment required from the bidder.  The ability to rely on the resources of another entity and the requirements for doing so are set out in section 10.2 of the project information memorandum and in the pre-qualification questionnaire.  There is effectively a parent guarantee from those on whom the bidder relied.  That was deemed appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#O00200"><p>On that point, what encumbrance is retained on the parent company to maintain that guarantee?  Can that company divest itself or change in character or nature over the period of the contract?  Will there be a lien any of those entities which were relied upon to get past the post?  Will some kind of encumbrance be placed on them through the contract or was it a matter of just getting past-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#O00300"><p>There are obligations in the contract.  As Minister, I have a role in preventing any such change in the make-up of the ownership of the company that would undermine the delivery of the contract.  There is a role for the Minister in deciding whether any such changes should occur.  In addition, if I am in a position to approve such a change, all the terms of the contract will continue to apply.  A change of ownership can only occur with the consent of the Minister in that early period.  Later on there are different terms, which are set out in the documentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#O00400"><p>Can I pick up on that for a second?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#O00500"><p>I want to let the Minister complete his answer.  I want to get through the answers to Deputy Dooley's questions because there are many more Deputies waiting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#O00600"><p>I accept that the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform has set out strong arguments but I assure the Deputy that the team evaluated all of those and they were also closely evaluated by the Government.  The Department of Public Expenditure and Reform was doing its job.  Its job is to look at different elements of a project and to challenge those elements, which is exactly what it did.  We looked at each element it challenged in great detail and, having done so, we are satisfied that the benefit is substantially in excess of the cost.</p><p>A cost-benefit ratio of 1:3 was arrived at on the basis of a very conservative application of the rules, but I believe that cost-benefit ratios, with which I am familiar from my previous occupation, do not allow evaluation of many of the reasons we are making this investment, which include the future use of the technologies about which we are talking.  It will be as cloud technologies and the Internet of things take hold and as e-health is rolled out that the big benefits of this will be seen.  When looking at home working, for example, the evaluation was based on 4% of people working from home.  As the Deputy knows, 20% to 25% of employees in some progressive companies now work from home.  When a secure network such as this is established, there will be many more people working from home.  Companies will be willing to allow their employees to work from home when there is a secure fibre network.  Not only was that very narrow cost-benefit ratio met, I am absolutely convinced that the benefits will enormous when one considers the significance of this technology in the long term.</p><p> Let it also be said that while the advice of one Department was negative, advice from many other Departments was very positive.  Many such Departments foresaw the impact access to such a network would have on the delivery of public services in their spheres.  Different advices were available to Government and we evaluated them all.</p><p> On the question of confidentiality, a confidential approach was of course taken in this matter.  Over the period to the end of the signing of contracts, this contractor will have to engage with different subcontractors and will have to work out contracts with them and will have to negotiate prices on key elements.  That is a key element of this work.  Confidentiality was required in respect of the bidder's financial information, including its projections, investment and so on.  In view of the issues the Deputy's party leader was raising and which he was raising himself, I asked my officials to ascertain whether the company would be willing to allow this information to be made public.  It has agreed to that.  I am not aware that it has issued a statement, but it is in accordance with the information which we believed it to be in the public interest to place in the public domain based on the comments of Deputies.</p><p> With regard to the investigation of the broadband plan, how it was evaluated, and the Deputy's desire to evaluate, it is important to note that all of these evaluations were carried out by independent teams rather than by politicians.  They were entirely insulated from the political process.  The evaluation teams, of which there were three looking at technical elements, financial elements, and all of the other elements, comprised groups of experts who were drawn in.  These groups included officials from the Department and people from the likes of the National Development Finance Agency - independent financial institutions.  It was they who did these evaluations and they who oversaw them.  As the Deputy will see from the documentation, there was a layer of committees to go through before the reports were presented and the teams told us that this proposal had met all of the robustness tests set out in the original documentation.</p><p> This is not me deciding that it was a robust company or that the technology was optimal.  These decisions were made independently of the political process.  Having received this information and appraised all of the advice from different Departments, Government had to make a decision and that is the decision we made.  The Deputy seems to be suggesting that this was a matter of covering a political case.  There was no political dimension to this other than that we took a political decision at the end which, in my view, is what Government is about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00200"><p>Can I take that as confirmation that the Minister's Department did not seek the release of that statement at some point today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00300"><p>We did not seek the release of any statement but we sought agreement that we could make public details of the initial investment and working capital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00400"><p>This company was just minded to do so at 1.45 p.m. today in advance of the Taoiseach going to----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00500"><p>We sought agreement.  What the company does is its business, but we sought that.  I am not surprised that it issued its own statement if it knew that we had sought that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00600"><p>Is the Minister prepared to publish a log of the communications that have taken place in recent days between his Department and the company?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00700"><p>Will the Deputy say that again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1274" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#P00800"><p>Is the Minister prepared to publish a log of the communications that have taken place between his Department and the company?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Q00100"><p>I am open to that if that is the wish of the Oireachtas.  We are subject to freedom of information requests.  My officials have handled this in an exemplary way to the highest standards of the public service, of which the Deputy would be proud.  I have no problems.  They are very open and have conducted their business in a way that is designed to protect the interests of the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Q00200"><p>I will move on to Deputy Stanley.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Q00300"><p>I welcome this opportunity to engage with the Minister and his officials.  The revelation today that the equity investment from Granahan McCourt is a mere &euro;175 million and the working capital, as matters move along and revenue is brought in, is &euro;45 million will raise eyebrows not only in these Houses but among the public.</p> <p>  I want to deal with the issue of when the company can divest itself or flip this infrastructure.  The contract synopsis states there are restrictions on the change of ownership that applied to the date of the agreement up to 12 months after the completion date of deployment.  The Government expected this project to be completed within seven years, according to page 18 of the national broadband plan document.  That effectively means that Granahan McCourt can sell this after 2028.  The contract synopsis states also that the Minister cannot unreasonably stop the sale before completion.  We have a contest on probably one of the most important aspects of this contract.  For what reasons does the Minister believe he or his successor could stop the sale?  While officials may pass him a note or he may say in reply that the State can have the opportunity to buy it back, will the State, in other words, taxpayers, be in a position to do it?  Will taxpayers then be asked buy back a company and a network that they built up?  The Minister might address that issue.</p> <p>  The figure mentioned on Clare FM was circa &euro;200 million.  We know now that a figure just shy of &euro;200 million was the answer the Minister, Deputy Creed, got.  The equity investment is &euro;175 million.</p> <p>  The Secretary General of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform raised concerns about the deal being frontloaded by the taxpayer.  He raised questions with respect to years four and six and that while there are breaks for the State to review it, unfortunately, by that point &euro;1.2 billion will have been invested and by year six, almost &euro;2 billion or &euro;1.95 billion or &euro;1.96 billion will have been invested.  The taxpayer will have done the heavy lifting and handed out the cash.  By 2026, the taxpayer will have put in &euro;2.2 billion while the company will be in a position to get its money back by 2028.  We know how meagre its investment is.  It would effectively be able to get into the game of trying to flip the company.  We have seen how often Eir was flipped after the disastrous sale of it in 1999 by the Government of the day.  What can this Government do to stop that?</p> <p>  I want to raise the issue of the contingency report shared with the Departments of the Taoiseach and Public Expenditure and Reform where it acknowledged that alternative options have not "undergone a project appraisal or any cost benefit analysis".  I find that amazing.  Since the Minister came into office, I have questioned him on this many times in the Chamber, and I also questioned his predecessor.  This is a major concern Sinn F&eacute;in has had about this project from the start.  We had many concerns but this is a major one.  The fact that the tendering process was dodgy and shaky is an understatement.  We were left in a situation where there was one remaining bidder.  I told the Minister two years ago that if there is one bidder for any project, that one bidder holds all the cards.  Anybody who has been to a fair, a mart or an auction or who has bargained at a street stall will know that.</p><p>That is position, never mind this being a major Government contract.  To use the Minister&rsquo;s words, it is the biggest contract ever undertaken by the State.  The Minister might directly address the following point.  If teams of civil servants who were working on this project, the people the Minister charges, to whom taxpayers pay good money, to consult experts and to be the experts to come to the best decisions and come up with the best advice, acknowledged that alternative options have not undergone a project appraisal or a cost-benefit analysis, so it is not only Sinn F&eacute;in, I as my party representative, or somebody else who is saying this, will the Minister advise the reason that has not happened, particularly now that we are in this situation?  I believe the Government would have known this ballpark figure.  Anybody who has done any kind of a negotiation would know that several months ago, going back to last year, the ballpark figure of the financial input from the one investor, Granahan McCourt, would have been known by the officials and people involved with the tender.  We had only one bidder remaining, there was no competition in the process, and the financial input and investment from that one remaining bidder is very small.  Issues have been raised and we have concerns about the capacity of the one remaining bidder to deliver the project.  I met people in Enet before this tender process commenced and the principal people there expressed to me on more than one occasion and also to my parliamentary assistant that their preferred option at that point was that the State would own the network.  We deduced from that and when this was probed with them, even though we have not explicitly said it, that the company did not have the financial fire power to deliver this project on its own.  Obviously, there would be State investment in it but that they had major concerns about the company's financial capacity and its capacity to roll it out.  Their preferred option was for the main arteries of this network to be owned by the State.  Will the Minister address that point?</p><p> The taxpayers' contingency fund of &euro;500 million, which is not the total input, is roughly three times the equity being invested by Granahan McCourt in this project.  It has been suggested this fund will be eaten up in compensation.  I remind the Minister of the children's hospital contract, which shows that if anything is left open-ended, the private contractors involved in the project keep coming back to the Government.  I remind the Minister once again there is no other show in town with this project for him, the State or the taxpayer.  We have become prisoners of it because at that point there is no reverse gear to get out of it.  The private operators are rolling out wireless broadband in every county and companies like Imagine and Eir, which is using its fibre, will be eating into the available customers.  How will that be defended?</p><p> With respect to the Eir network being used, figures for the rent per pole were mentioned in recent months.  These are poles of the Eir network which was sold off by a previous Government.  The Minister might confirm how much per pole and how much per metre the ducting will cost.  A figure being bandied about over the period of the contract is in the region of &euro;900 million to &euro;1 billion.  Will the Minster confirm that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#R00200"><p>The Minister can answer those questions in any order he wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#R00300"><p>I will start by putting in context the initial equity investment and the working capital.</p><p>The reason we are doing this in the first place is that there will be 540,000 premises left without any access to high-speed broadband unless the State intervenes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00200"><p>There is no argument with that.  I want broadband for those 540,000 households, as does every Member of the Oireachtas.  We know that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00300"><p>I am trying to answer the Deputy's question and the context for this is important.  If we are to reach those 540,000 homes the State has to provide state aid to deliver 146,000 km of fibre.  We evaluated how that could be done at least cost and to best advantage from the taxpayer's and the user's point of view.  The evaluation showed very strongly that the best way to do that was not to set up a new operation to carry out this investment but first to use the existing poles and ducts that are available and privately owned to provide that fibre on that network and that we would only pay in arrears as that is delivered.  We would pay for the network to be rolled out and they would get payment.</p> <p>  A large part of what the State is doing here is making sure that an existing service and network, which is running well commercially for nearly 4 million people, would be extended to reach the more remote areas.  We are providing state aid to allow that to happen.  The context in which the private investor is to come along is that it has a prospect of payments as the roll-out of the fibre is delivered, but we need to see that it has sufficient initial equity in the deal, the &euro;175 million and the &euro;45 million, to ensure that this can be funded right throughout the whole ten years, although we are only paying in arrears.  In those early years the private investor will not be generating huge revenues, and even when it is fully rolled out, the scale of this company will be about one tenth of the size of Eir today.  This is not a huge company in terms of the financial revenue that it will be generating.  It will be generating that revenue from a price controlled network with open access.  The company will get &euro;30 per month from those who sign up.  That is the home rate.  It is important to see the context of the revenue.  The investor is not only responsible for the initial equity to start the roll-out but also for &euro;2.4 billion to complete the project over 25 years.  If there is any shortfall on the investor's projections, and one of the items on which the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform was sceptical was its belief that this roll-out would not be achieved, the investor is entirely exposed.</p> <p>  The Deputy raised the question of whether there is encroachment and what happens if others encroach.  There is a limited pot, which the State has capped, where if there is an encroachment by a new company that enters and makes the commitment to deliver absolutely 100% to a part of this area, there will be compensation.  In other words, if the 540,000 is reduced again by a new entrant who makes a commitment to deliver high-speed broadband, there is an exposure but that is capped.  The State's exposure in every case is capped.  The Deputy raised a concern that there could be additional claims.  There cannot be claims outside of the pots that are capped.  There are specific contingencies and they are capped.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00400"><p>Given the rate of penetration by the existing operators in rural Ireland, with Eir and fibre for example and the other companies with a wireless signal, it is a safe bet that where one or two people have a connection at one end of a townland currently, we fill find that 30 or 40 people in that townland have it  a year later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00500"><p>If that happens-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00600"><p>The Minister and the taxpayer can say goodbye to their &euro;500 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00700"><p>If that happens, the investor-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00800"><p>The Government will have to compensate them in court for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S00900"><p>If that happens, it is the investor who is on the hook and who has to put additional equity into the company to deal with the fact that it is being competed with by those who are not making-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S01000"><p>And can claim compensation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#S01100"><p>We do not pay the compensation.  The investor is entirely exposed to the risks, so if a wireless operator delivers the service and encroaches on what the investor hoped to get, it is entirely at that risk.</p><p>That is when additional equity would have to be put into the company.  If the investor cannot deliver the &euro;2.4 billion for which it is responsible, it has to put additional equity in to deal with that.</p><p> On the sale after 2008, the reasons are set out for when a Minister can refuse.  They are limited and they are in cases where the person is effectively unsuitable.  They are available in the published information but a clawback is also provided.  If a sale occurs after the ten-year period, there is a clawback.  In the earlier period it is much more stringent.</p><p> The Deputy asked about the circumstances in which the State would acquire the network.  If the company fails at various checkpoints, either by failing the viability test or by failing the roll-out test, the State can become the owner and it would effectively revert to the State in the event of ownership.</p><p> The Deputy made the point that the Secretary General of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform pointed out that at different points along the trail the State will make significant investments and the company will be working off its initial equity investment.  If the State has paid out &euro;1.2 billion, that means 57% of homes will have passed and been connected so we will be well through the contract and the investor will be operating in every county.  At that point, a substantial part of the infrastructure will be in place so we have set up the contract in such a way that the State is protected.  We only pay in arrears as the network is rolled out.  It is certainly not our ambition that this would revert to the State but we will have ownership of a significant asset at that stage.  It will be fibre delivered to whatever percentage of homes are specified at those different checkpoints so there is a significant asset.</p><p> Of course the company can be sold on at certain points under stringent conditions that are set out but when the Deputy talks about flipping the company and large profits being made and so on, there is a clawback if such occurs and this is a regulated company whose prices are set by the contract.  The company cannot come along and decide on whatever price it likes as a monopoly does.  It must only sell at a regulated price and it must be open to everyone.  Any retailer that wants to sell off its retail platform must be allowed to enter.  There is significant control on how this company operates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#T00200"><p>I could argue that with ComReg.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#T00300"><p>On the contingencies, when we have looked at alternatives, in each of those cases we have looked at the critical issues.  For example, if one were to say this should be offered to the ESB, the critical issue is whether a contract could be terminated and offered to the ESB or not.  The most important issue that needed to be checked at that point was whether that could be done under state aid rules and the response we received was categorical that we could not terminate this contract, hand it to the ESB without a fresh procurement process where others would have the right to enter the fray and compete.  Leaving aside the fact that the ESB entered this particular contest and dropped out because it did not see it as a economic route for it to pursue, if we sought to do it again, it would have to be an open competition in which it could only be awarded to one of those entering the fray and that would take another two and a half to three years to set up.  We would have no confidence that it could deliver at a lower cost and we had a fair level of knowledge of its cost base when it dropped out but we would also have had to delay the project for three years while we retendered it.</p> <p>  Where we looked at other technologies we did bring in the technology evaluation.  What was done with these alternatives was that we looked at what the critical difference that this might bring to the party and we looked in depth at those elements to assure ourselves that there was not another option out there that ought to be pursued.  I refer to the wireless option, which was one of the options that was examined.</p><p>We did the robust analysis of how wireless would operate.  Members can see it in the documentation.  Both ComReg and Analysys Mason showed that that technology ultimately could not achieve the 100% without a substantial investment in new masts in locations that would ultimately prove more expensive in the long term but would not deliver this level of service.  Fibre gives a dedicated service to one's premises.  By contrast, a wireless solution provides a service that is shared with other users and can be diluted as other users come on board.  The Deputy raised a concern that the alternatives were not properly looked at.  We looked at the issue.</p><p> The Deputy asked if having one bidder created a problem.  We recognise that having one bidder created a problem.  At that point, there had been two comparable bids.  Eir made a bid which was comparable to the Granahan McCourt bid before it pulled out.  We had access to the cost base of the two that submitted their applications.  Granahan McCourt was not significantly more expensive than the other bid.  They were comparable and I will not go into details of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#U00200"><p>The Minister just said it was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#U00300"><p>When only one bidder remained, we recognised that there had to be much more robust due diligence than if there were a number of bidders.  We investigated the volume of fibre, the price of fibre, the terrain, the way this would be done, the expected labour cost, the expected material cost, and the pace at which ducts and poles would be made available.  All of that was investigated in significant detail to make sure that this was robust, so that when we evaluated the cost and made a judgment that this represented value for money from the State's point of view, it was based on benchmarks of all the critical features of the bid.</p> <p>  With regard to the capacity of this tenderer, the group involved has rolled out &euro;40 billion worth of telecommunication investment, so it is a seasoned investor.  Those who will head it up have had senior positions in both Irish and non-Irish international telecommunications companies.  To roll out the fibre, it will use the same contractors used by Eir, SIRO or any of the other players.  It passed the evaluation tests that were done independently, not by me, because it could show that it had the capacity to do it.</p> <p>  The contingency fund will only be released in specific, audited events.  If certain events occur, there will be a release.  For example, if the price of fibre is significantly more than the projected scale, the State could be exposed for some part of that risk but it is entirely capped.  Many other risks are carried entirely by the company, for example with regard to revenue.  We have used a contingency fund to identify certain risks which we are willing to share but we will put in place a vigorous governance system to make sure that is not called upon except where those events have occurred.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1232" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#U00400"><p>The Minister did not address the cost-benefit analysis.  It was not done on the alternatives.  The officials raised a question on that.</p> <p>  With regard to the regulated price, he referred to ComReg being the regulator.  ComReg is overstretched.  Can it be effective?  What is its workload?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#U00500"><p>Senator McDowell is waiting to go into the Seanad and I promised to let him speak before he goes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#U00600"><p>The price of rental is close to &euro;1 billion but that is fully regulated by ComReg and it is done on a cost plus basis.  It looks at the costs and is entirely independent in making that decision.  It is currently &euro;20 per pole per annum, and &euro;10 per pole per annum if the pole is shared.  That is regularly reviewed by ComReg.</p><p>We did not redo the cost-benefit analysis for each of the alternatives because one is considering whether there was an alternative which would deliver something equal with the same benefits, at a lower cost.  If an alternative reduced the numbers of people reached, some of the benefits were lost.  It was clear, without doing the full project evaluation on each alternative, whether these options would add anything to what we knew.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#V00200"><p>I want to make an observation on Leaders' Questions which happened two hours ago.  The Taoiseach sought to reach across the floor to get support from the Opposition for the plan.  It was ironic, given the lack of interest that he had in D&aacute;il support or D&aacute;il majorities a year ago when my party introduced a motion to review the national broadband plan, which was passed by the House.  It was completely ignored by the Taoiseach and the Government, despite constitutional constraints.  Article 28.4.1&deg; of the Constitution states: &quot;The Government shall be responsible to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.&quot;  That has been flagrantly violated in the current D&aacute;il, so <i>plus &ccedil;a change</i>.</p><p>I will take a more fundamental approach to querying the plan.  The basic premise behind the national broadband plan is that many areas, primarily but not exclusively in rural Ireland, are unviable for the private sector.  Broadband will not be delivered by the private sector because it is too difficult to do so and it is commercially non-viable.  As a State, Government, or perhaps Oireachtas, we are making a decision to subsidise somebody to go in and do it.  It cannot be done for profit.  We will pay somebody to do it as a State subsidy of the public good.  That is fine.  We do that in many different sectors, such as public transport and healthcare.  We can ask why we need a subsidy and why these areas are impenetrable in the first place.  Why are these areas commercially unviable?  Why is the private sector delivering to some areas but not to other areas?  That is where I would start.  I would put the question on its head.  We have seen one instance in the lifetime of the current plan where we had 300,000 houses, which were considered unviable two years ago, suddenly becoming viable.  To an extent, I am living proof because I live in a house which now enjoys 300 Mbps fibre broadband.  It was amber two years ago, then became light blue, then became commercial.  I have it.  I am paying for the privilege and I am happy to do so.</p><p>When I was a councillor, long before I was in this Chamber, I tried to get rural broadband rolled out in County Kildare.  It is a local example but it is reflected across the country.  I met the broadband providers and asked them why rural areas and other areas in my constituency were not being served by them, what the problem was and why they could not roll it out.  The locals were more than willing to pay for the service, even at a premium if they had to.  I got a number of interesting answers, including lack of planning consistency; different planning frameworks; different local area and county development plans; lack of economies of scale, some of which arose from the fact that were inconsistencies in planning overhead; regulatory overheads; legacy frameworks; and the lack of availability of access to State sites, such as through Coillte or the OPW or other State sites.  The bane of many people's lives is when a road is dug up repeatedly.  I asked the companies why they dig up the road repeatedly to lay new ducting and cable for utilities, though it was fibre in this case.  They stated that based on the rates that the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform mandates Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, to charge, it is cheaper to dig up the road than to lease infrastructure from TII.  All kinds of anomalies came out of these discussions.  It was useful for me to understand why the private sector was not delivering to these areas.</p><p>Many of these issues were mirrored by the many task forces.  We have had at least a decade of promises on broadbands, all of which have been missed, abandoned or rescheduled.</p><p>We have also had at least three different task forces reporting, summarising and consolidating the issues and asking why the private sector is not willing, able or viable to get into these areas.  The proof is in the pudding.  We have the proof from the many task forces and from the horse's mouth, as it were, from the broadband providers.<br/><br/><i>The Sunday Business Post </i>usefully wrote about this at the weekend and we have heard already about the likes of Imagine going to 5G and Eir going into 300,000 houses.  I appreciate there is a debate about the technology and I agree that fibre is the best according to the laws of physics.  We can deliver fibre, masts, 5G and multiple technologies faster and easier if we enable the private sector to get in there by reforming how we deal with planning, the frameworks around it and how they operate.  It is very unlikely we will get to 540,000 houses but could we get to 500,000, or 450,000, or 430,000?  Could that figure of &euro;3 billion become &euro;2.75 billion or &euro;2.5 billion if we chip away and look at the problems rather than trying to throw in a State subsidy of &euro;3 billion at the problem and try to make it go away?  We should get to the root cause and make proposals that would make it easier for the private sector and offer incentives, not with any subsidy or State handout, but by tackling the problems that make it more difficult for the private sector to go into these places, the reasons it is commercially unviable and the problems with the planning framework.<br/><br/>I was at the Hill of Kilteel two weeks ago on a local election canvass.  Counties Dublin, Kildare and Wicklow meet at that point and a provider putting a mast on that hill could feasibly have to engage with three different local authorities with three different local area plans and planning frameworks to try to put 5G or fibre infrastructure on that hill.  One would have to go and rent a ducting from the N7, a mile down the road, and might find out it is actually cheaper to go in and do it oneself rather than trying to lease it from the State.<br/><br/>Where do we go with all this?  Happily, I have legislation which I published in 2017, almost two years ago, which enables all of these things.  It takes the issues and anomalies and includes such provisions as a new planning permission for a new build to have ducting from the curtilage of the house back to the road.  It includes things like consistencies in planning frameworks and access to State sites and properties.  It also includes common-sense things that deliver economies of scale and protect communities and the environment such that if one provider erects a mast on top of a hill, a provider coming afterwards does not put in another mast but is mandated to reuse the existing infrastructure.  That provides free use of infrastructure, be that public or private, and once the cable is laid and the mast goes in, it will be reused and there for ever more.  <br/><br/>My legislation is not a sliver bullet to solve all the problems but it would make it much easier for the private sector to penetrate some of these areas and, as I say, the &euro;3 billion might become &euro;2.5 billion and the 540,000 homes might become 440,000 and so on.  We might be in a better position now had the Government adopted this legislation when it was published two years ago.  It can travel in parallel with the plan because they are complementary.  The price comes down every step of the way.<br/><br/>I ask the Minister to support this legislation, which is already in the system and before the Oireachtas.  It would be complementary and parallel to the broadband plan.  The Government might consider plan B because if the plan fails, which unfortunately it has for the past decade, this may allow greater private sector take-up and allow more houses get access to broadband more quickly without recourse to State subsidy of &euro;3 billion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#W00200"><p>I will talk about the model that we use and will then bring in the Minister of State, Deputy Canney, who has chaired the mobile and broadband task force.  The model we decided to go for was a competitive tender to seek to achieve universal access and we were open-minded as to what technology would deliver that and how it could best be done.  Interestingly, all three tenders proposed a fibre solution.  That is why fibre has become the winner of this process.  There was no alternative approach.  It has proved to be the most cost-effective way of achieving that goal.  What the Oireachtas wants and I believe to be necessary is that every home will have access to a technology that is future proofed.  Mixing and matching, hoping over time that it will work out was not the approach we adopted.  The Minister of State, Deputy Canney, has done a lot of work on precisely those issues, as to how the practical obstacles can be removed, and perhaps he might deal with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00200"><p>Regarding what the Minister just said, it is not about competing technologies.  I agree completely that fibre is the primary technology that can be used but it is a matter of how it can be got to people faster and cheaper in the current day without the need for any kind of State subsidy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00300"><p>As chairman of the mobile phone and broadband task force, I can inform the Deputy that we have been engaging in exactly what he talked about.  We have made many changes.  For instance, there is now single access to road-opening licences.  A nationally applicable standard form may be accessed on a portal.  There is also the question of the State assets.  The OPW, ESB and all the relevant State agencies are involved in the task force to map the State assets available and determine how they may be used.  TII has spent millions in the past couple of years retrofitting ducting along the motorways so it can be used as a shared service by all the communications providers.  This has been happening since the task force was set up.  There has been great progress made.  I agree that, in the past, local authorities were working in their own silos and creating different rules and regulations.  The elimination of development charges keeps the cost to the customer to a minimum.  When we carry out in any town or city an infrastructural project that involves the replacement of water services or sewage systems, for example, we now bring in the broadband officer to ensure the infrastructure is future proofed so it will not have to be dug up again.  There is an office in every local authority.  We are also working with the providers of the masts in identifying the areas where there are black spots and making sure the masts put up are shared by all the communications providers.  That is happening right now; it is the reality.  Therefore, much of what Deputy Lawless referred to is being worked on.</p> <p>  In Mayo, the broadband officer has mapped all the existing duct work in every village and town and put the information on a portal and app so anybody can see it and use it if they need it.  The service will be rolled out in every county.  We are doing considerable work addressing the difficulties that have arisen.  It is all in train.  It is a question of preparing for the future.  All the bidders who submitted a proposal for the national broadband plan said fibre to the home is the only solution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I have no issue with fibre.  Has the price of the tender been updated to reflect all the good work done, which the Minister of State outlined?  If not, why not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00500"><p>The price of what tender?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00600"><p>The &euro;3 billion handed over to Enet or whatever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00700"><p>On the tender, I do not know the detail of it but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00800"><p>If it is easier for the companies, it should be cheaper for them.  Therefore-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X00900"><p>Most of the fibre optic cabling will be along poles.  There is very little ducting going on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#X01000"><p>With some justification, the Minister and Department have said repeatedly that this is a visionary leap into the dark, and they have repeatedly compared this project with the electrification of rural areas and the building of Ardnacrusha.  With some justification, they are comparing the importance of the two projects.  The national broadband plan is to deliver fibre broadband to 56,000 farms, 44,000 businesses, 670 primary schools and probably many private houses.  The key difference between what we are doing here and what we did with rural electrification and the building of Ardnacrusha is that we did not spend on the process of tendering.  We have spent &euro;80 million so far on the current project.  With electrification, we did not tender out, hire elaborate consultancy firms or engage in elaborate competitions.  We constructed a State-run company with a single remit, namely, the ESB and instructed it to provide a vital service to rural areas.  The provision was not dependent on the profit margins of some private entity.  That is a key difference.  If, in order to electrify the country we had used the model we are using today, most of the country would still be in the dark.  The people would be listening to this discussion by candlelight because it would never have worked.</p><p>The main mistake we are making is that, once again, an essential service is being privatised at huge cost to the taxpayer, remarkably without the taxpayer even owning the service at the end.</p><p> Let me comment on points made repeatedly by the Ministers.  Their great concern for equality of opportunity for the people of rural areas is quite astounding when the Government has just closed down many rural post offices.  How many Garda stations were closed during the years of austerity and not reopened?  How many villages and towns throughout rural areas have been disconnected from bus services?  When this was happening, it was all about saving money.  Now there is significant expenditure on rural areas that is being justified on the basis of equality of opportunity, which the Government has consistently denied rural areas, whether it was through running down the fishing community, closing down schools needed in very rural villages and towns, or, as sometimes happened, closing hospitals and nursing homes.  The idea that what is being done represents efficiency is absolutely disgraceful.  The reputation of Fine Gael, a party known for its prudence in dealing with public funds, will be utterly changed from here on in.</p><p> I want to ask the Ministers a few questions on the whole scheme of things.  When we went to a briefing with the Department just less than a week ago, we were told there has been no study of the uptake of broadband rolled out to individuals&rsquo; homes.  There are comparisons with other studies but no study done on who in rural areas might avail of the service.  Clearly, we know who needs to service.  They include the 56,000 farms and the 44,000 businesses but do we know how many will avail of the service in total?  We have not done a study.  We have just been told there are broadband officers in every county but the level of uptake is still not clear.  As Mr. Robert Watt pointed out, at least 20,000 of the homes are holiday homes.  Their owners will probably not incur the expense of having broadband brought to them.</p><p> I wish to ask a couple of key questions.  Why was there no study of where the uptake might come from?  I have a couple of legal questions.  I am sure the Minister is aware of the legal action against Granahan McCourt by Cube Infrastructure Managers over the sale to Irish Infrastructure Fund of the stake in Enet.  Does the Minister believe this might at some point compromise the tender?  Does it have ramifications for what the State is about to do?</p><p> I have another legal question.  The investigation into Siteserv is not due to be completed until March 2020, yet we now regard the company that has taken over from Siteserv, Actavo, as a key component of the consortium.  Have the Minister or his officials considered the implications of the inquiry into the role of Actavo in the consortium and the bid on which he may be about to sign off?  Does he see a problem in that the consortium that now comprises the only remaining bidder is very different from what it looked like at the beginning of the process?  Those are my questions for now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Y00200"><p>I acknowledge that Deputy Br&iacute;d Smith recognises this is a really important issue for the future of the country.  I have worked in a number of Departments and I have seen how this is transforming, and it will continue to accelerate.  It is really important.  The difference between now and when rural electrification was considered was that we have at this point privatised, for good or ill.  Twenty years ago, we sold off Telecom &Eacute;ireann.  We sold off the core of the network so we are not in a position of owning and extending a network but of seeking to provide state aid to tack onto an existing network 146,000 km of fibre cable.</p><p>That makes a difference.  </p><p> The other issue is that procurement law is now very different.  Where state aid is being provided, it cannot simply be granted to a company that is a commercial operator.  There must be an open procurement process, which is different.</p><p> The amount spent by the State to date is &euro;25 million, not &euro;80 million.  It is important to have a robust evaluation because the issue is of such importance.</p><p> Contrary to what the Deputy said, I see a revival in rural Ireland.  I have travelled around the country to visit many projects and see a great new revival.  With the funds being made available from the Department of Rural and Community Development under the Minister, Deputy Ring, the bottom-up development that is occurring, the regional enterprise strategies that are being rolled out and the town renewal initiatives, there is a strong revival in rural Ireland.  Providing future proofed broadband will offer the super highway of the future to guarantee that remote regions will not be hollowed out by technology but will participate fully in it.  That is crucial to the success of rural Ireland because it will allow remote working and remote access to important public services.  I have a different view from the Deputy.  I consider this to be a very important future proofed investment.</p><p> On the studies the Department has made, we have looked at international precedents and also at what is happening in urban Ireland.  In principle, we must make the same level of service available to urban and rural areas.  There must be access to this digital technology on the same basis in both urban and rural areas, at the same price and with the same connection charge.  That is a principle we want to achieve.  My Department and I have no reason to believe from the evaluations that have been carried out that the appetite for the uptake of this service will be any different in rural Ireland from that in urban Ireland.  Where networks are available online and people can access high quality broadband, the uptake is 65%.  That is prevalent; therefore, there is no basis to believe there is a low level of interest and that we are making an investment that does not matter for the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00200"><p>The Minister does not have studies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00300"><p>We have made studies.  In all cases we have looked at international benchmarks to see what stands up to scrutiny.  We have done that work.</p> <p>  On legal actions and investigations, we are confident that none of them will have an impact on the roll-out of the national broadband plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00400"><p>Does that include the investigation of Siteserv which will be concluded by March 2020?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00600"><p>The Deputy said she had a final question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00700"><p>I do.  When we attended the presentation made by the Department, a worrying matter emerged regarding the construction of the National Broadband Ireland company, that the State would have one representative on a board of nine.  One person would represent the State, but the role of that person was not clear.  Would that person's role be in the interests of the State and the people or those of the company?  That matter was not cleared up.  It is important that we know the answers.  We saw in the debacle with the national children's hospital - interestingly, it has almost been completely forgotten because this matter has superseded it and become the issue of the day - that the person who represented the State on the board for the construction of the hospital was accountable to the board and the company, rather than to the State, despite the massive spending of public money.  This is a serious question related to the public interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#Z00800"><p>The position is it will be a stand-alone company which will be regulated in great detail.  Its primary element will be delivering on the governance commitments we have entered into under the contract.  Every member of the board will have an obligation to ensure delivery to the State under the terms of the contract.  We have written the contract in great detail to ensure we will have access to the auditing, that it will deliver on time and that it will be rolled out in a certain way.</p><p>We are very confident not only that we have the governance but also that by having a representative on the board we will have somebody who is overseeing the public interest, which is at the heart of the contract being negotiated.  This is different from, for example, having a public interest director in a bank whose job is to serve its shareholders.  This company is set up to service this contract and we have set out in triplicate what that means.  Our public interest representative will be overseeing not only the representative's role but the role of the company, which is to honour this contract.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#AA00200"><p>The departmental officials can now clarify that for us, less then a week after they could not clarify it when we met them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#AA00300"><p>The contract binds this company in every respect.  It has detailed reporting obligations and audit and delivery requirements.  The representative on the board will make sure that those important governance commitments, which apply to all board members and the company, are delivered.  This person will be at the core from a public interest perspective to ensure that the company honours all those obligations.  They are obligations of this company.  It is a different situation from a bank which has obligations to a number of different-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1367" speakername="Br&iacute;d Smith" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#AA00400"><p>There is an ambiguity and because that exists, the Minister should be obliged to publish the contract.  This is serious public expenditure.  That contract should be published in full so we can discuss it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#AA00500"><p>The contract will be published in full when it is finalised.  We have published a full synopsis of the contract, the details of the various items that must be overseen and the audit requirements in respect of when a contingency sum could be called upon.  The detail of this contract is immense in terms of the specified obligations of the company.  That must be borne in mind.  This is not just a director of a company that is floated with its own interests.  It is a company dedicated to deliver a project in which it has significant obligations imposed on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#AA00600"><p>I apologise if I ask some questions that were asked earlier.  I had to go to the Chamber for a priority question to the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  If the Minister is unable to answer any specific questions, he can provide a written reply.  As was suggested earlier, we will have to do further investigative work to make sure the public interest, as best we can discern it in the next six months, is protected in this contract.</p> <p>  First, everybody agrees that we want to have the same access and conditions for people throughout the country.  The contract that has been outlined refers to a wholesale price of &euro;30 per month from the national broadband company.  On 19 November last, ComReg issued its regulation regarding the wholesale access price for broadband, fibre to cabinet, primarily to Eir as the monopoly current provider.  It set the price at &euro;19.54 per house and it applied from 1 March last.  That is the current price for wholesale access for broadband.  We are being asked to agree a contract where it is at least &euro;10 more expensive.  Is that &euro;30 per month expected to be index linked?  Who will regulate any increases in it?  Is it ComReg's role to assess that price?  What role did ComReg play in the assessment of whether that is an appropriate price for this contract?  It is strange that there is such a gap in the prices given that the State will put more than &euro;2 billion into this product.  One would have thought it would be, if anything, lower than the private market wholesale price.  Similarly, the Minister said it is estimated that there will be a &euro;40 million payment per year to Eir for the use of the poles and the ducting.  Is that index linked?  How is that price regulated as the contract proceeds?  Is the Minister including index linking for it or is it something ComReg will oversee and regulate so we can ensure supernormal profits do not go to the bidder?</p> <p>  Second, I am told one of the main objections to this project from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform is that the State may incentivise or support a continuing sprawl model of development in which a one-off housing model of development is facilitated.</p><p>There are understandable concerns not just about the cost of delivery of broadband services but also about a range of public services related to the sprawl-development model we have seen here.</p><p> Based on the briefing we received, I understand the Minister expects 60,000 additional homes to be added to the 500,000 already covered by the network.  Does the contract make provision for the further expansion of one-off rural housing?  Is it being included in the contract or are we just doubling down on what the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform is concerned about and what goes completely against the national planning framework?  Rather than consolidating development in cities, towns and villages, this policy may signal that another 60,000 one-off houses need to be serviced as part of the scheme.</p><p> I ask for a detailed international analysis that backs up the statement that fibre typically decays in 25 to 35 years.  In other networks fibre has not been deployed in this way in many cases.  I am interested in knowing the scientific evidence.  The Minister can provide it in a written response if it is not available today.</p><p> The Minister expects an 80% uptake of the broadband service being provided in the 25-year period.  What is the projected uptake in the first ten years?</p><p> I have two further questions.  I apologise to the Chairman for having multiple questions.  We will have more in the coming months.  The industry experts, from whom I have sought advice, have said the percentage of houses we could address with wireless broadband should be higher than the 2% estimated in the draft plan.  The cost might be reduced significantly if the figure was closer to 10% or 15% and we stilled maintain a high quality service.  Is the 2% figure part of the radical price inflation from the original &euro;1 billion to &euro;3 billion now?</p><p> A mistake was made in parcelling the 300,000 houses which resulted in the ESB exiting the process.  I do not believe its role is necessarily finished.  Having spoken to officials and other parties involved in the process, I understand there will still be flexibility in the next six months when the contract will be finalised for the developer to use ESB poles as opposed to Eir poles, thereby bringing a competitive process into the final stages of the contract.  It is not the case that at this stage we want the ESB to take the whole project, but in some of their comments the Minister and the Taoiseach are ruling out the possibility of the developer negotiating with the ESB to use those wires.  We have a once-in-a-lifetime chance to move from having two sets of poles to one.  Even if it may not now be possible to do so for the whole project, I still think we should pursue it as a policy objective in the remaining months of the final negotiations.  The developer may have a real incentive because it may allow it to bid with Eir in a much more competitive framework if there was an alternative option before them.  I am interested in hearing how the Minister thinks the process of negotiation might work out.  I recognise that he is in a difficult position because he is also the shareholder of the ESB, but we should keep that option open.  I am keen to hear the Minister's views.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00200"><p>An existing fibre-to-the-home price is &euro;30 per month.  The Deputy is talking about fibre to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00300"><p>The cabinet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00400"><p>That is different.  I will need to confirm whether it is index linked.  I presume it is a regulated price and that it will depend on the regulator over time.  ComReg does not have a role in the short term, but it will certainly have a role in the longer term because the terms of the contract are such that it is unlikely that at this stage it would see a need for it to step in to regulate because effectively we are regulating the price under the terms of the contract.  Beyond the period the contract applies, ComReg would step in because it would be a body of significant-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00500"><p>May I ask two questions about that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00600"><p>Briefly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00700"><p>Is the Minister saying ComReg had no involvement in setting the price and is it index linked?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00800"><p>The Minister has answered that question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#BB00900"><p>I will confirm whether it is index linked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC00400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC00500"><p>This price has been set by the State in the contract.  It is based on prevailing prices elsewhere with the objective that people in urban and rural areas will pay the same charge.  It is anticipated that situation will prevail, and ComReg advised us throughout.  We are linking the prices in urban areas with the prospective ones in rural areas.</p> <p>  As I mentioned earlier, Eir charges &euro;20 per pole and &euro;10 if shared.  That is a regulated price.  ComReg sets the cost price which is based on a reasonable rate of return for the owner of the pole.  Obviously ComReg can alter the price independently, as it decides.</p> <p>  The lifetime of a cable is unproven.  In the unique conditions of rural Ireland, cables degrade over time and need to be replaced.  In terms of performance, manufacturers provide a range depending on conditions.  There is an expected life that is based on established standards in the marketplace.  We can get the Deputy more information on the matter.</p> <p>  I do not have the figure on the uptake at different points.  Obviously the contractor carries the risk.  Just as Deputy Br&iacute;d Smith said, the contractor has done the studies.  It is the contractor who would carry the risk if the uptake is lower.  The contract allows for 2% to be wireless.  It is open to the contractor to come back to the Department and establish that a higher percentage than 2% could still deliver the level of performance that we expect.  We could accept that but we would have to satisfied that the level of performance would be delivered.  It is only 2% that a contractor can decide at his or her own discretion but the standards set must also be achieved.</p> <p>  Of course the contractor can use ESB infrastructure.  It is open to the contractor to use whatever infrastructure is available.  We cannot oblige a contractor to use a particular provider of poles or ducts because that would be interference in the marketplace.  It is very clear that the contracts provide that a contractor can take access of any existing infrastructure, be it ESB, metropolitan area networks, MANs, or Eir.  That option is at the discretion of the tenderer.  As has been rightly pointed out, having choice certainly gives someone more leverage in the marketplace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC00600"><p>I wish to ask one last question that was not asked here.  Is there provision in the contract to allow for up to 60,000 new homes to be built in the area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC00700"><p>No, the figure that I have is 32,000, and that is the provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC00800"><p>I have been told that there is a higher band of up to 60,000 but I could be wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC00900"><p>I will get the details for the Deputy.  I would not like to think that what we are saying here is that we are encouraging ribbon development.  That is not at all the purpose of this.  The purpose of Project 2040, which I know the Deputy may dispute, is that we are trying, for every climate reason and all sorts of reasons, to have compact and connected development on a sustainable basis.  The bidder has to connect whatever is built in the area in which he builds, and in the baseline contract there is an envisaged possibility of what this might be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC01000"><p>Are an additional 32,000 homes envisaged?  That could go up to 60,000 homes within the contract.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC01100"><p>Yes.  We have not sought to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC01200"><p>How does the figure marry with the national planing framework?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC01300"><p>I do not know where the figure originated but I will come back to the Deputy on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#CC01400"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I also welcome the clarity that he has brought to many of the key issues in the national broadband plan and where it is going forward.</p><p>Deputy Eamon Ryan spoke about the 32,000 extra homes moving into the amber zone, which is welcome.  We should support the regeneration of rural areas, including one-off housing, whether they are agriculture, fishing or tourism based.  We need these people to keep rural communities alive.  Having an additional 32,000 rural homes in the next 25 years is positive and a step forward.  It is important that the Minister has provided that clarification.  That means approximately 575,000 homes will be connected in the next three or four years.  I do not share Deputy Ryan's views on that being negative; it is very positive because it ensures rural communities will have the ability to survive and renew.</p><p> There has been great fanfare about one Department making a submission on the national broadband plan and having a negative impact.  How many Departments made submissions on it?  There has obviously been significant engagement in the process, but we have talked extensively about one submission made by one Department.  Have there been others from other Departments?  What did they state about the plan?  We need a balanced approach to it.  If we were to say, "Stop," and start the entire process again, when would the 575,000 homes get broadband?  Would it even happen in the next decade?  Does the Minister believe this is an golden opportunity to deliver for the people concerned, of whom 75,000 live in County Cork?  We are the ones most grossly affected when it comes to the lack of high speed broadband.  Some 13.5% of the people on the list live in County Cork.  I live in a constituency that is more than 130 miles wide.  Some members of this committee could walk across their constituency in two hours.  I cannot drive across mine in two hours.  That is the significant difference.  On the doorstep people tell me that the biggest issue is the lack of broadband.  One can talk about low speed broadband, but they do not even have dial-up Internet access.  This is a real issue.  If we were to say, "Stop," and scrap the plan and enter into a completely new tendering process, when would there be a suitable broadband connection for the people who contact my office every day of the week?  When would they have the opportunity to survive and prosper in rural areas?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#DD00200"><p>I do not know the details of the national planning framework.  However, I am conscious that it seeks to revive rural communities, while also providing for the compact development of urban areas.  I do not want to pronounce on the numbers without obtaining more information.</p> <p>  We received submissions from most Departments which saw merit in the proposal.  Obviously, there is clear merit in smart farming, digital education, rural areas revival and e-health.  The benefits are outlined cleared by the Departments responsible for them.  However, it is also important to hear the sceptical voices and evaluate what they have to say, but at the end of the day the State must make a decision.  As I said in the D&aacute;il, one of the most momentous decisions ever taken was the decision to introduce free second level education.  It changed the face of Ireland.  However, it was opposed by what was then the Department of Finance.  We rightly elect Governments and Governments make decisions.  Our peers, people who are elected, ultimately make these decisions.  We listen closely to the advice.  I assure the Senator that hours and hours were put into an evaluation of the various alternatives.</p><p>The minimum estimate of what it would take to start a new procurement process and get it going again was 37 months.  That is the figure I have.  The expectation is that it would take more than three years if we had to start from scratch again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00200"><p>Where did the Minister get the figure of 37 months?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00300"><p>That was the Department's evaluation.  When the alternatives were being evaluated, it looked back at the time it would take having regard to a fresh state aid notification and approval, the undertaking of a new procurement process, a teasing out of that process, and moving to a final decision and the signing of contracts.  It is not a short process.  Anyone who has seen procurement processes of this nature-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00400"><p>Has that been made public?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00500"><p>I believe it has, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00600"><p>The KPMG appraisal report published in May talked about a number of alternative options.  It said that no costings or detailed cost-benefit analyses for any of the alternatives were provided in the report.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00700"><p>We have dealt with that already.  I will go back and take the Deputy's question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00800"><p>Would Deputy O'Brien like to list out the questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE00900"><p>My next question depends on the answer to this one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE01000"><p>The Minister has already made reference to that earlier in the meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE01100"><p>I am just asking the Minister to confirm that no cost-benefit analyses were carried out and that no costings were provided.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE01200"><p>In respect of each alternative, the key element in respect of which it represented a departure from the existing plan A was evaluated in detail.  For example, in examining the use of wireless technology as opposed to fibre technology, the cost and reach of such a system was evaluated.  When it was found that the cost would be greater and the reach less, no further cost-benefit analysis was undertaken because these findings implied that the benefit would be less and the cost greater and that therefore the cost-benefit ratio would be inferior.  We did not ask PwC to do that exercise because it was moot.  In the same way, when we looked at the ESB as a possible alternative, we had to look at what would happen to the existing tender if we returned to a body which had dropped out of the tender process and offered it the contract.  That would be unfair to the firm that had proceeded through the tender phase and incurred costs in getting to that stage when others had fallen away.  That would be seen to be an unfair legal process.  We could terminate the contract and then consider the ESB, but the advice we got from the European Union and our own Attorney General was clear, that doing so would result in having to conduct a fresh procurement process.  The ESB could only be considered a player if it won any fresh procurement process that was set up.  We judged it unwise to lose three years and to undertake a fresh procurement process when we knew it was likely that the ESB would not be more cost competitive because we had some knowledge of its cost model.  In each case we analysed the alternatives to the level that enabled us to make an informed decision.  That did not require calculating a new cost-benefit ratio for each alternative.  On the benefit side we looked at the number of people who would be connected and the potential benefits they would acquire from being on the system.  On the cost side we looked at the costs and whether any alternative would reach the same number of people as plan A.  It was not necessary to do a fresh evaluation in every case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE01300"><p>There would, however, have been some level of financial appraisal done on every case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#EE01400"><p>Absolutely.  There was detailed appraisal of different elements of each alternative, including reach, cost, risk of delay, and legal robustness.  Each alternative was looked at with regard to what it would bring to the party.  Those features were the ones in respect of which effort went into the evaluation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00100"><p>The financial appraisals in the KPMG report have all been redacted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00200"><p>The financial appraisals involve confidential models.  The full detail of how a company intends to roll out deployment cannot be given out because it is confidential under the tender arrangement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00300"><p>Was the financial appraisal done on the alternative options that could be available?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00500"><p>They were all redacted, however, so we do not have any information on those alternative options.  We have no cost-benefit analysis.  The Minister said that such an analysis did not need to be done in some cases because the initial appraisal indicated that there was no point in proceeding to a full cost-benefit analysis, but a financial appraisal was done on every option.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00700"><p>We do not have any of that information, however, because it has been redacted in the KPMG report.  Why is that the case?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00800"><p>I presume it is because these evaluations are confidential to the operation.  When alternatives are being examined, confidential information is received from firms who could be players in the project.  For example, there were discussions with the ESB.  Information about potential bidders is not going to be put into the public domain-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF00900"><p>Why not, if the public is paying for it?  Surely we have a right to know what the cost-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF01000"><p>This is confidential information.  This is a procurement process in a sector in which different companies are competing.  They have a right to protect their information.  If we suppose that plan A fails and we are not able to provide contracts, we may have to go back to those alternatives.  We should not have estimates for those alternatives in the public domain, as they may undermine the capacity of those alternative operators to negotiate with subcontractors since those subcontractors will have seen the costs.  A level of confidentiality must be provided while a contract is a live event.  This will still have to be negotiated with subcontractors and there are deals to be agreed.  If a whole lot of information about what it would cost for a subcontractor to lay fibre to a given place and about the different cost elements involved is put out, the hands of both this contractor and other contractors are exposed.  It is not the sort of information that one puts into the public domain when one is still seeking to sign up subcontractors and different partners in the roll-out of this scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF01100"><p>Deputy O'Brien may ask one final question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF01200"><p>With regard to the options, the report talked about a window of opportunity of approximately five months before the full contract is signed.  It goes through a number of options.  Perhaps the Minister could comment on one of them, the negotiated procedure without prior publication.  A number of those options were listed but no further detail was provided on four of them.  Is it possible to cancel the contract now and go with that option of a negotiated procedure without prior publication?  The Minister had said that the ESB was not an option but we are now told that the contractor could end up using the ESB network.  How is it that it is not viable for the State to cancel the contract and use the ESB network when the private contractor who will sign the contract in five months could end up using that infrastructure itself?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#FF01300"><p>The obligation of the contractor is to deliver 146,000 km of fibre.  It can use ESB poles, Eir poles, or ducts.  It is not obliged to use any one option.  Prices for both are regulated.  ComReg will decide the price at which a service will be made available.  Using ESB poles creates additional health and safety issues different from those associated with using Eir poles.  There may be requirements which make them more difficult to use, but that does not mean they cannot be used.  They will be used where it is effective to do so.  There are differences in these areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00100"><p>On a point of clarification, the use of ESB poles is not regulated at the moment.  The Government needs to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00200"><p>It needs to be regulated.  I beg the Deputy's pardon.  That is the intention of ComReg.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00300"><p>I asked about the negotiated procedure without prior publication.  It is in the KPMG report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00400"><p>It is an alternative-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00500"><p>The report refers to the alternatives; if a contract is cancelled, it goes back to an open procedure with an electronic submission of tenders.  The report lists about 12 or 13 of them.  No further information is provided about four, and one of them was the negotiated procedure without prior publication.  There are no details of how long that would take although the report gives details of approximate times for the rest of them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00600"><p>I understand that it has legal risks and that was the reason that it did not go much further.  I will get the Deputy a note on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#GG00700"><p>I thank the Minister for coming in.  I believe in a social and equal Ireland and that means bringing broadband to every house, home and business in the country.  That has to be the big aim of what we are trying to do.  I was very critical of the plan that referred to 30 Mbps.  I remember when we were talking about 5 Mbps sorting everybody out, then it became 30 Mbps.  As early as 2012, I was firmly convinced that it was a gigabit or nothing.  The only way of doing that is fibre to the home, FTTH.  There has been a very interesting debate on this issue.  One very good thing in respect of the physical feasibility of doing this is that Eir has already done 300,000 houses across the country from Ballyconneely and Roundstone up to Donegal - I do not know which little villages.  It is running up the countryside from each old exchange that was built.  People seem not to fully understand that.  There is not a community in Ireland that has not now got a digital divide in it, including the rural community in which I live, Cornamona, where 100 houses have it and 300 or 400 houses do not.  From those who have the FTTH I hear no complaints.  Those who are 100, 200 or 300 yd. away are going absolutely crazy asking when they can get it.  They want FTTH and they want it now.  Everything is focused on that.  Has the Minister information on the roll-out to the 300,000 houses?  How much of it was on ESB poles, how much was on Eir poles and how much was underground?  My impression is that they underground it where there is already a duct and where the Eir cable was underground, and they overground it along the poles everywhere there is the old Eir copper cable.  I wish we could get rid of the old copper cable by putting in the fibre.  I have not seen any approach into houses yet on the ESB side but I would be very interested to see if they did that.  In lots of cases in rural Ireland the ESB pole is coming in from a totally different direction because the whole layout is not along the route.  The Minister might clarify that point.</p> <p>  Can the Minister give information to the committee as to how many nodes, as I call them, of fibre are now in every county in Ireland?  I know they are on the Eir map and the Department's map.  There is a node of fibre running out about a mile in every direction from each of these old exchanges.  It seems to me that for anybody to build a total alternative system would be crazy when the core of the system is there.  There is plenty of fibre as far as it goes and then it suddenly stops.  To continue on to the next house, one just links in.  We need to have a debate about how this is really configured on the ground as of today, not what the Minister might do if he was starting again.</p><p>If the take-up exceeds the projection, does the cost to the State decrease?  If the State gets a much bigger penetration or if, despite what Deputy Eamon Ryan says, a lot of people build along the lines that are going to be there anyway and want to connect in and we therefore get a lot more people connecting into this, does the cost decrease?  It is very interesting to watch what happened to ordinary telephone lines in the 1970s and 1980s.  Eventually they went to a peak of about 95% penetration before the mobile phone came in.  It suddenly took off and everybody, rural and urban, wanted it.  The Department was publishing figures for a while, until it stopped, on take-up.  What is the pattern of take-up when FTTH is provided in urban areas and in rural areas per 100 houses?  There is a time lag between FTTH coming in and its being taken up.  Is there as fast a rise in the graph in the urban and rural areas?  I do not perceive a major difference between urban and rural.</p><p> On price regulation, the &euro;30 per month for anybody connected to this system is independent of any other regulated price that is going to exist it in the market.  Could the Minister confirm that?  Were all the observations of all Departments published?  If not, why not?  I have reasonable respect for the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform but it does take a negative view on most things.  It has done so before in the history of the State.  It can also totally misunderstand things at times.  I remember a classic case when I had dealings with the Department about a pier on Inis Oirr.  My colleagues will be amused at this one.  The answer I got back was that there was no need for a pier on Inis Oirr because we had just built a very expensive pier on Inis M&oacute;r.  That showed an incredible lack of information about how islands work.  The Minister gets the point.  Also, looking at the wording of the memo, what the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform seems to be telling us is that rural Ireland can wait.  It is worth looking at this.  There are 1.1 million people, forgetting about the figures for the houses because there are some holiday homes there, and they love the broadband, by the way.  Most of us use broadband every day and, when they put it into old people's houses where they are being monitored by family members and so on, it is going to be used every day.  Let us say that in ten years time, 600,000 people will be using this every day.  That is only 50% of them, at a cost of &euro;3 billion.  I looked it up on the web and got a figure that only 150,000 people are expected to use the new metro every day.  Per head of population this is working out as a very cheap technology.  I think BusConnects is something like &euro;1 million. To my way of thinking, this is quite cheap technology.  It is also going to solve one of Deputy Eamon Ryan's dilemmas.  If we get all this broadband, we will have to do a lot less travelling.  Many people who now travel every day to work will be able to work from home.  It will reduce the carbon footprint.</p><p>I congratulate the Minister because there is joined-up thinking in the Department.  This is a game changer.  None of us in rural Ireland with any kind of broadband ever goes to a travel agent or people like that to book tickets.  We do not go there.  It is the same problem with the post offices because people do not go to them anymore; they just do it at home without any carbon footprint.  Contrary to what many others think, this will dramatically reduce carbon footprints.  </p><p> It will also deal with a congestion problem in the cities.  For example, half of the people working in the massive industrial estates east of Galway city come from rural Galway.  If they could do some of their work from home, it would reduce the congestion at the busy times because they could choose when to go to work in the city.  This also has a major urban benefit.</p><p> Supposing we scrap this plan and start again, am I right in thinking that the State could no longer give this job to a commercial State company without a procurement programme because it is a deregulated industry?  Is that right or wrong under EU law?  Unlike what we can thankfully still do with the ESB and the water network, am I right that the State could build this through a commercial entity without a procurement?  We need clarification on that.  Perhaps I am wrong and the Minister could tell a commercial State agency to build it and the State would own it.  We need clarity on that because there seems to be some doubt.</p><p> All the people want broadband now and I get more queries about broadband than anything else.  They want to know if the successful bidder must roll this out across the country, if the target of providing for 133,000 premises is for the first two years and so on, or can it cherry-pick?  Eir was very fair in the way it went around the country, doing small and big places at the same time.  Can the successful bidder cherry-pick which premises it supplies?  For example, in the early years of the roll-out, could the successful bidder keep to areas near the towns where there would be many more houses per km and leave large swathes of the west of Ireland until the very end, five, six or seven years later?  Does the successful bidder have to roll this out in an equitable way?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#JJ00200"><p>The Deputy was, to some degree, prophetic in saying that 30 Mbps was probably too slow because the EU confirmed in 2016 that the requirement would be 100 Mbps for universal access and, as he will be aware, this will go live at 150 Mbps and has the capacity to grow to 500 Mbps in ten years.  He was absolutely right.</p> <p>  I hear most complaints and representations from people who were left frustrated in areas beyond the Eir roll-out.  I understand that the Eir roll-out is 90% overhead and all on the Eir network.  A total of 200 exchanges and 88 MANs that will be used.  I do not have those exactly dotted on a map but those are the core system on which we are building to deliver.</p> <p>  There will be gains if take-up exceeds the prediction in that 60% of the additional profit will be clawed back but it also means that some of the exposure, such as encroachment, may not fall to be activated so the State does gain from that.</p><p>I understand that Eir has ceased publishing the take-up of the rural roll-out.  The last published figure was 14% but the chief executive officer of Eir said a couple of months ago that it has since doubled.  I understand it is entirely on track with what Eir expected so there are no grounds for believing there is a different attitude to take-up in rural, rather than urban, areas.  </p><p> The &euro;30 price is set by ComReg.  That could change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00200"><p>May I ask a supplementary question on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00300"><p>The Deputy can ask briefly.  The Minister has been here for a number of hours now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00400"><p>I appreciate that, but we are getting now to the questions the people are asking, not the experts.  Is that &euro;30 the equivalent to what fibre to the home, FTTH, costs in a town or city?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00500"><p>Exactly.  It is the city price being applied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00600"><p>This will be universal pricing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00800"><p>That is absolutely key and important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK00900"><p>I will not comment on how one gets from Inis O&iacute;rr to Inis Me&aacute;in with a peer in only one location.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01000"><p>A good rope ladder.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01100"><p>Submissions to Government memorandums are not normally published but those to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform were published because they were submissions of a different order.  They were not only submissions to a Government memorandum but they had been made in the course of all of this process.  They were in a different category and that is why they were published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01200"><p>I want to be fair and straight down the line about this for the good of the people.  There is a narrative in the media that gives the impression that the weight of advice given to Cabinet was opposed to this plan.  Is there any way that consideration should be given, in some form or another, to making the views of the different Departments available to the public so we get the full view of what was fed into Cabinet?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01300"><p>That is above my pay grade.  I will have to check that out for the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01400"><p>The Minister will have to ask his boss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01500"><p>Exactly.  I agree with the Deputy's analysis that the carbon footprint will be impacted.  Many progressive companies engage in significant remote working and they only do that if there is a secure fibre link.  They will not do it on a wireless-based link.</p> <p>  The Deputy is correct that if this was given to a commercial State company, there would have to be a new procurement process.  One could set up a State company from scratch which would tender to get the fibre but state aid cannot be given to an existing economic undertaking without a procurement process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01600"><p>I want to get this right.  A State company could be set up and it could roll out fibre if it had the know-how.  That company would own the fibre but not the poles.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01700"><p>The company would have to rent the poles or build its own.  Within two years, the contractor would be active in every single county.</p> <p>  I understand the grid is separated into 110 zones of 5,000 each.  I presume there is a certain logic based on the nodes, as the Deputy described.  The MANs and Eir exchanges will be the base from which they will start.  They will seek to deliver on a least cost basis but it is certainly the intention that this will be done in a fair way.  The company must hit its targets and it will making its plans clear at an early date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1312" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01800"><p>It would be helpful for the committee if the company was to make known its plans for the roll-out.  The media debate is about the financial elements of the plan.  The people's debate, at least among those in the 500,000 premises, is quite simple.  All they are asking is when it will happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1315" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CC22019051400002#KK01900"><p>On that note from Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, I thank the Minister and Minister of State, Deputies Bruton and Canney, and all of their officials for coming before the committee this afternoon and providing comprehensive responses to all questions from the Deputies.  We look forward to engaging with them again over the coming months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-05-14a.267" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 5.55 p.m. until 9.30 am on Thursday, 16 May 2019.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>