<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.2" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Children and Youth Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.3" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Denise Mitchell, Senator Catherine Noone, Deputy Tom Neville, Senator Fintan Warfield. Deputy Jim O'Callaghan,+ Deputy Anne Rabbitte, Deputy Sean Sherlock,</p><p>+ In the absence of Deputy Anne Rabbitte, for part of the meeting.</p><p>DEPUTY ALAN FARRELL IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.4" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#A00100">Tackling Childhood Obesity: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#C00200"><p>I welcome everyone to this meeting of the Joint Committee on Children and Youth Affairs at which we will continue our hearings on tackling childhood obesity.  We will hear a presentation by a representative of the GAA, Gaelic Athletic Association.  I welcome its community and health manager, Mr. Colin Regan, whom I thank for coming before us.  I also welcome members of the committee and viewers who might be watching our proceedings on Oireachtas TV.</p><p>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  If, however, they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>I remind members and delegates to, please, switch off their mobile phones or switch them to flight mode, as they interfere with the sound system and make it difficult for the parliamentary reporters to report the proceedings of the meeting.  Television coverage and web streaming can also be adversely affected.  </p><p>I advise Mr. Regan that any submission or opening statement he has submitted to the committee will be published on its website after the meeting.  After his presentation there will be a quick question and answer session.  I call on him to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.6" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#C00300"><p>Thank you, Chairman.  Since the inception of the GAA in 1884, we have been concerned with the health and well-being of the people and the nation.  In a modern Ireland the association has worked tirelessly to respond to the ever-changing needs of our members and the communities we serve.  This may present in providing new and interesting ways for young people to enjoy physical activity which we know supports their health and well-being, particularly when it comes to being overweight or obesity, or providing safe environments that help to support their social and emotional development.  In providing part of the solution to the childhood obesity challenge facing Ireland the GAA takes an holistic approach to well-being, recognising that our members&rsquo; physical, emotional and social health needs are interrelated and linked.</p> <p>  We have endless reports telling us that children are failing to meet the recommended physical activity levels, both at home and in the formal education setting.  We have similar reports highlighting the explosion in childhood obesity levels, coupled with increased consumption of energy-dense foods by children and adults alike.  We know and see the personal and societal consequences of this shift in lifestyle behaviours which are exacerbated by conditions in the society in which we live - health inequalities, access to relatively cheap convenience foods, sedentary lifestyles and powerful marketing and promotion by big business.</p><p>Any attempt to address the consequences of the obesogenic environment in which much of modern society operates requires a multifaceted, all-of-Government, all-of-society response.  The GAA proudly plays its part by helping swathes of our juvenile population achieve their recommended weekly physical activity levels, while exposing them to positive values, experiences, habits and role models that scaffold them on their journey through life.</p><p> The 2017 GAA games development and research report highlights current participation levels in the various games development activities undertaken and outlines proposals for future initiatives that will further increase participation.  The highlights from 2017 can be summarised as follows: 142,467 participants on Kellogg&rsquo;s GAA C&uacute;l Camps - an increase of 11.5% on 2016 - making it the biggest child sport promotion in the world with 20% of all children of that age in the country; approximately 189,842 primary school pupils participating in the Hurling Go Games blitz programmes, with 217,532 pupils playing in five or more Gaelic Football Go Games blitzes, outside their traditional training with their clubs twice a week; more than 250,000 primary school pupils receiving coaching as part of a primary schools coaching programme; the total number of players participating in a Go Games blitz programme nationwide amounting to approximately 77,626 children; the launch of GAA fun and run, which is designed to provide access to our games for persons with special needs and disabilities and is primed to optimise participation within multi-ethnic and lower socioeconomic demographics; and the launch of the GAA five-star centres to significant acclaim from the INTO and teacher training colleges because of their potential to increase levels of physical activity through the medium of Gaelic games in primary schools.</p><p> In addition to our traditional games-based models, the GAA has broken new ground in its efforts to equip our members and communities with the opportunities to enjoy healthier lifestyles with the introduction of the healthy club project in partnership with Healthy Ireland, the HSE, the National Office for Suicide Prevention and supported by Irish Life through a CSR funding partnership.  This award-winning project, which has been heralded at European level through a joint initiative of nine sporting organisations across nine EU countries called Sports Clubs for Health, uses an evidence-based approach that has been independently evaluated by a team from Waterford Institute of Technology's behavioural health research department.  It has been successful in delivering health-promoting programmes, policies and partnerships to young and old through the medium of their local GAA club.  The model is based on the WHO's approach to health promotion, which targets the setting in which we live, work, play and learn rather than targeting individuals or specific health issues.  We believe that, with additional support, this project has the potential to deliver a healthier Ireland, one that engages and excites people, offering access to evidence-based health interventions and resources in a new way but through a trusted and traditional setting and one that is available in every community in Ireland - your local GAA Healthy Club.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00200"><p>Mr. Regan mentioned the 11% increase in the Kellogg's C&uacute;l Camps in 2016.  Is there any indication of what participation levels will be this summer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.9" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00300"><p>We are anticipating a further increase and we have introduced an online booking model, which has proven very successful.  Even though we have reached 20% of the population of that age in the country, we anticipate a 5% increase this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00400"><p>Will Mr. Regan briefly outline the healthy club project?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.11" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00500"><p>Its origins are the clubs themselves, which asked us for support relating to issues such as healthy eating, physical activity for non-playing members, emotional well-being of members, gambling, drug and alcohol education, and community development.  Those areas primarily focused on clubs reaching out to their older members and providing access to games for non-traditional cohorts, such as persons with special needs or the new Irish.  At present, we are in phase 3 with 150 clubs participating, including several in each county, and we are only limited by resources.  We want to reach all 1,600 clubs this year and, having invited expressions of interest in January, we had 220 applications.  We only had the capacity to take in 92, however, adding to the 58 that concluded phase 2.  There is great hunger for this and we deliver a two and a half hour training module, developed in consultation with our partners in the HSE, the National Office for Suicide Prevention and Healthy Ireland, to all participating clubs.  The same training is available to any other of the 150 clubs which are not in the evaluation model.  Last year we trained 400 GAA healthy club officers throughout the country, whose clubs are interested in getting involved.</p> <p>  On healthy eating, I am aware that Amanda McCloat from St. Angela's home economics teacher training college was here.  With Amanda and her team, and Dr. Crionna Tobin, a leading sports nutritionist, we developed a programme called Recipes for Success, targeting minor and under 21 panels.  We have a fantastic booklet with healthy recipes based on whole foods, endorsed by some of our intercounty stars.  These not only support a healthier diet but also boost performance.  The local healthy club reaches out to the home economics teacher training college and the teacher gives them a two-hour cookery demonstration class, in their own time as volunteers, in which they take the panel through at least two recipes.  They are at a critical juncture in their life development as many are finishing their leaving certificate and going on to third level or apprenticeships.  The classes arm them with an interest in nutrition and the skills to cook the healthy food that will boost their lifestyles and, it is hoped, even make them better players.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00600"><p>I acknowledge the hard work the GAA does.  We had the f&eacute;ile at the weekend in Galway and it was a magnificent weekend, much of which is down to Damien Coleman, the development officer in the area.  I have enjoyed C&uacute;l Camps for the past three years and I have three kids participating.  When the two younger children, who are girls, get to sixth class, however, it stops.  In Portumna we are trying to get to 120 and all clubs try to increase their numbers.  Is the organisation trying to expand the age range or to put on a separate week for teenagers?  The GAA does good work for the under 16 camogie girls in helping with their diet and so on but I would love it to be part of the C&uacute;l Camp week, particularly for teenagers.  Is any development work being done on that?  If the GAA wants to do a pilot, I ask it to come our way as we would be delighted to take it on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.13" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00700"><p>Great.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00800"><p>Teenage girls are an issue for me.  Mr. Regan said Go Games was non-competitive for under 12s.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D00900"><p>That is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#D01000"><p>After that, the gloves come off and everything is competitive, but we lose a lot of people very quickly when that happens.  How is the training of management and coaches organised?  We need to balance competitiveness and participation.  I am delighted the GAA fun and run includes children of all abilities.  The perception in the past was that if a person had any inability, the gate was not open to them.  Mentors, the management and officers need training in inclusion.</p> <p>  I am the chair of the local camogie club and I cannot see any rules about minimum participation.  That was what was beautiful about the f&eacute;ile.  One had the opportunity to play for 30 minutes.  Everybody should get 30 minutes but how is the GAA going to write such a thing into its policies, at least at minor level, and have participation?</p><p>If we have participation and training two evenings a week, then we will have active children.  They will not be sedentary.  It will also bring in diet.  People from a local gym in my area, the Engine Room, spoke to our girls who are under 14 about diet and things such as the importance of breakfast.  We could channel that through the local camogie club.  The organisation is wonderful but we need to move past those aged 12 years because the problem is those aged 16 years.  What are the GAA's plan for this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.18" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00200"><p>The Deputy has made a good point.  The drop-off is not only happening with teenage girls but everyone at that age, and it is across all codes.  We have introduced several initiatives that attempt to address that.  The Deputy is correct that the competitive element turns off some young people at that critical stage in their development.  When the Deputy has a chance, she might read the full submission.  In recent years the games development department has introduced super games centres which are non-competitive centres.  These are ongoing rather than summer-based, like the C&uacute;l Camps, but they are their equivalent and target that teenage cohort, both male and female, to offer them the opportunity to come together in a non-competitive environment.  It was only introduced in 2015, when there were only ten centres throughout the country.  That grew to 115 in 2016 and 793 of our clubs last year, almost half the clubs in the country, plus 381 post-primary schools engaged in at least three sessions exploring the concept of this super games centre.  It is driven by the young people themselves, rather than having a formal coaching-driven ethos.  The intention is for young people to come together and formalise and regulate their games, with fun and participation at the core rather than competition.</p> <p>  On where we move after the C&uacute;l Camp philosophy, the intention of the Go Games was that the volunteer coaches who put in so much time have realised that it is not necessary to introduce competitions to young people because they will find the level of competition they want themselves.  Any player pathway in any sports organisation must have an element of competition to allow for those who are striving towards being the best athletes or players that they can be in their code.  There has to be a pathway for elite players and that is the intercounty championships in the GAA.</p> <p>  We feel the Healthy Clubs project is an antidote, as it were, to the win at all costs ethos that, unfortunately, can permeate all sports.  It is detrimental to the children but is driven by the adults.  The Healthy Club project exposes children to nutritional advice, recommendations and best practice.  During phase 2, 60 clubs participated and more than half engaged in the Recipes for Success programme.  In addition to the partnership with St. Angela's, those clubs then adopted healthy eating guidelines.  When I was playing, traditionally it would have been the practice to be given a packet of crisps and a fizzy drink after playing.  Now they are given a bottle of water and fruit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00300"><p>That still goes on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.20" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00400"><p>It does, of course, but it will take a couple of generations to change that ethos and to reassure clubs that once the changes are made, it becomes the norm.  It has been embraced by the young people throughout the country.  For instance, St. Finbarr's in Cork, one of our leading healthy clubs, has entered into a very interesting partnership with the local SuperValu to provide the fruit and vegetables and bottles of water for the club's nurseries every Saturday morning.  It is win-win.  It has cost the club nothing, the local business gets positive promotion and the adults and parents are very grateful to the club for taking this positive step.  It requires a bit of thinking outside the box along with proper policy and support and the provision of guidelines from the national level down.</p> <p>  On the Deputy's second point about the fun and run and providing access for people who might not traditionally see themselves as a county star or be able to engage in games in their local club because of any special needs they might have, be they intellectual, physical or sensory, we are driving the implementation of the fun and run through the healthy club model.  For instance, Raheny in north Dublin has a Raheny all-stars programme every Saturday morning.  The Central Remedial Clinic is in its catchment area so Raheny has a large population base that can benefit from this targeted approach to people who want to engage in physical activity.  We know from research that people with special needs are a particular at-risk group for obesity and being overweight because the standard physical activity opportunities are excluded to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00500"><p>I have one more question.  I very much like the idea of the GAA fun and run.  How many clubs are doing that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.22" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00600"><p>We are piloting it this year.  We launched it in November and will target 40 of our healthy clubs.  We will also introduce it in a number of schools.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00700"><p>Is it in 40 clubs now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.24" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00800"><p>We have opened the expressions of interest for clubs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E00900"><p>Therefore it is not in any clubs?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.26" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01000"><p>Several clubs are trialling it.  They are helping us to test it before we roll it out more broadly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01100"><p>Are those 40 clubs throughout the country or are they just focused near Dublin, inside the Pale?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01200"><p>We all know where this is going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01300"><p>There is a health club in every county and the scheme is open to any club that is interested.  We welcome expressions of interest from any club.  It is an adapted version of rounders.  I expect we have all played rounders in our youth and enjoyed it.  Instead of the throw, which can limit some people, the ball is on a tee.  It is wheelchair-friendly.  Each station around the pitch has a little mat and one must engage in an exercise which promotes the fundamental movements.  If one turns the mat over, there is also a wheelchair-friendly exercise.  When we launched it on the grounds in Trinity College Dublin last year, some of the pupils from the Central Remedial Clinic came down.  The great thing was that those who might not have been physically able to swing a bat had special needs assistants or family member, often a parent or sibling out getting their exercise with his or her child, as part of the game.  It is very family-friendly and also special needs adapted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1231" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01400"><p>I thank the GAA for the good work it does.  I see it at home regularly.  The work the GAA does, and the volunteers who participate, are appreciated across the board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01500"><p>I thank Deputy Rabbitte.  I call Senator Warfield, Deputy Sherlock and then Senator Noone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01600"><p>I second Deputy Rabbitte's words and thank Mr. Regan for his contribution.  I played GAA until recently but no longer do so having returned to soccer.  I commend its work, however, and its commitment is beyond dispute.</p> <p>  This does not relate directly to minors, but when I was a councillor and involved in a club, an issue that arose was the space which the bar occupies within the club.  This comes to mind in the context of drinks, fizzy drinks and packets of crisps after matches.  The space that the bar occupies is a financial resource for clubs, it has been good to me as an artist and musician and serves as a social space.  Is the GAA conscious of the space that it occupies?  Looking a generation ahead, is it something that Mr. Regan thinks might change?  Will we move away from a connection with pubs and alcohol?  We are working on obesity and childhood obesity.  Senator Noone and others have done great work on the alcohol Bill.  We are doing ongoing work on smoking.  Does Mr. Regan see that, over a generation, there will be a disconnection?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#E01700"><p>It is happening.  Only a tiny percentage of GAA clubs have bars.  I am from County Leitrim where none of the clubs has a bar.  They would be largely urban-based clubs.  I imagine that less than 5% of 1,600 clubs have a bar attached to them.  I will find out the exact number and share it with the committee.  In 2006, the GAA introduced its alcohol and substance abuse prevention programme in partnership with the HSE.  At the time, Ireland was among the highest consumers of alcohol in the OECD.</p><p>Since then, more than 750 GAA clubs have introduced an alcohol and substance abuse prevention policy.  During my childhood, after an underage match we would be brought into the local pub for sandwiches.  After every county final, the pub was where the medals were handed out.  That idea or association has been completely broken.  The GAA sample club drug and alcohol abuse policy clearly indicates that no juvenile events should even take place in the local premises.  We do not allow sponsorship of any juvenile teams, gear or equipment by licensed premises.</p><p> As part of phase 2 of the healthy club project, more than half of the 60 clubs involved became completely smoke-free campuses.  More than half of the 150 clubs now in phase 3 have indicated that they will do the same.</p><p> A major cultural shift has been taking place.  It comes down to an appreciation that the GAA club is a setting for something beyond the delivery of the skills associated with Gaelic games.  It is a setting where people come together as families and as a community to socialise.  The idea is that this setting can promote positive health messages in a variety of areas.  Clubs are becoming far more mindful of how they can do that.  We are fortunate with some of the partnerships we have developed, including with Healthy Ireland, the HSE and the National Office for Suicide Prevention.  We have also received support from Irish Life through corporate social responsibility investment.  We have been able to development a community and health department in Croke Park that is solely responsible for trying to drive this shift.</p><p> It is also important to note that the association has no alcohol sponsorship at national level.  There has been no such arrangement since we parted ways with Guinness as the sponsor of hurling.  We are unique in an Irish context in that regard given how large the association is and yet we are in no way dependent on alcohol sponsorship.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00200"><p>I join in welcoming Mr. Regan to the committee today.  We have heard of a number of tremendous and positive initiatives.  It is good to have crystallisation of what the GAA is doing right down to the local community, because sometimes we think of the GAA in binary terms, whether hurling or football, camogie or handball and so on.  Often, we think of the GAA in binary terms and in an intercounty context only.  As policymakers we might not fully appreciate what happens across the land except perhaps through the prism of our individual clubs.</p> <p>  Given that we are good parochial people, I am keen to hear more about the fun and run activity.  My club in Mallow, County Cork, has world-class facilities.  We have a multimillion euro facility.  It is something that could be used as a hub for the Munster region for outworking in that regard.  I would be delighted to work with the GAA on this.  We should not simply look at the facility in terms of Mallow but from the Munster or regional perspective given its specific location.  Perhaps I will share more with Mr. Regan on that afterwards.</p> <p>  We cannot underestimate the metrics Mr. Regan has given us today.  The key metric is the top-line metric, which is a total of 142,467 participants in the C&uacute;l Camps.  It is the biggest child sport promotion in the world.  That is a phenomenal metric for what is an indigenous sport when we look at it in global terms.  We should be shouting that metric from the rooftops.  It is testament to the lateral thinking that now exists within the GAA.  The GAA sees itself as having a clear social function.  The association sees itself as having responsibilities to its community right down to the neighbourhood.  Committee members are delighted to hear the metric in the context of our deliberations on tackling obesity.</p> <p>  Does Mr. Regan believe more needs to be done in outreach to primary schools?  Are some primary schools not being reached?  Is the ability to get in the front door hampered for certain reasons?  If so, what are the reasons?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.36" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00300"><p>That is a good question.  I thank Deputy Sherlock for his kind words.  I will come back on the Mallow issue.  We delivered the healthy club orientation day for the Munster clubs in Mallow last month.  We will be there again in a couple of weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00400"><p>Excellent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.38" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00500"><p>A total of 326,493 primary school pupils received coaching through the GAA last year.  Some 54% of these were male and 47% were female.  There is always scope for increasing the numbers.  We know from the statistics that few primary school children are meeting their recommended physical activity levels through the physical education curriculum in the formal education setting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00600"><p>The same applies to their developmental goals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00700"><p>This is one of the rare times we have this age group captive, for want of a better word.  We know that, nowadays, we need to be able to introduce interesting and varied physical activity opportunities for young boys and girls.  It might be foolish of me to say it but organised sport is not for everyone.</p> <p>  The GAA works with primary schools.  Pat Daly is the head of games development.  Deputy Sherlock referred to the metrics that the C&uacute;l Camps have reached.  Sligo footballer Charlie Harrison is the national C&uacute;l Camp co-ordinator.  He has done extraordinary work on the increase in this area in recent years.  The games development department is mindful of providing fundamental movement opportunities for young people in the educational setting, especially primary school.  These are not solely GAA-specific.  The idea is to engage with them in a way that excites them and gets them moving.  This allows them to learn the fundamental and functional movement skills that will support a physical lifestyle throughout their lives.  We are not selfish about whether the means are GAA-specific.</p> <p>  The games department has introduced a 5 star centre concept.  This is in response to the fact that only 18% of primary school pupils are achieving the recommended of 60 minutes of moderate to vigorous activity every week.  GAA coaches support schools that take up the challenge and participate in the have a ball programme and the fun and run initiative.  It is centred around basic movements such as striking and the catch and kick experience.  Those involved get to participate in the Go Games at Cumann na mBunscol level and the Go Games skills challenge as well.  Schools that meet all these elements are recognised by the GAA as 5 star centres.  We are hoping that this incentive will see an increase in the positive influence that the GAA is having through its network and its links with schools.  This is being researched in partnership with DCU moving well-being well programme.  We will keep the committee abreast of the findings of that research.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00800"><p>I have another question on primary schools and how to reach a penetration rate of 100%.  Mr. Regan stated that the GAA is willing to reach out into other areas.  He referred to the principle of getting basic movements, how the GAA does not claim ownership of this, and how the association is willing to work with others.  The committee will have to make recommendations.  If Mr. Regan were to make recommendations, is there anything he would recommend by way of an action to try to reach a 100% penetration rate for every school so that every child in the country could hit that target?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.42" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#F00900"><p>The first step is to identify the current barriers preventing schools from supporting children in reaching the basic requirements of 60 minutes.  What are the barriers?  Is it is a matter of facilities or the knowledge base among teachers within the school?  Is it parents?  Is it the fact that not enough coaches from the various national governing bodies are able to cover the required additional support that would raise the level?</p><p>We could adopt a targeted approach to supporting those schools.  A number of schools are achieving that target.  It is a question of identifying the barriers preventing other schools from achieving what is required, often through the curriculum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00200"><p>My last question is more of a shout-out for handball.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00300"><p>Very good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00400"><p>It is a minority sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00500"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00600"><p>We have produced world champions in handball in my great town of Mallow and have invested heavily, through sports capital funding, in retrofitting our club.  I would always put my hand up for having handball.  The GAA, from a  global perspective, should consider that sport.  It is developing slowly but it could develop quickly if it was given a global platform.  I would welcome if handball could be translated into the work Mr. Regan is doing and be considered in some of these initiatives, particularly with respect to catching, throwing, forward movement and so on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00700"><p>Handball is our only global game.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00800"><p>Indeed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G00900"><p>If one were to go to South America, one would see people playing handball up against every wall.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01000"><p>Exactly.  I put my hand up for handball.  I thank Mr. Regan.  This has been a wonderful contribution to our discourse on obesity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01100"><p>Thank you, Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01200"><p>I thank Mr. Regan for attending.  I apologise for missing the oral presentation of his submission, which I read in advance and I have scanned it again.  I have a few questions.  Does he have a policy on energy drinks?  Many supermarkets have banned the selling of them for under 16 year olds.  Many studies show that the high sugar and caffeinated nature of those drinks has been associated with sudden cardiac syndrome.  There have been some high-profile tragic cases in GAA sports.  I would be interested to hear of any policy or thoughts Mr. Regan has on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.55" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01300"><p>Our healthy eating guidelines, which have been taken up by more than 50% of the clubs involved in the healthy club project, do not recommend the use of either highly caffeinated or sugary sports drinks.  We do not have a directive on it because that does not work.  We have found, based on the advice we have been given by bodies such as <i>safe</i>food that guidelines and supporting clubs in changing the culture and environment around this is a much more positive approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01400"><p>I appreciate that a positive message might work better but it probably would be no harm, given how harmful those drinks have been proven to be in many studies, to have an awareness campaign or something similar within the GAA because it is uniquely positioned to do that.  It would be great for children to understand at that early age that these types of sugar-laden, high-caffeine drinks besides being an obesity trigger could have detrimental effects on their health.  That is just my tuppence ha'penny worth on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.57" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01500"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01600"><p>Senator Warfield mentioned the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill.  We should have a public health obesity or sugar Bill or something along those lines and take similar measures when it comes to advertising junk food and other foods that have a high sugar, fat and salt content.  In the overall context, does Mr. Regan believe such a measure would be effective?  For example, parents have mentioned to me food items their children have been given when they to clubs.  I am not referring to only GAA events but to many different events.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.59" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01800"><p>One parent who has four children told me that one Christmas, one of his children got ten selection boxes in the run-up to Christmas at various events, including GAA events.  Should there be a policy or is there a need to introduce legislation in this respect?   I get slagged all the time for adopting too much of a nanny-state approach on this issue but we might need to nanny the state a little on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G01900"><p>I feel the Senator's pain because our department is looked upon as the nanny state within the GAA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02000"><p>I am queen nanny of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02100"><p>Congratulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02200"><p>I just love it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02300"><p>I was a member of the Healthy Ireland Council, representing the GAA for the past three years, under the chairmanship of Keith Wood.  I remember hearing that preschool children are exposed to 1,000 ads for unhealthy foods per annum.  How can they possibly want anything else if the advertising works?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02400"><p>And social media is a big problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02500"><p>Exactly.  We learned lessons from the alcohol and substance abuse prevention programme.  More than 750 clubs have drug and alcohol policies in place and swathes of them are moving in the direction of being completely smoke-free, There is a recognition in that area, and the same recognition and cultural change is now starting to happen with the products such as fizzy drinks and crisps.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02600"><p>And sugary food.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02700"><p>We have a duty of care to our young members, in particular, with respect to what we provide them with.  We are also trying to reach the parents in terms of what provide their children with when they send them to our C&uacute;l camps.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02800"><p>How does Mr. Regan do that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G02900"><p>During registration is the easiest time to do that. There are two periods of registration for young people with our clubs, first and foremost, when parents register to sign up their children at the start of the year.  The clubs, if they have healthy eating guidelines in place, have the opportunity to make the parents aware of that.  Most of them will carry information on that on their Facebook page and on their website.  Second, we are accessing 142,000 young people every year through our C&uacute;l camps, and that number is increasing year on year.  We have introduced healthy eating guidelines on the registration page for parents, outlining what we expect an appropriate healthy lunch to be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03000"><p>Mr. Regan may have covered this aspect and if he has my apologies.  Are they given any nutritional information?  I appreciate that C&uacute;l camps are activity based but one will never out-train a bad diet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.73" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03100"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03200"><p>I do not want to denigrate or be dismissive of the work the GAA does in the area of developmental goals.  It is fantastic.  Is there a captive audience?  As my colleague said, we have that metric of 142,000, and it is increasing.  Is there an opportunity to provide those young people with a few hours education on nutrition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.75" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03300"><p>We have explored it.  What we learned from the drug and alcohol space is that if we were to go to a club to do a presentation on the ills and evils of alcohol or drugs, we would get about three young people in the room.  However, if we speak to a squad about why excessive or inappropriate drinking or misuse of substances negatively impact on their performance, we would had a full room.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.77" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03500"><p>We are finding the same thing in the healthy eating space.  Instead of saying what one should not do, we are turning that coin on its head.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03600"><p>I would not suggest Mr. Regan should tell them what they should not do.  It would just be some education for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.79" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03700"><p>I know that.  In terms of education with respect to our submission, the age-specific information to be delivered to five to 12 years olds is something we would absolutely welcome some support and guidance on as a sporting organisation-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03800"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.81" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G03900"><p>-----from <i>safe</i>food or whatever entity is appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04000"><p>That is a good one for our information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.83" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04100"><p>It was one of the recommendations on the last page of our full submission.  We felt we had the skills set to target 16 to 21 year olds because we worked with St. Angela's home economics teacher training college on the development of our resources and guidelines in that space, and with Dr. Crionna Tobin, a leading sports nutritionist who is very health-orientated.  However, the specificity of the five to 12 year old age bracket in the area of nutrition and healthy eating and the sensitivities involved, particularly when speaking to parents about their children on this topic, can be highly emotive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04300"><p>We know that for some families, money is a major barrier to food choices.  Health inequalities is one of the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04400"><p>That is part of the requisite education-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04500"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04600"><p>-----in that it is not expensive to eat healthily.  Examples such as that referred to by Mr. Regan regarding the home economics professional, whom I know, and such positive messages about how inexpensive it can be to eat healthily are helpful.  There might be a possibility for the pairing up of <i>safe</i>food Ireland with the GAA in its C&uacute;l camps for a short percentage of the time.  It is all about movement and having fun but there could be a positive educational aspect to it.  That might be something we could recommend.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.89" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04700"><p>Thank you, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04800"><p>Last question, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G04900"><p>I do not feel I have had enough time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G05000"><p>That is the same for us all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G05100"><p>I have two brief questions. Does Mr. Regan find in lower socioeconomic areas that he has to make more of an effort or does he make a similar effort?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#G05200"><p>We know from research that, unfortunately, people in lower socioeconomic areas play less sport.</p><p>It is one of the contributing factors - combined with access to resources and services etc. - the health outcomes in those areas are also poorer.  We are making targeted efforts to reach into those areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00200"><p>That is good to know.</p> <p>  Insurance concerns in schools are an issue.  I did some work on this a few years ago.  Mr. Regan was talking about schools and developmental goals and getting them moving for the 60 minutes a day.  What of the anecdotal evidence that certain schools are stopping children from running?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.97" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00300"><p>Insurance is one of the biggest issues facing every setting where physical activity is enjoyed in Ireland at present.  It is a significant barrier for many of our healthy clubs.  Our own insurance allows for the delivery of Gaelic games related activities, officially sanctioned training and matches.</p> <p>  Our healthy clubs are now trying to completely change the understanding of what a GAA club is.  It is trying to become a hub for health for the entire community.  They are running out Operation Transformation-type events, couch to 5 km, walking groups for older members-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00400"><p>Marathon in a month - that type of thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.99" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00500"><p>-----park runs and everything that one can possibly imagine that could support people who never played football or hurling, or handball or rounders-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00600"><p>To get them moving.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.101" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00700"><p>-----and insurance is the biggest barrier that we are facing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00800"><p>Is Mr. Regan hearing that, in particular, from schools, or is he picking up that information, merely through the children with whom he works, that they are being prevented from moving in schools?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H00900"><p>It is anecdotal but we do not have any concrete evidence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01000"><p>I can get no concrete data on that.  Technology is the final issue I will raise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01100"><p>Senator Noone is four questions into her last one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01200"><p>No, no.  Those were tiny ones.  I really want to ask an important one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01300"><p>They are all important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01400"><p>Everybody had a lot of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01500"><p>In fairness, they are all important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01600"><p>I just want to ask about technology, if the Chairman would allow me a minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01700"><p>This is Senator Noone's last one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01800"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H01900"><p>This is Senator Noone's fifth last question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02000"><p>It is my last one.  Those were all brief questions.  I did not make a long contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02100"><p>Senator Noone got the same time as everybody else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02200"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02300"><p>The Senator should ask her question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02400"><p>Are the effects of technology on children and the unrestricted nature of the access to smartphones and the Internet generally, something with which Mr. Regan has a problem or what are his thoughts in that area?  Has the GAA a policy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02500"><p>It is not a significant problem in clubs.  It is one of the areas where they come in and gladly turn their phone off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02600"><p>That is what I thought.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02700"><p>It is a safe haven.  The only challenges we have in that space is using it to the best of our abilities in getting our messages and promotions out.  We have had a minute number of incidents where there might have been issues around online bullying or the likes of that.  As for it being an issue once they come to the club, it is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02800"><p>I thank Mr. Regan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H02900"><p>I will be brief.  I thank Mr. Regan for coming in.  He has answered many questions that I would have had anyway.  I have been listening for the past hour.</p> <p>  I have nothing but respect for the GAA and what it does through communities.  I am a rural Deputy who represents County Limerick.  We have many small rural GAA clubs, which are the heart of what happens in the community or the hub, like the schools in the parishes.  I want to put on the record I have nothing but the utmost respect for the GAA.  I myself used play GAA games.</p> <p>  I have one or two questions.  I will take a slightly different view to this.  Much has been answered about the younger children.  If I diverge slightly from the topic, I ask the Chairman to pull me up on it.</p> <p>  My question relates to older children.  A child, in legal terms, is under 18.  Does Mr. Regan see anything happening around performance enhancing or any of that starting to creep in, particularly for the older children aged 16 or 17, and even players aged 18?  What one hears is probably anecdotal.  I would be interested in Mr. Regan's comments on that and whether he is starting to see it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.124" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H03000"><p>I suppose we are mindful of it.  Thankfully, we have not had any notable incidents.  However, anybody who uses a gym now in Ireland will see that nearly everybody is walking round with some kind of container with a shake of some form or other in it.</p> <p>  Our concern is that, at intercounty level, our players are working with dietitians and are exposed to the best possible supplements that have the appropriate contents.  When these lads go back to their clubs after a year of conditioning with a dietitian, they are physically transformed and sometimes their clubmates say, "Wow, I need to do whatever he is doing."  However, they access the supplements online, which is completely unregulated.  It could be coming in from any part of the world and could contain anything.  We are concerned about an awareness that anything that one sources should be sourced through an approved dietitian and used with the proper supervision.</p> <p>  We have national guidelines that no juvenile should use any supplement whatsoever.  At that age of their development and the level of sport and training that they should be exposed to, a proper balanced healthy diet is more than enough to provide them with all their nutritional needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H03100"><p>The reason I ask the question is, obviously, at intercounty level, as Mr. Regan says, because the game is getting ever more competitive and ever more professionalised with the level they go to in order to get their fitness up, they are spending more time off-season in the gym and that, obviously, has an influence on the underaged players who look up to the senior players.  They want to be that senior player.  It might be something we could pop into our report in respect of enhancement.  I welcome the fact that the GAA is recognising that and has guidelines on it.  It is different.  I accept I am moving off obesity slightly but it is in the same vein.  I thank Mr. Regan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H03200"><p>On my own behalf, I thank Mr. Regan for his presentation.  No doubt the GAA provides an extraordinary service to the State and has done for generations.  This particular venture for the GAA, in terms of healthy eating promotion, is to be welcomed and appreciated.  The GAA is in every corner of every county.  It has two clubs in some towns.  It is fantastic to see such a big organisation take such a lead on it and it is important.  There are many other sporting codes that do the same but it should be noted that no other sporting code has the reach that the GAA has.</p> <p>  I will focus on three themes.  The first, which is the most important one - because one can have all the C&uacute;l camps in the world but if one does not promote participation, and the sustenance of that participation, we have a problem, and it is the problem that we are facing in this country in terms of obesity rates - is, of course, participation.  Our opening speaker, Deputy Rabbitte, touched upon it but it is important to dwell on it for a moment.  As somebody who was very good at one particular code and dreadful at most others, I was a willing participant in all sports.  On that drop-off in participation, because of the exclusion of individuals, and the competitive nature of sporting organisations, I can speak to one section of my community in Dublin Fingal where there are two other sporting organisations that grew as a result of the exclusion of hundreds of people because of that one organisation - it does not matter what code it is or where it is.  The point is there are two other clubs that now have hundreds of members because of this competitive nature and it started at under 12s.  That is wrong.</p> <p>  Senator Richmond made a point yesterday which was covered in the media - I am sure other members have made points about it in the past - that there should be encouragement for children to participate up to a particular age where there should not be competition involved.  When I say there should not be competition, they should be given a run at every game or every second game.  It is not good enough for a sporting organisation to exclude a child who shows up week in, week out, trains just as hard as everybody else but maybe just does not have that talent or for it, for instance, to encourage him or her to participate in a team that might play once a month.  I would be interested to hear Mr. Regan's view on that matter.  I am not targeting the GAA at all.  It happens right across the spectrum of sporting codes.  I would be interested to hear his view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#H03300"><p>The GAA's view is exactly the same as the Chairman's.  We find that unacceptable.  The Go Games philosophy was introduced specifically to address that.  The Go Games philosophy requires - it is compulsory for all clubs - that children up to under 14 level enjoy an opportunity.  Everybody plays is the philosophy of the Go Games, as we heard from Deputy Rabbitte.  Deputy Rabbitte attended the f&eacute;ile hurling in Galway last week and there was a requirement for roll-on, roll-off substitutes for participation in that.</p> <p>  Unfortunately, there is still a culture driven by some coaches within our clubs where they seek to live vicariously through the underage teams with which they are working.</p><p>We also now have a requirement that all coaches working with juvenile teams in the association receive foundation level coaching.  It will take a generation to deliver that cultural and philosophical change but we believe that if every club steps up to the plate and requires every coach to receive that training, which directs them on how to address this challenge, we will see a sea change within the association over the coming years.  We are delighted with the fact that, as I mentioned, 220 clubs applied to get involved in the healthy club project.  One of their big motivations is to address that kind of culture within their own clubs.  We see that project as being a further antidote to the win-at-all-costs ethos that can unfortunately carry across all codes.  I played pretty much anything with a ball as I was growing up and I unfortunately experienced that attitude myself.  The drop-off rate is one of the factors but the issue is multifaceted.  </p><p> I am excited to hear that, when a club lost those players through bad practice, another club was ready and able to provide something for those young people.  It is essential that we have a sufficient network of opportunities for young boys and girls to enjoy physical activity regardless of whether they do so under our own particular code.  In fact, I would go further and ask how we imbue a love of not just sporting activity, but activity in general among young people during the formative years of their lives that they will carry right throughout.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00200"><p>One of the other barriers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00300"><p>I must give Mr. Regan my apologies.  I have to go because I have to ask a question of the Minister now.  Could I get Mr. Regan's contact details before we finish?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00400"><p>I will send the Deputy an email.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00500"><p>One of the other barriers to participation in sport, which I have unfortunately learned of both as a public representative for the last 14 years and from having witnessed it personally, is competitive behaviour on the touchline, primarily from parents.  It can be a bit of an issue.  It is a barrier to certain parents returning.  In my experience it is especially the case with women bringing their children to GAA games and, indeed, soccer games and things like that.  That is my personal experience.  If a child is excluded or removed from the pitch or training ground - primarily the pitch because obviously there would not be much competition on a training ground - it is a bit of an issue.  Promoting participation should form part of overarching policies within any sporting code.  I am sure the GAA has some code in this regard.  Perhaps Mr. Regan would like to drill into it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00600"><p>We do.  I would actually go a little bit further and say that it is a big issue.  We introduced the respect initiative in 2009.  It outlines the behaviour that is expected on the sidelines in GAA grounds.  It has not had the impact we would have hoped that it would have had at this stage.  We launched our new strategic plan on Friday which covers 2018 to 2020.  It has explicitly called for a rigid implementation of the respect initiative right across the association.  Initially it specifically targeted juvenile games.  I know I keep returning to the healthy club project.  It is great to have a national code but an implementation arm is needed beyond even our traditional network of clubs.  We need clubs themselves to show leadership and to say that this is not acceptable within the club.  When the 150 clubs signed up at the provincial orientation days last month, they received a welcome pack which included pitchside signage outlining what kind of behaviour is accepted there.  At the moment the implementation committee for the new strategic plan is exploring how each of the actions are going to be distributed across the association.  I can assure the Chairman that the respect initiative will be getting the kind of support it needs to address that very important issue.  The healthy club project has provided an unexpected and very welcome development in that it has opened the door for female leadership within the association.  Some 50% of healthy club officers are female and 50% of the members of our national health and well-being committee are female.  The Chairman is exactly right.  We see that positive influence shining a light on these areas which the more male-dominated attitudes may, perhaps, have overlooked somewhat in previous years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00700"><p>On that, and without being 100% serious about it, I am sure there are historic reasons for the fact that camogie is called something different from hurling and that it exists as a name.  In terms of participation, is it really necessary?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00800"><p>Camogie has its own independent association, and proudly so.  It is the same case with the Ladies Gaelic Football Association, LGFA.  They are sister associations of ours but they are stand-alone associations.  We have just signed a memorandum of understanding with both organisations in order to facilitate much closer collaboration and co-operation, particularly in respect of access to pitches, co-ordination of fixtures and so on.  I think they would be very proud to maintain and hold their own identities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J00900"><p>I participated in football for three or four years but, like Senator Warfield referenced, I went back to soccer.  I mean no disrespect to the GAA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01000"><p>Not at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01100"><p>It was just me.  Touching on something Senator Noone raised in regard to sugary drinks on the sidelines, the packet of crisps after the game and the discouragement the GAA puts in place through its guidelines, Mr. Regan mentioned that approximately 50% of clubs are involved with those guidelines.  He also said that mandatory mechanisms do not work and that promotion does.  Is there a point at which he might feel it would be time to say that it should not just be sugary drinks but also high-sugar bars, and energy bars in particular?  Is there a tipping point at which the GAA would say that is enough, that players should not have the bag of crisps after the game and that clubs should not be providing them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01200"><p>It is an interesting question.  The challenge there, which we experienced in a broader sense in Europe when cheese was classified as unhealthy due to its inherent fat levels, is to determine the black and white of the matter.  If one is to draw a line in the sand, what exists inside and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01300"><p>Confectionery, sugary drinks and energy drinks would be a start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01400"><p>What specifically is classified as confectionery?  It is a challenging space because there is a time within club functions, which we have all the time, where it is more than appropriate to provide some confectionery, for example at Christmas gatherings or celebrations.  If one has a black and white policy it is a challenge to deal with that.  We prefer to show leadership in what is expected in this space.  We came to a tipping point with the alcohol issue.  We were supporting clubs in adopting policies themselves and encouraging them to do so.  We then actually put it into the rules in terms of juvenile activities.  It should have been a rule anyway, but there is now zero sponsorship of juvenile teams, gear, equipment or competitions by alcohol companies permitted.  Once we work with our members in order to let them know why we are working towards a goal, we will see general understanding and support for it and will reach a tipping point naturally at which the clubs themselves take ownership of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01500"><p>On that point, I am interested to know whether Coca-Cola or any of these companies are allowed to sponsor such items.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01600"><p>We have turned down a number of approaches from entities we felt did not align with our values in that space over recent years.  It is not written in the rules.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01700"><p>There is no policy as such.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.145" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#J01800"><p>It is dealt with on a case-by-case basis.  We have a national health and well-being committee that features the likes of Dr. Janas Harrington who lectures in public health and epidemiology in University College Cork and Ms Susan Kenny who is a qualified dietician.</p><p>When we entered the relationship with Kellogg's for our C&uacute;l Camps, a team of dieticians developed appropriate recommendations and nutritional guidelines for the healthy lunches that would appear on the C&uacute;l Camp registration page.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00200"><p>I am probably a bit of a hard liner, but I have an issue with Kellogg's because most of its cereals are loaded with sugar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.148" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00300"><p>The research shows that breakfast is the most important meal of the day.  Kellogg's provide a number of options that would more than fall within the acceptable parameters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00400"><p>That is a matter for debate.  Porridge is healthy and a good cereal option.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.150" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00500"><p>I will send the Senator the link to the guidelines on porridge.  Kellogg's has supported the endorsement of porridge as a healthy option.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00600"><p>That is good but many of its products are confectionery items sold as cereals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00700"><p>We will note the Senator's comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00800"><p>I do not mean to be negative but the volume of sugar in the cereals which children eat is a major problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K00900"><p>On classification and whether cheese is healthy, apparently it is but too much of it is not.  Like everything, it is all about moderation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K01000"><p>It is all about education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.156" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Colin Regan" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K01100"><p>It is an interesting debate.  With Kellogg's as sponsors of C&uacute;l Camps, the numbers participating have almost doubled.  That has to be weighed up as well.  Children in Ireland are not achieving recommended physical activity levels.  Through our partnership with Kellogg's, we have enabled 142,000 children to increase their physical activity levels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K01200"><p>It is definitely positive in that respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1300" speakername="Alan Farrell" time="09:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CYJ2018061300002#K01300"><p>I thank Mr. Regan for his presentation and for our answering our questions in a comprehensive manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.159" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 11.05 a.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 27 June 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.160" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.161" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Bernard J. Durkan, Senator Paul Coghlan, Deputy Sen Haughey, Senator Terry Leyden, Deputy Mattie McGrath, Senator Neale Richmond. Deputy Frank O'Rourke,</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL HEALY-RAE IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.162" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#A00100">General Affairs Council: Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Deputy Brophy and Senator Craughwell.  I remind members to switch off their mobile phones or put them in silent mode.  The purpose of this meeting is an engagement with the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy McEntee, on the work of the General Affairs Council.  I am glad she and her officials were able to take time out of their busy schedule to be here today.  They are all very welcome.  The next meeting of the General Affairs Council takes place in a couple of weeks.  The committee's engagements with the Minister of State on her work in the Council on the strategic issues facing the European Union are useful, particularly in light of what is happening in England.</p> <p>  The General Affairs Council agenda is likely to be full.  As we cannot cover all the issues, we will focus in particular on the Brexit negotiations, the future of Europe's work, the Government's position on the enlargement perspective for the Western Balkans and the future budget of the EU.  We had an interesting meeting yesterday with an official from the European Commission on the Commission's proposal for the future budget, which I am sure will be added to in today's discussion.</p> <p>  Before I invite the Minister of State to make her opening statement, I remind everyone that the normal rules of privilege apply.  I welcome the ambassadors and embassy staff and members of the public in the Visitors Gallery.  The Minister of State may make her opening statement now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#A00300"><p>I thank the committee for the invite.  As always, I am delighted to be here.  It has been a particularly busy period since we last met.  There have been many developments and so as mentioned by the Chairman I will confine my remarks to the four key areas.  If there are other areas on which members have questions I am happy to deal with them in the questions and answers session.  As highlighted by the Chairman the four key areas are the current state of play in the Brexit negotiations, which I am sure is top of most people's agenda at this time; the debate on the future of Europe, including the national citizens' dialogue which concluded last month - I take this opportunity to thank the chairman and all members who attended the events throughout the country and also the final event; the EU enlargement perspective for the Western Balkans, particularly following on from the summit in Sofia, which I attended with the Taoiseach; and the multiannual financial framework, MFF, which the committee addressed in detail yesterday with the Commission but on which members may still have questions.</p> <p>  I will start with the multiannual financial framework as it dominated much of the General Affairs Council which took place in March.  We had an initial discussion on the Commission's recent legislative proposal for the MFF, the EU's next seven-year budget framework.  This issue will also be discussed by the Taoiseach and other Heads of State and Governments at the European Council on 28 and 29 June, which is approximately two weeks away.  This is the beginning of the negotiating process between the Commission, the Parliament and member states, which will last into at least the middle of next year.  As the current framework runs to the end of 2020, it is crucial that agreement is reached before that deadline.</p><p>I warmly welcome the fact that Ms Jennifer Brown, an official from the Commission, travelled from Brussels to Dublin yesterday to address this committee and other interested stakeholders.  I am sure the committee is well-versed in the details so I hope I do not go over too much ground or repeat what was said by Ms Brown yesterday.</p><p> As with any organisation, it is fundamental that as EU member states, we agree on how much we can spend, how and when we spend it, and how to raise the money.  It is a question of adapting to the changing global environment and, most important, of prioritising competing and evolving requirements and demands.  Since last year, I have been running a series of citizens' dialogues or national engagements about the EU and we are asking citizens what they want to see, and this consultation on the future of Europe will feed into our position on how the EU allocates its resources.  The initial proposal was published by the Commission just over six weeks ago, on 2 May.  It was a highly anticipated publication and over recent weeks it has been further elaborated, with each sectoral package in turn being published.  These cover a wide range of areas in the EU's role, touching on agriculture, cohesion funding, the Erasmus programme, research and innovation, the EU's external actions including development aid, and much more.  The whole proposal runs to thousands of pages and it is now the subject of intensive analysis by all member states and the European Parliament.</p><p> The Oireachtas involvement has likewise begun, and I greatly appreciate this committee's engagement with the multiannual financial framework, MFF.  Given that the budget proposal by the Commission amounts to some &euro;1,135 billion and covers almost all aspects of our society and economy, it is only appropriate that a number of Oireachtas committees should offer their specific concerns and consider specific aspects of the package as they relate to their areas of responsibility.  Across all Departments, analysis is now being carried out, closely co-ordinated by the Department of Finance together with the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.  Our representatives in Brussels will also be closely involved throughout the process.  Similarly, at EU level, a wide range of European Parliament committees and ministerial councils will closely debate and negotiate a final framework to ensure that our limited resources are spent in alignment with our agreed priorities.  The General Affairs Council, GAC, which I attend, will take a horizontal approach to the MFF negotiations, with input from almost all other council formations.  At the next meeting of the GAC, in two weeks, we will have a lunch discussion with Commissioner Oettinger, the first opportunity for member states to react in the round on the basis of all the sectoral proposals which have been published since the initial document six weeks ago.</p><p> The European Council meeting at the end of the month will also have an initial discussion on the MFF and it will give guidance on the likely timeframe for the negotiations.  There are strong arguments for completing the negotiations before the European Parliament elections in May next year.  There are strong arguments as to why such difficult and complex negotiations can take time.  Either way, the Government will not be found wanting.  The important thing, whatever the timeframe, is to get it right.  While it is too early to speak in great detail, we know so far that these negotiations will be particularly challenging for Ireland.  This is the first time that we will be negotiating an EU budget without the British contribution, and it is the first time that Ireland will be a net contributor from the outset.  As our economy recovers and grows, our contribution to the EU will grow.  In recognition of the broader value of our EU membership, the Government has stated that we would consider an increased MFF contribution from Ireland to address new and emerging EU priorities and challenges that we face.  We can only do so provided that our core interests are met and European added value is ensured.  Protecting the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, remains a priority for Ireland.  We are also supportive of a range of programmes to support jobs and growth, including cohesion funding, supporting research and innovation with the Horizon 2020 budget, digital Europe and the Connecting Europe Facility.  I am very pleased to see the proposal for increased funding for a further expanded ERASMUS+ programme.  I know the Commission has suggested that we double the amount of money being spent on our young people, which we need to consider in the overall context of the budget.</p><p> I will move on to the Brexit negotiations.  We moved on to a critical phase.  All phases have been crucial but we are now entering one of the last phases of the negotiations.  As members of the committee are aware, the overall objective is that the full legal text of the withdrawal agreement, as well as a detailed political declaration on the framework for the future relationship, should be concluded by the October meeting of the European Council.  In order to meet this objective, negotiations have been continuing between the EU and the UK teams in recent weeks and will further intensify in advance of the European Council in June, in less than two weeks.  The aim of these discussions is to make significant further progress on the outstanding withdrawal issues, including on the draft protocol on Ireland and Northern Ireland, and avoiding a border on the island of Ireland.  We see the UK's presentation last week of a paper on a temporary customs arrangement, which it sees as relevant to aspects of the island of Ireland backstop, as a welcome, though incomplete, step forward.  After its publication last week, Michel Barnier, while also welcoming this step, raised questions and concerns about the proposal.  The Commission is the Union&rsquo;s negotiator with the British Government on these issues.  We have to allow the Commission to address some of the concerns which it has already raised and to further negotiations on these issues.</p><p> The Government's focus remains on the outcome we need to see, of which a key element is ensuring the protection of the Good Friday Agreement and the gains of the peace process, including avoiding a hard border on the island of Ireland.  It is welcome that the UK&rsquo;s commitment to this is reaffirmed in its proposal and that the commitments and guarantees provided by the UK in the joint progress report of December 2017 and repeated by Prime Minister May in the March Council meeting and her letter to President Tusk in March have been reiterated.  While our preference is still for an overall EU-UK relationship which would resolve all issues, it remains essential that a backstop is agreed which provides certainty that, in any circumstances, and no matter what the outcome of the negotiations on the wider EU-UK framework and future relationship, a hard border will be avoided.  We must have certainty in all scenarios on the commitments made on Ireland and Northern Ireland.  This certainty requires agreement on the protocol to the withdrawal agreement.  I therefore very much hope that there will now be further intensive negotiations and discussions between the British Government and the Commission before the European Council on 28 and 29 June.  As we have repeatedly stated, substantial progress is required by then.  We know that this week, more detailed negotiations are perhaps happening from a legal point of view and otherwise, and next week, higher level discussions between Barnier and Davis are to take place.  We will keep a watchful eye on how that progresses.</p><p> The debate on the future of Europe, which was energised by the UK's decision to leave the Union, is continuing across Europe.  This committee held its own very successful public outreach initiative and I look forward to seeing its findings when they are available.  Last November, the Taoiseach, accompanied by the T&aacute;naiste and me, launched Ireland's own national citizens' dialogue, which culminated in a major event at the Royal Hospital Kilmainham on 9 May, marking Europe Day.  I thank the Chairman for accepting our invitation to participate in the event, including as a panellist for one of the sessions.  It was very much appreciated not only by me but by all concerned.  I thank the members who attended and contributed on the day.  Between November and May, I travelled the country, covering 2,000 km getting to and from Galway, Cork, Limerick, Maynooth, Letterkenny, Navan and many other venues.  Hundreds of people turned out to our regional sessions and the level of engagement at each of them was impressive.  From the outset, we were adamant that this would essentially be a listening exercise.  To give some shape and continuity to the various dialogues, participants were encouraged to focus on the five questions posed to citizens deriving from the Bratislava Declaration, agreed by EU countries in 2016.  These centred on jobs; competitiveness and consumer rights; peace and security; better management of our natural and built environment; equality and fairness; and education and training in order to maintain the EU's competitiveness.  If there was a theme which emerged throughout these discussions, it is fairness.  People wanted to ensure fairness in an increasingly competitive world.  They want the environment to be protected so we can hand it on to future generations in a fit state.  There is also a demand for inter-generational fairness.  People want to ensure that our young people are given the best of opportunities when they start their careers and their families, and also that older people are able to enjoy their retirement in dignity and comfort.  Education at all ages and all stages in life played a key part in that discussion.</p><p> We are taking that information and compiling a report which I hope will feed into the wider consultations that are still taking place in Europe.  On 9 May next year, at a summit in Romania, EU leaders are expected to mark the culmination of this process with a renewed commitment to an EU that delivers on the issues that really matter to people.  We will be well placed at that stage to actively input into that summit based on the experiences of our national consultations.  Our consultations are over but we hope to continue our engagement with people in various different formats, so we will have a lot to input into next year's summit.</p><p><b></b>Let me now turn to the latest developments regarding EU enlargement.  Ireland is a supporter of the European perspective of the Western Balkans, and will continue to be.  I was pleased that the renewed focus on the region provided by the Bulgarian Presidency was reflected in the successful EU-Western Balkans summit on 17 May last.  At this summit, the Taoiseach and I were pleased to engage with our EU and Western Balkans counterparts across a range of issues.  In the summit declaration, the EU pledged unequivocal support for the European perspective of the Western Balkans, and the associated priority agenda set out six flagship initiatives to drive progress in the areas of rule of law, security and migration, socio-economic development, connectivity, the digital agenda, and good neighbourly relations in the Western Balkans.  It is our hope that implementation of these initiatives will lead to deeper continued engagement with the Western Balkans.<br/><br/>We believe that the European perspective of the Western Balkan countries must be a credible prospect in order to advance the stability and security of the region, and are clear that candidate countries must give the rule of law, justice and fundamental rights the utmost priority in terms of reform.  We need to encourage the Western Balkans to continue to pursue these reforms vigorously, and we, as the EU, need to give practical assistance and ensure our message is communicated effectively across the region.<br/><br/>The next discussions on enlargement will take place at the General Affairs Council on 26 June, which will review the European Commission country reports published in April and make recommendations for the coming period.  Four countries in the Western Balkans currently have EU candidate status.  They are Montenegro, Serbia, Macedonia and Albania.  Of these, both Serbia and Montenegro are well advanced in their accession negotiations, while Albania and Macedonia have not yet opened negotiations.  Ireland will support opening negotiations with Macedonia and Albania in line with the Commission's recent recommendation.  Although significant work remains to be done in both countries, we feel they have made sufficient progress to warrant opening.  Opening would also serve as a signal of EU commitment and provide motivation to the region.  The Albanian Foreign Minister, Ditmir Bushati, visited Ireland last month.<br/><br/>I said I would touch on four topics but because I know the Chairman has a meeting later today I will briefly outline just one important issue that has been preoccupying the General Affairs Council, namely the issue of the rule of law and Poland, which was discussed at the May Council and which will be discussed again in the coming weeks.  Commission Vice-President Frans Timmermans provided an update.  As the committee will know, the central issue here is the rule of law and its application in Poland.  Ours is a union based on shared values, including democracy, human rights and the rule of law.  It is essential that all these commitments be reflected clearly in the internal arrangements in all member states.<br/><br/>At the last Council meeting, the Commission informed member states that, while Poland had amended some of the changes recently introduced to the operation of the judicial system, these amendments did not address the primary concerns that have been identified by the Commission.  At the May Council, I welcomed the fact that dialogue had taken place and stressed that the dialogue should lead to an early outcome that addresses the very real concerns that have been identified.  This, I said, is clearly in all of our interests.  The Commission has now called for a hearing on the rule of law in Poland at the General Affairs Council later this month.  It is important that, in the time available, concrete proposals to address the outstanding concerns can be agreed by the Polish authorities and the Commission.<br/><br/>I understand the committee will be discussing this further with the Polish ambassador, who is to appear before the committee later this afternoon.  I wish the members well in those discussions.<br/><br/>As I said in my introduction, there are other issues I could discuss but I have taken up enough time.  I want to hand over to members to ask questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  We appreciate very much her comprehensive overview and the work she put into it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for that very comprehensive address.  The entire committee is grateful, as always, for the level of engagement she and her officials have had with it over her time in office.  It has been an interesting time, to say the least.</p> <p>  I will touch on all five key issues the Minister of State raised and work backwards.  On Poland, I agree absolutely that we need to protect the European values.  We must emphasise increased dialogue between the Polish authorities and the EU authorities over the coming weeks and months to ensure that when one signs up to the European Union one respects its rules.  A state has the ability to make the rules of the European Union but once it joins, it must implement them.</p> <p>  With regard to the multi-annual financial framework, we had, as Minister of State noted, a good discussion with the relevant Commission budget official yesterday.  I acknowledge the great challenge facing the Union as whole with the United Kingdom leaving and Ireland's position.  We need, however, to increase our commitment to the European Union.  It is actually a healthy reflection of the state of our economy and country that we are net contributors and that we will be required to increase our contribution.  We have received wholesale solidarity over recent years from the other 26 member states who are to remain in the Union, particularly regarding Brexit.  It is also important that we show that solidarity in turn.  I must agree, unfortunately, with the statement of our Minister for Finance, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, that Ireland is not of a mind to contribute more to security and defence expenditure.  That is a matter we must examine.  The threats on the borders of our friends in Estonia, Greece and other countries are equally our threats if we truly believe in European solidarity.  I respectfully ask the Minister of State to bring this back into the discussions.</p> <p>  With regard to enlargement, I really welcome the agreement made by the Greek and Macedonian Governments on the name change, which will be put to the Macedonian people in a referendum.  Macedonia is a country I visited a number of times.  In a previous life, I was on the consultative committee on Macedonian accession.  There is considerable potential in this regard.  I truly believe in an ever wider and deeper European Union.  We need to examine the positives of enlargement but we must also examine the status of our candidate countries and make sure that we set down the Copenhagen criteria.  We require great sacrifices and changes but we also need to be returning the compliment.  We need to show there is a material benefit in order to make sure the pro-European sentiment remains in the countries in question and so we do not witness the kind of frustration that can arise among people who are waiting indefinitely to try to join the Union.</p> <p>  Ultimately, with regard to the future of Europe project, I absolutely commend the efforts of the Minister of State in traipsing around the country over recent months.  The level of engagement between the Minister of State and European Movement Ireland at the civic dialogues was breathtaking.  It was fantastic to see crowds in places such as Letterkenny and beyond.  Huge crowds engaged with major questions.  To see the relevance of the European project in Irish people's lives now is phenomenal and reassuring.  Does the Department have a timeline for issuing the report on the future of Europe?</p> <p>  With regard to Brexit, I must consult a different page of notes, if the Minister of State does not mind.  Could she outline the process we can expect before the key Council meetings on 26 June and 28 June and the activities involving the EU negotiating team and its meetings with its British counterparts?  Irish officials were brought into various discussions in April.  Could the Minister of State outline where Irish Government officials may be required to have an input?</p> <p>  With regard to the paper produced by the UK Government last week, I agree it is absolutely incomplete.  It is not enough.  It does not respond to the political agreement of December or the repetition of that agreement by Prime Minister May in March, nor does it really acknowledge the European legal interpretation of those agreements.  Therefore, I welcome Commissioner Barnier's swift response and commitment to examining this.  I have been blown away by the solidarity on a European level.  It is such that we can hold a united, uniform position involving 27 sovereign governments, ranging from the far left to the far right.  It is very reassuring as an Irishman who is phenomenally pro-European.  It is also reflective of the European position by comparison with the British position, possibly.  A number of people have suggested that when we receive the paper, we should pause the negotiations.  I believe we need to do the exact opposite.  In the coming two weeks, we should intensify negotiations and really get the European and British teams get down to it and work towards a common path that will ultimately lead to what I hope will be a withdrawal agreement in October.  It will not be a good deal; there is no good deal.  Brexit will be bad.  This is a process of damage limitation and we need to engage in that process and try to limit the damage, not just for the rest of the European Union but also for Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#C00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Helen McEntee, and her officials.  I also welcome the ambassadors and embassy staff to the meeting.  It is important that we have dialogue with other EU member states to get an idea as to what is happening.  Naturally, Brexit is our greatest challenge since the foundation of the State.  There is general recognition that the restoration of the 500-km Border is not a practical proposal so it will not be supported by the Irish Republic or the United Kingdom, nor will it be maintained by the European Union.  Even if there were a will to staff it, there would be immense difficulties, to say the least.  It would not be acceptable to either side.</p><p>They would not be allowed to man such a border.</p><p> We are an island beyond an island so what options will we face?  The Government must be prepared to look outside the box and see exactly what is practical.  I am a former Minister of State with responsibility for trade and I was given responsibility by a former Taoiseach, Mr. Haughey, relating to the Single European Act.  I appreciate everything is possible within these negotiations and compromises can be made.  We should nevertheless look at the possibility of an economic zone within the European Union containing the United Kingdom and Ireland, both North and South.  This would guarantee the future of trade, unimpeded, between both islands.  That is absolutely vital to the interests of both islands.  All trade from the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland going outside that zone would be subject to whatever levies are agreed at the time and, naturally, the Republic would be part of the European Union and have the appropriate exemptions.</p><p> It is time for unique thinking in this.  We should look at the possibility that because we are in a such a difficult position compared with any other of the remaining 26 countries, we are unique.  In those circumstances, the Government must look at a different arrangement.  It should consider all possibilities.  What is in the best interests of this country and the United Kingdom?  We share the UK's interests and a good deal for the United Kingdom is a good deal for Ireland.  I also believe that unless there is a good deal for Ireland, we should do everything we can, whether that is vetoing the deal if it is not in our interest or negotiating it as far as possible.  I know our officials are in Brussels working hard; I also know the Government and the Minister are working hard.  We must absolutely state that Britain's removal from the European Union should not have a detrimental effect on Ireland.  It is my wish and I know it is the wish of most people.  It is a view shared by most of our friends at the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly in Sligo at the weekend who were very anxious for a deal to be made in the best interests of both countries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her comprehensive overview of the issue.  I will follow Senator Leyden's comments on Brexit, which is the biggest question facing us.  The UK's presentation last week was not anything like a full deal but in speaking about a customs arrangement, it was a stumble in the right direction.  Following what I heard from Senator Leyden in Sligo at the plenary meeting over the weekend, there is a slight movement now among British politicians on both sides of the divide on an overall preference for EU-UK relationship.  That will eliminate the need for a backstop.</p> <p>  In light of the votes in the House of Commons yesterday, and, more pertinently, the assurances given to the group of at least politicians led by Mr. Dominic Grieve, a Conservative MP, and which are being sought in writing, how does the Minister of State feel about the current state of play?  She is closer to the process.  What is happening with the negotiations involving the teams led by Mr. Barnier and Mr. Davis, which are ongoing and probably pretty intensive?  I am interested to hear the Minister of State's comments in that regard.  I very much welcome what Senator Richmond has said in that there is such a unified approach.  That must give us hope and encouragement that matters will resolve at the finish.  Will the Minister of State comment on what she thinks will come from this June summit?  I presume it will allow matters to go on further and be dealt with finally and satisfactorily in October.  I look forward to hearing her comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#D00300"><p>Before going to Deputy Durkan, I apologise for Deputy Frank O'Rourke, who had to leave to chair another meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and her colleagues to the meeting.  I compliment her, her ministerial colleague and the Taoiseach on the tremendous stance they have taken and work done relating to Brexit in particular.  I will speak to the other issues in a moment.  I worry sometimes when I hear comments from negotiators on the British side resembling jingoism in the oldest form.  Reference was made by an individual in the past week to &quot;the enemy&quot; but we are not in a war situation yet.  If we allow ourselves to go down that road, we will eventually talk ourselves into it.  I refer specifically to the European Union.</p><p>There is much more at stake here than the UK and Brexit.  It is a brick in the wall and it could be the first brick to come loose.  The European Union has an obligation and duty to its member states to ensure the Union stands firm.  The EU did not decide that some member states should leave.  A member state decided to leave by itself on the basis of misinformation given by public representatives.  The information was erroneous and grossly misleading.  One member of the European Parliament spent 18 years undermining the European Union and its concept.  The only thing offered at the end of the day was nothing at all.  There were going to be benefits for everybody in the UK but there was nothing tangible when it came down to it.</p><p>European Union negotiators, including Mr. Barnier and his colleagues, should be complimented on the way they have handled this.  They are negotiating with us and on our behalf, so we must be very careful not to undermine them.  If we undermine them it would be an indication to UK authorities that all is not well and we are not all united.  In one fell swoop, the European Union could disintegrate.  That is what will happen.  If one brick is taken from the wall, it will come down.  There are people who want to hark back to older and better times, and so on, and I am not certain to what times they refer.  I am not sure if they refer to the empire that ruled before or the communist regimes of the past.  Do they prefer war when the last world war cost the lives of approximately 60 million people?  I do not know what some people are referring to when they are so determined to roll back the carpet.  We must be extremely careful and the Irish Government and European Union have adopted the most fortuitous position that could be found.  It is the only workable position, and deviation from it will lead to disaster.</p><p>It should be remembered that very little reference has been made by UK authorities to the fact that the Good Friday Agreement is an international peace agreement, signed, accepted and contributed to by the international community, including the EU and the United States.  All of a sudden it seems to be no longer relevant and is being pushed away.  We must be careful in the negotiations of compromises and what they might mean.  In the normal course of events it might be that compromises take place in negotiations but any compromise by the EU will be fatal.</p><p>I will very quickly go through other points, including enlargement.  I totally agree with the process and it is important that the western Balkans, a tinder box in the past, come under the strong influence of the European Union.  That includes compliance with the <i>acquis communitaire </i>and the regulations, as has been referred to with respect to the operation of the European Union.  In some countries there is a tendency to move independently of the European Union but membership entails compliance with the rules that prevail within the Union.  That is for a very good reason and the benefit of all, so no country can break out and make its own unilateral decisions for its own benefit, now or in the future.</p><p> I forgot to mention one thing on Brexit.  No country, however big or small, can be allowed to move away from the Union and improve its status as a result.  The Union would be finished then.  If one country breaks out and decides to get a better deal - for strategic, geographic or whatever reason - the Union is gone.  It cannot prevail in those circumstances.  We would be back to where we were in the "good old days", to which some people keep referring.  That is an appalling prospect.  I could spend time on other issues but I will not.  </p><p> We have all mentioned the peace process and the importance of ensuring the Union prevails.  The biggest single process in the history of Europe and the globe was the European Union itself.  It came together from the ashes of utter and total destruction when man's inhumanity to man saw new depths and the most appalling atrocities were accepted without demur.  We found out about them only afterwards.  Many people at the time, however, knew what was going on.  We need to learn from that.  It was a very bitter and costly experience.  If there are those who think there are advantages in harking back to that era, or something like it, they are wrong.  We do not need a war to prove that nor do we need the fragmentation of the European Union.  It has worked extremely well for the past 50 years and is capable of doing that into the future for as long as it takes.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#E00200"><p>I thank Deputy Durkan.  From my own point of view, we know the Government and the Departments are going through the details but does the Minister of State have any initial impression or is it fair to ask whether Ireland can support the European Commission's proposal on the future budget?  I am thinking of the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, in particular, following on from yesterday's meeting where we heard an outline of that.  From a constituency perspective, we are dealing with people worried about the future budget for CAP and what that will mean for our people on the ground and our farming community.  I often deal with people in that sector.  They are worried about the future for young farmers.  There is a drive on - I acknowledge work in this regard by the Commissioner - towards making it more attractive for a transition from the present generation of farmers to the newer generation.</p> <p>  As the Minister of State knows herself, farming in future will not be sustainable, unless the farm is large and has full time employment for any young man or woman wishing to take over a family farm.  I am worried and fearful for what future budgets are going to mean for transitions on what I call the family farm.  In the past, different schemes were available as incentives for farmers.  They were helpful because people, before they got older, were able to see the financial sense in transferring over to the younger generation.  Schemes such as the young farmers installation grants were helpful.  I would like to hear the Minister of State's view on this.  Also on Brexit-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#E00300"><p>If I can interrupt briefly, a vote is being called.  Can I be excused?  I ask the Minister of State to forgive me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#E00400"><p>That is not a problem and I thank Senator Coghlan for his participation.  To return to the issue of Brexit, does the Minister of State think a deal will be struck by the time the European Council meets in June?  If it goes on beyond that, will there be enough time?  Have the chances increased of no deal being reached?  We are all worried about what is happening across the water.  It seems they are riding rudderless.   Things seem to be out of control for some time.  There was a bit of saving grace yesterday but there seems to be a lack of coherency.  I know one thing.  If it was our Government allowing things to carry on the way that things have been allowed to do so across the water, it would not be tolerated by the Government or by the Opposition.  We have our act together better than those across the way.  I am interested in the Minister of State's views on that.  I thank her again for taking the questions from our members.  We appreciate it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#E00500"><p>I thank the Chair.  I will come back with responses and the members can read them later.  I will address Senator Neale Richmond's comments first.  The increased commitment to the MFF does not identify what we are talking about in respect of that commitment and where that funding will go.  The overall negotiations are only starting to take place.  Senator Richmond's suggestions on increased security and defence will be fed back in and I will make sure the Minister hears them.</p> <p>  I agree with the Senator on the status of the candidate countries from the western Balkans.  We need to support them as much as we can.  They have obligations to fulfil on the reform of the rule of law, justice and fundamental rights in their own countries.  We need to make sure we are extending the European hand of friendship and supporting them in all those areas.  The more visits we can make and the greater the presence we can have, at a European level, in those countries, the more beneficial it will be.  On the timeline for the publication of the future of Europe report, we hope to have it published by the end of this summer.  We will ensure that all the members of the committee receive the published report and afterwards, if needs be, we could discuss it here if any of the members want to go through it.  </p> <p>  Senator Richmond also asked about the process between now and the June summit, and in particular the negotiations and discussions taking place following the publication of the document by the UK Government last week.  A further round of intensive discussions and negotiations is considering some of the legal aspects.  The legal team is looking at the document, how feasible elements of it are and whether it is a basis for further discussions and negotiations.  That will then feed into the fifth round of negotiations between Mr. Michel Barnier and the EU task force and Mr. David Davis and the UK Government.  That will be the fifth of five.  The last one was last week.  </p> <p>  A question was also asked about the Irish involvement leading into the summit.  Our officials, here in Ireland, in Brussels and throughout Europe, are engaging daily with the EU task force.  Any information needed on the Irish issue or protocol is, of course, fed into that process.  Mr. Michel Barnier and Mr. Jean-Claude Juncker will visit Ireland next week.  They will make known their thoughts and sentiments on the discussions to date on the proposal paper published last week.  We will have in-depth discussions on that and we will make known our comments in the summit the week after.  </p> <p>  Senator Richmond raised the fact that there are a number of concerns on the customs document.  Mr. Barnier was very clear, when it was published last week, that three questions needed to be addressed. First, is it an operational text and will it ensure there is no hard Border on the island of Ireland.  The answer to that is "no" because it is only one part of the Irish protocol - regulatory alignment is another key part of it.  It is, however, an element of it, so we have to welcome that part.  Does it impact on the integrity of the Single Market and the customs union is the second question.  Questions on that, and the more technical detail, have been asked this week.  The final question is on whether it is an all weather solution and will it work in all circumstances.  Concerns were raised because of suggestions of a 2021 date mentioned in the document.  A backstop for us is what it says it is.  It is there unless and until another solution is found.  We and the EU task force have been very clear on that.  We have to allow continued discussions and negotiations on the document to happen.</p> <p>  A question was asked as well on a pause in the negotiations.  We do not see that happening.  It would only further jeopardise the process and the likelihood of us reaching an agreement by October.  Instead of pausing it, we need to increase and intensify the discussions and negotiations in as much as we can.  Senator Leyden suggested we need to think outside of the box.  I agree.</p><p> On the idea of a specific economic zone for just Ireland and the UK, it would essentially suggest Ireland also leaving the EU if we were to have in place a different system or measure from the rest of Europe.  The most recent survey undertaken shows that 92% of Irish people want to remain within the European Union, so I would not agree with any suggestion that we be in any way separate or different.  We have a huge amount in common with the UK, not just in terms of trade but also historically and in the links between our people.  There is &euro;65 billion worth of trade between Ireland and the UK overall.  However, this represents between 16% and 17% of our trade, although that percentage is much higher for agriculture.  The EU represents 35% of our overall trade.  While we are very much focused on getting the best outcome with the UK, that will be achieved through the wider EU-UK future relationship.  Separate from the backstop, we are focusing our energy to make sure we have as close and comprehensive as possible future relationship between the EU as a whole and the UK.  I agree that we would want there to be as little disruption as possible to the lives and livelihoods of our Irish citizens.  That is our key priority.</p><p> Senator Coghlan raised the issue of the votes in the House of Commons yesterday.  While I do not want to get into internal UK politics, the votes are still being discussed and there have been a number of amendments.  It is very clear that come what may, whatever result we have in terms of an overall agreement on the withdrawal Bill, come October the House of Commons will have a part to play in the overall agreement of the deal that is reached.  We also know, however, that other member states will have to bring back any deal to their own Governments for ratification.  We want to ensure this happens by October so that other countries have an opportunity to ratify the agreement in their own individual Parliaments.  </p><p> Deputy Durkan raised the issue of supporting Monsieur Barnier.  I fully agree.  At every General Affairs Council we have attended, Ireland and the other 26 member states have fully endorsed the manner in which he and his negotiating and task force team have been carrying out the negotiations and this support will continue.  He made it very clear that no country can be better off outside of the EU than it was when it was inside it.  A number of outlines have been made in respect of ensuring that the Single Market's four freedoms of movement are upheld, particularly in terms of the customs union.  It is clear there can be nothing that interrupts the integrity of either of those and that is our position also.  </p><p> The Deputy is absolutely right that the EU is the best example of a peace process that we can see anywhere in the world.  While the EU is not expressly mentioned very often in the document of the Good Friday Agreement, the EU membership of Ireland and the UK, and hence Ireland North and South, has through our membership of the Single Market and customs union removed those physical barriers and infrastructure.  Our EU membership has thus played a key part in bringing about the peace process and has allowed people to go about their lives as they have for the past 20 years.</p><p> The Chairman made some remarks on the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP.  We are in the very early stages.  Various sectors have been publishing their initial reports on it over the past six weeks.  There is still a lot of discussion to be had on the CAP.  The Minister, Deputy Creed has met a number of his counterparts from Spain, France, Portugal, Greece and Finland to suggest that the proposed 5% cut should not happen and that we should essentially have the same budget as the last time.  That is why we are saying we are willing to pay more money.  However, we want to see that our key concerns and priorities around the CAP, cohesion, research and innovation and investment are upheld as well.  The discussions will be going on for some time.  We will give our initial reaction in the next two weeks at the General Affairs Council.  We will do everything in our power to make sure our key concerns, particularly the CAP budget, will be addressed and we will make every effort to ensure that budget is impacted as little as possible.</p><p> By the June European Council we have said we want to see as much significant progress as possible.  If we do not see it, the idea of reaching an agreement in October will be in jeopardy.  While we have had an additional proposal on the customs element of the backstop, we would very much like to see additional progress on the regulatory alignment piece of the backstop, which is in a sense bigger than the customs element as a key part of ensuring we have no border on the island of Ireland.  We have two weeks left.  Intensive discussions are happening this week and a further round of negotiations is taking place next week.  We will then have a greater sense of whether anything else will be proposed by the UK Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#F00200"><p>It is very important that I clarify something.  I am speaking in my own capacity as a Member of the Oireachtas and one of its longest serving Members.  I am floating these ideas at this stage to at least get people to think.  I floated them in Sligo at the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly and there was a tremendous response from all sides.  All who were there felt there was some merit in looking at this.  It is like the regulatory arrangement about which the Minister of State is talking.  That is a special arrangement.  I am not advocating in any way that Ireland be a lesser member of the European Union after Brexit takes place.  We must consolidate our position but we must recognise that we make up about 1% of the population of the EU.  The effect on us as an island off an island is unique within the European Union.  The Good Friday Agreement, as mentioned by my colleague, is unique within the EU and was endorsed by it and the United Nations.  There are cross-border operations in place which must continue after Brexit.  I am talking about joined tourism, fisheries and all those issues.  They are unique and cannot be scrapped after the UK leaves, if it actually leaves.  That is not certain yet.  Those bodies will still continue and will have to be recognised by the EU and will have to continue in place.</p> <p>  I understand the unionists' point of view that they will not accept a border on the Irish Sea.  The border between the United Kingdom and Europe will be across the Channel.  I can understand their worries in that regard but other than that, they want to see the continuation of trade between North and South.  This is a unique situation.  I am saying to the Minister of State's officials here and in Brussels that they should be prepared to think outside the box.  From my experience as a Minister of State with responsibility for trade, when we and the UK put forward proposals, they were supported by our colleagues in the European Union.  We never had a vote when we negotiated the Single European Act and the representative at that stage was John Redwood, MP, who is now a Brexiteer - but that is another day's work.</p> <p>  I am throwing out this as a point of debate today.  I ask the Minister of State to at least consider these issues as a possible last resort solution.  The Minister of State must not feel that Monsieur Barnier and the European Union will reject unique situations in the context of Ireland's unique position.  We would be in great jeopardy if there was any danger of a hard border or a breakdown in trade between Ireland the UK.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#F00300"><p>I thank the Senator for his comments.  Michel Barnier, the task force and the 26 other member states have already recognised that Northern Ireland is a unique scenario.  That is why we have the Irish protocol.  It is why the Irish issue was one of the three key issues in phase one and continues to be one of the key issues being discussed.  It will be probably the main issue for discussion at the June European Council in terms of the overall Brexit discussion.</p> <p>  As the Senator has pointed out, there are indeed many areas of co-operation North and South, including electricity, tourism, health and agriculture.  At least 142 such areas have been already identified by the UK Government itself.  That is very much part of the Irish protocol and it is what we are working towards.</p><p>The task force has been very clear that the backstop and the unique scenario for Northern Ireland cannot be applied to a whole-of-UK position.  This is one of the concerns that was raised when it was suggested that customs proposal could apply to the UK as a whole, including Northern Ireland, but as a temporary backstop measure.  We have consistently said that the backstop would be specific to Northern Ireland and that business would not have to change rules and regulations more than once.  The transition is there to ensure it has the time to adapt if it was then, as a whole, to have to change.</p><p> Essentially, we are talking about the future relationship and obviously the backstop is very separate from the future relationship.  In terms of Ireland and the UK having the best relationship possible into the future and Ireland getting the best outcome out of this because, while North-South is important, east-west is equally important and that will have to be dealt with.  We have to work to the best possible outcome of a future relationship between the UK and the EU as a whole.  Obviously that is our priority in terms of dealing with the Border issue and protecting the Good Friday Agreement, but we must have the backstop separate from that to ensure our interests are protected.  In that regard, it cannot apply as a whole to the UK; it must be specific to Northern Ireland.  We will obviously work to ensure that what was agreed before Christmas in the December joint report is translated in full into a legally operational text that will apply and that will be part of the withdrawal agreement in October.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#G00200"><p>The problem is that the DUP will not accept that.  It has ten Members of the House of Commons and they will veto any deal that proposes that.  We need to be realistic about this.  This would bring down the British Government, if they proceed with this alone.  The Minister of State can believe me; the DUP will bring down the British Government on this issue.  Let us be quite clear about it.  I met them in Sligo and I know their feelings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#G00300"><p>We also need to be cautious not to show weakness in our negotiating position.  If we are seen to waiver in any way in our negotiating position, negotiated by the European Union on our behalf, then we are lost because that then becomes the starting point and then there will follow a series of compromises.  That is not the way those negotiations should take place.</p> <p>  A country decided to leave the European Union of its own accord.  It has been repeatedly stated that Brexit means Brexit, regardless of what anybody else thinks.  That is fine, but there are consequences arising from that for the country leaving as well.  There obviously will be consequences for the countries remaining.</p> <p>  I have a different attitude to the vote in the UK House of Commons yesterday.  I think it shows a weakness in its government and its opposition.  There is no alternative.  There is only one show in town, which worries me.  Brexit means Brexit and so they are going anyway.  If others want to follow, they can do so.  That is what it means.</p> <p>  We are at a very precarious point.  We need to hold our nerve.  We need to fix our vision firmly on the interests of our European Union, uphold the principles in that and not deviate from it.  If we do, we will be the weak part.  We will become an appendage of the UK, which will be a dangerous place to be.  They will be speaking for us because they are going.  We need to be cautious about it.  I had hoped at this stage that we would have seen the emergence of a stronger pro-European sentiment within the UK, but that has not happened and it will not happen.</p> <p>  If it happens the other way, it follows on that the UK goes.  However, the British cannot dislodge the fundamentals of the European Union on their way out.  They cannot destroy the European Union on their way out.  They cannot reform it in such a way as to make it unworkable.  They cannot create an option for others to follow that will entitle them to envisage an improvement arising from being outside the European Union.  In other words, as the saying goes a house divided within itself cannot stand.</p> <p>  Based on my reading of European history, we are in a very precarious position.  Of most concern to me is that the UK authorities seem to be hell-bent on going in this direction.  They treat the debate as if they were releasing themselves from oppression.  When we listen carefully to the dialogue, we pick up many warnings that we need to keep in mind.  In the course of negotiations, there is only one place we can be.</p> <p>  The UK never took ownership of the European Union.  It never regarded the European Union as being part of its territory - politically, socially or economically.  It was always a them-and-us situation.  If the European Union member states wish to go about it in that fashion, they could all decide at some stage to go back to the old days when they were much better.  Were they much better then?  That is salutary thought for us all.  I strongly urge us all to recognise where we would be heading, if we went down that road. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#G00400"><p>Did the Minister of State get a chance to digest that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#G00500"><p>Ireland's future is very much at the heart of Europe.  Europe is very much at the heart of Irish citizens' future and that will not change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#G00600"><p>I think we should send out Deputy Durkan as well.  He might help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1319" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="14:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2018061300002#G00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State and her officials.  We appreciate that she has some very important meetings over the coming weeks.  The committee is not 90% or 95%, but 100% behind her in the work she is doing.  We are all flying the same flag on this issue and we are very supportive of her and the people working with her.  I wish her the best of luck with everything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.189" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.07 p.m. and resumed in private session at 3.19 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.190" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 4.12 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Wednesday, 4 July 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.191" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" url="">Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.192" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 16:40</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy John Halligan (Minister of State at the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation), Deputy Tom Neville, Deputy Billy Kelleher, Deputy Maurice Quinlivan. Deputy James Lawless,</p><p>DEPUTY MARY BUTLER IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.193" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#A00100">Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Bill 2018: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B00200"><p>The purpose of this meeting is to consider the Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Bill 2018, which was referred to the committee by order of the D&aacute;il on 8 April 2018.</p> <p>  I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Halligan, and his officials.  Three amendments have been tabled.  It is intended to conclude Committee Stage today.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  I refer members to the list of amendments groupings for debate, which has been circulated.  We will proceed to consideration of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.195" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 26, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.196" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>SECTION 27</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B00500"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 21, line 41, to delete &ldquo;thereof).&rdquo;.&rdquo; and substitute the following:<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;thereof).<br /><br />(4B) (a) It is not an infringement of the rights conferred by this Act if a Board or authority to which this section applies reproduces any work that is made available in the State through the internet.<br /><br />(b) Where any work has been made available in the State through the internet without a restriction as to its access or use, then it is not an infringement of the rights conferred by this Act if a Board or authority to which this section applies reproduces that work and makes it available through the internet without a restriction as to its access or use, whether or not that work continues to be available elsewhere through the internet.<br /><br />(c) For the purposes of this subsection, a work shall have been made available in the State through the internet where&mdash;<blockquote>(i) it is made available to the public either from a website with a domain name which relates to the State or to a place within the State, or by similar or related means, or<br /><br />(ii) it is made available to the public either by a person any of whose activities relating to the creation or the publication of the digital publication takes place within the State, or by a person with similar or related connections to the State.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>I will outline the intention behind the amendment.  The Bill is welcome and we support it in the main.  The purpose of this amendment is to address a lacuna.  Certain web content may not have been available to preserve a historical registry of the <i>.ie</i>domain name content.  A web archive is like any other kind of archive such as a library or copyright.  We took advice from people like Professor Eoin O'Dell in Trinity, who is the foremost expert in this area, a constitutional expert and an intellectual property expert.  His advice is that this measure is needed to strengthen the provisions.  Essentially, the idea is to ensure that Internet content is treated in the same way as any other content for copyright purposes, such as content in a library or any other schedule.</p><p>That is the intention.  It is put forward in good faith and comes from academic authority.  I am interested in hearing the views of the Minister of State.  I am always interested in hearing different views.  If there are concerns about it, I am open to hearing them.Deputy Quinlivan may also wish to comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B00600"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B00700"><p>Is Deputy Quinlivan happy with that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B00800"><p>Deputy Lawless has covered it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B00900"><p>I am pleased to bring the Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Bill 2018 before the committee and I thank it for the opportunity to do so.  I have brought a number of Bills through the Houses but this is the most technical and detailed legislation with which I have had to deal.  It is necessary to update and modernise the copyright regime in Ireland.  I thank the representatives of all parties who were constructive and who, in general, support the Bill.</p><p>I will comment on the amendment put forward by Deputy Lawless and Deputy Quinlivan.  I have listened to the rationale.  I will explain why I do not propose to accept it.  I spoke to the Chairman about the matter earlier.  The amendment proposes the inclusion of a section that will permit a deposit institution, in other words, a board or authority, to reproduce any work made available in the State through the Internet - if the website is not paywall-protected or password-protected - without infringing the copyright of that work.  Essentially, the amendment is to provide for a full digital deposit system that would facilitate the recording and making available of websites with Irish domain names, the <i>.ie</i>domain, that are not currently archived.  Such action has been referred to as capturing or preserving the web.</p><p>In the first instance, the problem we have is that this is a matter for the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, which is responsible for policy is this area.  That makes matters a little difficult for my Department.  The Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht is currently undertaking a detailed and extensive examination and analysis of the proposal, after which it may then be presented to Government to seek approval to pursue this policy change.  Such a change would include all necessary legislative amendments and seek Exchequer funding for the purpose proposed.</p><p>The Department and I understand the desire of the Deputies to capture the web for preservation purposes.  However, it is essential that sufficient time is allocated to conduct the appropriate level of analysis and consider the potential impact such a proposal may have on the rights of right-holders.</p><p>I will cut to the chase.  The difficulty we have is that if we were to go back and include this amendment and go through all the details of including the amendment, it would possibly set back the Bill.  It could delay the 11 October deadline and delay all 28 member states from ratifying the treaty.  Sections 24 and 26 include several changes in this regard.  I could go through a great deal on the matter but basically this will go back to the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, which is responsible for policy in this area.  It is out of my remit and the remit of my Department.  It was considered by my Department as part of Professor O'Dell's report in 2013.  That is where we stand in terms of the amendment.</p><p>I could easily say to the Deputies that I am not accepting the amendment but I do not want to go down that road.  I hope the Deputies will not call for a vote on it.  We should let it go to the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, which is responsible for policy in this area and see where it lies.  If we include the substantive provision, we would have to go through a legal process.  We would have a great deal to do and that would set us back months.  That is the position of the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B01000"><p>If the amendment is withdrawn, will the matter be referred back to the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht?  Will the amendment come back before the House on Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B01100"><p>If the amendment is withdrawn, we can get further clarification on the matter.  Is that reasonable?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B01200"><p>We could also submit the amendment - or a version of it - again on Report Stage.  Is that the case?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#B01300"><p>I do not know the technicalities of the matter.  I think the Deputy can probably do it in the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00200"><p>He can.  As the matter has now been flagged under section 27, the amendment can be retabled on Report Stage.  The Deputy can raise it, but the amendment does not have to be accepted on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00300"><p>We can definitely resubmit it however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00400"><p>The Deputy can do so because he has raised the matter under the section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00500"><p>Has the Chairman anticipated roughly when Report Stage might be taken?  I will not hold her to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00600"><p>According to what I have been told, Report Stage may be ordered at short notice.  It is, therefore, recommended that amendments be submitted to the Bills Office as soon as possible.  It is hoped to get the Bill through before the recess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00700"><p>Obviously, the amendment will be scrutinised to make sure it will go through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00800"><p>As the matter has now been addressed under section 27, the amendment can be retabled on Report Stage and debated on the floor of the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C00900"><p>The Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht is actively working on the proposal and my Department is working with it.  We are open to a technical Bill being brought forward in the autumn, which is a reasonable suggestion.  I have examined the amendment in detail and there are elements which are reasonable proposals.  If the Deputy has further specific queries in respect of it, we can provide a briefing in advance of Report Stage, if desired.  That is very reasonable.  Is the Deputy be okay with that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01100"><p>I accept the Minister of State's rationale and bona fides, but I have a couple of observations to make.  The fact that something might impact on EU directives or regulations is not really a sufficient or good reason for us not to do it because our job, as legislators, is to scrutinise, challenge and produce the best case possible.  Sometimes we can lead the European Union and do not have to accept its lead.  The Minister of State has said there is work under way within his Department and others to analyse the position and perhaps come back with a better way of doing things.  I am absolutely open to that approach and look forward to hearing the response.  I am a little confused about the timelines because I have heard two dates being mentioned - October and before the recess.  The Minister of State has mentioned that this has to be done by late October, but we are also hearing that there is a rush to get the legislation through before the recess.  Perhaps the position might be clarified.  It is an important objective and the amendment would do something important which we still need to do.  However, if there is another way to do it, on which either the Minister of State's Department or another Department could come back to us, I look forward to engaging on it.  I ask the Minister of State's Department or the relevant Department to engage with me and Deputy Maurice Quinlivan, perhaps even offline, and we can work something out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01200"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01300"><p>On that basis. I am prepared to withdraw the amendment, while reserving the right to reintroduce it on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01400"><p>That is appreciated.  I know that the Deputy is very reasonable on all issues.  What I should have said is there are legal, governance, regulatory and financial issues relevant to the proposal which, again, really set it back by months.  Members of my Department absolutely will be delighted to sit down with the Deputy to see where we can push forward on the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01500"><p>The proposal came from Dr. Eoin O'Dell of Trinity College Dublin.  As somebody who came of age in the digital age, I remember being in Trinity College Dublin in the late 1990s when the web was a shadow of what it is now.  It was a couple of blue screens and Linux logins, from which it is now worlds apart.  It is important that we do not lose sight of that in the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01600"><p>I thank the Deputies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01700"><p>Is Deputy Maurice Quinlivan also prepared to withdraw the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01800"><p>We will withdraw it while reserving the right to reintroduce in on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C01900"><p>Absolutely.  That is accepted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C02000"><p>We will do so based on what the Minister of State has said.  I thank him for his co-operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.225" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.226" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Section 27 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.227" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Sections 28 to 39, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.228" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>SECTION 40</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C02500"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C02600"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 30, to delete lines 11 and 12 and substitute the following:&ldquo;(d) in section 127&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in subsection (1), by the insertion of &ldquo;and shall, subject to section 127A, also be capable of being treated as an application for a patent under Part II&rdquo; after &ldquo;European patent designating the State&rdquo;,<br /><br />(ii) in subsection (5), by the insertion of &ldquo;designates the European Patent Office and&rdquo; after &ldquo;which&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(iii) in subsection (6), by the insertion of &ldquo;designates the European Patent Office and&rdquo; after &ldquo;which&rdquo;,<br /><br />and&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>As these two technical amendments to the Patents Act 1992 are interlinked, I welcome the opportunity to address them together.  Amendment No. 3 inserts a revised version of section 127A into the Patents Act.  The purpose of section 127A is to open the national route for patent co-operation treaty, PCT, applications by allowing current patent applicants to choose to convert an international patent application into a national patent application.  Applicants may choose to do so for a number of reasons.  During the international applications process which usually takes approximately 31 months to complete applicants may discover that an international patent is not suitable.  This may be due to the high costs involved, the patent not being commercially viable, protection in international markets no longer being necessary or the results of the search report and written opinion precluding the patent from being granted in certain countries.  Section 127A facilitates the opening up of the national route for PCT applications which will provide an additional choice for applicants which has not been available up to now.</p><p>The differences between the revised section 127A and the version included in the Bill, as published, are a new section 127A(1) and a revised section 127A(2)(d).  The new section 127A(1) allows the controller to assign the all-important patent filing date where an international PCT application has been refused a filing date owing to an error or omission by the international patenting organisation.  The national patent application can then be accepted and processed in the normal way on the basis of this filing date.</p><p>Following publication of the Bill, users of the PCT route suggested an additional instance in which a PCT patent applicant might opt for a national as opposed to an international patent.  The revised section 127A(2)(d) takes this on board.  Under this provision, a PCT patent applicant may at any time within a 31 month period apply to the controller for that application to be treated as a national application, while the PCT application could be pursued separately.  For example, the applicant may want a national patent for the purpose of securing an investment opportunity or to pursue infringement proceedings.  Recognising the merit of the users' proposal, I am happy to be able to facilitate the proposal by way of the amendment. </p><p>Section 127 of the Patents Act provides for the handling of international patent applications.Amendment No. 2 contains three technical amendments to section 127 that are consequential on amendment No. 3.  The amendments take into account that an international application designating the European Patent Office may also be treated as a national patent application under section 127A 2(d).  I know that this all sounds exceptionally technical, but if the committee requires any further information or a breakdown of the detail, we can supply it to members of the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C02700"><p>I will take the Minister of State's word for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C02800"><p>The Deputy need not worry; we will do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C02900"><p>The Minister of State is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.234" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#C03300"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 30, to delete lines 14 to 42, and in page 31, to delete lines 1 to 13 and substitute the following:<b>&ldquo; &ldquo;Circumstances in which international application for patent designating State shall be treated as application for patent under Part II</b><br /><br /><b>127A.</b>(1) If an international application for a patent which designates the State is refused a filing date under the Treaty and following a request made in the prescribed manner and within the prescribed period, the Controller determines that the refusal was caused by an error or omission in an institution having functions under the Treaty, he may direct that the application shall be treated as an application under Part II, having such date of filing as he may direct.<br /><br />(2) Subject to compliance with the prescribed conditions, an international application for a patent which designates the State shall be treated as an application under Part II if&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the applicant withdraws the international application at any time prior to the expiration of 31 months from the filing date or the priority date of the application, whichever is the earlier, and the international processing procedures in the international phase are discontinued,<br /><br />(b) the International Bureau determines, for any reason, that the international application or the designation of the State in it, is withdrawn or considered withdrawn,<br /><br />(c) the international application is considered to be withdrawn on the ground that it has not, within the period prescribed by Article 20 (as that Article is construed in accordance with Rule 47 of the Treaty Regulations), 22(1) or 39(1) of the Treaty, been received by the European Patent Office, or<br /><br />(d) the applicant decides, at any time prior to the expiration of 31 months from the filing date or the priority date of the international application designating the State, whichever is the earlier, to request the Controller to treat the international application as a patent application under Part II.</blockquote>(3) Subject to compliance with the prescribed conditions, an international application for a patent designating the State which has, under subsection (1) or (2), ceased to be deemed to be an application for a European patent designating the State shall, upon that cesser taking effect, be treated as an application under Part II.<br /><br />(4) Subsection (5) applies to an international application for a patent designating the State which is treated as an application for a patent under Part II.<br /><br />(5) An application for an international patent designating the State which has been published by the International Bureau in accordance with the Treaty in a language other than Irish or English shall be treated, for the purposes of sections 56 and 66(3), as published under section 28 when a translation into Irish or English of the claims of the application have been filed and published by the Office.<br /><br />(6) Article 2 of the Treaty shall apply to the interpretation of this section as that Article applies to the interpretation of the Treaty.<br /><br />(7) In this section, &lsquo;Treaty Regulations&rsquo; means the Regulations under the Treaty as such Regulations are in force from 1 July 2016.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.236" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.237" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Section 40, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.238" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Sections 41 to 105, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.239" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Schedules 1 to 4, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.240" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.241" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.242" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#D00500">Message to Dil.</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018061300002#D00600"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 90, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation has completed its consideration of the Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Bill 2018 and made amendments thereto.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-06-13a.244" nospeaker="true" time="16:40:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 5.15 p.m. until 4.45 p.m. on Wednesday, 20 June 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>