<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Defence</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 15:00</p><p>The Joint Committee met at 15:00</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Teachtaí Dála / Deputies Teachtaí Dála / Deputies John Brady, Gerard P. Craughwell, Sorca Clarke, Niall Ó Donnghaile, Barry Cowen, Diarmuid Wilson. Gary Gannon, Brian Leddin, David Stanton.</p><p>Teachta / Deputy Charles Flanagan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Senator Joe O'Reilly.  I understand that Deputy Brady is in the Chamber and may be some time.  In the meantime we will proceed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.6" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#A00300">Turkish Foreign Policy and Turkey-Ireland Relations: Engagement with Ambassador of Turkey</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#A00400"><p>I am pleased to welcome to our meeting this afternoon H. E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay, ambassador of the Republic of Turkey to Ireland.  He is very welcome.  This is the first opportunity for the members of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence to meet him since his arrival in Ireland earlier in the year.  I welcome  you on behalf of the committee.  We look forward to working with him not only today but also throughout his tenure here as ambassador to Ireland.  I also welcome his deputy head of mission, Ms Balca Kurhan Elayouti.  Some members of the committee are wearing face coverings in accordance with our restrictions.  Some members are in here in the room and others are joining us from their offices because of the Covid-19 restrictions.  The witnesses will appreciate that our meetings are not yet back to what we would describe as normality.  In any event, they are most welcome.</p> <p>  The format of the meeting is that we will hear the ambassador's opening statement, following by discussion, with some questions and answers from members of the committee.  I ask members to be concise in their questions so as to allow all members an opportunity to participate.  We may even have a second opportunity for members to come back in if they so desire.  </p> <p>  I remind our witnesses of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity, by name or in such a way as to make them identifiable.  I remind witnesses that if they make any statements that might be potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks.  It goes without saying that any such direction should be complied with.  I remind members of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against any person or body outside the House, or any official, either by name or in such a way as to make them in any way identifiable.  Members may only participate in this meeting if they are physically located in the Leinster House complex.  </p> <p>  Ambassador, once again you are very welcome.  I now call upon you to make your opening statement. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.8" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#A00500"><p>I thank the Chair and distinguished members of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence for giving me this opportunity to address this respectable committee about Turkish foreign policy and Turkish foreign relations, as well as matters of mutual interest between Turkey and Ireland.  Before proceeding to Turkish foreign policy, I would like to dwell shortly on the bilateral relations between Turkey and Ireland.</p> <p>  Turkey and Ireland enjoy historical bonds of friendship dating back to the Great Irish Famine.  Aid sent by the then Ottoman Sultan to Ireland in 1847 built an everlasting friendship bridge between our countries.  We are pleased that there is no outstanding political dispute between Turkey and Ireland.  Hence, we strive to give an impetus to our current political relations and interactions.  We also would like to increase our economic, commercial, trade, cultural and educational relations.  We are eager to make efforts to double the current trade volume between our countries, which is around &euro;1.5 billion.  Also, we would like to increase mutual investments in our countries.</p> <p>  There are almost 5,000 Turkish citizens in Ireland.  Most of them are working in international companies and one fifth of them are students.  We believe that further interaction between educational institutions in Turkey and Ireland is needed.  It will further increase the number of Turkish students in Irish universities and language schools.</p> <p>  The Covid-19 pandemic has proved that Turkey has a more resilient health system when compared to many developed countries in the world.  While providing the best healthcare to our citizens, we sent medical aid to 159 countries and 12 international organisations.  We also know that many non-Covid-19 patients from Ireland choose Turkey for their routine or normal medical treatments.  Owing to this background, we can increase the co-operation between our medical institutions and healthcare workers.  One other promising co-operation area is in the construction sector.  Turkey, which ranks in the top five countries in this sector, may contribute to Ireland&rsquo;s ambitious new housing and infrastructure projects.</p> <p>  After this short introduction about Turkey-Ireland relations, I would like to continue with Turkish foreign policy and matters of mutual interest.  Turkish foreign policy aims to protect Turkey&rsquo;s interests in a volatile regional and global environment, while also shaping conditions for sustainable peace and development in our neighbourhood and beyond.  In the pursuit of this primary goal, like Ireland, Turkey contributes to peace, prosperity, and stability around the world.</p><p>Guided by our enduring objective to achieve &quot;peace at home, peace in the world&quot;, as set out by the founder of our republic, Mustafa Kemal Atat&uuml;rk, we implement an enterprising and humanitarian foreign policy, which, in our President's words, &quot;reflects the enterprising spirit and humanitarian values of our nation&quot;. <br/><br/>In order to eliminate threats and challenges and to take advantage of emerging opportunities, Turkey is compelled to pursue a foreign policy that is strong on the ground and at the table by implementing an insightful and agile diplomacy.  In this regard, Turkey benefits from deep-rooted traditions of diplomacy and derives strength from several factors, including its central geographical position, rich historical experience, robust institutions, strong human resources and a dynamic economy.  As such, Turkey's foreign policy is the embodiment of a bridge between tradition and the future.<br/><br/>In line with the enterprising aspect of its foreign policy, Turkey conducts a diplomacy that thinks globally but also acts locally in every corner of the world.  With 253 diplomatic and consular missions, Turkey has spawned the fifth largest diplomatic network globally.  Turkey maintains close ties with countries in the Balkans, the Middle East, north Africa, the southern Caucasus, and southern and central Asia.  Beyond these neighbouring regions, we are expanding the horizons of Turkish foreign policy, reaching out to Africa and Latin America.  In  Africa, we have increased the number of our embassies from 12 to 43.  Our trade volume with Africa is currently approximately $26 billion.  We  intend to hold the third Turkey-Africa summit in December 2021.  In Latin America, we have increased the number of our embassies from six to 17 and our trade volume, parallel to that increase, has gone up from $1 billion to $12 billion.  The Asia Anew initiative announced in 2019 has given Turkey the opportunity to lay the foundations of a holistic and comprehensive policy towards Asia and the Pacific, home of the rising powers of the 21st century.  We have established strategic relations with China, Japan, Indonesia, Malaysia, South Korea and Singapore.  <br/><br/>As a pluralist secular democracy that began westernising its economic, political and social structures in the 19th century, Turkey chose western Europe as the model for its new secular structure following the proclamation of the republic in 1923.  Ever since, Turkey has closely aligned itself with the West.  Turkey is a founding member of the Council of Europe and the Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe, OSCE, and a member of NATO and the OECD.  Turkey is a part of Europe and will remain so.  In addition, Turkey has a strategic partnership  with the United States as a NATO ally and considers the transatlantic link vital for security and prosperity in Europe. <br/><br/>As the committee knows, Turkey has been a candidate country to the EU since 1963.  Full membership of the Union remains a strategic priority for Turkey and accession negotiations are the backbone of Turkey-EU relations.  Turkey believes in the necessity of developing a positive agenda in Turkey-EU relations based on our accession perspective.  That will serve the interests of both sides and contribute to the stability in our region.  Starting a Turkey-EU customs union modernisation process and full implementation of the 18 March statement will make a difference in the relations we have with the EU.  In this context, we appreciate the ongoing support of Ireland for Turkey's EU accession process and for  keeping the channels of communication open.  <br/><br/>As a founding member of the United Nations, Turkey, like Ireland, is a strong supporter of multilateralism.  Finding solutions to global challenges depends on collective efforts forged by co-operation and effective multilateralism.  This reality guides Turkey's active diplomacy within multilateral fora.  We are a founding member of several regional organisations and initiatives such as the Organization of the Black Sea Economic Cooperation, the South-East European Cooperation Process and the Economic Cooperation Organization.  In addition, Turkey is a prominent member of the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation, the Developing-8 Organization for Economic Cooperation, the Cooperation Council of Turkic-Speaking States, the Asia Cooperation Dialogue and the MIKTA partnership comprising Mexico, Indonesia, Korea, Turkey and Australia.  Turkey has also been an active member of the G20 since its inception, holding its term presidency for 2015.  Turkey served at the UN Security Council during 2009 and 2010 as a constructive member, contributing to global peace, stability and security.  Under the motto of &quot;The world is bigger than five&quot;, coined by President Erdoan, Turkey has been advocating the reform of the UN Security Council, the UN and other multilateral organisations in order that they be fit for the purpose of today.<br/><br/>On the basis of its enterprising and humanitarian foreign policy, Turkey provides developmental and humanitarian aid programmes.  Turkey is the largest humanitarian donor in the world and the most generous country on the basis of <i>per capita</i>humanitarian spending.  At the same time, Turkey is currently the top refugee-hosting country in the world.  It hosts almost 5 million externally displaced people, approximately 3.7 million of whom are Syrians under temporary  protection.  Turkey has spent more than $40 billion to provide aid and services to the Syrians.  Turkey supports the voluntary and dignified return of Syrians to Syria and, thanks to our efforts, nearly 462,000 of them were able to return to their homes.<br/><br/>The international community cannot allow the Syrian crisis to linger on for another ten years.  We need to display a stronger will to find a political solution to the problem, based on United Nations Security Council Resolution 2254 and in a way that will meet the expectations of the Syrian people.  We welcome the extension of the United Nations' humanitarian assistance mechanism, which is delivered to the north-west of Syria via Turkey, for another 12 months.  We appreciate the strong efforts of Ireland and the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, in this regard.  We had the pleasure to host the Minister in Turkey last January within the framework of those efforts.<br/><br/>Following developments in Afghanistan, we have recently been faced with the possibility of yet another inflow of migrants from that country.  The humanitarian situation in Afghanistan is getting worse.  There are approximately 300,000 Afghans in Turkey.  For comparison, the figure was 35,000 in 2015.  As a country that saved human dignity in the Syrian crisis, we no longer have the capability, nor the tolerance, to absorb new immigration waves.  On the basis of fair burden and responsibility sharing, it is high time for all stakeholders to do their part on this issue.  We support the UN's efforts to provide impartial humanitarian assistance to Afghans in Afghanistan and neighbouring countries.<br/><br/>As far as the Syrian crisis is concerned, our struggle against terrorist organisations that threaten the territorial integrity of Syria and our national security will continue with determination.  Making any distinction between terrorist organisations in the region and using them as subcontractors is unacceptable.  Acts of terrorism in different countries of the world over the past ten years have shown that terrorism is not only our common enemy but also a common enemy of all mankind.<br/><br/>While combating terrorism, Turkey gives particular attention to fundamental rights and freedoms.  Advancing our democracy to a higher level has always been a top priority on our agenda.  Our policies of zero tolerance against torture and violence against women continue firmly.  Two years after the publication of the judicial reform strategy, the human rights action plan is a further indication of Turkey's unwavering resolve for reform.  The action plan lays out concrete steps for further protecting and promoting human rights and strengthening the independence of the judiciary, such as reviewing legislation on freedom of expression and assembly, enhancing women's rights and combating violence against women, fighting against discrimination and hate crime and intensifying meetings with representatives of non-Muslim communities living in Turkey.<br/><br/>I am aware that the eastern Mediterranean issue and the situation in Cyprus have been discussed in the Oireachtas on several occasions.  I consider today's session as an opportunity to put forward Turkey's views on those issues.  Turkey's policy towards the eastern Mediterranean has two dimensions.  The first is related to the maritime boundary  delimitation in the region.  The second dimension concerns the protection of the rights of Turkish Cypriots over the offshore resources of the island.  We hope the problems regarding maritime boundary delimitation will be resolved within the framework of international law and good neighbourly relations.</p><p>Our proposal to organise an eastern Mediterranean conference in which all actors in the region will take part for dialogue and co-operation is still on the table.</p><p> Similarly, we believe that the problems in the Aegean Sea should be resolved through a bilateral dialogue.  Thanks to our efforts, dialogue channels are in place and are operating.  The 63rd round of consultative talks with Greece were held in Turkey last week on 6 October.  With regard to the Cyprus issue, the current deadlock proves the failure of all federation negotiations since 1968.  A new round of federation negotiations will lead us nowhere.  Neither Turkey nor the Turkish Cypriots have another 50 years to lose.  A fair, lasting and sustainable solution to the Cyprus issue is possible only through a result-oriented, realistic approach.  It should be based on the realities on the island.  Also, for a solution, it is necessary to reaffirm the sovereign equality and equal international status of the Turkish Cypriot people, who are the co-owners of the island.  Therefore, we believe that it is high time to consider a negotiated two-state settlement.  We just want the international community to evaluate the views of the Turkish Cypriots as announced in Geneva with an open mind and without prejudice.</p><p> Another primary issue in Turkish foreign policy is the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, which fuels instability and threatens peace and security in our region.  As long as the persecution of the Palestinian people continues, lasting peace and stability in the Middle East is not possible.  Therefore, occupation, annexation and illegal settlement policies must absolutely and immediately be brought to an end.  In this context, we welcome and are closely following the developments regarding the occupied territories Bill in Ireland.  The peace process and the vision of a two-state solution must be revived without further delay.  The establishment of an independent and contiguous Palestinian state, with Jerusalem as its capital, on the basis of the 1967 borders remains among our primary objectives.</p><p> There is one crucial issue that is common for all countries and nations, irrespective of being European, Asian, American, African, rich or poor.  It is climate change.  As our President put in detail during the UN General Assembly meeting last September in New York, Turkey plays its role in taking necessary measures in fighting climate change.  If effective measures are not taken and greenhouse gas emissions continue to increase, our children will not inherit a habitable world.  The duty for all of us is to take measures against this threat, with fair burden-sharing, and to fulfil our obligations quickly.  Acting with this understanding, Turkey was among the first signatories of the Paris Agreement of 2015.  President Erdoan announced during the United Nations General Assembly meeting that the agreement will be submitted to the Grand National Assembly of Turkey this month for approval, and the ratification process of the agreement will be completed before the United Nations Climate Change Conference which will be held in Glasgow in late November.  Indeed, I am happy to announce that the agreement was ratified by the assembly on 6 October last.</p><p> Before finalising my remarks, I wish to take this opportunity to renew the invitation from Mr. &Ccedil;aatay Kl&ccedil;, the president of the commission for foreign affairs of the Grand National Assembly of Turkey to visit Turkey.  The committee's alternate date proposals for the visit will be welcome in due course.  With such a visit, I am confident that the inter-parliamentary contacts between our two countries will also develop and strengthen to our mutual benefit.  I thank the committee for this opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#C00200"><p>Thank you for that wide-ranging and comprehensive overview of Turkish foreign policy and, at the outset, a comprehensive note on the positive and constructive bilateral relations between Ireland and Turkey.  As you pointed out, there is much to build on in our relationship.</p> <p>  I will call on members of the committee for questions.  I will commence with Deputy Gannon who is with us in the committee room.  Members can raise their hands if they wish.  I will follow on to Deputy Clarke as soon as we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1560" speakername="Gary Gannon" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#C00300"><p>I thank the ambassador for his statement.  I have a question about Turkey's role in the conflict in the Nagorno-Karabakh region.  Does the ambassador have any comments on the recent conflict in that region?  Does he believe that the issue of drone warfare, particularly in that conflict, would aid a further destabilisation of tensions and add new dimensions to warfare in that region?  I also have a question about Turkey's relationship with Azerbaijan.  Who else is Turkey providing regional support to in that region in a manner similar to that which it is doing for Azerbaijan?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#C00400"><p>I will group a number of questions, Ambassador, if that is okay.  I call Deputy Clarke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1495" speakername="Sorca Clarke" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#C00500"><p>I thank the ambassador for his time today.  He is most welcome to the committee meeting.  I have one question.  How does the ambassador reconcile his opening statement with the withdrawal of Turkey from the Istanbul Convention, which set out comprehensive standards for the prevention of violence against women, protection and support for survivors and prosecution of perpetrators, as well as establishing minimum essential support services for victims, such as shelters and medical assistance?  I ask for his own view on this and for his opinion on the impact the withdrawal has had on Turkey's international standing and on how women from outside Turkey view Turkey as a safe place for them.  I say that as the only female Deputy on this committee.  Given that I have researched this and seen over 2,000 cases of femicide reported between 2008 and 2017, which I understand was also echoed in another report by Turkish law enforcement, how can the ambassador reassure the international community and this committee that Turkey is a safe place for women and girls, particularly in light of yesterday being the International Day of the Girl Child?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#C00600"><p>I invite the ambassador to respond on Nagorno-Karabakh, Azerbaijan and the domestic matter raised by Deputy Clarke in respect of the Istanbul Convention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.16" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#C00700"><p>As the committee knows, the Karabakh conflict has been going on for 30 years, ever since the independence of Azerbaijan.  One fifth of its territory was occupied by Armenian forces.  Then the Minsk Group was established to try to find a diplomatic solution to the problem.  However, it did not work for the last 30 years.  In June 2020, new attacks started and they started to escalate going into September.  Finally, a year ago today, the Azeri forces started their 44-day operation in Nagorno-Karabakh.  Nagorno-Karabakh is Azeri territory.  The committee must also take that into account.  I am sure the ambassador of Azerbaijan would have been in a much better position to answer this question but Turkey wants normalisation across the region.  The new landscape in Karabakh offers a realistic opportunity to establish enduring peace and stability and this opportunity should not be missed.</p> <p>  President Erdoan announced recently that we can gradually also normalise our relations with Armenia if it takes concrete and sincere steps.  We will reciprocate to any positive steps coming from Armenia.  We also expect Armenia to be part of the regional co-operation projects.  We are of the opinion that the recent Azeri proposal to negotiate a peace agreement with Armenia will contribute to lasting peace across the region, so there will be a win-win situation with a normalisation in that region.</p> <p>  Coming to the drones, we see Azerbaijan as one nation, two states - Turkey and Azerbaijan.  For the last 30 years since its independence, we have developed many co-operation projects, including co-operation in military training and technical aid.  As a free country to purchase its weaponry, it may have bought drones from Turkey as well.</p><p>It may have also been involved in training in Turkey for its operations.  That is all the information I have on the use of drones.</p><p> The Istanbul Convention has been the subject of debate in Turkey since its entry into force not only in Turkey but also in a lot of other Council of Europe countries.  Six EU members and the UK have not ratified it yet.  In different segments of our society some elements of the convention became the subject of criticism.  As a result of the evaluation made, the decision to withdraw from the agreement was taken.  Our decision is not a step back from our determination to fight violence against women, and in all our laws we have the strictest applicability to punish any crime against women.  We will continue to show no tolerance to violence against women.  Also, we announced the fourth national action plan on combating violence against women on 1 July of this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1560" speakername="Gary Gannon" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#D00200"><p>This is not a follow-up question.  I asked who else in the region Turkey is providing such support to.  Is Turkey selling drones to Morocco, for example, similar to the way it is selling to Azerbaijan?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#D00300"><p>I know we are in the process of selling to Poland but this is the first time I have heard about Morocco.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#D00400"><p>The ambassador mentioned in his opening statement the situation in Syria, Turkey's neighbour.  He will be aware of the dire humanitarian situation in evidence in Syria and the fact that in the north east, for example, the water level in the Euphrates river has become critically low.  Currently, more than 13 million Syrians are reliant on humanitarian aid to survive.  I note, as the ambassador stated, that Turkey is currently hosting more than 3.5 million Syrians, who have been in Turkey for some time.  The ambassador might be in a position to expand on how he and the Turkish Government see a resolution of the conflict in Syria, having regard to the fact that, as he stated, it is over ten years since the horrific conflict commenced.  There does not appear to be an immediate sense of a resolution.  Having regard to the authority and influence of Turkey in the neighbourhood, what does the ambassador see as being the priority situation?</p> <p>  As for the issue of refugees specifically, given the large number of Syrians in Turkey, given the strain and pressure that this places on the country's resources and given the dangerous situation for many returnees from many refugee camps to Syria, what does the ambassador see as the priority?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.21" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#D00500"><p>Since the beginning of the Syrian crisis, Turkey has followed a human-centred approach.  We had our borders open to refugees.  For the past ten years we have been providing many services to Syrian refugees, including counselling, language courses, vocational training, health, education and social services free of charge.  The number of Syrian children born in Turkey since the beginning of the crisis and since their arrival into Turkey exceeds 700,000 newborns.  There are more than 1 million school-aged children attending schools in Turkey.  In the initial years the attendance rate was about 30% but, as of 2016, we have achieved a school attendance rate of 64.4%.  The number of Syrians attending Turkish universities is about 40,000.  This figure is higher for refugees because the global average is about 2% but in Turkey the average is about 7%.  The healthcare sector is another area where we continue our efforts.  To date, more than 2.2 million surgeries have been conducted on Syrians, inpatient treatment exceeds 2.7 million and the number of polyclinic visits is over 80 million.  The committee will understand that the amount of resources needed to maintain this is quite high.  The $40 billion I mentioned in my opening statement is just a rough estimate because it is not possible to quantify some of the services provided.</p> <p>  Providing only financial support is not a sufficient answer to solve the problem.  We need to focus more on preparing the conditions that could facilitate returns of Syrians.  That should be one of our primary tasks.  Owing to our efforts and the operations we had in the border region - we have a 900 km joint border with Syria - almost 500,000 Syrians have been able to return to Turkey in the past year or so.  The returns have to be safe, dignified and voluntary, based on legal guarantees and in line with international law.  The process has to be co-ordinated with the United Nations, and priority should be given to the return of internally displaced peoples and to the prevention of new displacements in Syria.  UN Security Council Resolution 2254 gives the framework for resolving the crisis.  There are two process continuing.  One is the Geneva process and the other is the Astana process, in which we take part as well.  If the new constitutional commission can establish a new constitution for the Syrians and if the will of the Syrian people is taken into consideration, I think that would be the only way of resolving the problem.  In the meantime we have to make sure we preserve the territorial integrity of Syria from other sources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#D00600"><p>I confirm I am in my office in Leinster House.  I welcome the ambassador to the meeting and thank him for his presentation.  Obviously, Turkey is a very important country, historically and geographically.  It is a very influential country as well.  Turkey is involved in lots of engagements right across the region.  The ambassador might comment on the current situation with respect to the involvement in Libya and how he sees that developing.</p> <p>  I note that the ambassador spoke about climate change earlier.  He might let us know how that is progressing and what the plans and targets are in respect of Turkey.  How does he see that developing and what are Turkey's plans in that regard?</p> <p>  The Istanbul Convention was mentioned by my colleague, Deputy Clarke, and the ambassador has covered that.</p> <p>  Can the ambassador tell me whether Turkey has plans to withdraw from north-eastern Syria and what the situation is there at the moment?</p> <p>  I note that the United States has been concerned about religious freedom in Turkey.  The ambassador might take the opportunity to comment on that as well.</p> <p>  Finally, what is the position of the Turkish Government on LGBT rights, that is, the rights of gay or homosexual people?  I note there have been some media reports that tolerance in Turkey is not very high but, again, the ambassador might comment on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.23" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#D00700"><p>We are heavily engaged in Libya and trying to help it to find a peaceful resolution of the divisions in the country.</p><p>After long years of war, the fighting is still continuing within Libya between two factions.  We have been on the side of the legal government, which is recognised by the United Nations and we have had some agreements with them.  Some of that is for military co-operation - training, for the most part.  If the elections take place as scheduled in December, they will give a clearer pathway to a solution in Libya.</p><p> Withdrawal from the north-east or the north-west of Syria for the time being is not possible because without the maintenance of the Turkish presence there, we will not be able to protect the civilian population which is finding a safe haven or refuge in north-east Syria along the Turkish border.  Our withdrawal would increase pressure for a new exodus because there are more than 1.5 million people living in the border area.  If the protection shield is lifted from there, we will have a new impetus for a new wave of migration from Syria to Turkey, which is not desirable.</p><p> As far as LGBT rights are concerned, I am sure the Deputy is referring to the events that took place in Istanbul during Pride week.  We do not distinguish between the preferences of people and there is no sentiment against that.  Of course, Turkish culture may not see LGBT as &ldquo;normal&rdquo; &ndash; I am just quoting - but with regard to the standpoint of the state, there is no discrimination against that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#E00200"><p>We are joined by Deputy John Brady, who is welcome.  Before I call Deputy Brady to make some observations and ask questions of the ambassador, I want to briefly raise the issue of Cyprus.  It is a long-standing issue of controversy going back to 1974.  In particular, I want to raise with the ambassador the issue that, on the anniversary of the invasion, during a visit to northern Cyprus, President Erdoan raised the issue of the fenced-off area of Varosha.  This is a matter of some controversy.  I and the Irish Government are concerned at recent actions in regard to Varosha.  The ambassador states that dialogue is the only way forward and that any long-term settlement can only be achieved by a dialogue and by people around the table by way of talks.  Again, the Irish Government would encourage progress towards the achievement of a long-term settlement and the achievement of a bizonal, bicommunal federal state on the island of Cyprus in accordance with UN Security Council resolutions.  I ask the ambassador how he would see a Turkish contribution towards that, having regard to what, on the face of it, would appear to be action on Varosha that would seem to fly in the face of what might be described as diplomatic dialogue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.26" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#E00300"><p>The Chairman referred to 1974 as being the start of the conflict but it goes back to 1968 because the Cyprus state really never functioned from its outset.  The main reason for that is the Greek Cypriot side does not want to share power of governance and also the wealth with the Turkish Cypriots.  This fact lies behind the failure of all federation negotiations ongoing since 1968.  The Greek Cypriot side rejected the solution in the Annan plan in 2004, which was an opportunity missed, in my opinion.  In turn, however, they were rewarded with EU membership in 2004.  Later on, the Greek Cypriot side left the table at the conference on Cyprus in Crans-Montana in 2017.</p> <p>  We need to be realistic because there are two peoples and two states on the island.  The Turkish Cypriot side wants to establish a co-operative relationship in Cyprus.  They submitted a written proposal at the informal five-plus UN meeting in Geneva in April of this year.  The essence of the proposal is to secure enhanced sovereign equality and equal international status of the Turkish Cypriot people, and Turkey fully supports that vision.  Any future negotiations should be carried out between two states on the island, not between two communities.</p> <p>  The Greek Cypriots still hide behind the EU, as well as the outdated UN Security Council resolutions stemming from the 1970s.  The EU's blank cheque to the Greek Cypriots under the pretext of Union solidarity does not help the efforts for a settlement.  If the EU sincerely wishes to contribute to the settlement of the Cyprus issue, first and foremost, it should acknowledge the existence and the will of the Turkish Cypriot people, and should fulfil its commitments stemming from the 2004 arrangement.  On the other hand, the UN parameters, to which the Chairman referred, reflect an understanding between the two sides reached at the end of the 1970s and there is no agreement on that today.</p> <p>  On Varosha, the Turkish Cypriot Government exercises full control, jurisdiction and authority in Varosha and is the only authority to decide on matters pertaining to that suburb.  Varosha is a suburb of the city of Mausa.  In October 2020, the Turkish republic of northern Cyprus allowed public access to two main streets and the beach and, since that date, more than 200,000 people, including Greek Cypriots, have visited the area.  On 20 July, the anniversary of the founding, the Turkish republic of northern Cyprus lifted military zone political status only to a pilot area, which corresponds to about 3.5% of Mara, that is, Varosha.  The decision allows it to address the property issue in Varosha through the immovable property commission, which expands the horizons for the people who own properties there.  The Greek Cypriot side attempts to portray these developments as if Varosha is open for new settlements at the expense of property rights, and this is absolutely not the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#E00400"><p>Would the ambassador accept, with respect, that the recent action amounts to something of a breach of trust and if there is going to be a long-term settlement, that settlement will be based on trust and confidence?  What steps would he see as appropriate for his government to take in order to rebuild trust and ensure a level of trust and confidence that would engender talks towards a longer-term solution?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.28" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#E00500"><p>That trust should be built between the two communities, first and foremost, because we are the guarantor power, like the UK and Greece.  It should be the two peoples on the island which should have trust in each other and build on that.  For the Turkish Government to talk on behalf of a decision taken by the Turkish Cypriot Government on partially opening Varosha would not be appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#E00600"><p>Thank you.  I hope a form of dialogue can take place in order to ensure harmony among people.  I call Deputy John Brady.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1625" speakername="John Brady" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#F00100"><p>I thank the Chairman and wish the ambassador a good afternoon.  He is very welcome to the committee.  I congratulate him on his recent appointment to Ireland.  I apologise for being late in joining the meeting.  Much like other colleagues, I was tied up in the D&aacute;il Chamber dealing with the budget, which is a not insignificant event going on as a backdrop within the D&aacute;il today.</p> <p>  I have a number of questions and issues I want to try to address this afternoon.  I will pick up the topic on which the Chairman finished, which is the whole issue of Cyprus.  It is an issue on which I have been very vocal and one of the many reasons for which I wanted an engagement with a representative from the Turkish Embassy.  I am, therefore, glad to be able to raise the issue directly with the ambassador today.</p> <p>  In my mind, the occupation by Turkey of northern Cyprus since Operation Atilla in 1974 must not only be condemned but the ratcheting up of tensions by Turkey, certainly over the last year or more, has really added to tensions rather than to the prospect of any peaceful resolution to the issue.  As I stated, this has gone on now since the occupation of northern Cyprus in 1974.</p> <p>  I will not labour some of the points the Chairman made around tangible talks and efforts which are, in my mind, being taken by Turkey to undermine any prospect for talks.  Last year, there were major tensions in the eastern Mediterranean Sea and much of that would have stemmed from the Turkish position and rights around exploration for oil and gas.  Is the position of Turkey really ultimately about controlling large sections of the Mediterranean Sea for oil and gas?  Is that influencing any positions being taken by Turkey with regard to a peaceful resolution?</p> <p>  I have a number of questions.  Perhaps we will deal with them first and maybe the ambassador will want to come in at that point.  Over the last number of years, an approach has been adopted by Turkey on the international stage and particularly in that region, which I believe to have been a very unsettling position.  We see that in terms of the Turkish involvement in the recent Armenia-Azerbaijan conflict around Nagorno-Karabakh.  The Turkish intelligence transferring of jihadis from places such as Syria into the midst of that conflict was widely reported.  The ambassador might address the Turkish involvement in tensions and hostilities in that particular region, what involvement Turkey had in it and what involvement it still has to this day.  The use of drones, for example, which were used to target Armenian civilian populations, was widely reported.  He might address that issue.</p> <p>  While I am talking about the transfer of jihadis from places such as Syria, it was also widely reported that Turkish intelligence again transported thousands of jihadis from places like Idlib in Syria into Egypt.  Again, I listened intently to what the ambassador had to say in terms of why Turkey was involved in the situation in Libya.  I will pose the point that the involvement of Turkey actually ratcheted up tensions within the region, particularly the transferring of thousands of jihadis into that particular conflict zone.  The ambassador might also touch on that.</p> <p>  I have a couple of other issues, one of which is the treatment of the Kurdish population and Kurdish people by Turkey.  We see that in terms of the ongoing attempts to ban a Kurdish political party, namely, the Peoples Democratic Party, HDP.  I want to ask specifically about the ongoing efforts by President Erdoan and Turkey to ban the HDP.  What is the rationale for that?  Why has the decision been taken to outlaw political activity?</p> <p>  With regard to the ongoing tensions within the region concerning the Kurdish population, we see continuous incursions into Iraq by Turkey to target Kurdistan people, much to their annoyance and rightfully so.  Ongoing incursions into Iraq are an intrusion into another country against international law.  We also see the unlawful occupation of large sections of Syria.  I mentioned the Idlib province already.  We see it right along the northern borders of Syria and the southern borders of Turkey.</p> <p>  I noted with interest comments made yesterday by President Erdoan that in my mind were almost an indication that there was going to be a renewal of military hostilities against Kurdish people in those regions.  I would like to get a view from the ambassador on the illegal occupation of Syria, the ongoing hostilities against the Kurds and their right to self-determination.</p> <p>  The final issue I want to raise with the ambassador is the that of the prevention of violence against women and combatting domestic violence.  Of course, I am talking about the decision taken by Turkey to withdraw from the Istanbul accord.  That was the 2011 Istanbul Convention, which was ratified by Turkey in 2012 and to which it was the first country to sign up.  The decision by Turkey to withdraw from the accord is a retrograde step.  It has been condemned and rightfully so.  I utterly condemn the position taken by Turkey on its withdrawal from the Istanbul accord.</p> <p>  I will pose this question to the ambassador.  What is the rationale for the withdrawal from the Istanbul accord?  Ongoing violence against women is obviously prevalent in society right across the world and it must be condemned.  Signing up to conventions such as this must be welcomed.  I do not believe enough has been done internationally to target the ongoing issues of persecution and violence against women.  Any withdrawal of positions by a government or by a country with regard to any measures to protect women in society anywhere in the world must be condemned.  What is the rationale?  I do not think any rationale would stand up to scrutiny.  I would be interested to hear what the ambassador has to say to try to defend that indefensible position, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#F00200"><p>I thank Deputy Brady.  The ambassador dealt with the latter issue in the context of an earlier question from Deputy Clarke.  I understand that the Deputy was otherwise engaged.  I am sure the ambassador would like to advert to matters in his reply to Deputy Brady.  There were a number of questions, which I will leave with the ambassador for his reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.32" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#F00300"><p>I thank Deputy Brady for that short question.  It was a rather extensive statement for the most part.</p><p>As the Chair has said I have already answered some of the questions but I am happy to repeat some of what I have said.<br/><br/>The Turkish policy towards the eastern Mediterranean has two dimensions.  The first is related to the maritime boundary delimitation in the eastern Mediterranean.  According to international law, coastal states should enter into negotiations in order to reach an agreement on maritime boundaries and this should be based on the principle of equity.  Turkey has the longest coast in the eastern Mediterranean.  The second dimension of Turkey's eastern Mediterranean policy concerns the protection of the rights of the Turkish Cypriots over the offshore resources of the island.  I am happy to say that since July 2020 there have been no additional tensions in the eastern Mediterranean.  With Germany as an intermediary, we have come to an understanding and the drilling and exploration were halted by both sides.  I hope the <i>status quo</i>remains in the coming period.<br/><br/>The tensions started in 2003 when the Greek Cypriots concluded a delimitation agreement with Egypt despite our objections because that agreement violated the Turkish continental shelf.  In 2007 the Greek Cypriots signed another delimitation agreement with Lebanon, disregarding the Turkish Cypriots' rights in the zone.  In 2011 the Greek Cypriots started their drilling activities in the region.  We did not take any action at sea from 2003 until the first offshore drilling operation of the Greek Cypriots in 2011.  The commencement of those unilateral actions left us with no option but to react.  Following the first drilling, Turkey signed a maritime boundary delimitation agreement with the Turkish Cypriots in 2011.  Then we identified offshore licence blocks just like the Greek Cypriots have done and we granted survey and drilling licences to the Turkish Petroleum Corporation.  We still waited until 2019 for our first drilling activity in the region, which was eight years after the first drilling activity of the Greek Cypriots.  These developments brought us to sign a maritime delimitation agreement with the UN recognised legitimate government in Libya in 2019.<br/><br/>All these topics are being taken up with Greece as well and the latest round of the consultative talks were held on 6 October this year.  The continuation of the calm environment in the eastern Mediterranean is in our common interest.  For this it is necessary to first abandon the understanding whereby Turkey, which has the longest coast in the eastern Mediterranean, is ignored in the region.  Our proposal to organise an eastern Mediterranean conference in which all actors in the region would take part for dialogue and co-operation is still on the table.  Recently there was a slight provocation with a Maltese-flagged ship, <i>Nautical Geo</i>, which tried to do some research on our continental shelf but that was also averted and the situation did not grow out of proportion.<br/><br/>The Deputy asked about our policy on the HDP and the intention of closing that party down.  Political parties in Turkey are among the indispensable elements of democratic and political life but they are also expected to respect democratic and universal principles of law.  The request by the chief public prosecutor to Turkey's Court of Cassation for the dissolution of HDP was made on the grounds that its actions as a political extension of the terrorist organisation the Kurdistan Worker's Party, PKK, and statements and activities that it made are not in line with the democratic and universal principles of law.  Dissolution of political parties is a legal measure applied in all democracies so it is nothing particular to Turkey.  Everybody should respect the judicial process, which is carried out in accordance with the Turkish constitution.  As for the lifting of the parliamentary immunity of some members of the HDP, there are judicial remedies and in a recent example Mr. &Ouml;mer Faruk Gergerliolu took his case to the Constitutional Court of Turkey and was reinstated.<br/><br/>In northern Syria we have established a secure zone for the internally displaced persons, IDPs, in that region to avoid another influx of migrants coming to Turkey who would then go onwards to European countries.  The PKK's extension in northern Syria, the YPG, which is the so called People's Defence Units, exploits the pretext of fighting against Daesh to gain legitimacy and to expand its oppressive role in the region.  For this reason we had to fight Daesh and the PKK in the region.  Turkey has carried out three operations in the region.  The first was in 2017, Operation Spring Shield and then in 2019 and 2020, two other operations took place.<br/><br/>Turkey has not sent any jihadists to Azerbaijan at all but the opposite is true because there is plenty of evidence that PKK elements were used in Nagorno-Karabakh by the Armenian forces and by some foreign fighters from its diaspora.  That is all I have to say on that issue.  I refer to President Erdoan's statement yesterday that we may have to do something in Syria.  That was a reaction to the sad event of two police officers who were stationed in northern Syria being killed on the same day near Idlib.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#G00200"><p>I will bring matters to a conclusion if there are no other members offering.  Deputy Brady can make a brief supplementary contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1625" speakername="John Brady" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#G00300"><p>I thank the ambassador for his comments but he did not really deal with the question on the banning of political parties.  He danced around the issue and said it was a matter for the Turkish judiciary.  I posed the point that many members of the Turkish judiciary, many journalists and many members of opposition political parties have been rounded up and are languishing in prison because of their opposition to the Turkish Government and its policy under President Erdoan.  I would not take what the ambassador is saying at face value.  How many political prisoners are in prison in Turkey?  How many journalists are in prison in Turkey for speaking out against the Turkish Government?  How many members of political parties are languishing in prison in Turkey for speaking out against the oppressive nature of the Turkish regime?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#G00400"><p>I see Deputy Stanton offering to make a supplementary contribution as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1515" speakername="David Stanton" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#G00500"><p>When I was in earlier I asked the ambassador to comment on religious freedom in Turkey.  We have seen some reports which would lead us to be concerned about that.  Could he also comment on the impact of Covid-19 in Turkey, especially on the economy?</p><p>Could the ambassador give us an update on the economic situation in Turkey?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="H.E. Mr. Mehmet Hakan Olcay" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#H00300"><p>Religious freedoms are constitutional guarantees, so I see no problem in that area.  They enjoy all the rights the Muslim majority in the country enjoys.</p> <p>  Coming to the Covid-19 problem, as I said in my opening statement, we have a resilient healthcare system, so we were not that bad.  On the vaccines, although we cannot match Ireland, where 90% have been vaccinated, in Turkey 112,356,099 vaccines have been used.  Some 54 million are first dose, which represents 75% of the population, while 46 million are second dose, which represents 74.36% of the population.  During the pandemic, we had 7 million people who were infected by the virus and to date we have recorded 63,000 deaths, but of course we are a country of 83 million so when you take this figure, you have to base it on that population.</p> <p>  Our economy was also affected by the pandemic and the curfew which was imposed on and off.  We had a different system.  Instead of a prolonged lockdown, it was lockdown on the weekends, on certain holidays and so forth.  However, the economy was affected just like all other countries.  The economy is also being affected by the rise in energy prices, which is the same problem Ireland has begun to experience in the last year.  Electricity and natural gas prices have gone up, so it has affected many areas of life.  Part of that is because of the pandemic, which I hope we will soon leave behind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1589" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FDJ2021101200002#H00400"><p>I thank the ambassador.  It is my intention to bring matters to a conclusion.  I remind members that we have some private business to engage in immediately following this meeting.</p> <p>  Again I thank the ambassador for being with us.  I wish you well in your tenure in Ireland in terms of our bilateral relationship with Turkey.  Ireland, as an active and engaged member of the European Union, acknowledges the fact that relations between the European Union and Turkey have regressed somewhat in recent years.  We believe it is important that there is a constructive and stable relationship between the European Union and Turkey.  We trust that both you and your government will positively engage to ensure that stable, constructive and positive relationship.</p> <p>  With that in mind, I thank you most sincerely for your invitation on behalf of Mr. &Ccedil;aatay Kl&ccedil;, the president of the commission for foreign affairs in the Turkish Grand National Assembly.  My members and I would be very keen to give appropriate and due consideration to that invitation and we will revert to you.</p> <p>  On behalf of members I thank the ambassador for being with us and dealing with the many and varied questions.  We look forward to an active and positive engagement between our committee and yourself in your time here.  I also thank Mrs. Elayouti for being with us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.41" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 4.14 p.m. and adjourned at 4.24 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, 2 November 2021.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.42" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="">Seanad Committee on the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.43" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>Tháinig an Roghchoiste le chéile ag 12:00</p><p>The Select Committee met at 12:00</p><p>COMHALTAÍ A BHÍ I LÁTHAIR / MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Seanadóirí / Senators Seanadóirí / Senators Malcolm Byrne, Malcolm Byrne, Timmy Dooley, Timmy Dooley, Robbie Gallagher, Robbie Gallagher, Róisín Garvey, Róisín Garvey, Niall Ó Donnghaile. Niall Ó Donnghaile.</p><p>Seanadóir / Senator Lisa Chambers sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.44" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#A00100">Dispute Resolution Mechanism: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#C00100"><p>Apologies have been received from Senators Flynn and Joe O'Reilly.</p><p>I welcome members to this meeting of the Seanad Special Committee on the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union.  On correspondence, we have a number of matters to note.  Correspondence on the EU-UK Parliamentary Assembly, dated 7 October 2021, was sent by the Houses of the Oireachtas liaison officer to the EU Parliament dated 7 October 2021.  There is correspondence from the House of Lords European Affairs sub-committee on the protocol, dated 1 October 2021, regarding the proposed format of meeting with the clerk to the EU affairs committee.  The third item is a brief note by the clerk to the committee, dated 7 October 2021, on the visit to the Northern Ireland Executive committee.  Can I ask that correspondence be noted?  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p> The minutes from our public meeting on 30 September also have to be noted.  The meeting in question was terminated due to IT issues, but can we adopt the minutes in any event?  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p> The purpose of this meeting is to discuss the dispute resolution mechanism for the trade and co-operation agreement, TCA, and the withdrawal agreement between the United Kingdom and the European Union.  I welcome our witnesses from the European Union division of the Department of Foreign Affairs: Ms Maeve Collins, director general; Ms Deirdre Farrell, director, EU-UK unit; and Mr. Karl Gardner, director, EU-UK unit.</p><p> I must inform our guests that witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence that they give to the committee.  This means that a witness has a full defence in any defamation action for anything said at a meeting of the committee.  However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's direction.  Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard.  They are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third party or entity.</p><p> As witnesses are all present in the committee room, there is no need for the next section. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside the proceedings held by the committee of any matter arising from the proceedings.</p><p> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I also remind members that they are only allowed to participate in this meeting if they are physically located within the Leinster House complex.  In this regard I ask all members prior to making their initial contribution to the meeting to confirm they are on the grounds of the Leinster House complex.  If they are directed by the Chair to cease giving evidence on a particular matter, please respect that direction.</p><p> With regard to Covid-19 guidance, members and all in attendance are asked to exercise personal responsibility in protecting themselves and others from the risk of contracting Covid-19.  They are strongly advised to practise good hand hygiene and also to wear masks.</p><p> Without any further ado, I invite our witnesses to make their opening statements.  I call Ms Collins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maeve Collins" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#D00200"><p>I thank the Chair and Senators for the opportunity to speak to the committee.  I have just returned from Brussels where I was serving as Ireland's deputy permanent representative to the EU.  I took up duty in my new post last Thursday.  I am delighted to have a chance to join the committee so early in my tenure as the new director general for the EU division of the Department of Foreign Affairs.</p> <p>  While I am new to this role, my time in Brussels has provided me with an awareness of the many challenges that Brexit brings to so many sectors across the European Union, but especially in Ireland.  I am also aware of the valuable contributions Members of the Oireachtas have made to Ireland's Brexit response.  Between them, the EU-UK withdrawal agreement, which includes the protocol on Ireland and Northern Ireland, and the TCA underpin the UK's withdrawal from the EU and establish the framework for our new relationship.  While both agreements contain provisions and structures for governing the relationship, like most international agreements, they prudently also outline how the parties should engage where difficulties or issues of concern or disputes arise.</p> <p>  The avenues available for resolving disputes differ between the agreements and between the specific parts of the agreements depending on the issue in question.  However, the most important recourse is to try to resolve differences through dialogue.  This takes place, in the first instance, within a series of governing structures.  In the case of the withdrawal agreement, the joint committee is the overarching committee.</p><p>In the case of the withdrawal agreement, the joint committee is the overarching committee.  For the EU&ndash;UK trade and co-operation agreement, TCA, this is the partnership committee.  Both are led by Commission Vice-President &Scaron;efovi for the European Union, and Lord Frost for the UK.  This ensures that the appropriate political engagement and direction can be provided.  Each agreement provides for additional co-chaired specialised committees and working groups where EU and UK officials can engage on specific issues and discuss any points that could give rise to difficulties.</p><p> Ireland closely monitors the implementation of the withdrawal agreement and the TCA.  We are fully engaged with the Commission and other member states to raise any concerns we might have about the implementation of the agreements and to make sure that our voice is heard.  In the case of the specialised committee on the protocol on Ireland and Northern Ireland, the Irish delegate is the only member state observer invited to speak for the EU side.  In hopefully infrequent cases where difficulties cannot be addressed in the committee structures, both agreements provide a framework for dispute resolution through arbitration.  The main features of the two arbitration systems are set out in the briefing note that we provided.  The note also highlights differences in approaches on issues such as timelines, panel sizes and remedies for non-compliance with an arbitration ruling.  A significant difference is that the withdrawal agreement allows for possible recourse to the European Court of Justice.  However, in both agreements, non-compliance can lead to suspension of treaty obligations.  Both agreements mandate the establishment of separate independent arbitration bodies.  For the withdrawal agreement, a panel of 25 members is now in place and includes one member who is Irish.  The 25-person panel for the TCA is in the process of being established.  While the arbitration process has not been invoked, should it be required, members will be selected from the appropriate panel.</p><p> I will address two other areas that may be of interest.  The TCA provides for the creation of an EU-UK parliamentary assembly to include 35 members each from the European Parliament and the UK Parliament.  Once established, it will be informed of the partnership council&rsquo;s decisions and can make recommendations to it.  The European Parliament has agreed its approach, and is in the process of determining which of its members will attend.  The UK Parliament is yet to determine its approach.</p><p> The protocol also includes elements relevant to dispute resolution.  The EU has twice initiated infringement proceedings against the UK for breach of obligations under the protocol.  The first of these was dropped after the offending clauses from the UK&rsquo;s Internal Market Bill were removed.  The second is currently on hold pending wider developments in EU-UK engagement on the implementation of the protocol.  Article 16, which we hear so much about, is a safeguard option which either party can invoke, if the application of the protocol leads to "serious economic, societal or environmental difficulties that are liable to persist" or to "diversion of trade".  It is important to note that invoking Article 16 does not immediately suspend the protocol or allow either party to dispense with it.  It starts a process of engagement with a view to finding a commonly acceptable solution engagement.</p><p> While we have focused today on how we would address any difficulties that may arise, we hope that recourse to formal dispute resolution procedures under both of these agreements is not something that needs to be regularly relied upon by either party.  The agreements are about building a positive and mutually beneficial set of arrangements, supported by sustained, regular and detailed dialogue at official and political levels.  We remain committed to doing our part in making the relationship work.  I thank the Cathaoirleach.  I am happy to take any questions, as are my colleagues, who are probably more familiar with the technical details than I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#E00200"><p>I thank Ms Collins.  I am sure she is being modest.  I wish her the best of luck in her new role.  It is great to have this opportunity to engage with her, Ms Farrell and Mr. Gardner.  We did not foresee when we set up this meeting that it would be so timely.  We are all acutely aware of the political happenings related to this.  We want to be cautious and make sure that we do not do anything to disrupt that process in any negative way.</p><p>I ask members to indicate if they have a question but I might come in first.  There is quite a lot in that.  The witnesses have done a good job in putting together a succinct document.  It is all factual and every sentence is relevant.  It is a good opening statement and briefing document.  We might just break the discussion into two sections, first the withdrawal agreement and then the trade and co-operation agreement, TCA.  We might first focus on the withdrawal agreement, which currently is the main topic for discussion.  We are probably realising more and more how important it is to have those dispute resolution mechanisms.  While we hope that we never need to use them, they could be one of the more lasting things that stay with us when we move to the next phase of Brexit and the phase after that.  This will obviously be an ongoing process for many years.  </p><p> On the withdrawal agreement and the specialist committee, the witnesses should give a little more detail on how that works.  The Irish delegate has an opportunity to speak.  In the witnesses' opinion what is the strength of that?  Is the delegate's view heard?  At present, Commissioner &Scaron;efovi is representing the European Union, both overall and in the committee, and then there is the UK representative.  There has been an accusation previously that there is a lack of democratic oversight in terms of an elected person who could represent Ireland's interests.  Obviously therefore, this delegate is important to us in having our views heard.  To what extent does this delegate make his or her views known and to what is the strength of that?  What does that mean in practical terms?  If we have a dispute with all of the different agendas at play and all of the different wants and demands at play, how protected are we to make sure that in ten or 20 years&rsquo; time, we will be able to protect Ireland&rsquo;s interests?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#F00200"><p>I will take that question.  The key point is that by the time we get to those meetings, a huge amount of work has been done in advance.  A huge amount of engagement in respect of the agenda and our key points happens both in Brussels and through headquarters in Dublin before those meetings even happen.  In terms of political input, there is constant engagement between the Minister, Deputy Coveney, and Commissioner &Scaron;efovi.  Ireland&rsquo;s inputs are fed into this process from an early point.  I am the delegate on the specialised committee and by the time one gets to the meeting, in general nothing will be said that will be a shock or a surprise to anyone.  On the day, we will be reinforcing our message again, as well as ensuring that it is not just the voice of the Commission and the UK, but that member states are watching this closely and are clearly engaged in the process.</p> <p>  As I am an official, I do not engage in the kind of political input the Chair is talking about.  However, as I said, the Minister, Deputy Coveney, and the Minister of State, Deputy Thomas Byrne, have direct engagement with senior Commission officials and with the Commissioners and so on.  That is happening on an ongoing basis. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#F00300"><p>Can Mr. Gardner talk us through the committees?  There is the joint committee and the specialist committee on the protocol itself.  In the last number of weeks, practically, how have they interacted?  How does the joint committee interact with the specialist committee?  How does that work?  This is probably the first time it has been tested to this degree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#F00400"><p>The last meeting of the specialised committee was a couple of weeks back.  There are several specialised committees and we are focusing on the committee that deals with the protocol, which is the one in which the Chair is interested.  The specialised committee talks through the agreed agenda.  It was a useful meeting on the last occasion because it gave us a chance to catch up on elements of the protocol that the EU had concerns about, as well as to hear what the UK was doing in terms of implementation.  More broadly, it was a chance to allow the EU to once again repeat the need for complete, fuller implementation by the UK side.  That, then, will feed into the next meeting of the joint committee.</p> <p>  The joint committee is the committee that has the power to take decisions, whereas the specialised committee is the advisory committee.  The specialised committee gets a chance to go through the issues on its agenda.  I do not have a date for the next meeting of the joint committee.  We would hope to see a meeting soon after tomorrow's announcements, as part of that the bigger discussion around the Commission&rsquo;s papers that will come out tomorrow.  It feeds into that process.  </p> <p>   Again, there is constant engagement between the co-chairs of the committee, so for the UK and then on the Commission&rsquo;s side and the EU is where we feed in.  There are regular meeting of the working party on the United Kingdom at Brussels, where Ireland is a constant voice that member states look to for views as to what the Commission is considering.</p><p>Members will be familiar with the work being done in Brussels by continually engaging with representatives of other member states and with the Commission.  I refer to engagement with the UK service and to the broader Directorates-General, DGs, to ensure that our voice is heard.  It is, therefore, a parallel but joined-up process between the political and official side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00200"><p>Does the specialised committee make formal recommendations or is it more of an informal engagement?  Is there a formalised process to link the specialised committee with the joint committee regarding how they interact in the context of making recommendations, or is that process still being determined?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00300"><p>That element is still being worked through.  The specialised committee is working through the technical detail, while the joint committee tends to take the bigger political and strategic overview.  There is not a sense that a set of recommendations will be handed over from every meeting to just be rubber-stamped.  The two bodies are working together.  The co-chairs of the specialised committee are the deputies of the chairs of the joint committee and there is a close link between the two committees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00400"><p>Would it be fair to say that whatever papers that it is anticipated will be presented by Commissioner &Scaron;efovi tomorrow will have been informed by the work of the specialised committee and that Ireland&rsquo;s views are reflected therein?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00500"><p>They will have been informed by the specialised committee and by the meetings the Commission had in Northern Ireland.  The papers will also have been informed by the work that we and our colleagues in Brussels have done, as well as by the views of many other member states.  It is not just the specialised committee.  A great deal of information is feeding into this initiative.  I have not seen all the formal papers, but what I understand is that they will cover all the elements that I imagine would have been discussed at the specialised committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00600"><p>To return to the question about Ireland&rsquo;s delegate, what is the strength of that position?  I ask that question because it is not a democratically-elected position and we have no other way of feeding our views into this process.  Criticism has been made about the democratic deficit and there being no accountability to elected representatives.  How strong is the position of Ireland&rsquo;s delegate in that context?  It appears to be the case that an opportunity has been given to speak, which is great.  Does the position go any further than that though?  It seems to be a position that is quite limited, if I can put it that way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.60" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maeve Collins" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00700"><p>The delegate is speaking on behalf of the Government of Ireland.  I will let Mr. Gardner talk in more detail about the role.  It can be guaranteed, however, that this is not someone who is going to put forward a position that has not been agreed within Government.  Brexit is given much attention across all Departments, so whatever is said is going to be representative of a position that is held by the Irish Government, which is democratically elected and accountable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00800"><p>The specialised committee is a meeting of officials.  Everyone there is an official.  That is the key point.  It is not considering the views of the Department of Foreign Affairs based on those of the members here.  There is close co-ordination across a variety of issues in those meetings and we also have the usual regular engagement with our Ministers in this regard.  This matter, as can be imagined, is also a regular topic of conversation between officials here, in Brussels and in London, across the Department with the Minister, the Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs, Deputy Thomas Byrne, and also elsewhere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G00900"><p>Would it be fair to say then that the ultimate decision-making power rests with the joint committee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.63" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G01000"><p>Yes, the joint committee has the power to make decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G01100"><p>Moving on to Article 16, Ms Collins very properly touched upon the conditions or the bar to be met in respect of invoking it.  This aspect is perhaps sometimes not discussed in as much detail as it should be.  A high bar must be met in this regard.  How can it be decided whether one partner to the agreement has had serious economic, societal or environmental difficulty?  Ultimately, if one side says that such difficulty has been experienced and the other side says it has not, does that question then move into the realm of the European Court of Justice, ECJ, for determination?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#G01200"><p>Again, this comes down to one side to decide.  There is no definition of these things.  Therefore, it comes down to one side to decide that certain elements of the experience meet the requirement to trigger Article 16.  Once that happens, the question goes straight into a process which includes an announcement in that regard.  I have the exact choreography of what happens here.  There is an announcement that this is going to be done through the joint committee-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00100"><p>I am sorry to interrupt but before Mr. Gardner moves on to the process itself, if there is a dispute over whether the bar has been met, in other words, if the UK said it met the bar in that there was a serious economic and societal impact but the EU said there has not been, then I assume the process simply does not start.  If there is disagreement at the outset, how is that determined?  That might be the crux of the issue in the next number of weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00200"><p>Let us say one of the parties, we will not say which, decides it is going to invoke Article 16.  The first thing that party does is notify the joint committee it is doing this and there are immediate consultations with a view to trying to find the solution.  If no solution can be found one side or the other can take safeguard measures, but there is also a dispute settlement mechanism within that which allows the development of an arbitration panel, just to decide on issues that arise within Article 16 as well.  Again, as with what Ms Collins was saying earlier, it is a process.  It is not that suddenly Article 16 crashes things; instead it is a process of joint committee discussions and then various options which flow from that as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00300"><p>Ultimately then, if there is a disagreement as to whether that bar has been met to even trigger Article 16, it could end up before the ECJ.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00400"><p>Yes, it ultimately could.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00500"><p>The irony of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maeve Collins" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00600"><p>That would be a long journey though.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00700"><p>Yes.  The marker of this entire process has been that it is a long journey.</p> <p>  I move to the EU-UK Trade and Cooperation Agreement because there is an interesting element of that, namely, the parliamentary assembly.  Will the officials take us through what that is going to look like?  How will its members be selected?  How will it operate?  Ultimately, what powers does it have with respect to overseeing the implementation of the TCA?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.73" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maeve Collins" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00800"><p>We do not have an awful lot to add beyond the opening statement.  The European Parliament will appoint members.  We are still waiting for the UK to take a position and begin nominating its own members.  Regrettably, it is yet to happen.  We are not sure yet.  Obviously, we would like to see some Irish representation on that body but ultimately it is for the European Parliament to decide which of the 25 members will be on it.  I understand that is being worked on at the moment.  My colleagues may have something to add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.74" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Deirdre Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H00900"><p>I add that the TCA is not prescriptive.  It is very much that the parliaments themselves may establish the parliamentary assembly.  It does not prescribe what that looks like and it is thus very much up to the European Parliament on the EU side to determine what that looks like.  The information we have is what has been set out so far but it is certainly at an early stage in the process, as Ms Collins said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H01000"><p>The officials are saying there is no guaranteed way for an Irish MEP to sit on the assembly, though we would obviously hope to get a slot there .</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.76" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maeve Collins" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H01100"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H01200"><p>The officials have said it can make recommendations.  What happens when recommendations are made?  Must they be acted upon or are they just to be considered and noted?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.78" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H01300"><p>I will double check that but my sense is they will be considered and noted.  There is no sort of prescriptive duty for the joint committee to take them on board.  They would have to have some form of weight, coming from elected representatives on both the EU and UK sides.  I do not have the exact language in front of me but my sense is it is for consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#H01400"><p>It is early days and I appreciate that.  We are waiting for one side to catch up in some aspects of it.</p> <p>  Returning to the specialist committee, it has been debating and deliberating over the last number of weeks around ways to make the protocol work a bit better for people.  It has been fantastic to see the engagement between the Vice President, Maro&scaron; &Scaron;efovi, the Irish Government, the Department and all the stakeholders in Northern Ireland to really get to the crux of what the problem is.  There seem to be very practical issues.  From the officials' work in the Department, what have been the key issues businesses and citizens are saying they want us to look at, in terms of day-to-day, practical living and business requirements?  What are their asks, essentially?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.80" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#J00100"><p>Their biggest ask for them all is certainty, as the committee will have heard.  Businesses do not particularly like any form of uncertainty.  It is important to note that it has been good on citizens and business, it is not just focused on economics but the broader community.  They would like to see some form of clarity on customs and how the process is to work.  SPS checks have been raised in our engagements with businesses there and the committee will have heard that too.  Medicines are raised all the time.  The fourth thing is similar to the point the Chair made earlier which is the need for some form of engagement process between Northern Ireland and the Commission, that they understand what is happening in the Commission that impacts on them.  Those are the four broad areas that tend to be covered in our engagements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#J00200"><p>The engagement process is something that would have been raised at the committee.  Citizens and businesses in Northern Ireland are subject to Single Market and customs union rules but there is a democratic deficit as they do not have an elected member representing them at the table.  Do the officials have any thoughts?  The committee has done a little work on citizens' rights and democratic representation for those in the North.  Have there been any conversations around the shape that might take in coming years in terms of having that voice heard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.82" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#J00300"><p>From tomorrow, if our understanding is right, we will see a set of proposals from the Commission that will address a number of these issues so that they will be better informed and engaged through the process.  At a political level, the Taoiseach, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and so on, are constantly engaged with the parties in Northern Ireland, and not just the parties but also civic society, and business groups to make sure that what we are hearing also feeds into the Commission in the work we spoke of earlier, ensuring that the Commission is aware of what we are hearing on the ground.</p> <p>  Much of this not only falls on the Commission and the EU side; the UK can also decide how it will engage and bring certain elements of Northern Ireland, whether politics or civic society, into the debate as well.  It is not purely an issue for the EU to solve, the UK also has capacity to do it. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#J00400"><p>Absolutely, we would certainly agree on that.  I have one final question on the dispute resolution mechanisms, around the arbitration panels, how they are selected and comprised and how it is agreed between the parties to the withdrawal agreement and trade and cooperation agreement, TCA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.84" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maeve Collins" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#J00500"><p>I will hand over to Ms Farrell for more detail but in the case of the Irish person who is on the panel, quite a detailed selection process was undergone.  There was a list of candidates all of whom had to be qualified and eligible to hold the highest judicial office in the land, so they all had a detailed legal background.  An assessment panel was then set up which included senior officials from the Departments of Foreign Affairs and the Taoiseach and from the Office of the Attorney General.  It reviewed the CVs, publications and track records of the candidates and finally put forward two candidates, one of whom was agreed in Brussels as a suitable candidate for this panel.  My assumption is that other member states followed quite a similar process.  From the Irish perspective, it has the potential to be a very important role indeed so it was crucial to have a very rigorous assessment process of the person's professional and technical abilities and qualifications.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Deirdre Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#J00600"><p>Just to add, that was the arbitration panel for the withdrawal agreement which includes the protocol but the process is still under way for the arbitration panel for the TCA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00100"><p>Is that a similar process for us domestically and beyond?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Deirdre Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00200"><p>If I recall correctly, the European Commission runs the process in a similar way to free trade agreements and other international agreements.  The process is run centrally from Brussels and not so much with a nomination process that we went through for the withdrawal agreement.  That is why it is managed centrally from Brussels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00300"><p>Is there one or more Irish applicant?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.89" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Deirdre Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00400"><p>The process is run centrally through the Commission without, quite rightly, oversight or involvement from member states.  We have no information and the process is still under way.  We hope to shortly hear who the nominees are on the EU side and, hopefully, we will then have agreement with the UK to have that panel set up and ready to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.90" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Karl Gardner" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00500"><p>There was a call so Irish people could apply, if they so wished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.91" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Deirdre Farrell" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="00:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2021101200002#K00700"><p>This mechanism is of particular interest to me.  It has not gotten anywhere near the level of discussion other elements of the process have and yet we will have to live with these mechanisms for a very long time.  It is important that as Brexit slips off the agenda Ireland is still front and centre because we have the most to lose.  The mechanism is still in the process of being established and we will watch to see how things pan out.</p> <p>  Last July, this committee produced an interim report but we did not touch on this area.  I am very keen that we include this area in our final report before the end of the year because it is a crucial element of our work.</p> <p>  As no other members are offering and we cannot make contact with Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile, I thank Mr. Karl Gardner, Ms Maeve Collins and Mr. Deirdre Farrell from the Department of Foreign Affairs for coming here.  The clerk to the committee will forward a copy of our final report to them and we hope to publish the debate in December before we go into recess.  I wish Ms Collins the best of luck and wish everyone else the best of luck with their work.  It is going to be a busy few days and few weeks for everybody.  Obviously we hope that any issues are resolved and move forward to where we want them to be.</p> <p>  The date of the next meeting is Thursday, 14 October, and it will commence at 3 p.m. in the Seanad Chamber.  A further meeting will take place at 12 noon in Committee Room 4 on Tuesday, 19 October when we will meet officials from the Department of Health and the HSE to discuss the cross-border healthcare directive.  For the second hour of the meeting, we will have witnesses from Medicines for Ireland who will discuss the supply of medicines and medical devices post Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2021-10-12a.93" nospeaker="true" time="00:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 12.47 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 14 October 2021.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>