<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Pat Breen,* Deputy Seán Barrett, Deputy Ciarán Cannon, Senator Tom Sheahan. Deputy Pearse Doherty, Deputy Regina Doherty, Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly, Deputy Sean Fleming, Deputy Mary Lou McDonald, Deputy Michael McGrath, Deputy Kieran O'Donnell, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, Deputy Arthur Spring,</p><p>* In the absence of Deputy Tom Barry.</p><p>DEPUTY LIAM TWOMEY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 2.17 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100003#B00100">Business of Committee.</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100003#B00200"><p>The committee is in public session.  We have two separate items.  Session A concerns an update on issues pertaining to the liquidation of Setanta Insurance.  The purpose of session B will be to consider the following orders referred to this committee by the D&aacute;il: Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Effective Date for Certain Bodies) Order 2015; Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Exempted Public Bodies) Order 2015.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100003#B00300">Liquidation of Setanta Insurance: Progress report</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100003#B00400"><p>Setanta Insurance Company Ltd. went into liquidation in April 2014.  At the time of entering liquidation the company had approximately 75,000 policyholders.  There are currently just 1,800 claims still open.  As part of the liquidation process, all policies were cancelled by the end of May 2014.  The purpose of the meeting is to update the committee since our previous engagement on this topic and specifically to review progress related to claims and the liquidation process.</p>  <p>  I welcome the liquidator of Setanta Insurance Company Ltd, Mr. Paul Mercieca, who is based in Malta.  I thank him for taking the time and trouble to travel to Ireland and for his willingness to appear before the committee.  Mr. Mercieca is accompanied by his colleague, Dr. Matthew Bianchi.</p>  <p>  I welcome Mr. Sean Quigley, Accountant of the Courts of Justice.  Mr. Quigley is joined by his colleague, Ms Denise Mullins.  I welcome Mr. R&oacute;n&aacute;n Hession of the financial services division of the Department of Finance.  My Hession is accompanied by Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha.</p>  <p>  The format we will follow is that Mr. Hession, Mr. Mercieca and Mr. Quigley will make their opening remarks.  I ask them to be brief.  A question and answer session will allow matters to be clarified.</p>  <p>  I remind members, witnesses and those in the public Gallery that all mobile phones must be switched off.</p> <p>I advise the witnesses that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Finally, members are reminded of the long-standing ruling of the Chair to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/><br/>I ask Mr. Hession to make his opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.10" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100004#C00200"><p>I thank the Committee for the invitation to attend today to discuss Setanta Insurance.  My name is R&oacute;n&aacute;n Hession and I am a principal officer in the financial services division of the Department of Finance.  I am joined by Antoine Mac Donncha, head of the department's legal unit.</p>  <p>  In my opening statement I would like to outline for the committee the role of the Department in the Setanta process thus far and to explain the role of the Minister more generally in respect of the statutory framework for insurance compensation. </p>  <p>  The Minister's primary role in this situation relates to the statutory framework and funding arrangements for the Insurance Compensation Fund.  The Insurance Compensation Fund was established under the Insurance Act 1964.  The purposes of the Act are to establish the Insurance Compensation Fund to meet certain liabilities of insolvent insurers; to provide for the making of loans to the fund by the Minister; and to provide for contributions to the fund by insurers.  The fund is maintained and administered under the control of the President of the High Court acting through the Accountant of the Courts of Justice.  The Minister has no statutory role in the payments process or in the administration of the fund.  Section 5 of the Act provides that the Minister for Finance may, on the recommendation of the Central Bank, advance from the Central Fund to the Insurance Compensation Fund such sum as he thinks proper to enable payments out of the fund to be made expeditiously.  The funds provided by the Minister are in the form of a repayable loan.  Having regard to the potential calls on the fund, the existing reserves, and the expected insurance levy receipts, the Central Bank wrote to the Minister in January 2015 recommending that up to &euro;140 million will need to be advanced by the Minister to the fund this year.  As any potential calls related to Setanta could be met from existing reserves, this figure is required to cover calls by Quinn Insurance limited related to the disposal of its UK book, as announced earlier this year.  The Minister has agreed to make a repayable loan to the fund in respect of this amount. </p>  <p>  The Insurance Compensation Fund is, ultimately, funded by contributions from insurers.  The Insurance Act 1964, as amended, provides that the fund is funded by contributions from insurers who issue policies in respect of risks in the State, whether the insurers are based in Ireland or in another member state.  Under the Act, the Central Bank has responsibility for determining whether the fund requires financial support and the level of contribution to be paid to the fund by insurers.  The contribution may not exceed 2% of the aggregate of the gross premiums paid to each insurer for policies issued in respect of risks in the State.  A levy in accordance with section 6 of the Act came into effect on 1 January 2012.  The Central Bank has set the levy at the maximum 2% of the aggregate of the gross premiums paid.  The levy is payable quarterly in arrears to the Revenue Commissioners, which has responsibility for its collection, and it transfer the proceeds of the levy to the Insurance Compensation Fund account. </p>  <p>  Under section 2, the Accountant of the Courts of Justice is required to submit an abstract of the fund&rsquo;s accounts and a report of the administration of the fund to the Minister, which the Minister must publish and lay before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  The most recent published accounts relate to 2013.  They show a total owing to the Minister for Finance of some &euro;986.9 million, of which &euro;197.8 million was issued in 2013, and they show insurance levies for that year of some &euro;64.7 million.  The accounts also show outstanding amounts owed to the fund from companies placed into administration previously: Icarom, which is formerly the Insurance Corporation of Ireland, &euro;164 million; Primor, formerly PMPA, &euro;139 million; and Quinn Insurance, &euro;1.158 billion.  I am advised that the current balance in the fund is some &euro;96 million. </p>  <p>  Having set out the Minister's role under the statutory framework, I will now explain the Department's role in Setanta thus far.  On 16 January 2014 the Central Bank first wrote to the Department alerting it to the concerns about the solvency margin of Setanta Insurance and advising that a potential call on the Insurance Compensation Fund could arise.  On the same day the Maltese Financial Services Authority directed Setanta to cease writing new business.  On 16 April, the Maltese regulator informed the Central Bank that Setanta had handed back its licence after the shareholders had resolved to wind up the company.  At that stage, the Department's understanding was that claims that were not honoured by Setanta could be submitted to the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland (MIBI).  On 30 April 2014 a liquidator was formally appointed to Setanta Insurance.  The Department met with the liquidator's representative in Ireland and with the liquidator himself within a week of their appointment.  At that time, the Department of Finance also held meetings with senior officials in the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport and the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland. </p>  <p>  I should explain that the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland was established in 1955 for the purpose of compensating victims of road traffic accidents caused by uninsured and unidentified vehicles.  It operates under a written agreement dated 29 January 2009 between companies underwriting motor insurance in Ireland and the Minister for Transport.  The Minister for Finance is not party to the agreement and has no responsibility in respect of MIBI or the agreement.  On 23 July 2014, MIBI advised the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport that it had obtained legal advice from which it had concluded that the 2009 agreement with the Minister for Transport does not require MIBI to satisfy awards against drivers covered by a policy of insurance where the insurer is unable to pay all or part of an award because of insolvency.  On 25 July, the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport and the Department of Finance jointly sought the advice of the Attorney General on the question of any MIBI liability.  On 1 September 2014, the Attorney General&rsquo;s advice was received, on foot of which the Minister for Finance decided to proceed on the basis that MIBI will not be playing a role in compensating claimants due awards under Setanta policies.  On foot of this, the Department of Finance met with the liquidator and the Courts Service regarding the arrangements for processing of payments by the Insurance Compensation Fund.  Based on the information available, the liquidator stated that it was not likely that he would be in a position to meet more than 30% of the insurance claims out of the assets in the liquidation.  Therefore, on the basis that the ICF may only pay out up to a maximum of 65% on an eligible individual claim, the question of the possibility of advance payments of 65% on eligible claims to the ICF was examined by the Accountant.  The Accountant obtained clarification on this question.  He informed the Department that, having considered legal advice on the operation of the legislation, he was satisfied that it was appropriate to make applications to the President of the High Court for approval to release monies from the ICF for compensation, prior to completion of the liquidation of the company.  Any payment from the ICF would be a once-off and final payment.  The State Claims Agency was engaged to provide support to the Accountant in terms of (i) the necessary expertise to ensure that only valid claims would be paid out of the ICF and (ii) administrative support required to deal with the volume of work arising from the Setanta case.  At that time, the liquidator advised that he was aiming to make application to the ICF for outstanding claims early in the New Year 2015 in respect of the following categories of claims: claims where settlements have been agreed between Setanta and the claimant; claims where the Personal Injuries Assessment Board has issued orders to pay that have been accepted by Setanta and the claimant; and claims that have been subject to court awards.  The Accountant advised at that stage that he was aiming to make an application in respect of this first batch of 300 claims to the President of the High Court before end of March 2015. </p>  <p>  On 26 March 2015, the Minister for Finance received a letter from solicitors acting for the Accountant of the Courts of Justice.  The letter states that prior to making any application to the High Court for payment out of the Insurance Compensation Fund pursuant to the Insurance Act 1964, the Accountant must be satisfied that it appears unlikely that the relevant claim can be met otherwise than from the Fund.  On foot of legal advice, the Accountant has decided to make an application by way of special summons to the High Court, pursuant to Order 3, Rule 22 of the rules of the superior courts, for a trial of an issue of law to determine whether the MIBI is liable for claims made under policies issued by Setanta.  The letter emphasises that the Accountant is anxious that this issue of law be determined without delay with a view to providing certainty to affected Setanta policy holders as soon as possible.  We have been further advised that the direction of the High Court is being sought as to the appropriate parties to the trial of this issue, which may include the Minister for Finance. </p>  <p>  Obviously this impending trial limits what I can say today about any issues that may be relevant to the forthcoming judicial consideration of this matter.  However, I will endeavour to be as helpful as I can to the Committee within that constraint.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100004#C00300"><p>I thank Mr. Hession.  I ask Mr. Mercieca to make his opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.12" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100004#C00400"><p>I thank the committee for inviting me to this meeting which I gladly accepted because I feel and hope that the presence of me and my team will be of assistance to this committee.  I also hope that my presence will help facilitate an early resolution to the process of dealing with claims.</p> <p>To give some background on the company, it was incorporated on 21 June 2007 in Malta and was regulated and supervised by the Malta Financial Services Authority, MFSA.  The company was authorised to write the following classes of insurance business: accident, land vehicles, goods in transit, motor vehicle liability, miscellaneous financial loss and legal expenses.  The company was also authorised to sell private and commercial motor vehicle policies in Ireland in exercise of its European passport right as an insurance undertaking to provide services in terms of the relevant EU legislation and directives.  Accordingly, since 2007 the company carried out its business from its offices in Dublin.</p> <p> On 23 January 2014 the board of directors resolved that, save in the case of receiving funds, the company would cease writing any new business, and offer renewals beyond the close of business on 24 January 2014.  As a consequence, at an extraordinary general meeting of Setanta held on 16 April 2014, it was resolved that the company surrenders its insurance business licence to the MFSA and be immediately dissolved.  Furthermore, at a meeting of the creditors of the company held on 30 April 2014, I was appointed liquidator of the company.  The liquidation is a creditors voluntary liquidation under the provisions of the Maltese Companies Act 1995 and is, I am advised, similar to a creditors voluntary liquidation under the Irish Companies Act.</p> <p> The situation I found on liquidation was that the statement of affairs drawn up by the company as at 16 April 2014 showed a deficiency, meaning net liabilities exceeding assets, slightly in excess of &euro;17 million.  The outstanding claims reserve included in the statement of affairs was &euro;28 million.  This reserve is the provision for claims that have not been paid and should include provisions both for claims which had been notified to the company and for claims which had occurred but which had not been notified to the company.  At the time of being placed in liquidation, the company had approximately 75,000 policyholders, approximately two thirds of which were commercial vehicle policies and approximately one third being private motor insurance policies.</p> <p> Policyholders were immediately advised of the liquidation by means of the company website and notices in two national daily newspapers in Ireland.  They were advised that their policies would be cancelled in due course and advised to take out new policies with immediate effect.  All insurance policies were subsequently cancelled on 26 May 2014 with respect to private vehicles and 29 May 2014 with respect to commercial vehicles.  The cancellation was considered to be in the best interest of policyholders in order to avoid a situation where policyholders would continue to drive vehicles insured by the company in circumstances where their claims will not be paid in full.</p> <p> I have appointed Deloitte Malta to perform a review of certain procedures and decisions on the transactions undertaken by the company in the six month period leading up to the liquidation of the company.  This review is to be carried out in connection with the requirements of the relevant provisos of the Maltese Companies Act 1995.  This review has been hampered due to the fact that details of the majority of the ultimate beneficial shareholders are not publically available as the shareholdings are registered in the names of licensed trustees and-or nominees.  Accordingly, an application has now been made to the relevant Maltese courts to obtain the names of the ultimate beneficial shareholders from the trustees and-or nominees holding the shares and from the MFSA.  Furthermore, Deloitte Malta has been asked to perform a review of the business to assist me in obtaining an understanding of the circumstances that brought about the failure of the company.  On the basis of the draft report provided to me by Deloitte Malta, I have engaged a lawyer to review the company&rsquo;s records and relevant documentation to establish whether, in his opinion, there are grounds to suggest an action could be brought against the persons responsible for running the company.  This review is currently ongoing and I am due to have a preliminary meeting with the lawyers next week on this matter.</p> <p> Upon my appointment as liquidator of the company, I proceeded with appointing the actuaries Towers Watson to review and assess the claims position and to report such assessment of the claims reserve.  Towers Watson presented its report on 3 September 2014 and subsequently issued the final report on 16 September 2014.  The report comprises an analysis of the unpaid reserves, estimates of the liability for outstanding claims at 31 May 2014 together with a valuation of the volatility of the estimate.  The report estimates the gross claim liability at &euro;67.7 million on the assumption that the claims run off is paid in line with normal circumstances.  The report further concludes that additional reserves of between &euro;20 million and &euro;27.5 million represent a reasonable estimate of the adverse development potential on future gross unpaid claims as a consequence of the company&rsquo;s liquidation.  Accordingly, the total provision for claims is estimated at between &euro;87.7 million and &euro;95.2 million.</p> <p> I will provide some information on where we are today.  In active claims, on my appointment on 16 April 2014, there were 1,669 claims, which has increased by 79 to 1,748 last week.  There are 1,037 personal injury claims and 711 damage to property claims.  Out of these claims, 1,265 are eligible for payment from the fund and 483 are not.  The claims estimate I referred to in the statement of affairs was &euro;28 million, which has increased to &euro;53 million as of 24 March.  This means it has almost doubled, increasing by &euro;25 million.  The basis of estimating liability for claims by the company is still based on the assumption that claims run-off is paid in line with normal circumstances and does not include any provision for adverse development potential arising as a consequence of both normal random variations in claim costs and from the impact of the company&rsquo;s liquidation.  It is pertinent to point out that, even on this basis, claims have already increased by &euro;25 million from the date of liquidation.  I have appointed Arthur Cox as my legal advisers in Ireland and the firm is co-ordinating all the court cases involving the company and liaising with other lawyers handling our cases.</p> <p> There has been an increase of 201 active cases since the company's liquidation in April 2014, taking it to 619 cases.  I have prepared an estimated outcomes statement on the assumption that the liquidation process will take at least another three years to conclude.  I have also taken in to account the actuarial report available to me in terms of the potential claims liability and the assets available.  Based on the above, I estimate that the amount available to creditors having insurance claims on the final liquidation of the company will not exceed 30% of the amounts due to them.  I must emphasise that this is a best estimate and the estimate could change materially as circumstances change.</p> <p> On the insurance compensation fund, discussions have been ongoing with the Department of Finance and, in particular, the accountant of the courts of justice since I met his representatives on 3 September 2014 about accessing the insurance compensation fund in Ireland.  As it is the prerogative of the accountant of the courts of justice to apply to the court for access to the compensation fund, I have been working closely with him through my representative in Ireland to facilitate this process in every way possible.  Indeed, there has been a high level of co-operation between all concerned in dealing with what is a very complex issue.  I have submitted a preliminary list of claims to the accountant of the courts of justice who retained the Irish State Claims Agency to review those claims. I understand that the agency has confirmed that the claims are suitable for submission to the compensation fund.  While I have been informed that the accountant of the courts of justice had received advice that the MIBI had no role to play in compensating claimants, I understand that a contrary legal opinion has been received recently from his solicitors.  Until this matter is resolved the accountant of the courts of justice is reluctant to submit the relevant application to the Irish courts for access to the compensation fund.  While, as liquidator, I am entitled to seek access to the compensation fund, I am advised that I have no direct right of recourse to the MIBI.  Recent developments have unfortunately created a situation of uncertainty, which hopefully will be resolved speedily for the benefit of all concerned, and most especially the claimants.  I consider the positive resolution of this matter to be fundamental in unlocking the claims situation and therefore speeding up the liquidation process.</p> <p>I am also advised that the equivalent compensation scheme in Malta is not available for claims against the company made by any of its policyholders and claimants.</p> <p> I am obliged to hold a creditors meeting by July 2015 at which I shall present an account of my actions and dealings in winding up the company, together with a summary of receipts and payments.  It is my intention to hold this meeting in June this year.</p> <p> It is not possible, unfortunately, to make an accurate prediction as to how long the liquidation proceedings will take as there are too many variables at this point, many of which are out of my control.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100006#E00200"><p>I thank the Chairman and members of the committee for the invitation to attend the meeting and brief the committee on the operation of the Insurance Compensation Fund, with particular reference to Setanta Insurance Company.  I am joined by Ms Denise Mullins from the accountant's office.  I am conscious of the time constraints so I will keep my opening statement as brief as possible.  However, I wish to take the opportunity to briefly outline the background to the fund, how it operates and some significant activity in managing the fund, particularly since 2011.  I will also update the committee on the current position regarding the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland, MIBI, relating to Setanta Insurance.<br/><br/>The Insurance Compensation Fund was established under the Insurance Act 1964 to make arrangements to meet certain liabilities of insolvent insurers.  The fund is maintained and administered under the control of the President of the High Court acting through myself, the Accountant of the Courts of Justice.  Amounts are paid from the fund, with the approval of the High Court, to a person in relation to an insurer in liquidation or administration, in respect of claims under policies issued by the insolvent insurer in circumstances where it seems unlikely that the claims can be met otherwise.  In regard to claims for companies in liquidation, all payments are subject to a limit of 65% of the amount of the claim or &euro;825,000, whichever is the lesser.  The fund will also pay the full amount of legal and other costs necessarily and reasonably incurred by the person endeavouring to secure payment from the fund.<br/><br/>As was stated earlier, the Minister for Finance puts the Insurance Compensation Fund in funds where there are insufficient moneys to pay out.  From October 2011 to the end of December 2014, the State has advanced a net<b></b>&euro;833.3 million to the Insurance Compensation Fund.  The total interest charged by the Minister for Finance on amounts advanced during this period amounted to &euro;80,390,482.  The closing balance on the loan from the Minister for Finance to the fund at the end of December 2014 was &euro;913,690,482.  The current balance on the Insurance Compensation Fund is<b></b>&euro;96 million.<br/><br/>A levy was introduced in 2012 and &euro;190.3 million has been paid into the fund by the Revenue Commissioners in respect of that levy up to the end of December 2014.  I provide an annual statement on the fund to the Department of Finance and the Central Bank.<br/><br/>Furthermore, the Accountant of the Courts of Justice is, in respect of any amount paid out of the fund, a creditor of the insolvent insurer which has received the funds.  The total creditors of the fund at 31 December 2014 amounted to<b></b>&euro;1.361 billion.  The details of that have been provided to the committee.<br/><br/>To focus on some of the activity since 2011, since the introduction of the Insurance (Amendment) Act 2011 there has been significant activity for the accountant&rsquo;s office in managing the fund.  I will give a brief summary of the main areas of activity.<br/><br/>In March 2010, by order of the High Court following an application by the Financial Regulator, joint administrators were appointed to Quinn Insurance Limited, QIL.  Between November 2011 and December 2014 the fund made nine payments amounting to &euro;1.158 billion to the Quinn Insurance administrators.  In 2014, the fund received &euro;100 million back, which was forwarded to the Department of Finance as part repayment of the loan.  The net payments to Quinn Insurance administrators have amounted to &euro;1.058 billion to date.  The last payment to Quinn Insurance was in November 2013, which was &euro;40 million, at which time the President of the High Court set a limit of &euro;1.158 billion<b></b>on the amount that would be paid to Quinn Insurance administrators.<br/><br/>Another claim on the fund arose in respect of Lemma Europe Insurance Company Ltd., in liquidation.  Lemma Europe Insurance Company Ltd. is a Gibraltar registered company and the Supreme Court of Gibraltar ordered its winding-up on 24 January 2013.  In November 2013, a claimant against Lemma Europe Insurance Company wrote to my office making an application to the fund.  Our legal advisers reviewed this claim and were satisfied that it was valid.  I subsequently made an application to the High Court in July 2014 to pay out 65% of the total claim.  The amount that was paid was &euro;29,166.  The Lemma Europe Insurance Company liquidator has indicated that there are potentially 14 other claims.  However, these claims have not been settled and we are not in a position to give a value for these potential claims.  One distinction between Lemma Europe Insurance Company and Setanta Insurance is that the former did not issue motor insurance policies.<br/><br/>As the committee is aware, Setanta Insurance went into liquidation in April 2014.  It was a Maltese incorporated company.  While this company was based and regulated in Malta, all of its policies covered motor insurance risks in the Republic of Ireland.  Following Setanta Insurance going into liquidation in April 2014, the Office of the Accountant of the Courts of Justice has had significant engagement with the Department of Finance and the liquidator through his representatives in Dublin.  There were a number of legal and administrative issues to be resolved, which also required extensive engagement with our own legal advisers.  This was the first time we had to deal with an insurer in liquidation on this scale and the first time we had to deal with one that was registered in another EU state.  The processes are different compared with an insurer in liquidation registered in the State.  The essential differences are, first, it is the accountant and not the liquidator who makes application to the fund and, second, claims on the fund can only be made very six months.<br/><br/>The Setanta Insurance liquidator indicated at an early stage that there would be a significant shortfall between the funds available from the liquidation and the value of the claims.  The available funds after liquidation would not exceed 30%.  On this basis, given the cap on the payment that can be paid from the Insurance Compensation Fund of 65%, as the Accountant of the Courts of Justice, I decided to facilitate the processing of payments from the fund as soon as possible, and therefore it was agreed to make advance applications to the fund before the liquidation process was completed.  The liquidator had advised that settlements could only be paid out by him after all of the company's liabilities were quantified, including claims.<br/><br/>The legislation provides for the recovery of amounts that, in the aggregate, exceed a sum due to claimants from an insurer in liquidation in respect of a risk situate in the State.  These provisions and penalties give me, as the accountant, sufficient comfort should a situation arise where an overpayment is made.  I will only make an application to the President of the High Court where I am satisfied that claims qualify under the provisions of the applicable legislation.  To ensure this is the case, we have been working closely with the liquidator of Setanta Insurance to identify eligible claimants in accordance with the Insurance Act 1964, as amended.  I am also pleased to inform the committee that the State Claims Agency agreed to my request to provide expert advice and input that was not available within my office to validate claims before they are brought forward to the High Court. <br/><br/>The accountant's office had all of the necessary arrangements in place to deal with Setanta Insurance claims by the end of December 2014 and it was expected that the first tranche of claims would be submitted to the High Court in the first quarter of 2015.  The first tranche of claims reviewed by the State Claims Agency on my behalf included 189 claims with a value of some &euro;4 million, together with legal costs of approximately &euro;132,000.<br/><br/>There was one other matter we had to deal with in respect of the Insurance Compensation Fund in recent years.  This was a judicial review relating to an insurer, Independent Insurance Company Ltd., a UK insurer that had gone into liquidation in 2001.  I refused an application for payment from the fund, as the liquidation occurred before the introduction of the Insurance (Amendment) Act 2011 and, as such, the claimant was not deemed eligible under the provisions of the Act.  The claimant did not agree with this decision and initiated judicial review proceeding against the Accountant of the Courts of Justice.  This matter came to court in July 2014 and the position taken by the accountant was upheld. <br/><br/>Finally, I will address the issue of the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland, MIBI, in relation to Setanta Insurance.  The issue of the possible liability of MIBI for claims from policy holders arising from the Setanta Insurance liquidation was raised with me at meetings in the Department of Finance in August and September 2014.  I was advised that MIBI was not liable.  This was confirmed in an e-mail dated 29 September 2014 from the Department of Finance.  I was informed that this position was based on the advice of the Attorney General.  While I did not receive a copy of the Attorney General&rsquo;s advice, details of the key points considered by the Attorney General in arriving at the decision were provided to me by the Department.  At that stage, taking account of the Attorney General&rsquo;s advice, I had no reason to believe that MIBI was liable for Setanta Insurance claims.<br/><br/>I then proceeded, as a matter of priority, to address the legal and administrative issues that had to be resolved to enable claims to be made on the fund.</p> <p>As I mentioned, we had all the necessary arrangements in place to deal with claims in December 2014.  In late January 2015 the President of the High Court received representations from the Law Society expressing serious concerns regarding the exclusion of the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland, MIBI, from the process of dealing with Setanta claims.  Having immediately reviewed the matter with the President of the High Court it was agreed that the matter needed to be resolved, in the interests of protecting tax payers&rsquo; money, before we could proceed to make any payments from the fund.  As you will appreciate, the President as the person who controls the fund, needed to be satisfied that any payments made from the fund complied with the legislation.  I immediately sought senior counsel opinion on the matter. That opinion was received on Thursday, 19 March 2015.  While I cannot disclose details of the opinion I can give the committee an extract from it:<blockquote><br /><br />I believe there is an arguable case that the MIBI could have a liability in respect of Setanta claims. It would be incumbent upon the Accountant, and ultimately the Court, to ensure that before payments can be made out of the fund, a view is formed as to whether it is unlikely that the relevant claims can be met by the MIBI before approving payments from the fund. I do not believe that the Accountant or the Court can be satisfied of that without having the issue judicially determined.</blockquote>Arising out of that,  since Thursday, 19 March 2015 I have been actively engaging with my legal advisers to progress the matter of having the issue judicially determined as soon as possible.  The President of the High Court has indicated to me that this matter will get priority in terms of scheduling of hearings. It is hoped that it can be concluded by July 2015.  On Thursday, 26 March 2015, my legal advisers wrote to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, the Minister for Finance, the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland, and the Attorney General regarding the matter.  The letter indicated that I, as the accountant of the Courts of Justice, would be making an application by way of a special summons to the High Court, pursuant to Order 3, Rule 22 of the Rules of the Superior Courts, for a trial of an issue of law to determine whether the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland is liable for claims made under the Setanta policies.  My legal advisers are currently finalising this application to the High Court and I expect it will be filed during the first week of the next law term, which is the week beginning Monday, 13 April 2015.  As of this morning I have agreed the wording of the special summons, an affidavit with my legal advisers, and this will be filed very shortly with the central office in the High Court.  That is a very brief overview of what is a large and complex matter and I am happy to take any questions from the members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00200"><p>Thank you Mr. Quigley.  Deputy McGrath it is very detailed so could you just try to limit it to questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00300"><p>Thank you Chair.  I welcome all the witnesses and thank them for their time and for their opening statements.  It certainly is a complex issue.  It is something of a mess at the moment and there is obviously quite a legal wrangle going on which is going to have an impact in terms of the liquidation and the way that claimants will be dealt with as part of this process.  First I will go through some of the issues with the liquidator Mr. Mercieca.  The statement of  affairs which the company prepared initially in April of last year, showed a deficiency of about &euro;17 million.  If we go forward to page three of his statement the picture seems to have changed considerably with the outstanding claims reserve at &euro;28 million.  Does Mr. Mercieca have an estimate now, in terms of liabilities versus assets, of what the deficiency is likely to be compared to the estimate of &euro;17 million almost a year ago?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00400"><p>As I said in the report, the estimates outcome statement predicts a 30% maximum repayment to insurance creditors.  That is based on the actuarial report from Towers Watson which took the claims reserve up to the figures I mentioned earlier.  In terms of the actual claims we have today I also mention the projection of a &euro;25 million increase in claims estimate, based on the latest information available to me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00500"><p>The information given to this committee, I believe by the Department or Central Bank in July 2014, was that there were in the region of 2000 claimants with claims amounting to &euro;35 million. Does that &euro;35 million now equate to the gross claim liability of &euro;67.7 million?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.21" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00600"><p>That &euro;67 million is an estimate of the projected claims and development of those claims, based on an  industry standard as prepared by Towers Watson.  I am not sure what that figure is you mention but the current claims estimate is at &euro;53 million.  That is what the company is reserving today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00700"><p>53?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.23" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00800"><p>&euro;53 million, which is the equivalent of the &euro;28 million stated by the directors in their statement of affairs.  In 11 months, as I explained, that has gone up by &euro;25 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F00900"><p>Can the witness reconcile that &euro;53 million with the gross claim liability of &euro;68 million?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01000"><p>On Wednesday, 16 April 2014 when Setanta went into liquidation the statement of affairs, prepared by the company directors at the time, had a claims reserve, including the initial &euro;17 million, of &euro;28 million.  As of Tuesday, 24 March 2015, this is increased to &euro;53 million, an increase of &euro;25 million.  Towers Watson reported to me in May 2014 that it projected this could go all the way up to &euro;67.7 million with a further &euro;20 million or so in terms of further deterioration.  But we have not got to that figure, that is the projected figure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01100"><p>Okay. But the witness has to plan on the basis that this is a possibility -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01200"><p>One can see that in 11 months it has already increased by &euro;25 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01300"><p>Yes, but the scale of the claims reserve increase could be from &euro;28 million one year ago to a figure of potentially over &euro;90 million, if Towers Watson's worse case scenario comes to pass?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01400"><p>Exactly.  I will be re-engaging Towers Watson to look at those figures again in April 2015, when I am obliged to prepare the statutory accounts, to see if that figure, in its opinion, could change either way.  There will be an update on that figure as we go forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01500"><p>But it is fair to say that the picture has deteriorated considerably since the witness's appointment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01700"><p>The claims reserve may have gone up from &euro;28 million to as high as &euro;95.2 million, if Towers Watson is correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01800"><p>It could reach that figure yes, if Towers Watson proves to be right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F01900"><p>Is it correct that the witness has 1,748 Irish claims on the books?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02100"><p>Have any payments been made to any claimants so far?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02200"><p>None at all?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02300"><p>None whatsoever?  The witness estimates that 30% of the value of the outstanding claims will be met?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02400"><p>Of the value, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02500"><p>Does that hold true even if the total claims liability reaches &euro;90 million?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.41" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02600"><p>It is based on that figure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02700"><p>What is preventing the witness from commencing the process of making payments in respect of claims which are agreed?  Where a settlement is agreed, why can the witness not pay the estimate of 30%?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.43" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02800"><p>By law I am not allowed to make payments until I know the full extent of my liabilities, which I do not know at this point in time, if nothing else because there are 600 court cases still in progress and cases are still developing.  Until I know the full extent of my liabilities I am not permitted by law to make out any payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F02900"><p>But the witness will not know the full extent of the liabilities until each and every case is concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F03000"><p>Essentially, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F03100"><p>That could take years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F03200"><p>That is why the resolution of the issue we talked about earlier today is fundamental to unlock the claims situation.  The situation today is that we cannot actually sit down with anybody and settle a claim.  For arguments sake, if someone has a claim for &euro;10,000 and if I sit down with him or her to say " I do not know how much I am going to pay you and I do not know when I am going to pay you," then I believe the chances of reaching agreement are remote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F03300"><p>Can I clarify that if the legal issue surrounding the potential liability of the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland is clarified, the liquidator will still be unable to make payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100007#F03400"><p>If the fund is able to make payments up to 65% in the circumstances where they can make payments, then we will be able to sit down with claimants and say that potentially "you can get so much from the fund, there is a balance of 30% or 35% of your claim due".</p> <p>There is more chance of unlocking the situation and reaching agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00200"><p>Okay.  I suppose what Mr. Mercieca is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.52" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00300"><p>I apologise for interrupting, but this is fundamental in not letting the situation deteriorate further.  The longer it takes, there will be more court cases and higher costs.  It will not be in anyone's interests.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00400"><p>I can see that and am coming to the issue among others, but I am unclear.  A few moments ago, Mr. Mercieca stated that he could not make any payment until the full extent of the liability had been clarified.  It will not be clarified until 1,619 cases have been concluded.  Even if the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland, MIBI, legal issue is concluded, is Mr. Mercieca saying that he is prohibited under Maltese law from making payments until he has complete clarity on the extent of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.54" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00500"><p>Yes.  It is a provision in the Companies Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00600"><p>In Malta.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00700"><p>Yes.  Dr. Bianchi might wish to expand on this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.57" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Matthew Bianchi" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00800"><p>It is the nature of a liquidation process that everyone is paid the same percentage of his or her claim.  One cannot give someone more than someone else in percentage terms.  One must wait to identify the entire payment that must be made and then given everyone the same percentage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G00900"><p>Pro rata.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.59" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Matthew Bianchi" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01100"><p>Will any claimant receive money from the liquidator as opposed to the Insurance Compensation Fund, ICF, and the MIBI until after all of the court cases have been concluded?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01200"><p>No.  The Deputy is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01300"><p>Mr. Mercieca has no discretion in that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.63" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01400"><p>Absolutely none.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01500"><p>It is provided for in Maltese law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01600"><p>There is no discretion.  That is the law.  That is what one must stick to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01700"><p>On the potential role of the MIBI, it is clear that the initial advice from the Attorney General sits alongside alternative advice that the accountant has received and at the very least puts a question mark over the Attorney General's advice.  Having read the extract from the senior counsel's opinion that the Courts Service received and given the mandate within which Mr. Quigley must work, I accept that the service must exhaust the issue and get a final determination on the liability of the MIBI before it can make a payment.  What are the consequences for the fund or its role if the MIBI is found in law to have a liability?  How would it relate to the as much as 65% liability of the ICF?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01800"><p>I must be careful about an issue that is to be determined by the courts.  That may well be one of the issues that will be determined by the courts, but if we operate on the basis that the ICF is a payer of last resort and if the MIBI has a liability, the ICF could possibly not get involved.  I have to be careful in what I say, because this matter will be before the courts shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G01900"><p>If the finding is that the MIBI does not have a liability, can Mr. Quigley proceed with his application to the High Court and can the ICF pay out ahead of any payment from the liquidator to claimants?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02000"><p>Yes.  If the ruling is that the MIBI does not have a liability, the process on which we were already working will be recommenced.  We will proceed to make payments on eligible claims that are brought forward by the liquidator from the fund.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02100"><p>I will revert in a minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02200"><p>I have two questions to ask before moving on.  Has Mr. Mercieca identified who the shareholders are and what are their responsibilities in the collapse?  Who had supervisory responsibility?  What supervision of Setanta Insurance was there?  Mr. Mercieca might answer before I invite Deputy Regina Doherty to contribute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.72" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02300"><p>The answer to the first part of the question is that we have not yet established the beneficial shareholders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02400"><p>A year later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.74" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02500"><p>We have not yet established who they are.  We have applied to the courts because most of the shareholdings are registered in the names of nominees and trustees.  We have applied to the courts for those nominees and trustees and the Malta Financial Services Authority, MFSA, to divulge to us who the beneficial shareholders are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02600"><p>To which courts has Mr. Mercieca applied?  The Irish courts?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.76" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02700"><p>The Maltese courts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02800"><p>But most of the shareholders are supposedly domiciled in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.78" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G02900"><p>I would not know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.79" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03000"><p>It is a Maltese company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.80" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03100"><p>Yes.  If one looks at-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03200"><p>We know nothing about the shareholders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.82" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03300"><p>My recollection, which I can correct from my notes, is that the report from the Maltese regulator that was provided to the committee in July identified some of the key players involved, but a substantial amount of the shareholding was in the name of a company or trust of sorts.  The net issue is who is behind that.  This is the basis for the liquidator's application or legal work to get the courts to release those names.</p>  <p>  On the second part of the Chairman's question relating to who was responsible for supervising, the regulatory authority involved was the MFSA.  The way that the regulatory system across Europe works is that firms can get authorised in one country by their home regulator and sell business on a passporting basis into other jurisdictions.  Setanta Insurance was authorised in Malta.  Therefore, the MFSA was its home regulator.  The Central Bank was what is called a host regulator, that is, it dealt with conduct-of-business issues, the consumer interface, etc.  As to the financial position, the lead supervisor was the MFSA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03400"><p>We will revert to this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03500"><p>It is a pity that the lead regulator is not present to discuss the matter with us.  The questions so far have kept coming back to it.</p>  <p>  I have two questions.  I welcome our witnesses and thank them for attending, particularly the two gentlemen who have travelled.  The directors who prepared the statement of means in April arising from the &euro;28 million have all left.  Were any of them shareholders?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03600"><p>I cannot answer as to whether any of them was a shareholder, as I do not have a list of shareholders.  To be technical, I have one shareholder.  It is a holding company called Setanta Holdings Limited, but I am talking about knowing the shareholders in that.  As to whether the directors are gone, their powers ceased upon the company being placed in liquidation.  It is not a question of whether they are gone.  Their involvement ceased on that date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03700"><p>Their powers were well established before 16 April, unfortunately.  I did not mean that they might continue to have power, but they have information that is relevant to Mr. Mercieca's work.  He does not know whether they were shareholders even though they were directors.  Does the regulator know whether they were shareholders?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03800"><p>I believe that the regulator has a list of shareholders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G03900"><p>But he has not shared that list with Mr. Mercieca.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.89" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04000"><p>He is prohibited from doing so by law.  That is why I have applied to the court to get it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04100"><p>It seems bonkers.  What changed between the original statement of &euro;28 million in claims right up to the &euro;53 million or potential &euro;92 million in claims today?  Did the directors give Mr. Mercieca false information in April 2014 or have other claims come out of the woodwork of which they were not aware at the time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.91" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04200"><p>It is a combination of things.  There have been 79 new claims.  There has been a deterioration in the claims that existed, in other words, developments in those claims.  New circumstances have come to light, requiring new provisioning, reserving and costing.  There are 200 odd new court cases, which require further provisioning.  This is the reason for the increase to &euro;53 million from &euro;28 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04300"><p>What behaviour gave Mr. Mercieca concerns enough to hire a body to investigate the actions that were taken before the liquidation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.93" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04400"><p>It is a liquidator's responsibility under any circumstance, particularly where a company is insolvent, to examine and understand what brought about that insolvency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04500"><p>Mr. Mercieca is saying that it was not obvious from the statement of means in recent years as to what caused the company to go under.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.95" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04600"><p>Not at this point.  That is why this review is being undertaken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100008#G04700"><p>I thank Mr. Mercieca.</p>  <p>  Turning to Mr. Hession and Mr. Quigley, are two arms of the State arguing with each other about which is responsible for paying or whether both are responsible?  Is this where the legal action is going?  According to the Department of Finance, the Attorney General has stated that the MIBI is not responsible whereas another arm of the State is suggesting that it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.97" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00100"><p>The Attorney General's advice is that MIBI, the Motor Insurance Bureau of Ireland, might not have role and that it might not be down to a State body but the insurers themselves as a private company.  Their own advice is that they are not responsible.</p>  <p>  The recent development arises from approaches from the Law Society. It has advice raising a question over the issue.  On foot of that, advice was sought by the Courts Service accountant that stated this needs to be resolved judicially.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00200"><p>The value of the insurance fund is &euro;96 million.  If the courts determine that the fund will not share the costs, is Mr. Quigley in a position to cover whatever the outstanding claims come to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.99" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00300"><p>If the court determines that the insurance compensation fund, ICF, is the only payee, then it is not a question of whether the &euro;96 million is sufficient because there could be other claims against that from any of the other parties and ones that we do not know about at this stage.  If the fund has a liability and sufficient funds are not available, the Minister, in consultation with the Central Bank, can then put extra funds into it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1075" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00400"><p>In a worst-case scenario, does Mr. Quigley envisage the fund will be able to fulfil the full value if the courts determine it to be the case?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.101" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00600"><p>This is sometimes a bit difficult to follow and a royal mess for those who have claims with Setanta Insurance.  The last thing they wanted to see was this ending up in the courts which will delay payment further.  I appreciate all involved are doing everything they can to resolve this, however.</p>  <p>  Given their experience in this case, what do the delegations believe needs to be done to ensure a mess of this nature is not created again?  I know it is a unique situation where an Irish company registered in Malta sold into the Irish market but went belly up.  Are there any proposals to ensure we are not in such a situation again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00700"><p>I am probably the person who has least impact in this.  Obviously, it is only through legislation that the courts - that is myself and the president - have a role.  It is a matter for the Minister and the Oireachtas to legislate for these situations.  I am probably least qualified to offer an observation on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.104" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00800"><p>There are several elements to this.  How does one ensure firms are run right in the first place?  How does one ensure regulators make sure the companies are run correctly?  If there is a problem, how does act on them early to ensure more than 30% of the company's assets are left for the liquidation process?  If things go wrong, how does one ensure the safety nets work and do what they are supposed to do?</p>  <p>  Change will kick in from January next year's with the solvency II directive, a major new directive in the insurance field.  There will be a new basis for capital requirements which will be more consistent across Europe.  These will be more risk-based and will be more robust, as everyone agrees they need to be.  There will also be an emphasis on qualitative aspects such as governance, a key issue which has been addressed upfront in other parts of the financial sector and has now been given more emphasis in the insurance sector.  There will be a greater emphasis on closer supervision across borders as there are many firms in the European market which sell insurance products across the Continent or are based in one country but selling them in another.  Group supervision will be much tighter and the level of overall co-operation between supervisors will be better.</p>  <p>  I have been in this committee room a few times over the past several years with the Minister for Finance discussing various regulatory reforms to enhance our own Central Bank&rsquo;s powers.  We have had several historical cases in Ireland of insurance companies failing.  Up to &euro;6.5 billion of state aid has been put into European insurers over the past six years according to the European Commission.  Ireland has the ICF and we have yet to find out what its role would be, if any, in this case.  The payments have only gone through the initial assessment phase before actually going through any pay-out phase from the ICF.</p>  <p>  Not every country has an insurance compensation fund.  There are only 11 in Europe.  In some of those, such as Germany and Poland, it is just for life assurance.  Ireland is one of the few countries that has a compensation fund which has been in place for the past 50 years.  This is a very difficult, complicated and unprecedented example which will test the ICF framework.  The Minister has asked the Department to review the framework and to report back as to whether it needs to be strengthened.  We will be doing this when there is greater clarity with the legal position concerning substantive insurance later this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H00900"><p>Mr. Hession spoke at length about the preventive arm of the framework to ensure that a company does not go belly up.  While we may be one of the unique countries to have an insurance fund, it is of little comfort at this point to claimants with Setanta Insurance because it is not clear as to who will meet their claims.  Maybe it is premature given legal clarity is required around certain issues but we need to streamline the system to ensure if something happens like this in the future that we will not be in a situation into the second year where the courts have to decide on key issues which we were told were resolved last year.</p>  <p>  Is it the delegations&rsquo; understanding that the MIBI got legal opinion itself on its own initiative to suggest that it should not be included in the scheme?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.106" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01000"><p>Yes, that is my understanding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01100"><p>Then the Government asked the Attorney General for her opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.108" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01200"><p>That is correct.  As a public servant myself, I had no reason to question that advice.  It was only when a third party, the Law Society, challenged that interpretation that we needed to get a senior counsel opinion.  This will result in having the matter determined for once and for all in the High Court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01300"><p>Will Mr. Quigley explain to me the process as to how this is determined?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.110" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01400"><p>There is a special summons which will be the trigger mechanism.  The first action the courts have to take is to determine who the parties to the case will be.  At this point, the Law Society has agreed that it will be bringing the argument concerning liability.  It will be a matter for the court to determine the four other parties which we have identified.  The Minister of Finance, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport and the Attorney General will decide how they will approach it.  I will not be a party; I will simply trigger the mechanism.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01500"><p>I presume the Department of Finance and the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport can decide not to be a party to this.  It would be financially beneficial to the State if the MIBI were subject to paying out on some of these claims.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.112" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100009#H01600"><p>That is a matter for the Department and other parties need to decide.</p> <p>Obviously, it will reduce the liability on the State from the ICF.  Would that not be so?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.114" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00200"><p>That is correct.  The High Court will determine who the parties are to be.  I would anticipate that MIBI will be taking the lead role in terms of any argument or opposition against the application from the Law Society because MIBI ultimately are the people who have got the most skin in that game.  It may be that the High Court will direct that any of the other potential parties would also be a party to it.  Our role is likely to be much more limited than the role that MIBI is going to take in that event.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.115" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00300"><p>Any money that the Minister, on behalf of the taxpayer, gives to the Insurance Compensation Fund is repayable to him.  Whatever the fund pays out, therefore, is ultimately recouped from the insurers and goes back to the Minister.  The Minister therefore gets his money back from the fund.  If MIBI pays out, that is also the insurers paying.  I want to clarify that it is not necessarily the case that the State is in or out of pocket.  Ultimately, the insurance companies are paying.  Of course, if the fund pays out, that will impact on its ability to repay the Minister and what sort of timeline it will repay it over, because it will be paying out more.  However, what the Minister gives the Insurance Compensation Fund is a repayable loan, so he gets that back in the final reckoning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00400"><p>Yes, but there are costs associated with that when one has to make big lump-sum payments and it affects borrowings.  One has to borrow the money if one does not have it lying around, so there are issues there.  Has there been a determination that the Minister will argue that MIBI would not be liable for this payment?  Has that decision been taken within the Department?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.117" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00500"><p>So far, the court has to determine whether the Minister for Finance is a party at all.  That has not yet been determined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00600"><p>Mr. Quigley can correct me if I am wrong, but he said he did not have access to the detail of the Attorney General's legal opinion.  Would that surprise him?  I know the legal opinion is only for the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00700"><p>No.  That did not surprise me but I was provided with sufficient detail, in terms of the matters that were considered by the Attorney General, to be satisfied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00800"><p>Without straying into the case, but on the generalities, if MIBI is liable, it is not governed by the 65% rule in terms of payment for claims.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J00900"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01000"><p>As regards people who have claims with Setanta Insurance at this point, if the courts decide that MIBI is liable, they could have their payments paid in full.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.123" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01100"><p>I would not want to hypothesise but let us leave Setanta aside and say that ordinarily if MIBI makes a payment it is not subject to 65%.  The Minister for Finance is not part of that agreement, but my understanding from MIBI is that it is not subject to the 65% limit.  I think its liability is really for third party, rather than first party.  So as regards the Setanta first party or third party claims, we do not know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01200"><p>As regards the third party claims, which MIBI would be liable for up to a level of 100%, how many of those claims is the liquidator dealing with at this point in time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.125" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01300"><p>Of the 1,748 claims I referred to earlier, there are 304 first party claims and 1,444 third party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01400"><p>So the outcome of this court case for 1,444 claimants is really important.  If the Minister is a party to this claim and if he wins, the claimants will only get 65% from the ICF, whereas if he loses and MIBI is deemed liable, the claimants could get up to 100% of their claims outside what the liquidator will then step in with.  Is that not correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01500"><p>The Deputy is probably asking me to go further than I can in terms of clarifying.  Leaving aside Setanta, MIBI is not subject to the same limits.  It ordinarily pays for a third party.  We do not know what their role will be.  I am not sure if it is a case of winning or losing.  It is a case of clarifying what the law says.  It is a trial of law as opposed to people suing each other.  I am not a lawyer so I probably should not go beyond saying that.  However, if the nub of the Deputy's question is that at the moment responsibility does not involve a 65% cap, we will have to wait for the liquidation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01600"><p>I appreciate that and I appreciate that we cannot stray into the legal matters, but this case could be of huge importance for 1,444 claimants.  This could be of quite substantial beneficial importance to them.  They could be paid extra as a result of this and their claims could be met to a larger capacity.  We were talking about the insurance fund, MIBI is paid by its insurance holders, and the State's share will be recouped, but this is crunch time for the claimants in terms of the payments that could be made.  Is that not correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.129" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01700"><p>Absolutely.  It is very important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01800"><p>In relation to the benefit-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J01900"><p>I am sorry Deputy but the slot is full, so I am going to move on.  I will come back to Deputy Doherty later, so he should hold his next question.  I now call Deputy O'Donnell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02000"><p>I wish to check something with Mr. Quigley.  The whole issue around the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland appears to be critical.  When this issue first arose in August-September of last year, was any counsel's opinion sought at that time?  It appears to have arisen on the basis of the Law Society getting on to the President of the High Court.  Was any legal opinion sought at that stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02100"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02200"><p>At that time, what was the basis for the opinion that MIBI would not be responsible for any claims?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02300"><p>It was based on the Attorney General's advice to both the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02400"><p>So Mr. Quigley followed up then when the President of the High Court was requested by the Law Society.  Based on a senior counsel's opinion, I am assuming that this categorically will be going to a court hearing.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02500"><p>It will be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02600"><p>Am I correct in saying that there is no cap or limit on what the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland claim?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02700"><p>That is my understanding.  Correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02800"><p>Unlike the Insurance Compensation Fund which has a cap of 65%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J02900"><p>That is correct.  The Insurance Compensation Fund is a statutory fund.  MIBI is an agreement between the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, and the industry.  From what we have reviewed of the agreement, there is no cap in play there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03000"><p>So if it transpired - and I am not pre-judging it - at the court hearing that MIBI was liable to pay, who would be deemed responsible in terms of the sequence of events?  Assuming that MIBI was liable to compensate for claims, who is the first party to pay out?  Is it MIBI or the insurance compensation fund, legally?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03100"><p>I cannot speak for the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03200"><p>What view would be taken in terms of the Insurance Compensation Fund?  That is obviously the critical aspect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.145" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03300"><p>If MIBI is deemed liable?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.147" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03500"><p>My initial reaction would be that the Insurance Compensation Fund is not then in line to make any payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03600"><p>There could be a situation whereby, if MIBI is liable, individuals could get 100% compensation as distinct from a cap of 65%, with the liquidator currently saying that around 30% of the compensation could be provided on top of the 65%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.149" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03700"><p>As far as I know, there is a cap on the Insurance Compensation Fund.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03800"><p>Some 65%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.151" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J03900"><p>There is not an equivalent for MIBI, but I do not know what would actually happen if they were liable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J04000"><p>I would like to welcome Mr. Mercieca, the liquidator, to Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.153" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J04100"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J04200"><p>Where does Mr. Mercieca fall in the sequence of events in terms of paying out?  At the moment, he thinks that a claim will get up to a maximum of 30% of the value of whatever claim is outstanding.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.155" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100010#J04300"><p>Based on the actuarial reports that I have, which project the claims up to the figures I mentioned earlier, and based on the estimates of the cost of running the liquidation for the next three years, and I keep repeating that they are best estimates, ultimately we would not be able to pay more than 30% of the insurance claims.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00100"><p>This company is effectively regulated by the Maltese regulator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.157" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00200"><p>Correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00300"><p>Mr. Mercieca appears to have a difficulty in locating the beneficial owners of Setanta Insurance.  Am I correct in saying that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.159" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00400"><p>Yes, a difficulty in terms of the nominees and trustees who hold the shares on behalf of the majority of the beneficial shareholders.  They are not permitted to divulge that information unless ordered to do so by the courts and the regulator as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00500"><p>Would they not have been required to do that as part of getting the licence from the Maltese regulator at the time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.161" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00600"><p>Yes.  That is why the regulator actually has this information.  That is public information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00700"><p>Would the regulator not be obliged to provide that information directly to Mr. Mercieca?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.163" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00800"><p>I made a request for the regulator to divulge information and they said they are not allowed to do that.  They actually suggested that I get a court order and this is what we are doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K00900"><p>Do we have someone from the Maltese regulator here today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01000"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01100"><p>In terms of Mr. Mercieca's work, I was a Setanta mortgage policyholder through a broker so I know first hand what happened at the time.  Basically one's policy was renewed but there was no guarantee on how long it would last.  This happened around the start of 2014 and then it ceased so that people had to go to other insurance companies, as I had to do.  It seems extraordinary that a company of this size was regulated by the Maltese regulator.  Mr. Paul Mercieca was appointed liquidator on 16 April 2014-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01200"><p>On 30 April.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01300"><p>-----on 30 April.  The statement of affairs posted at that stage showed a deficit of &euro;17 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01400"><p>Correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01500"><p>We are now at a situation-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01600"><p>Deputy, I am hearing an interference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01700"><p>I apologise.  What is that deficit now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.173" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01800"><p>I would have to draw up accounts as of now to answer the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K01900"><p>The latest-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.175" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02000"><p>I have not drawn up accounts recently but I will be doing that, closing up on 16 April 2015, which is an anniversary of my appointment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02100"><p>Okay.  Does Mr. Mercieca believe, looking back now - I do not want to prejudice anything - that the company was trading  while insolvent for a period?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.177" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02200"><p>This is an ongoing review and it is happening as we speak.  As it is something we will be discussing at the first meeting next week I would not like to speculate at this stage or prejudice the review which is going on at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02300"><p>There were 75,000 policyholders.  The company traded exclusively in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.179" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02400"><p>That is correct</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02500"><p>The 75,000 holders were exclusively in Ireland.  Is it correct to say that the company was given the licence by the Maltese regulator?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.181" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02700"><p>By whom was it supervised?  Was it supervised in terms of inspections on how the company operated?  How did that happen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.183" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02800"><p>The responsible party was the MFSA</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K02900"><p>It seems extraordinary that we are in a situation where we do not know who are the beneficial owners.  I assume when Mr. Mercieca locates the beneficial owners, and they have substantial assets - am I correct in saying that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.185" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03000"><p>Sorry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03100"><p>If Mr. Mercieca locates the beneficial owners and they have assets I assume he will pursue those assets on behalf of Setanta mortgage holders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.187" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03200"><p>Again, that is premature because I have to conclude the review before I can-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03300"><p>But on the basis that there are assets, would Mr. Mercieca in his role as liquidator be required to pursue those assets on behalf of Setanta mortgage holders?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.189" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03400"><p>I do not think I would be able to pursue the shareholders.  It is a really a question for the people who are running the company.  The shareholders as distinct-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03500"><p>Sorry, obviously the shareholders but they may be one and the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.191" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03600"><p>Yes, but again I cannot reach that conclusion at this stage.  It is something that is ongoing.  It is something that we are looking at.  I am trying to establish if there was wrongdoing.  I am not suggesting there was any wrongdoing but I need to get a proper understanding of the circumstances as to why this has happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1060" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03700"><p>Chairman, may I conclude by asking the relevant party, Mr. Mercieca, that his review be expedited as quickly as possible, that he pursue the beneficial owners of Setanta Insurance in the interests of the 75,000 policyholders in Ireland, many of whom had private motor insurance policies, that he advance the proceedings as quickly as possible in terms of the High Court review and ultimately that the claimants in respect of the Setanta liquidation be paid their entitlements as quickly as possible.  This issue has gone on for too long.  We must ensure that something like this never happens again.  As a committee this is an issue we will be pursuing but in terms of regulation we have to look at the situation in terms of companies like Setanta Insurance which are effectively operating onshore but being regulated offshore.  That is an issue to which we need to give careful consideration to ensure this never happens again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03800"><p>In his opening statement, Mr. Mercieca said that he had engaged with a lawyer to look into whether, in his opinion, there are grounds to suggest that an action could be brought against persons who were responsible for running the company.  Has Mr. Mercieca suspicions that there may be concerns about how the company was run and that he may well need to pursue the directors or those responsible for running the company?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.194" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K03900"><p>As I said earlier, it is expected of me in my responsibility as liquidator to get a good understanding.  I would be failing in my duties if I did not have this understanding and reach my own conclusions.  At this stage, it is premature to speculate whether there was any wrongdoing of any sort.  I am not suggesting that there is, I am just saying that the review I have commissioned is one that I have a responsibility to do.  If I did not do that I would be failing in my responsibilities.  It is ongoing.  I have not had any feedback yet.  It is premature to speculate as to what that might be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04000"><p>The total number of claims as of end of March 2015 is around 619, that is approximately 1% of the 75,000 people who were insured with Setanta Insurance.  As the cost of the claims could run to &euro;90 million the average cost of claim is running at &euro;150,000.  That appears high when compared with equivalent costs in other insurance companies.  Mr. Ronann Hession said there has been &euro;6.5 billion worth of insurance collapses in Europe?  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.196" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04100"><p>In terms of State aid, the Commission has reported that from its annual report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04200"><p>Are we are responsible for &euro;1.5 billion of that &euro;6.5 billion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.198" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04300"><p>Yes, &euro;1.15 billion, I think.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04400"><p>A quarter of all State aid towards collapsed insurance companies is paid out by Ireland and we are members of the European Union.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.200" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04500"><p>I do not have the exact breakdown but the Chairman is correct.  The size of the Quinn intervention compared to the overall European expenditure gets across the extent of the seriousness of the Quinn failure in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04600"><p>The fact of the Quinn failure and this company as well.  Is there a problem with regulation?  Should we be looking at our own regulations in this area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.202" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100011#K04700"><p>Broadly speaking, when one speaks about insurance one is speaking about a European regulatory framework.  As I outlined to Deputy Pearse Doherty earlier a complete overhaul is taking place.  From January 2016 that will become effective and should make the system much stronger.  We have also enhanced our domestic regulator, the Central Bank.  The Central Bank has done its own review internally of its own procedures and is stepping up the management information it requires from insurers especially looking at brokers and more on-site inspections of brokers.</p> <p> The Central Bank tends to do risk-based supervision.  Brokers, being quite small by comparison, up to now were possibly not as high risk.  They have tried to correct for that.  Setanta was operating about 230 brokers so it was a sizeable company in terms of the market.  They are paying greater scrutiny there.</p> <p> There is a need to make sure the regulatory system is fully kitted out to deal with this type of problem.  It will still be a European system and will rely on good co-operation.  The good co-operation is there and there is no reason to suggest there is a breakdown.</p> <p> In this case, looking at how the problems at Setanta came to a head, it really goes back to September 2013 when the Central Bank asked a straight question to the Maltese: "Is Setanta solvent or not?"  The Maltese came back with the solvency certificate to say it was meeting its minimum requirements.  The bank brought it a step further, did a sample of claims from the office in Blanchardstown and raised the question of the level of reserving.  That was challenged by the Setanta directors at the time and in fairness to the Maltese they got Grant Thornton Malta, I think, the auditors of Setanta, to do a review.  They came back and said it was a little bit short on reserving but not materially so.  The bank pressed further and got an independent assessment and at that stage, coming up to December 2013, there was a more serious question emerging.  There was a level of persistence from the Central Bank and in spite of the objections from the directors the Maltese and the Central Bank kept pressing to get the answer.  It was really from there that the first direction came in January, I think on 16 or 24 January, to stop writing new business.  There was then a period of months where the Maltese were pressing the Setanta directors to raise capital.  There were a couple of bidders in the frame who dropped out about 11 April, roughly a week before the company was liquidated.</p> <p> It is always important to make sure there is connectivity around a system.  The system in insurance is global so if there is not co-operation between supervisors it cannot work.  In this case, quite a detailed report was given to the committee last July from the Maltese regulator which sets out those steps and brings out the level of interaction that can happen in a case like this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00200"><p>Finally, Mr. Quigley, if the Motor Insurers' Bureau of Ireland, MIBI, is made liable, is 100% responsible and is involved in 1,400 of the 1,700 cases here, does it then have recourse to go back to the liquidator for funding?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.205" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00300"><p>I can really only comment on the insurance compensation fund - that is all I am responsible for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00400"><p>Can anybody comment on that?  If they are made responsible for 1,400 of the cases can they go back to the liquidator?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.207" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00500"><p>Maybe also function as a compensation of last resort, effectively.  To the extent that those claims could be met by the liquidator, maybe could potentially choose not to meet the claims in full and to leave the balance to be met by the liquidator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00600"><p>So the liquidator should pay out first and then MIBI----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.209" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00700"><p>Not necessarily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00800"><p>We could actually end up in a situation where anybody with a claim could be waiting a decade while we wait for the statute of limitation to run out and for claims to be settled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.211" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L00900"><p>In fact, there is provision in the MIBI agreement met for MIBI to pay out where a judgement is not.  I would guess that MIBI would then be entitled under the agreement to try and recover that from the liquidator subsequently.  MIBI will have to deal with that on its own and reach its own conclusion on it.  It is not necessarily for us to give any firm view on it here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01000"><p>It looks like it will go on for years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.213" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01100"><p>We are hopeful that the forthcoming trial of law will tell everyone what the law means, who is responsible and to what extent.  That should hopefully bring clarity one way or the other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01200"><p>What I have heard so far, and please do correct me if I am wrong, is that of the 1,748 claims, no claimant has received a cent since the company was put into liquidation, nobody can say with any certainty when any money will be paid out to a claimant and nobody can rule out the possibility that claimants will suffer a loss at the end of this.  Is there anything inaccurate in any of that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.215" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01300"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01400"><p>What level of communication is there on an ongoing basis with claimants?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.217" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01500"><p>With claimants?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.219" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01700"><p>There is a degree of communication because there are still staff employed by the company who are dealing with claims, correspondence and queries as they come in.  To the extent that----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01800"><p>Are they being proactively contacted and given updates or is the onus on them to check in with the liquidator?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.221" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L01900"><p>The updates are being posted on the company's website as and when we think it necessary to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02000"><p>Some time ago I saw a letter issued by a solicitor acting on behalf of the liquidator warning a former Setanta policy holder that he may be personally liable in the event that a third party injury claim succeeds and there is insufficient money to settle the claim.  The letter went on to say that such a successful third party claim could result in a judgement being registered against the former policy holder.  Is that the case?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.223" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02100"><p>I cannot comment on that.  That is a question of Irish law which I am certainly not competent to get into, I am afraid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02200"><p>The liquidator has not instructed lawyers to issue such letters, that Mr. Mercieca is aware of?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.225" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02300"><p>I would have communicated - the lawyers would have told me at the time but I cannot go into the legal arguments behind that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02400"><p>Does Mr. Quigley know what led to the intervention of the Law Society regarding the role of the bureau?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.227" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02500"><p>Once the Law Society approached the president of the High Court it emerged that the Law Society had been in correspondence with the Minister for Transport over the MIBI liability.  We would not have previously been aware of that so it was really only from the point at which the Law Society raised it with the president that we decided we needed to get clarity of the issue and get senior counsel opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02600"><p>The insurance compensation fund, ICF, can only apply to the court for permission to make a payout every six months in the case of a foreign company that has been liquidated, so it has to bundle the cases.  It has not gone yet because of the outstanding court cases.  Is that the position?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.229" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02700"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02800"><p>My next question is for the liquidator again.  Can he give us the broad categories of the 483 claims that are not eligible for payment from the compensation fund?  Do they involve companies and so forth?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.231" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L02900"><p>Basically they would be claims which do not meet the criteria of the fund.  There are a number of issues, probably they would be corporate - I do not have the breakdown of the 483.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L03000"><p>Regarding the company law in Malta that governs a liquidation process, is the hierarchy or ranking of creditors that get paid in the scenario similar to Irish law or are there differences between Maltese and Irish law in terms of the distribution of resources?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.233" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L03100"><p>The advice I have is that it is very similar to Irish company law but I am not an expert on Irish company law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.234" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Antoine Mac Donncha" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L03200"><p>Just to clarify that, as I understand it under the Maltese law the assets of Setanta are all technical provisions, so those assets will be available to claims in respect of policies in priority to any other claimant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100012#L03300"><p>Deputy Doherty teased out the issue of the bureau and that depending on the outcome of the case in the court, the bureau may be 100% liable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.236" nospeaker="true" time="15:35:00" ><p>That is a matter of speculation.  If it is not, the insurance compensation fund, ICF, liability is capped to 65% and the liquidator cannot make any payments to claimants until all of the cases have been concluded and there is absolute certainty about the total liability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.237" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00200"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00300"><p>How long, typically, does a liquidation of this nature take?  There have been liquidations in Europe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.239" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00400"><p>These liquidations, particularly of this nature, tend to be complicated.  As we have just discussed, there are many legal issues surround them so it is completely impossible to speculate on how long it will take.  All I can do is repeat what I have said.  To me, this is fundamental in resolving this issue.  If this process takes too long, it will increase costs and make finance settlements more difficult.  The resolution of this issue is fundamental on unlocking the claims position, as I have indicated.  I cannot tell the Deputy how long that will take.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00500"><p>I know.  We all need to remember that behind this story there are many victims of accidents and crashes.  There are people who suffered very serious injury.  One Deputy mentioned that a fatality was involved in one accident.  I do not know the detail.  People are out of pocket and people's livelihoods have been destroyed in some cases.  These are ordinary tradesmen.  There are major consequences.  If we can do anything as a committee or Parliament to help the liquidator's work in bringing this to a conclusion, it should let us know.  Perhaps we can raise matters with the Government and the appropriate Minister, or there may be legislative matters.  The witnesses would find willing support here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.241" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00600"><p>The President of the High Court is giving this the highest priority as he is very aware and sensitive to the issues mentioned by the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.243" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Se&aacute;n Quigley" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00800"><p>We expect the legal issue to be resolved quite quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M00900"><p>Average claims are &euro;150,000 so there are serious litigation issues within the &euro;90 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01000"><p>Where is the Chairman getting that figure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01100"><p>I am dividing the &euro;90 million among the 700 cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01200"><p>There are approximately 1,700 cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01300"><p>Yes, I apologise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01400"><p>There are 1,748 cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01500"><p>My figures are wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/993" speakername="Michael McGrath" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01600"><p>The average would be approximately &euro;54,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01700"><p>It still significant, although some would be very small.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.253" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01800"><p>On that point, I stated earlier that the &euro;90 million is a projection of what the claims could be.  It does not necessarily mean there will be 1,748 claims.  There could be many more claims to reach that &euro;90 million.  The 1,748 claims we have today equate to the &euro;53 million we are providing.  The projection from actuaries is that the &euro;53 million could be &euro;90 million; in the same way, claim numbers could go up from 1,700.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M01900"><p>That is useful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02000"><p>We appreciate the clarification.  Without divulging any confidential information, what are the highest third-party claims?  What is the ball park figure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.256" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02100"><p>There is one claim in excess of &euro;1 million.  I do not have any other breakdown of figures with me.  That is the largest single claim that exists.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02200"><p>It is in excess of &euro;1 million.  If the insurance compensation fund paid out for that case, that party would be at least &euro;350,000 short of the claim, depending on other factors.</p>  <p>  There was a bit of discussion regarding shareholders and the liquidator is going to the courts to find out who is the beneficiary owner of the company.  I examined the company records for 2013 and 2012, which mentions two holding companies.  The witness mentioned that he is aware of one, Setanta Holdings Limited.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.258" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02300"><p>That owns the shares of Setanta Insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02400"><p>In 2013, it owned 11,049,195 shares.  The second shareholder was GANADO Trustees, which owned one share.  From the witness's experience, is that type of structure usual?  Would there be two trustees and holding companies, one with 11 million shares and the other with one share?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.260" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02500"><p>I cannot really comment on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02600"><p>There is a vote in the D&aacute;il so we might finish the session when the Deputy concludes his questioning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02700"><p>Both of these shareholders are registered at the same address, 171 Old Bakery Street, Valletta.  Is this a familiar place?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.263" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02800"><p>To comment on what the Deputy has said, there is a requirement under Maltese law that there must be two shareholders in any company.  There cannot be just one shareholder.  It is very common to have one shareholder holding 99.9% and another holding 0.1% of a company.  The one share is probably that arrangement.  The shareholdings have now changed to new shareholders.  The nominees quoted by the Deputy were subsequently changed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M02900"><p>That was changed after 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.265" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03000"><p>Yes.  The register of companies today indicates a different nominee trustee company in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03100"><p>Company accounts indicate directors from Foxrock and Dundrum.  We have their names and addresses.  Have the directors given any information about the owners of the company?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.267" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03200"><p>No.  I have not asked the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03300"><p>Okay.  Setanta continued to sell after January 2014.  I wrote the financial regulator in Malta last year and I am thankful that I received a response.  It stated very clearly that the Maltese financial regulator at the time directed Setanta to cease with immediate effect in carrying out any new or renewal contracts of insurance, as of close of business of 24 January 2014.  Following inquiry with the company as to the number of live policies in its book and expiry dates of these policies, it transpired that a number of live policies from Setanta extended to March 2014.  This, in effect, means the company continued to renew insurance policies after 24 January 2014.  Is there any possibility that those policyholders will be able to claim under the liquidation process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.269" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03400"><p>I have not discussed that possibility.  I do not know the answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03500"><p>If members wish to submit more questions to the witnesses, would they answer them and return to the secretariat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.271" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Mercieca" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03600"><p>Yes, to the extent that we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03700"><p>Unfortunately, we must suspend the session as there is a vote in the Parliament.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/959" speakername="Pearse Doherty" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03800"><p>I have a final question on the Motor Insurers Bureau of Ireland, MIBI.  Under the conditions that it has entered into with the 2009 agreement with the Department, anybody paid out by the MIBI would have the potential for the MIBI to reclaim the amount from a future insurance policy.  If the individual mentioned by Mr. Mercieca was paid &euro;1 million as a third-party claimant, the MIBI could recover that amount by a levy on a new policy.  Are the witnesses aware of this or concerned by it?  The policyholders that may be paid by the MIBI, depending on the court judgment, could see all the payments recovered by the MIBI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.274" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ronan Hession" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100013#M03900"><p>I am not familiar with the clause referred to by the Deputy.  My understanding was that there might be a payment on third-party claims.</p> <p>For example, if somebody does not hold insurance then they are not insured and they hit somebody else because a claim may pay the third party and be entitled to pursue the uninsured first party to recover costs.  That was my understanding of the way one might pursue somebody.  In response to what has been described by the Deputy, I was unaware of that interpretation but we will reflect on the matter.  If the committee has a question on the matter we are happy to consult the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport and provide whatever clarification we can.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100014#N00200"><p>We must suspend the meeting due to a Vote.  On behalf of the joint committee, I thank all of the witnesses for attending here today, particularly Mr. Mercieca who travelled all the way from Malta.  We appreciate and thank him for his forthright answers.  The same applies to the officials from the Department of Finance and the Courts Service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.277" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.01 p.m. and resumed at 4.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.278" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100015#O00100">Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Effective Date for Certain Bodies) Order 2015 and Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Exempted Public Bodies) Order 2015: Motion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100015#O00200"><p>The purpose of today's meeting is to consider, pursuant to an order of the D&aacute;il on 24 March, the proposal that D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann approve the following Order in draft:<blockquote>Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Effective Date for Certain Bodies) Order 2015 and Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Exempted Public Bodies) Order 2015.Copies of the Order were laid in draft form before the D&aacute;il on 10 and 12 March, respectively.  The joint committee also received an order of the Seanad regarding these motions on 31 March.  The order of referral requires the joint committee, when we have completed our consideration, to send a message to that effect to the D&aacute;il and the Seanad.  The message must be sent not later than 2 April.<br /><br />I welcome the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, together with his officials.  I thank them all for attending and assisting our consideration of the motions.  Briefing notes were provided by the Department.  The Minister will address the committee, after which we will open the debate to members for questions and comments.  Is that agreed? Agreed.  I call on the Minister to commence.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100015#O00300"><p>I thank the Chairman for facilitating a debate on two orders under the Freedom of Information 2014 - a new Act that we debated at some length.</p>  <p>  One order provides for a different effective date for certain bodies under FOI, as I indicated would happen.  The second order provides for exemptions from FOI in whole or in part for certain bodies.  Both of these orders are to be made under section 6 of the Freedom of Information Act and require a positive resolution of both Houses before they are made.  That is the reason I am here today.  I shall deal first with the effective date order.</p>  <p>  In the context of FOI, effective date means the retrospective date back to which records are available once an FOI body becomes subject to FOI.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.281" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>It is about how far back one looks.  Section 2 of the Freedom of Information Act 2014 provides that in the case of a body that was not subject to FOI under the 1997 Act but is subject to FOI under the new Act, the effective date is 21 April 2008 unless provision is made to the contrary by order under this subsection.  We debated that for some time.  My Department received a number of applications from public bodies requesting that I set a later effective date in respect of the application of FOI to their organisations.  I considered these applications very carefully.  It was always my intention that any change from the standard provisions in relation to a retrospective date would be agreed in respect of only a small number of bodies where there was a clear justification for an exceptional date.  Therefore, the only applications I agreed and propose the Oireachtas agrees are in respect of the Refugee Applications Commissioner and the Refugee Appeals Tribunal, for which I propose an effective date of 14 October 2014 which was the date of enactment of the legislation, and the Private Residential Tenancies Board, for which I propose an effective date of 21 April 2012 to coincide with the time when that body moved to electronic operation.</p><p>I want to explain the rationale for those decisions.  These organisations hold large volumes of information, the bulk of which is personal in nature.  Where records created before the effective date relate to personal information about the person seeking access to them, the effective date does not apply.  In any event, when one is looking for information about oneself, the effective date does not apply as one is entitled to access such records back to whatever date they were created.  My agreement to an effective date of 21 April 2012 in respect of the Private Residential Tenancies Board and 14 October 2014 in respect of Refugee Applications Commissioner and the Refugee Appeals Tribunal does not, therefore, affect this provision.  The bulk of non-personal FOI requests these organisations expect to receive relate to third-party requests for access to personal information.  Given the nature and sensitivity of the personal information involved in respect of the commissioner and tribunal, we must give these matters very careful consideration.  It is difficult to envisage circumstances where there would be a compelling public interest in the release of such records to third parties.  However, if the records remained subject to release under FOI, each individual record would be subject to review giving rise to a very substantial administrative burden on the organisations concerned.  That is why I have given the effective dates as set out.</p><p>I move on now to the bodies I propose be exempted in whole or in part.  As the committee is aware, a generic definition of what constitutes a public body was included in the 2014 Act.  This enables FOI to apply to the widest possible definition of public bodies.  Instead of making orders to apply FOI to bodies as happened under the 1997 Act, the new approach means that an order is needed if a body is to be exempted.  The default position now is that a body is in unless by order of the Houses it is out.  The old order was that everybody was out until they were put in.  My Department has received a number of applications for exemptions from FOI and these have been considered very carefully.  I have only approved exemptions where it is clear that the application of FOI to those bodies in whole or in part would affect their ability to perform their core functions or would affect the security or financial interests of the State.  The exemptions which I am proposing to the committee and, subsequently to the D&aacute;il and Seanad, cover six bodies.  I am only proposing a full exemption from FOI for two of those bodies.  I am proposing to exempt only certain records of another three bodies.  Finally, a technical change is being proposed to the exemption already included in the Act in respect of schools to reflect the original policy I set out when the legislation was going through the Houses.</p><p>I will deal with full exemptions first.  The bodies for which I am proposing a full exemption from FOI are the Irish Red Cross and the Shannon Group.  The Irish Red Cross conforms to the generic definition of a public body because it was established under enactment and so would be automatically due to come under FOI in mid-April.  I accepted the case made by the Department of Defence that the inclusion of the society for FOI purposes represented an anomaly in that it had to be established under legislation to ensure, in accordance with the Geneva Convention, that only one Red Cross society could exist in the State.  It is a charitable organisation operating in an environment where both Exchequer resources and charitable donations have been reducing in recent years.  The application of FOI would represent a cost for the body which would require some diversion of resources.  The application of FOI to bodies in receipt of Exchequer funding, including the Irish Red Cross, will be considered in the context of section 7 of the Act once the application of the Act to this round of public bodies has bedded down.  Members will recall that we debated this at some length during the passage of the Act.  In this way I would not be imposing an administrative burden on the Irish Red Cross now as compared to other national and international independent charitable and humanitarian bodies based in this country who are not included as public bodies for the purposes of the Act.  I hope that is not too convoluted a way to put it.  In other words, charitable bodies in general will be looked at under section 7.  The Irish Red Cross is an anomaly because of its unique nature.  It is deemed to be a public body having been created by statute as required under the Geneva Convention.</p><p>I turn to the other exempt body.  The State Airports (Shannon Group) Act 2014 provided for the establishment of the Shannon Group as a commercial company under the Companies Acts and the subsequent transfer of both the Shannon Airport Authority and the re-structured Shannon Development, which was re-named Shannon Commercial Enterprises, to the group.  Consistent with the broader policy approach which we debated at some length and which I have been consistent in supporting, commercial State bodies such as the Shannon Group should not be subject to FOI requirements because of the uneven competitive playing field this would create as compared to privately-owned competitors which are not subject to FOI.  Given the very important responsibilities assigned by the Government to the Shannon Group in terms of regional development of the midwest region, it is critical to ensure that the organisation is able to operate without commercial disadvantage.</p><p>I deal now with exemptions in part.  I am proposing an exemption from FOI for the newly established Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, SBCI, in respect of certain specific classes of sensitive records because of the very high standard of banking confidentiality expected by market counterparts in respect of such an organisation.  I have been advised by the Minister for Finance that if such an exemption was not provided, there would be a real risk that potential funders, on-lenders and clients of the SBCI would not engage with it and its capacity to perform its functions would be severely curtailed.</p><p>I am proposing two exemptions in respect of records of the NTMA reflecting recent legislative developments it was not possible to take account of up to now.  The NTMA (Amendment) Act 2014 conferred new legal cost claims management functions on the NTMA relating to considering and adjudicating on bills of costs presented for payment by third parties who were awarded their costs by the Mahon and Moriarty Tribunals.  These functions were previously carried out by the Office of the Chief State Solicitor and attracted an exemption from FOI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100017#Q00100"><p>It is necessary that an identical exemption be granted to the NTMA in respect of records associated with these functions in view of the fact that they are performed by the NTMA on behalf of the Attorney General.  </p>  <p>  The NTMA also has functions in relation to the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland.  I have already set out the case for putting in place certain specific exemptions for the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland to meet market requirements applying to banking confidentiality.  The NTMA is conferred with certain functions under the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland Act 2014.  For the same reasons, these records need to be protected when they are held by the NTMA in the performance of their functions under the Act.  The exemption I am proposing for the NTMA in this regard is a mirror image of the exemption for the SBCI itself.</p>  <p>  The third exemption relates to Oifig Choimisin&eacute;ir na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la.  Exemptions from FOI are proposed for Oifig Choimisin&eacute;ir na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la in respect of records relating to monitoring of compliance by public bodies and investigations under the Official Languages Act 2003 so that the office is treated for FOI purposes in a way that is consistent with the approach applied to other Ombudsman's offices.  Oifig Choimisin&eacute;ir na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la operates as an Ombudsman in respect of the provision of services through Irish by public bodies.</p>  <p>  Consistent with the broader policy approach adopted under the FOI Act, schools with boards of management are already exempt from FOI under the 2014 Act.  I am proposing a technical change to the exemption in the draft order to ensure that all schools, other than education and training board schools, will remain exempt from FOI.</p>  <p>  I am satisfied that the orders I am proposing are limited, modest and necessary for the reasons I have outlined.  They are also consistent with the line I have taken throughout the significant debate we have had on completely remodelling the FOI Act to restore many provisions of the 1997 Act and to strengthen it even beyond that.  The committee will appreciate that, while previously FOI only applied to bodies explicitly scheduled, now everybody is in unless they are out.  The relevant Ministers have given their consent to the provisions of both orders and most of them, in fact, sought the changes.  I look forward to hearing any comments that members have to make and to replying to any questions that might arise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100017#Q00200"><p>I thank the Chairman for the opportunity to speak.  I am shocked that we are here after the trumpeting of the introduction of freedom of information.  We are now proceeding to unravel freedom of information.  We are introducing new exemptions and changing effective dates.  It is a serious rowing back, a U-turn on the promise to reform and expand freedom of information.</p><p>This raft of changes introduces secrecy in a whole range of areas that were intended to come under the freedom of information legislation when it was announced.  It <font color="#2F2F2F">excludes the performance of the new Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, certain aspects of the National Treasury Management Agency, the entire Shannon Group, the Irish Red Cross and investigations by An Coimisin&eacute;ir Teanga.  It also restricts the effective date for the Private Residential Tenancies Board and the effective date of information available from the Refugee Applications Commissioner and the Refugee Appeals Tribunal.  That amounts to eight restrictions being introduced today.  I had hoped the Minister would expand the legislation, not curtail it.  This is a serious change in approach and I cannot contemplate how we can support it in the D&aacute;il tomorrow.</font></p><p><font color="#2F2F2F">  We received a briefing note on the effective date.  I heard what the Minister said about the effective date and retrospective requests for information.  He is changing the effective date in respect of the Refugee Applications Commissioner and the Refugee Appeals Tribunal to last October, a few months ago.  The briefing note we received from the Department in the context of the motion in the D&aacute;il contains a paragraph which has been left out by the Minister today.  The note states, &quot;In the case of the refugee bodies an additional concern communicated by the Department of Justice and Equality is that third party FOI requests would have the potential to delay judicial reviews of the organisations' decision making, giving rise to significant additional cost and direct provision.&quot;  That is the real reason for the change but the Minister studiously dropped that sentence from his statement today.  Some people will agree with the Minister but I did not think he was in the position of wanting to send people home earlier and not allow them the full protection of the law applying in Ireland at the moment.</font></p><p><font color="#2F2F2F">  On potential judicial delays, I understand that third parties who might request this information are probably the legal teams acting on behalf of the individuals concerned, rather than the persons themselves.  The legal adviser would be seeking information about other cases and about how matters were dealt with in the past.  That information might have helped them with the judicial reviews so it seems the Minister is bringing in this change to help the Department defeat applicants in cases of judicial review.  He really let the cat out of the bag with the briefing note from the Department of Justice and Equality, which shows that his aim was to reduce the significant costs associated with direct provision, meaning we can send these people home earlier.  There is a market out there for that kind of action but I did not think it was the Labour Party market.  New parties around town might agree with it but I did not think the Minister was in that camp and I am shocked he is going down the road of reducing direct provision costs and reducing people's ability to have a judicial review.</font></p><p><font color="#2F2F2F">  There is also a change to the retrospective date relating to the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  Again, we received a note from the Department on the matter.  It stated that the organisation would be too busy handling the new deposit scheme, which involved a significant amount of additional work.  The note also said something which was left out of the Minister's statement today, namely, that the Private Residential Tenancies Board was in the process of taking on significant additional responsibilities in taking security deposits.  These will come to approximately &euro;1,000 per tenancy and will relate to 300,000 tenancies.  The board will be dealing with the regulation of approved housing bodies, approximating to 28,000 households, and there is a concern that the resource implications of full retrospection of FOI to 2008 may encompass large numbers of files which would have the potential to impact adversely on the organisation's ability to successfully discharge those roles.  The briefing note stated that the body would be very busy with all the new deposits and setting up the new system and that it could not possibly be expected to deal with FOI.  I do not think the board has started taking deposits yet and I do not think the legislation has even been finalised yet.</font></p><p><font color="#2F2F2F">  The Minister could have taken another option.  A couple of weeks ago he pushed the effective date for EirGrid back from April 2015 to the end of October and that would have been a more honourable way of doing it.  If the PRTB has an administrative problem for six months, the right thing to have done would have been to give them the extra six months.  I do not know how many other bodies the Minister did this for.  I only came across the information because EirGrid is a big issue in my constituency and I got the information by way of a parliamentary question.</font></p> <p> On the Irish Red Cross, the Minister might have a point.  I do not know, but I understand that organisation is in some turmoil.  That is probably the real reason for this and if it is, we would be happier if the Minister said that.  I am aware that several senior positions have not been filled but the Minister said he intends bringing this in under freedom of information, FOI, legislation in due course.  I do not understand why we are taking it out now only to bring it back in later.</p> <p> I have an issue with exempting the State Claims Agency from this process because nothing can be disclosed.  Adjudicating on bills and costs is essentially an administrative function.  There are no legal implications here.  It has nothing to do with the substance of the cases before the various tribunals.  My view is that if there is an area where there should be more transparency it should be with regard to considering how bills and costs presented for payment by third parties awarded costs by tribunals are being adjudicated on.  It is shocking that the Minister wants to put a veil of secrecy over an area that should come under this proposal, even though they are working for the Attorney General.  That is an administrative area that should be subject to FOI.</p> <p> There might be a valid case to be made regarding the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland in terms of who will lend money, who it will lend money onto and market confidentiality.  Various Ombudsman offices are already subject to the Freedom of Information Act.  The Minister said he is making Oifig Choimisin&eacute;ir na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la consistent with that.  He might explain where it is currently inconsistent and how it will be made consistent with the other Ombudsman offices.</p> <p> The Minister might have a point on the School Exemptions Board.  Generally, however, I am very disappointed that he, as a Labour Party Minister in government, is bringing forward some of these proposals to prevent people in the asylum process getting information that could help them with their judicial review.  There is also the underlying issue of the cost of direct provision, and the issue of the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  We would be better off giving them another six months to get their houses in order internally rather than changing the effective date, which will apply from now on.  </p> <p> I have asked for some clarification on one or two points but it is not a question and answer session.  I have read the briefing note but I disagree with the approach being taken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100018#R00200"><p>I broadly share the concerns expressed by Deputy Fleming.  I appreciate that the new regime differs in as much as bodies have to be exempted.  That is the right approach.  However, I am not convinced by the Minister's proposals before us.  Above all, I am alarmed in terms of the change of effective date, particularly in respect of refugee bodies.  My position on the issue of direct provision is that I want to see it abolished.  I want to see cases dealt with appropriately and lawfully and an end to the practice where people spend years in these centres.  Children spend their entire school careers coming and going in these centres.  The abuses of people's rights, and I put it as strongly as that, are very well documented and it is a scandal that has slowly built and unfolded under our eyes.  The system in this State knows it is happening and yet it is allowed to continue.  It is scandalous.  I acknowledge that there is a working group working on this area.  I hope that working group manages to abolish direct provision sooner rather than later.</p>  <p>  The reason I am deeply alarmed by any limitation being put on access to information in respect of these bodies is because if ever there were a process and a system that is veiled in secrecy and a lack of clarity, it is the process of refuge and asylum in this State.  We have an archaic and opaque system that leaves people who find themselves in the midst of that system utterly at sea, often with virtually no support, and in many cases very little information.  The Minister might respond by saying that individuals will still have access to their own files.  I accept that, but the oversight of third party bodies in respect of this system in particular is essential, and it is wrong for the Minister to introduce this change in terms of effective date.  I do not doubt that the line Department in question made the request.  That does not surprise me one little bit, but I believe the Minister is making a big mistake in agreeing to it, and it is certainly something I could not countenance supporting.  It is simply wrong, and I put it to the Minister in those strong terms.  However, I do not believe it is an effort by the Minister or the line Minister to necessarily deny people their legal rights, which is a concern of Deputy Fleming.  I believe it is more that the system is so banjaxed that there has been, and the track record reflects this, a strategy of information containment and keeping things in the dark, and what the Minister is proposing here today adds to that trend.  That is most worrying and disappointing, and I ask him to take that particular proposal off the table.  Of any issue the Minister has come to committee looking for our assent, this is the most worrying of all of them.</p>  <p>  In respect of the Private Residential Tenancies Board, I will tell the Minister my experience of that organisation.  It is a miracle if they answer the telephone.  They are horribly under-resourced and anybody who has to interact with them can tell the Minister that at first hand.  I do not know if other Deputies have had that experience.  When one eventually gets through to them I find them helpful, professional and courteous, in fairness to their staff, but it is very clear that they are under-resourced.  I do not accept that they should have this limitation in respect of FOI afforded to them.  It is a fact, and I accept that they need more staff and more resources, but I am sure all of us in our various constituencies can confirm that, increasingly, there is a huge volume of people presenting in respect of disputes with landlords.  It may be most acute in the city of Dublin where property prices are increasing, and rents have increased approximately 9% in the last period.  The problem is very acute.  This is a body that as we speak is difficult to get in contact with.  People report it is difficult to get interactions with its staff.  I believe that is a resource issue.  Others might have a different view but given the sensitivity of this whole area now I see no argument in policy terms or good practice to limit access to information through this body.  On the contrary, we should be looking to resource it more effectively and to make information flow more easily.</p>  <p>  I take the Minister's point in respect of the exemption of some of the public bodies.  With the exception of the Oifig Choimisin&eacute;ir na dTeangacha Oifigi&uacute;la, I would have thought there are already sufficient checks and balances within the legislation in respect of information that might be deemed to be commercially sensitive.  The Minister might recall that during the passage of the legislation we had endless debates on what was and was not commercial sensitivity.  It strikes me that those provisions protect those legitimately sensitive areas the Minister identifies.  The Commissioner might be a different kettle of fish.  I accept the Shannon Group is in line with the Minister's thinking in respect of other commercial semi-State entities.  We had that debate here.</p> <p>I see the logic of where the Minister is coming from in that instance.  I am not sure about the Irish Red Cross.  My concern relates mainly to the National Treasury Management Agency, the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland and the State Claims Agency.  I do not accept that the Minister has presented a conclusive argument for the action he is taking.  The change that alarms me most is the changing of the effective dates, particularly as they pertain to the Office of the Refugee Applications Commissioner and the Refugee Appeals Tribunal.  It is a mistake to do that.  If the Minister listens to nothing else I have said today, I ask him to take that point on board and withdraw that particular proposal.  It is simply wrong and will make what is a bad situation a whole lot worse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00200"><p>I have one question which may not, however, be within the Minister's remit.  Does he have any information, in so far as it relates to the Oireachtas, as to whether there has been increased usage of the Act since it was enhanced?  If so, has it been for the purposes of establishing complex and substantive policy issues, or what has been the nature of it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00300"><p>I invite the Minister to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00400"><p>I thank members for their contributions.  It speaks volumes as to how we are in a whole new regime in that the freedom of information provisions now apply to everybody unless this committee discusses exceptions and both Houses agree to them.  That has transformed the system.  I do my best not to be discordant but it is difficult to listen to lectures from Deputy Fleming on broadening the application of freedom of information.  I am confident that the 2014 Act we enacted as an Oireachtas last year will stand the test of time.  It is already regarded as one of the best internationally, unlike the 2003 Act which eviscerated the good work done in 1997.  As I outlined, the changes I am proposing fall into two categories.  I am changing the retrospective date applying to a couple of organisations for very practical reasons.  One of the points we made right through the debate on freedom of information was that we must avoid, within reason, creating burdens that are just too much for any organisation.  These are modest changes involving a couple of organisations out of the many hundreds of bodies that are now subject to FOI.</p>  <p>  Deputies Fleming and McDonald focused on the slight movement of the date for the retrospective application of FOI to the Office of the Refugee Applications Commissioner and the Refugee Appeals Tribunal, and there was a suggestion that I did not convey the full briefing note in this regard.  That note is as comprehensive as we can make it given that I have been asked by the clerk to confine my comments to ten minutes.  One has to do some editing in such circumstances.  Either I restrict the quantum of information I give in a briefing note or I exceed the instructions as to the time allocated.  I cannot do both and it is important to give members as much information as I can.  Of course I have an absolute focus on ensuring the refugee bodies deal with applications as expeditiously as possible.  I am obliged to heed them and their parent Department when they say that if there is too much backdating and we divert personnel to the processing of FOI rather than the processing of applications, then there will be a negative impact for asylum seekers who need to have their case heard and, where there is a coherent case to be made, need to have their applications approved so they can get on with their life rather than being caught in direct provision.</p>  <p>  I share Deputy McDonald's concern regarding the direct provision system.  As she knows, the Government has established a review group and the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, will report on that matter very shortly.  The Office of the Refugee Applications Commissioner estimates that the number of records it holds amounts to 4 million, including paper files and databases, both live and archived.  We are going back to 2012 in all of this but any individual who has a concern about his or her own records will not be affected by the change.  All individuals will be able access their own records.  Likewise, a lawyer acting on behalf of an individual will not be debarred from accessing that person's records.</p>  <p>  I am conscious that staff have been squeezed both in the refugee area and in the Private Residential Tenancies Board.  All such public bodies have been subject to recruitment embargoes in recent times.  We have had to deploy staff more effectively in an effort to save money and reduce the public sector pay bill, as people were advocating for.  The burden we place on personnel must be very carefully measured in the public interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00500"><p>That is a disingenuous thing to say as regards the refugee process.  I do not accept the Minister is so ignorant of the problems in the system as to make that argument.  It is outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00600"><p>The Deputy should let the Minister finish his contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00700"><p>Pardon me, Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00800"><p>There were no interjections until a journalist arrived.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S00900"><p>It has got damn all to do with a journalist entering the room.  The Minister should appreciate that, given the publication for which the particular journalist writes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S01000"><p>I will have to ask the journalist in question to leave the room if there is going to be a row.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S01100"><p>I want to be clear on this.  The outworking of this legislation on FOI, which is, by international acknowledgment, ground-breaking and world class, will change the whole way in which bodies become subject to FOI such that they will be automatically included as opposed to being automatically excluded unless specifically included.  However, we do have to have some discernment as to what is practical in terms of bringing in this whole raft of new bodies for the first time.  As I said, in the case of the Office of the Refugee Applications Commissioner we are talking about 4 million files.  Individuals will have access to their own records without let or hindrance, but we must apply a commencement date in respect of any third party looking for any file if we are to avoid placing an undue burden on the organisation.  It is just disingenuous and wrong for people to claim this in any way impacts negatively on the processing of applications.  Any individual will have access to his or her records, as will a lawyer acting on his or her behalf.  That is the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S01200"><p>It is not the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100019#S01300"><p>If we were to allow a raft of third-party people to make applications, that might delay the processing of applications and would not be in the interest of applicants.  All of these things are fully encompassed in this comprehensive legislation.</p>  <p>  On the Private Residential Tenancies Board, I am, again, applying an effective date of 2012.  I picked that date and not 2011 or 2013, for instance, because it is the year in which the board began to gather data electronically.  Before that, it operated a paper-based system, processing some 1.2 million paper-based records annually.  The workload of the PRTB is heavy and intensive, with 300,000 registrations per annum, 150,000 individual landlords to deal with and 635,000 tenants.  Despite Deputy McDonald's difficulty in getting through, I am advised that the board dealt with 54,000 telephone calls in 2013.  Clearly, somebody's calls are being answered.  One must take a practical decision as to whether it is reasonable to say that the date from which the board began gathering data electronically should be the effective date, or if one should put a burden on the board such that it would have to search 1.2 million paper-based files manually for each year prior to that date.</p> <p>The answer is if it is the person's own file then they will have to do that, but not for a third party.  That is a reasonable position.  I have argued throughout the debate that I want to be as comprehensive as I can be, but the approach must be tempered by some semblance of reasonableness in order that we do not kill off organisations by putting a burden on them that simply stops them from functioning effectively.</p> <p> To be clear on the position in response to the question posed by Deputy McDonald on the Coiminis&eacute;ir Teanga, the Coiminis&eacute;ir has exactly the same status as any other Ombudsman.  The effect of the motion will put the office in exactly the same position as other Ombudsman offices.  In other words, the administrative files relating to the office will be subject to FOI but how it deals with individual cases is not.  Have I been too long, Chairman?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00200"><p>No, but we have a vote and I propose that we suspend and come back after the vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00300"><p>I have said all I have to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00400"><p>I wish to make one brief point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00500"><p>The Deputy should make it quickly before we go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00600"><p>The Minister has set the commencement date for the Refugee Appeals Tribunal to October 2014.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00700"><p>It was last year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00800"><p>That is a big mistake.  It adds further to the opaque nature of the process and the lack of surveillance of the entire process in which people find themselves trapped for years, and of which direct provision is a part.  The Minister knows that as surely as I do.  Could he indicate whether it was the Minister for Justice and Equality who sought the measure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T00900"><p>The Minister might be kind enough not to interrupt Deputy McDonald, and to send the committee a note on the question I raised.  I am curious to know the answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1097" speakername="Brendan Howlin" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01100"><p>The Minister might also answer which Minister made the request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01200"><p>Could I finish please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.311" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputies" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01400"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for attending.  We have now completed our consideration of the motion.  Under Standing Order 86(2) the message is deemed to be the report of the committee.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.313" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01500">Messages to the Dáil and Seanad</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2015040100020#T01600"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:<blockquote><br /><br />The Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform has completed its consideration of the following motion:That D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann approve the following Order in draft, <br /><br />the Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Effective Date for Certain Bodies) Order 2015 and Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Exempted Public Bodies) Order 2015,<br /><br />copies of which were laid before D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann on 10 and 12 March, respectively.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.315" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>In accordance with Standing Order 72 the following message will be sent to the Seanad:
The Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform has completed its consideration of the following motion:That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:
the Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Effective Date for Certain Bodies) Order 2015 and Freedom of Information Act 2014 (Exempted Public Bodies) Order 2015,
copies of which were laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 10 and 12 March, respectively.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-04-01a.316" nospeaker="true" time="16:35:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 5.02 p.m. until 12 noon on Wednesday, 15 April 2015.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>