<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.2" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.3" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 15:45</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Pat Deering, Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, Deputy Martin Ferris, Senator Pat O'Neill. Deputy Martin Heydon, Deputy Willie Penrose, Deputy Michael McNamara, Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív, Deputy Thomas Pringle,</p><p>In attendance: Senator Michael D'Arcy.</p><p>DEPUTY ANDREW DOYLE IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.4" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 4.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.5" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00100">Vote 30 - Update on Pre-Budget and Policy Issues: Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00200"><p>I remind all those present to turn off their mobile phones completely, as they interfere with the broadcasting of proceedings.</p><p>  The purpose of the meeting is to conduct a review of the position on expenditure under Vote 30 in 2014 for the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and consider the Department's proposals for 2015.  I welcome the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, and thank him for appearing before the joint committee.  I also extend a welcome to his officials and thank them for the briefing material supplied to the committee.</p><p>  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>  We agreed to the format of the meeting in private session.  I understand the Minister will make an opening statement, following which we will try to deal with sub-programmes A to D, inclusive, individually, assigning approximately 30 minutes to each.  If we are not too constrained by time at the end, we can have a discussion on the overall budgetary position.  I invite the Minister to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00300"><p>I am sorry, but I do not have two hours.  If it were helpful, I could skip my opening statement in order that we might go straight to examining the expenditure programmes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00400"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00500"><p>I could make the statement.  I am in the Chairman's hands, but as I will also be making a statement to the D&aacute;il at 6.45 p.m., I must be out of here by 6.30 p.m. at the latest.  I would rather it to be 6.15 p.m., if possible.  I could make a statement at this meeting that would take seven or eight minutes, but I am happy to skip it, if the committee wants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00600"><p>No; it would be useful if the Minister made the statement.  We can be well gone in two hours, given the lateness of the hour and the fact that there is much happening this week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00700"><p>Yes.  We would have started earlier, but one of the committee's members tabled a private notice question that I had to take.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00800"><p>No problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H00900"><p>We understand things became a little muddled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H01000"><p>I will make a quick statement, if the committee wants, to give some context to the discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H01100"><p>The Minister might condense it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300003#H01200"><p>I am pleased to accept the invitation to attend the committee's hearing.  This is a valuable opportunity to review how we are progressing through the various challenges and opportunities presenting across the agriculture, food development, marine and forestry sectors and discuss market prospects and new investment opportunities in same.<br/>As we head into the final quarter of 2014, we have many successes on which to reflect and, in equal measure, many challenges to face.  I am pleased to have secured agreement at Government level for a new rural development programme worth &euro;4 billion in the 2014-22 period.  The plan is in Brussels and I look forward to securing approval which, in turn, will enable me to launch new schemes aimed at dealing with the many challenges we face in order that we can be well positioned to respond to growing market opportunities.  I want to secure the same future for the marine sector and have negotiated a new, substantially improved allocation of &euro;147 million under the European Maritime and Fisheries Fund, EMFF, increased from &euro;70 million.  My officials are working on a draft operational programme that will set out a series of measures to drive investment in the sector to 2020.<br/>This is a valuable opportunity to consider some of the wider issues beyond the financial data, including trade developments, issues relating to implementation of the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, and the Common Fisheries Policy, CFP, and the proposals for the main sectors, particularly milk production, where we are on the cusp of achieving for the first time since 1984 a dramatic increase in milk output <i>via</i>the elimination of quotas next year.  If members want an update on superlevy issues, I will try to provide one.<br/>In the financial data we have supplied in the briefing material we have tried to tie the financials and outputs together.  While expenditure in 2014 is the central issue at this meeting, budget 2015 is not too far from members' minds.  However, they are aware that I am somewhat constrained in what I can say about the budget.  In 2014 we are operating within the expenditure ceilings set down of &euro;1.019 billion for current expenditure and &euro;200 million for capital expenditure.  Our outlook for the year is that we will be as close as possible to reaching the target current and capital expenditure limits.  The overarching objective for 2014 has been to build on the progress achieved in recent years in developing the agrifood sector and, in particular, further contributing to future growth and prosperity that the sector can achieve for Ireland.<br/>In terms of the budget, the key priorities were supporting vulnerable sectors and protecting the incomes of family farms; supporting small farm holdings in disadvantaged areas; taxation measures to restructure, modernise and promote growth in the agrifood and farming sectors; providing support programmes in line with the targets of Food Harvest 2020, in particular job creation; supporting the future of the sector through new research and development funding and investment in food safety and animal health and welfare controls; and an ongoing programme of reform within the Department and its agencies aimed at continuing improvement in service delivery and reduced costs.<br/>As members know, my Department's activities are organised under four programmes.  Given my understanding that this is how the committee will review expenditure in 2014, I will not make specific comments at this point.  However, it is useful to highlight the fact that 2014 marks a transitional period between two rural development programmes.  We must take this into account when considering the issue.  I am pleased that, since this discussion session last year, the overall funding package for the seven year programme has been completed and that we are close to completing a similar arrangement for the new seafood development programme.<br/>Elsewhere in the Houses today we have already discussed the beef sector.  Developments in the past 12 months have presented us with a real challenge.  Many of the solutions lie outside the framework of Government spending and policy, but I have been active in seeking to influence and in taking direct action.  I assure the committee that the sector is foremost in my priorities and I will continue to work with the industry at all levels to ensure that not only will we resolve the current issues facing the sector but that we will continue on a path towards achieving the key targets for the sector to which the industry has committed itself in the period to 2020.<br/>In framing last year's budget in difficult financial circumstances I allocated &euro;23 million to supporting the new beef genomics scheme, which will further progress the genetic quality of Irish beef and deliver world best practice in beef traceability.</p> <p>When taken together with the beef data programme, worth &euro;10 million, this allowed me to provide the equivalent of payments worth &euro;60 per calf for some 32,000 herds, covering up to 550,000 suckler calves.  In addition, we had the continuation of the &euro;5 million beef technology adaptation programme, giving a total sector-specific package this year of &euro;40 million for the suckler beef sector.  That, of course, was distinct from the benefits to the sector of the disadvantaged areas scheme payments of &euro;195 million and the single farm payment of &euro;1.21 billion.</p><p> Another special feature of this year's budget was the Government's response to the severe storms and the damage these caused to harbours the length and breadth of the country.  In addition to the increased provision for fisheries harbours, which rose from &euro;8.6 million to &euro;12 million, I announced an additional capital package of &euro;8.5 million for the repair of publicly-owned piers harbours and slipways damaged during the winter storms in early 2014.  The &euro;8.5 million comprised &euro;7 million for 111 projects to repair local authority-owned storm damaged harbours, piers and slipways and &euro;1.5 million for remediation work at four Department-owned non-fishery harbour centres.</p><p> Looking to 2015, arising from the public finances situation, total Exchequer expenditure by my Department has reduced from &euro;2.1 billion in 2008 to &euro;1.219 billion in 2014.  The 2015 expenditure ceiling for the Department was provisionally set down in the 2014 budget report as &euro;1.005 billion in current expenditure and &euro;168 million in capital expenditure but the financial determination of the 2015 allocation was postponed until after the completion of the Comprehensive Review of Expenditure 2015-2017.</p><p> Among the particular priorities this year is to provide an appropriate level of funding to launch both the new rural development programme and the seed food development programme under the European Maritime and Fisheries Fund.  The successful negotiations of both the new seven-year rural development programmes and the seed food development programme will heavily influence the Department's current and capital spending plans for the coming years.  The RDP provides for an overall funding envelope, EU and Exchequer, over the period of some &euro;4 billion.  As part of that decision, it was agreed that the total Exchequer allocation would be subject to an affordability review in 2016 but the members will be familiar with the figures we have committed to in terms of the 46% co-funding rate.</p><p> The June 2014 announcement by the Commission of an allocation of &euro;146.3 million for Ireland under the new European Maritime and Fisheries Fund is significant for the sector.  In aggregate terms, this is roughly a doubling of Ireland's allocation of EU funds relative to our allocations under the former EFF and EU financial instruments for sea-fisheries control and data collection.  The Department is preparing a new operational programme within the EU co-funding framework, and this must be submitted for approval to the Commission shortly.  The expanded EMFF will give rise to increased Exchequer co-financing of the sector which is being finalised within the budget process at the moment.</p><p> I hope that gives an indication of some of the issues we are managing at the moment.  If members have any questions, I will be happy to answer them.  Otherwise, we can go through the four different programme areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300004#J00200"><p>We agreed to go through the programme individually so I now invite questions or comments on programme A, starting with Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300004#J00300"><p>I thank the Minister for the outline.  I am not saying this as a personal criticism of him as the same thing was happening when we were in government.  However, when all of this talk about output targets came in, I remember being very critical of it at the time because I always believed that the output targets would be just another layer of bureaucracy, another box-ticking exercise we would all get involved in, taking staff time without really having any benefit.</p><p>  Programme A states that the target is to secure a beneficial outcome for the agriculture, food, forestry and fishing sectors in EU and international negotiations.  As any person would say, first, the Minister is unlikely to try to do anything else and, second, he is very unlikely to come back and say the outcome was not beneficial.  It is a pity the target was not more specific.  I am sure that when Senator Mary Ann O'Brien was running her business, the targets were more specific than that.  I am sure she did not just say the business should increase sales but that it should hit a specific target, as that is what the private sector would do, and if the target was not hit, that would be admitted.  I believe that either this exercise should give us real and meaningful targets next year or we should just abandon it.  We have no way of measuring success or failure against nebulous targets like that, and it would take us all day to find out what the specific targets were and how they were measured.  I doubt the Minister succeeded in getting everything he set out to get but we do not know.</p><p>  With regard to trade, the target is to continue the initiative to facilitate trade and market access for exports of food, beverages, genomics and live animals.  The Minister talks about all of the different things he did in regard to incoming and outgoing trade visits and market access.  Do we have any quantification as to what proportion of markets these visits represent?  For example, what proportion of our sales are to the markets of Mozambique, the Philippines, Nigeria, Ethiopia, Palestine, Japan and Australia?  What are the target increases we are going to achieve in these markets from all the activity?  While I am of course in favour of the activity, I believe it should be much more specific.  I do not expect the Minister to have all these answers today but this is very disappointing because we have all these targets yet the committee has no way to measure them.</p><p>  The Minister's brief states that he will continue to implement Food Harvest 2020.  He said a progress report was launched on 17 September and that 74% of the Food Harvest recommendations have either been achieved or that substantive action has been taken.  Is it the case that this action was taken on the recommendations?  How do we measure the recommendations or the achievement of output results against what was in Food Harvest 2020?</p><p>  While I do not want to delay the meeting, I believe this exercise needs to sharpen up in terms of targets if it is to be worth having at all.  If we are not going to do that, we would be better going back to the old system and just going through the figures and measuring against those figures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300004#J00400"><p>I thank the Minister for his presentation.  As Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v said, it is almost impossible to get into the actual specifics so I would like to focus on the prospects and the intentions that formed part of the Minister's presentation.  The Minister referred to the opportunities regarding the implementation of the CAP and the CFP and regarding the main sectors, particularly milk, where, for the first time since 1984, there has been a dramatic increase in milk output with the elimination of quotas.  How confident is the Minister that the vision or intent can be realised in regard to achieving the potential that exists?</p> <p>I say that in relation to my concern, on which I have been consistent since the very beginning, about the abolition of quotas.  In effect, it will be the end of the smaller producers in particular.  As is happening in the beef sector at the moment, margins are getting smaller and smaller.  Is the Minister satisfied that the potential can be realised and that this will not have an impact on the weaker, marginal producers?  What is the Minister's target for production in that regard in 2020?</p><p> Referring to the weaker sector again, concerns have been raised in the committee and the D&aacute;il Chamber on the curtailing of farm assist payments.  What interaction has Deputy Coveney had with the relevant Minister in that regard?  Is there any prospect of returning to the 2009, 2010 or 2011 level of farm assist, which helped the marginal, weaker farmers to survive?</p><p> Regarding the rural development programmes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00200"><p>That is in programme C.  We will stick with programme A and I will come back to the Deputy for programme C.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00300"><p>I welcome the Minister and his officials to the committee.  Regarding the Food Harvest 2020 targets, 74% of the recommendations have been achieved or substantive action has been taken in relation to them.  How does the Department quantify what has been achieved so far, considering that we are now six years from 2020?  There has been a great deal of discussion and debate on the beef situation over the past 12 months or so.  From a beef point of view, how are we doing with regard to the Food Harvest 2020 targets?  How do we see ourselves in the next year?  The past year has been a difficult and challenging time.  Are the targets set out in Harvest 2020 achievable and attainable from a beef point of view?  New markets are crucial to developing the beef industry.  Extra funds were spent by Bord Bia over the last year to generate new markets.  How have we been progressing from that point of view?</p><p>  As we approach next March and the end of the super-levy, which is welcome, the milk targets seem to be very achievable.  While I am probably getting off the point to a certain extent, a potential consequence for a number of farmers building up in advance of the abolition of the quota is a huge super-levy bill in the coming period.  What progress have we made to alleviate or soften the blow for those who may be liable for super-levy bills in March?  Might that have an effect on the possibility of future development in the area?  While development is welcome, I concur with Deputy Ferris's view regarding the small milk producer.  Is there a need to be careful and conservative as we progress in the coming years to avoid creating a bubble similar to the property bubble?  A number of farmers may be transferring from other sectors to the dairy sector unaware of the consequences going forward and unsure or unaware of their future financial situation, considering that in the past two months we have seen a 4 cent drop in the price of milk per litre.  That may continue and they may not have budgeted for it.  Is it sustainable, and do we need to flag it to warn people that it may not all be honey going forward and of the need to be careful and conservative?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/949" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00400"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for coming before the committee.  I will not rehash the areas touched on, but will ask a general question on trade and trade missions.  I am mindful, looking at beef, that the key thing about getting into America is not necessarily quantity, but rather the quality of the cuts they take and, reputationally, how much that helps us.  What is the difference between the key markets?  When it comes to milk, beef and our key exports, what markets have the potential to be about real quantity?  Is it the Middle East, where there is a growing middle class?  How many of the markets are more like niche markets in relation to our beef?  If one looks at England, to which we provide so much, is there scope for growing our export opportunities over there?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00500"><p>I have a quick statement for the Minister, in case I am missing something.  The Department's budget was &euro;2.1 billion in 2008.  In 2014, it has a &euro;1.219 billion budget.  Food Harvest 2020 came about when I first attended the Global Irish Economic Forum in 2011.  It appears from the other questions that it has gone terribly well, particularly in light of the budget the Minister now enjoys, which is rather smaller than previously, yet we seem to be enjoying humongous growth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00600"><p>We spend it better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00700"><p>From where I am looking in, the Minister is doing more with less.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00800"><p>Going back to the old format, I note that the research and training allocation is &euro;28 million, but to the end of August, &euro;9.7 million is all that has been spent.  I am not sure if there is a reason for that.  It might be back-ended.  Does the Minister have any insight into that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K00900"><p>The Minister's progress report sets out in relation to Food Harvest 2020 that 55% of recommendations were achieved and substantial progress was made on another 37%.  That is good progress, adding up to nearly 92%.  In relation to the 37% figure for substantial progress, can the Minister provide a breakdown of what can be done to achieve full progress?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300005#K01000"><p>To reply to Deputy &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, we are trying not only to talk about numbers, but to set policy targets also.  To be fair, the process probably began before we came into office.  The targets are pretty general but the mid-year outputs are specific.  An example relates to securing beneficial outcomes for the agrifood, forestry and fisheries sectors in EU and international negotiations.  What we did in relation to the EU-Canada free trade agreement was very specific.  I assure the committee that Ireland was in the middle of that.  It would have been a very different deal if we had not been in terms of access to Europe for Canadian beef.  We took a trade mission to the USA, which was very useful in terms of any future EU-USA trade deal.  Likewise, some very constructive things were done in New Zealand, particularly with Fonterra.</p><p>  While we did the specific things itemised, I take the point that if there are very general targets, it is easy to make the case that one is meeting them.  It may be that for next year we need to consider more specific targets.  However, one needs to set targets at the start of the year, which often change during the year.  I am very involved in speaking to the European Commission about how we are responding to the Russian ban on agrifood exports.  We now have butter and cheese in the scheme for aid to private storage, whereas it would previously have been only butter.</p> <p>These are things that happen and which must be responded to, but they are covered by the general target of responding to international challenges as they arise.  The document details many measures taken in order to make specific the more general targets that were set, but I take the point the Deputy makes; perhaps we should be more detailed in setting targets, particularly in the Food Harvest 2020 plan.  However, last week we published this very detailed response outlining our position relative to the Food Harvest 2020 targets.</p><p> We are ahead of most in this regard.  There is speculation as to whether we can meet the Food Harvest 2020 targets on beef, but in fact we are already meeting them.  The beef target was a 40% value growth between when the target was set and 2020.  We are at 39% already, so it is understandable that farmers are questioning whether it is wise to expand the beef industry when prices are weak, but we have met the Food Harvest 2020 targets for beef.  Regarding dairy, we have had a 42% increase in value before any volume increase.  We are ahead of schedule for practically all of the actual Food Harvest 2020 targets.  That is why we will soon put a new programme in place for 2025, so that we will have a ten-year horizon with new targets, taking up new challenges like climate change, generational change, land mobility, and so on, which are all linked to productivity and modernisation within Irish agriculture and primary food production.  That process will get under way soon.</p><p> I have to say, and I hope people will recognise that I am generous about this politically, the Food Harvest 2020 plan has been the best thing to happen to agriculture in many years.  It was put in place by the previous Government, but we have picked that up, we have run with it, we have added to it and we have changed the targets.  We invite professors from Harvard to come over and assess it each year under the pathways programme and challenge the industry at all levels on how they are meeting the targets that Food Harvest 2020 sets for them.  That has been a very good focus for the industry from point of view of productivity, competitiveness and production.  Of course there is another side to agriculture that we must look after, but the Food Harvest story has been a very good one and I would encourage people to read Food Harvest 2020 Milestones for Success 2014.  It goes through in great detail, sector-by-sector, what we are doing and what we must do to keep the growth story going.  </p><p> On Deputy Ferris's questions on dairy quotas, there is an assumption out there that if we produce less milk prices will stay stronger.  There is a feeling that there may be a danger for small farmers that if we focus on volume output, we are becoming more commercial and that prices will decrease and margins tighten.  Dairy is very different from beef, for example.  Dairy prices in Ireland are almost entirely determined by the international price of traded dairy product.  If we increased our output by 50% over the next five years, as planned, or if we did nothing to increase output, the price per litre of milk, in terms of price volatility, would remain more or less the same between now and 2020.  We export 90% of what we produce and we are a small player in relative terms; if Ireland doubles its output we will still be a significantly smaller producer than the US state of Wisconsin, which produces 12 billion litres of milk per year at the moment.  We currently produce just over 5 billion.  If we get to 10 billion litres per year, which I think we could, we will still be smaller than one state in the United States.  </p><p> It is important that people understand that we are operating in a world market in dairy products more so than in any other product, and there are both positive and negative aspects to that.  For the last two years it has been fantastic because prices have been strong and there has been a shortage.  Dairy consumption growth has been well ahead of dairy production growth and so we have had the strongest prices we have ever seen for dairy products for the last two years.  That price is weakening now.  We have two very good years for grain production and there is a direct correlation between cheap grain and milk prices weakening, which is exactly what is happening at the moment.  Grain has been relatively cheap globally for two years, milk production has increased as a result, especially in the United States, and so the price of milk is coming under pressure.  For us, on a grass-based system, the price of grain is far less relevant, so when grain is expensive we will be very price competitive in terms of producing milk on the back of grass.  When grain is cheap, we will find it more of a challenge.  Either way, Ireland is very well placed over the next five to ten years to produce more milk and to get a good return from that milk.  </p><p> Choosing not to expand our dairy production and meet the Food Harvest 2020 targets would not contribute significantly to maintaining a higher price for smaller farmers because prices will be determined by markets outside Ireland, where we sell practically all our milk.  I am probably over-emphasising that point, but we cannot make assumptions based, for example, on the view in the beef industry that once one goes over 30,000 animals a week the price seems to weaken.  That is a matter for debate but this does not hold for dairy.  New Zealand, for example, has quadrupled the volume of milk production in the past 30 years and the price has roughly doubled in the meantime.  This is about world markets for dairy products and it is about getting into markets that can pay premium prices for premium product.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300006#L00200"><p>I do not think that is the concern that has been voiced.  I have no doubt that if established dairy farmers grow their businesses and do not have to borrow inordinate amounts of money, they will be able to take the vicissitudes and volatility that are inevitably involved in any world trade commodity.  The big worry people have, as we should know from what has happened in recent years, is that those who borrow large amounts to expand, or who do not have huge experience in the industry and lack that knowledge of a lifetime passed from family to family, will rush in and have money thrown at them.  Then when the price drops or anything else goes wrong, they are totally vulnerable.  I see this particularly in the people who went bust when the housing bubble burst.  If they had bought their houses with cash, all they would have to do is to wait long enough for the value of their houses to rise again.  The problem is that they bought them on borrowed money.  On the other hand, the forestry industry, which I am very familiar with, survived despite a massive shock because they had not borrowed.  They were cash-rich businesses, so that when shock came, they could absorb it, gain new markets and get over the hump.  This has meant that we have not had one casualty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300006#L00300"><p>That is a fair point.  I have met all the banks in Ireland on multiple occasions to discuss this issue.  Many farmers in New Zealand are effectively working for the bank rather than themselves.  We cannot allow that to happen to a new generation of Irish farmers with the excitement around quota expansion.  Ironically, in some ways the weakening of dairy prices forces dairy farmers to ensure that their business plan is robust.  In terms of investment proposition and increasing output, anybody can build a business on 40 cent a litre, but can this be done on 30 or 28 cent a litre?  I have said to all the banks, and they say they are listening, that they should insist on business plans on the basis of 30 cent a litre and no more.  Some are looking for plans based on 28 cent a litre.  If milk has a higher price than that, which I hope it will have, then all the better, but that should be the basis for the business plan.</p> <p>There is also a big job for us to do in training new dairy farmers, and that is why we are investing significant money in knowledge transfer, discussion groups and  education programmes.  Our plans for expansion will, in my view, be realised.  </p><p> Along with the Taoiseach and a few others, I had the privilege of opening some new facilities for Dairygold during the week.  The total value of the investment in the two projects in Mallow and Mitchelstown was about &euro;120 million.  As a farmer-owned co-operative, Dairygold has direct access to information from the farmers, and based on this it is planning for a 57% expansion in volume in the next five years.  This is because Dairygold comes from a part of the country that can do that.  Glanbia will have similar figures, somewhere around 60%.  Dairygold and Glanbia will probably have the highest figures, but the others are not a million miles behind.  Even in Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v's part of the country they have very ambitious plans for growth and expansion.  The key is for them to operate on the back of good business plans as opposed to having inefficient systems spending money that they do not have, and to put pricing models in place in the dairy sector that can insulate farmers from the price volatility that will undoubtedly happen.  </p><p> Prices will weaken for the next six to eight months, but I think they will strengthen again after that period.  We will get weather patterns that will result in crop failures, and grain and milk prices will increase again.  That is the kind of pattern that we have to get used to.  We are very well placed to insulate ourselves where possible from that price volatility because of the steadiness of grass production systems in terms of input costs and because we are developing a premium brand around Irish dairy.  This is no longer about commodity trading of skimmed, semi-skimmed and whole milk powders, although we have some of that.  It is now about premium cheeses and butters - we produce the premium butter in the world in Kerrygold - as well as infant formula and nutrition, sports nutrition and so on.  All of that premiumisation of the dairy industry helps to insulate us from the price volatility that exists when one is trading commodities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300007#M00200"><p>It is now 5.30 p.m., so we have twenty minutes remaining for the other three programmes.  It would be helpful to concentrate on the Vote.  Programme A is agrifood policy, development and trade, and training and the various different sectors' pay.  The narrative is around trying to support that but there is also the matter of how the budget is channelled.  Going back to what Senator O'Brien said, getting more for less and being more efficient is key.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300007#M00300"><p>The one financial question that you asked me, Chairman, concerned the training and research budget.  This looks to be way under-spent.  The research programmes and the call for new expenditure always happen in the autumn, so there will be a dramatic increase in expenditure between now and the end of the year.  Some of the schemes and funded research programmes are very much autumn-focused.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300007#M00400"><p>Do the enhanced young farmer and training initiatives, such as the dairy management diploma among others, come under A.3, or is that from the Teagasc fund?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300007#M00500"><p>I suspect they do.  If we are going to have about 300,000 more cows in our herd between now and 2020, which is an increase of approximately 25% to 30%, we will get the other 25% growth from increased yield in cows.  As a rule of thumb, it takes about one person to milk 100 cows.  That is a conservative figure so it may take more in many family farm situations.  That means that we are going to have an extra 3,000 people milking cows in five years.  Many of those people will not have farms but will be coming in to milk on other people's farms.  This will be similar to the current situation in New Zealand, where professional dairy experts advise on management, grazing, feeding, delivering the best yield and feed conversion efficiency, and all of the other things that our dairy industry will be about.  This requires training programmes and we are putting some of those in place as we speak, although more are needed.</p><p>  On the beef question that Deputy Deering asked, we have spent more time on beef this summer than anything else and I suspect we will also be spending more time on it this autumn than anything else.  The big target market for the next six weeks or so is the US.  We have been working on that for two years and are more or less through all the barriers.  Irish beef will be the first European beef into the US market in 16 years, since BSE, and for the first time ever the price of beef in the US is as high as the price of beef in Europe.  It is a great time to be getting into the east coast of the US in particular.  It will be a big new opportunity for us.  </p><p>  In recent days we have also finalised veterinary certification for exporting beef to Iran, and ironically I have had two meetings with the Iranian ambassador in the past ten days and am meeting a political delegation today.  We may take a trade mission to Iran in the spring.  They have 80 million people and import a fortune's worth of beef, from Brazil at the moment.  They are very interested in trying to get European and Irish beef back into Iranian markets at premium level.  We are also going to China in six weeks' time.  We will have at least 60 Irish companies with us and all the big beef companies will be there.  We are currently selling about &euro;40 million worth of beef hides into China, but if we can sell beef into China and can get the restrictions removed, this would be most exciting as there is a very high-end premium market in big cities like Shanghai, Beijing and Nanjing.  </p><p>  The two markets that will excite the industry most are the US and China, however last year we opened markets in Japan, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, and UAE.  Previously 40% of beef in Saudi Arabia was Irish, so these markets have been a proven success story in the past, and there are multiple new market opportunities opening up for us.  This is why we should be able to slaughter more than 30,000 animals a week in the future, and still get premium prices for our products.  However, we have to be very proactive in opening up some of these new premium markets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300007#M00600"><p>It is evident that there is going to be a surge in the dairy sector.  Within the farming community, the returns in dairy have been far more beneficial than in any other sector.  The Minister, Deputy Coveney, mentioned that dairy in New Zealand has quadrupled, and that is true, but so has the number of farmers there whose property is practically owned by the banks.  My fear is that the same thing can happen here.  People may go into huge investment.  The small farmer might not be able to invest in developing his farm to reach the potential that is necessary, because he will not be able to get the money.  There is a certain group within the dairy sector that will benefit considerably in this regard.  There will also be people switching into dairy from other sectors.  Anybody who is coming from potatoes, corn, vegetables or beef and switching over to the dairy sector will have to make a huge outlay to get into that sector.  I would love to see it working as the Minister, Deputy Coveney, has put it, but I do have worries.  I come from that background myself, so I have seen it all on a different scale going way back to when I was involved in farming and when I was a child.  People were switching from one sector to another, following the market.  It was easy enough at that time because they did not have to make huge investments in milking parlours, or robot parlours as they seem to be now, for want of a better word.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00100"><p>I compliment the Minister.  It is important that we open new markets and it is to be hoped the US market will be an exciting one for Irish beef.  I have a question on the new markets.  They will also be opened to other countries.  The Minister and the new Commissioner will be part of the discussions on world trade agreements, especially those on South American beef, which will become our largest threat in supplying certain markets.  What is the current position in regard to the disease status of South American beef?  Will that have an effect should it gain status in regard to world trade agreements and competition for our beef?  Japan is a considerable distance away in terms of exporting beef.  I presume we would only export certain cuts and offal, and the same would apply to the Chinese market.  The US would not be as difficult to export to.  It was mentioned that 40% of the beef consumed in Saudi Arabia was exported from Ireland, but a lot of that comprised live exports.  Is it envisaged that the sanctions on live exports will be eased in terms of the compliance regulations regarding animal welfare for shipping companies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00200"><p>I am anxious that we concentrate on the budget, because we are constrained by time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00300"><p>I asked a supplementary question.  It came from what the Minister said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00400"><p>I know it did, but we are in more abstract territory.  In regard to the point made by Deputies Ferris and &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, it is important that the banks learn from their mistakes and that everybody does not follow a fad or fashion.  Someone who is considering entering the dairy market may factor in a budget of 30 cent, rather than 35 cent or 40 cent, a litre as a tipping point; otherwise, the business plan may not work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00500"><p>I refer to the beef genomic scheme in which the Minister is investing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00600"><p>The Deputy is covering a lot of schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00700"><p>For some reason it is under programme A.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00800"><p>My apologies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.48" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N00900"><p>I would prefer to take all the schemes together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N01000"><p>Will we put that under programme C?  We will move on.  We have gone over time on this matter.  We have 50 minutes to discuss three programmes.  Programme B concerns food safety, animal health and welfare and plant health.  Are there any observations from members?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N01100"><p>About ten years ago there was a major effort to get all-Ireland arrangements on animal and plant health, rather than treating the North as part of Britain which, whatever one's political leanings, does not make sense from the point of view of geography and bio-security.  It was proposed that there be one common regime for animal and plant health for the island, because it was the only chance we had to secure the sea border.  Is that still on the agenda?  Given that devolution is now happening in many places, could Ireland be recognised as one unit for the purposes of animal and plant health and welfare?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N01200"><p>Are there any other questions on food safety and animal and plant health and welfare?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/949" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N01300"><p>The mid-year output for TSE testing is at 32,500.  These tests were not outlined in the 2014 target.  Is there a reason they were conducted despite the fact that no targets were in place?  Are there targets?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300008#N01400"><p>The target was to carry out 85,000 TSE tests on prescribed animals, and to date 48,000 have been tested.  On animal health, we have learned some valuable lessons from the horsemeat issue.  Safety and hygiene inspections and supervision in factories protect the reputation of our industry.  If our reputation is damaged, our capacity to enter the new markets we have discussed is affected.  Within our Department it would not be an exaggeration to say we are somewhat obsessed with hygiene and food safety.  We need to be because when things go wrong it is as if there is a red alert in the Department due to the potential for reputational damage.  That is why we have carried out 9,500 food safety and hygiene inspections.  By the end of June 8,500 were done.  We were supposed to do fewer than 9,500 in the full year but by the end of June we had almost reached the threshold.  We will go way beyond the targets we have set for ourselves.  We overdo inspections from a safety and hygiene perspective for the reputational reasons to which I referred.</p><p>  In terms of the all-island strategy, animal and plant health is probably the main and most consistent feature of the North-South Ministerial Council meetings.  It is constantly inching forward.  There are some problems about which it is important to be up-front.  We have spent a lot of money and time building the reputation of Irish beef and dairy products.  We have an orange and green programme and quality assurance schemes, and a dairy sustainability assurance scheme is being rolled out.  Many of these schemes are not being taken up in Northern Ireland.  We have to ask what is the target.  In terms of the broader politics, I want a united Ireland at some stage in the future which deals with these issues collectively as a food-producing island.  In the meantime, we are working to ensure there is co-operation, collaboration and partnership around managing risk in terms of animal and plant health spread.  A good example of that is how we are dealing with ash dieback disease, where there is very close co-operation.  We have led on the BVD scheme; there is good partnership and it is being implemented.  The North is slightly behind us, but on Johne's disease it is slightly ahead.  We are working with it in order that we have the same types of scheme.  </p><p>  On TB, unfortunately there are differences of approach for political reasons.  Our approach has been hugely successful.  There is a slightly different approach in the UK but we work quite closely together.  There are lots of good examples of efforts to create ease of movement of animals North and South in terms of trade and trying to manage risk in terms of disease and animal health so we can create the kind of consistency which, it is to be hoped, will allow us to have a brand around an Irish product coming from the island of Ireland.  However, the risk should not be ignored in our efforts to be open to partnership with the North.  The risk is that if a product is labelled as Irish but comes from Northern Ireland, and there is a problem such as dioxins, disease or whatever which compromises food safety, as the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine I have to stand over it, even thought my vets were not in the factory where the animal was slaughtered or at the processor which packaged the product.  We need to have very tight protocols with Northern Ireland to ensure there are common standards, because if I am to stand over something which was produced in a different jurisdiction there are risks.</p><p>  There are other issues with regard to currency, for example.  If all milk in Northern Ireland is deemed to be part of the Irish milk pool on the island of Ireland and sterling weakens, there would be competitiveness issues which we could not ignore.  There are similar difficulties with petrol.  We have to manage the North and South in a way that focuses on partnership and working together mutually to build up a reputation for food being exported from the island.  I would be open to joint trade missions, for example, but I do not want to undermine the fantastic work done by organisations such as Bord Bia to build a reputation around Irish food produced under our system, which involves controls, checks, inspections and all the rest.  The industry is worried about that in the context of a broader ambition to create an island-of-Ireland approach towards food production. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00100"><p>I wish to clarify the point I was making.  We are on one landmass but we have two different standards.  There are farmers who own land on both sides of the Border and who move the cattle over and back.  Given all of that, the nature of animal health and welfare and that diseases can travel easily on land, it seems to me a totally unsatisfactory situation if any part of the island, under whatever jurisdiction, does not adhere to the highest standards.  Even if we have all the protection that the Minister has referred to, including different marketing and so on, we are at far greater risk than we would be if they had exactly the same regimes that we have.</p><p>  Given that we now have a Northern minister and that devolution seems to be the catchphrase from London, rather than adhering to the British standards, which by all accounts are not the high standards we are going for, I am suggesting that those in the North come up with a common all-Ireland top-level standard for everything produced on this island.  This is not for political reasons but for practical reasons and because it is the most bio-secure thing we can do.  I imagine that when the Minister speaks to his colleague in the North, she will be totally with him on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00200"><p>The only issue is that many of these schemes are voluntary, but they have effectively become non-voluntary.  Let us consider the beef quality assurance scheme, setting aside what the Irish Cattle and Sheep Farmers' Association has been saying recently.  There is an increasing take-up of the quality assurance scheme because farmers get better prices for their beef.  Several factories will not now take beef that is not quality-assured.  Therefore, it is effectively becoming mandatory.  It is part of the premiumisation of Irish beef.</p><p>  Farmers in the North can buy into that if they want, but there is a far lower take-up.  I get what Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v is saying.  I have been very open to the rolling out of Bord Bia programmes in the North.  In fact, quality assurance schemes are available to Northern farmers in many cases.  Anyway, we have some work to do yet to create an all-island standard.  There are some in the North who would be far happier remaining with British standards.  It is an ongoing discussion and we will have it again on Friday week, I suspect, at the next North-South Ministerial Council meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00300"><p>I have a brief question on a different area completely.  Last spring twelvemonth we had difficulties with the fodder prices and so on.  There were almost 1,100 calls to the Department on the issue.  How does that compare to the past year?  How does it compare to previous years?  Traditionally, farmers would have been reluctant to ring the Department when such a situation arose.  How have the figures compared?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00400"><p>We will hear a quick question from Deputy Heydon, and I have another point I wish to raise myself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/949" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00500"><p>My question is on tuberculosis testing.  The projected outturn or target is 8.4 million tests, while 8.5 million tests were carried out last year.  How do we get rid of TB and, by extension, TB testing?  We have made good progress in recent years, but surely the more progress we make the harder it is to get rid of the last of it.  Is it realistic to suggest that we can eradicate TB when we consider the problems we have in the wild outside of our control stock?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00600"><p>My question relates to TB testing as well.  I have the figures on BSE testing in front of me.  I note the Department is not testing healthy slaughtered animals from 4 March.  In other words, animals that are brought to knackeries have to be tested.  Does this apply only to animals over four years of age?  Are they the only animals being tested or are all animals at knackeries over a certain age being tested?  Given age and demographics, will we eventually be in situation whereby we will not need to test any animals at knackeries for BSE?  Any animal born after a certain date is BSE-free because we stopped feeding meat and bonemeal and so on.  Will that be a saving in the budget?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00700"><p>My apologies, Chairman, for arriving late.  My question relates to the outturn at the end of August.  Given the average for the year, the Department appears to be &euro;11 million behind budget under programme B.  The figure for wages seems to be &euro;5 million above what has been budgeted based on the average over the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00800"><p>Which section is &euro;5 million above?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O00900"><p>The section relating to overall expenditure under programme B, with an outturn at the end of August of &euro;128 million.  If we project that number out over 12 months it will be approximately &euro;11 million below budget.  Also, the figure for wages is running at &euro;7 million, or &euro;5 million above budget.  Does the Minister have any information on this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01000"><p>The current expenditure outturn for 2014 is currently &euro;128 million.  The estimate was &euro;203 million.  The expenditure does not always happen in an even manner throughout the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01100"><p>That is what I wanted to ask.  Is it likely that things will take off in the next four months to close that gap?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01200"><p>Yes, I think so.  My understanding is that we are likely to spend our full Estimate this year.  That has not always been the case and obviously the process is managed.  My understanding is that this is the case.  We have made savings in terms of food safety, animal health and so on.  Let us consider TB, for example.  I am unsure whether it was Deputy Heydon or Deputy Deering who said that we are not making progress on TB.  In 2009 there were 23,500 cases of TB.  Last year, there were 15,500 cases, fully 9,000 fewer animals.  There has been phenomenal progress on TB.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01300"><p>I will interrupt here.  I come from one of the black spot areas, as the Minister is probably aware, where there has been a spike and we have many problems.  Clare is possibly another such area.  The national average has gone down to approximately four per 1,000, but the average is eight per 1,000 in County Wicklow.  Will black spot areas have targeted resources that have been saved from other places to try to identify and isolate cases and bring the figures down to the national average?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01400"><p>That is the case at the moment.  We target resources, including for culling badgers.  Herds are frozen, effectively, once there is an outbreak.  We are trying to isolate problems, deal with them, slaughter the animals, compensate the farmers and deal with the wildlife issue, including badgers, and I know there is a potential issue with wild deer in the Chairman's area.  We must take on these issues, as difficult as they may be.  Let us consider the average figures nationally.  We have gone from spending approximately &euro;60 million per year on this problem four or five years ago to spending &euro;34 million per year now.  It is major progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01500"><p>I am not saying it is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01600"><p>I take your point, Chairman.  If there are specific problem areas we will have to try to develop solutions for those problem areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01700"><p>Let us consider the &euro;83 million for animal welfare.  I realise the figure is not broken down specifically.  How much of that figure is going on BSE testing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01800"><p>The figure for BSE testing is rather small.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O01900"><p>It was identified in the original Vote last year in the budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O02000"><p>The figure is &euro;1.25 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O02100"><p>That figure is down from what, approximately?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300009#O02200"><p>We are still carrying out many testing programmes on carcasses to ensure that we are monitoring and on top of that, but it is down.  The actual test is not a big expense; compensation is the main expense.  Sorry; I am referring to TB.  BSE testing represents small money.</p><p>  Deputy Deering asked me about the fodder crisis.  Let us recall when the fodder crisis arose.  It had been predicted because we had an extraordinary weather pattern involving a very bad winter, no summer and then straight back into another very wet winter.  There was virtually no break for farmers for almost 18 months.  Land was totally sodden.  Then we had a late spring.</p> <p>We had virtually no grass growth in much of the country and even where there was growth, the ground was too wet to put animals out on it.  An extraordinary number of weather patterns, one after the other, added hugely to the problem.  We learned significant lessons from this.  We are now in a very healthy position and have been all year in terms of fodder.  We had a great summer last year and again this year, the inverse of what happened previously.  We had a mild and relatively dry winter and probably the best grass growth ever this year.  Some farmers are taking four cuts of silage.  </p><p> We are entering winter this year in a healthy state from a stock point of view.  Teagasc now conducts a national audit of fodder availability at intervals to ensure we are properly prepared.  We will not always have summers like that we have just had and need to prepare for the kind of nightmare scenario and weather patterns we had two years ago and ensure we have enough fodder in stock next time.  We do not want to have to import grass from France and the United Kingdom.  From our perspective, that is a bit like Eskimos importing snow.  We should never find ourselves in that position again.  Farmers, dairy farmers in particular, have learned lessons from what happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00200"><p>We will move on to programme C - rural economy, environmental and structural changes.  It is now 6 p.m. so we have half an hour for this and the next item.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00300"><p>I refer to the whole ball of wax in regard to direct payments - the single payment, area of natural constraint, ANC, and everything else.  If we look at all of the grants, there was a 10% drop between 2011 and 2013 and last year there was a drop of &euro;1.769 billion.  The total will be down again this year and next.  Part of the reason for this is that the single payment has decreased globally, but we are also going to be in a valley period in terms of money coming under the rural development programme, because the REPS payments have virtually stopped and AEOS is coming to an end.</p><p>  As the Minister rightly said in the D&aacute;il today, the GLAS payments will not come on stream in a significant way until 2015.  Has the Minister the figures in regard to how much direct payments will have dropped between 2011 and 2015 - payments which keep many farmers going?  What is he going to do to try to level off this payment?  It has come down, but I accept it will rise.  However, it will never go back to where it was.  Live horse, get grass - the farmer must survive, but there will be huge pressure on farmers.  Can the Minister quantify how much the total in direct payments will drop from 2011 to 2015 before they begin to rise again?</p><p>  In regard to piers, I notice under C7, fisheries - as I would have predicted because I know how slow these things are - that only &euro;2.4 million of the &euro;17.95 million put into the Revised Estimate has been spent.  I know the Department will receive a pile of bills from the councils in November or December.  However, knowing what is happening in my county, I would reckon that between planning permission, the National Parks and Wildlife Service and whatever else, many of the works that have been approved will not be done and dusted by the end of the year, depending on the amount of work.  Can the Minister guarantee he will be able to carry forward those capital moneys into next year?   This is vital because in the case of substantial works, if works are approved in March and one must go through all the statutory obligations and consultation, particularly in highly sensitive environmental areas where there are significant problems as a result, it will prove impossible to get the various planning requirements in place and work tendered and completed by the end of the year.  Can the Minister guarantee he will be able to guarantee a roll-over of the moneys in question to next year?  Normally one can carry over unspent capital and it is vital we are assured of that.</p><p>  My next question relates to genomics.  Based on the figures given by the Minister, I estimate a little under the Minister's budget of &euro;23 million, some &euro;22 million, indicates that give or take half the farmers joined the scheme this year.  If the other half does not join the new scheme in time next year, will this have a detrimental impact on them or will it undermine the whole project?  Significant money is being spent on trying to get the genomics project right and to improve the suckler cow herd.  Has any study been done on the effect of a significant increase in the number of dairy animals that will comprise the dairy herd?  Only a proportion of these will be needed as heifers for replacements.  Given that selection of the sex of calves will be more prevalent, we will have huge numbers of dairy cross beef breeds, which will change the metrics of the genomic scheme.  Therefore, we could have these animals coming in from the side, whose primary purpose as dams is to produce milk but which will have to be disposed of into the beef herd because of the huge surplus.  Has the impact of this on the suckler cow farmer been examined?  How does this fit in regard to genomics and trying to get the best beef breeds when we will have a greater proportion of dairy breeds going for beef?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00400"><p>I have just two questions.  In regard to the target to achieve 200 agriculture licence determinations this year, how many have been made and what progress is being made on the appropriate assessments in regard to Natura 2000 bays?</p><p>  In regard to the increase in tonnage of foreign catch to be processed in Ireland in the whitefish sector, has any assessment been made of the impact on prices for Irish vessels of encouraging foreign vessels to land whitefish here?  I have heard anecdotal evidence that this has caused a reduction in prices for Irish vessels, because they do not have a quota that can guarantee supply to processors.  Has any information been gathered on the impact of this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00500"><p>Will the Deputy put that question again please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00600"><p>What is the policy in regard to foreign vessels landing whitefish here for processing.  I have heard some anecdotal stories that this is impacting on the prices Irish vessels can get for whitefish because they do not have a quota that can guarantee supply to processors.  Has any assessment been made of whether there is any basis to this or whether there has been a significant impact in regard to prices Irish vessels can get when competing with vessels that have far bigger quotas and can guarantee supply?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00700"><p>I have a brief question in regard to the targeted agricultural modernisation scheme, TAMS.  There appears to be a significant backlog of applications in the system, going back months or even to last year.  What is the reason for this?  I presume the funding is there.  Is there a problem with the application process or have the criteria changed?  Can the process be streamlined?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00800"><p>Are there any other questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300010#P00900"><p>I have a technical question.  Last week I asked a question about the increase in employment in the area of agriculture, fishing and forestry, but I received a reply giving me a figure for the increase in employment in the agri-industry, food and fisheries.  The area of agriculture, fishing and forestry is a separate CSO heading, but the reply included the figure for the agri-industry.</p> <p> According to the CSO figures, the numbers employed in agriculture, forestry and fishing have increased hugely over the last few years.  As the saying goes, I may be a gullible man but I do not believe that one.  The CSO keeps telling us that it is only partly so because of the way data collection has changed.  Can we accept that there is no increase and, if anything, there is a decrease in direct employment in agriculture?  I am not talking about the agri-industry but about agriculture, forestry and fisheries.  There are no more people engaged in those primary industries than there were two years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00200"><p>First of all, I would not accept that.  I think there are more people working in those sectors now than there were before.  I do not have an exact number on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00300"><p>More farmers, fishermen and forestry workers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00400"><p>If one looks at the seafood and fish processing sector, there are more jobs now than there were before.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00500"><p>I did not say that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00600"><p>I heard what the Deputy said.  As regards forestry and agriculture, if one asks the CSO for clarification of its figures, it is not talking about the food industry but about primary sectors.  There is a slight increase in the numbers this year, whereas last year there was a significant increase, although the same methodology was used.  I am not suggesting that there is a massive flocking to the land, but the numbers of young people studying agriculture-related courses and those attending agricultural colleges have increased dramatically compared to three or four years ago.  Presumably those young people are going somewhere when they leave agricultural colleges.  On more than one occasion I have had to increase the staff availability for Teagasc to deal with the number of young people seeking to study farming and agriculture.  I think it is credible that there are increased numbers, but to know whether they are as significant as was suggested last year in the CSO report, one would have to ask the CSO.</p><p>  As regards overall spending on CAP, there was some reduction in the Pillar 1 spend and some adjustment in the transition.  However, we are still talking about &euro;1.2 billion or more.  It is still a very significant spend on Irish agriculture.  The whole point of what we are trying to do in agriculture at the moment is to help farmers make more money from the marketplace, rather than talking indefinitely into the future about solely making a living from the amount of money that comes from Europe.  The money we get from Europe should be about supporting incomes for farmers.  It is also about helping farmers who do not have the capacity to increase their income from the marketplace because of the challenges and disadvantages they have and the types of farm they have.  Primarily, we should be spending money to allow farmers to produce better, safer and more premium products that they can get better prices for.  That is what we are trying to do with the Food Harvest 2020 programme.</p><p>  The average spend on the rural development programme, RDP, over the lifetime of this CAP will be &euro;565 million.  That was agreed with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin.  We are only spending &euro;405 million on the rural development programme this year.  So Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v is right; it will take a while to ramp this up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00700"><p>Next year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300011#Q00800"><p>Farmers can look forward to an increased RDP spend every year for the next six years if we are going to get to an average spend of &euro;565 million.  However, we cannot go straight from &euro;405 million to &euro;565 million overnight, given budgetary constraints and the expenditure profile.  It does show the success of negotiations around getting Exchequer co-funding for a rural development programme which is essentially the same in value terms as the last rural development programme.  Given the budgetary pressures we now have, I think that is a pretty good achievement.</p><p>  We are currently spending &euro;23 million on the beef genomics scheme, but we will be spending &euro;53 million when it is fully up and running.  The figure will be &euro;43 million next year plus &euro;10 million, which is &euro;53 million for the suckler beef sector.  It is true to say that we are focusing on the genomics scheme for suckler beef, but the dairy industry has been focused on genomics for years - it just has not been paid for it.  Those in the industry get their money from better breeding and better-performing animals in terms of DNA assessments and genomic research in dairy.  The Deputy is right that in future, as we see an increased dairy herd size, we will get more beef animals coming from the dairy herd.  As we see more developments on sexed semen, we will see dairy farmers being able to essentially set aside perhaps 15% of their breeding for replacements.  They will then be breeding the rest of their herd to beef animals or bulls in order to get a much better beef animal coming out of the dairy herd.  That is a good thing because it will raise standards.  I still think the best beef in the country will come from the suckler herd and I certainly hope it will get the highest price abroad.</p><p>  We need to look after the suckler herd.  The last thing we want is to see beef become a by-product of a growing dairy industry.  That is why I have been putting a lot of money into the beef sector, particularly the suckler beef sector, when there has not been a lot of money around.  We will see that happening into the future also.</p><p>  Deputy Pringle raised the question of foreign fishing vessels.  Prices for whitefish have not been great this year and there are a number of reasons for that.  Part of it was that early on in the year there was very little fishing going on.  In fact, in January and February we only caught half our normal quota.  In an effort to try to get some cashflow back into the industry we agreed to increase quotas significantly in March and April.  Other countries did the same and there were market problems in terms of oversupply for a lot of whitefish in those months.  I am aware that there are price pressures on the whitefish sector but I am not convinced that that is because of foreign vessels landing in Ireland.  If we cannot catch fish with Irish trawlers the next best thing is to have foreign trawlers landing into Irish ports, where we can process, package, add value and grade fish.  We can thus employ people in rural coastal communities to do that.  There are good examples of that in the pelagic sector, including with blue whiting in Killybegs.  There are also some good examples concerning whitefish in places such as Ballycotton and Castletownbere.</p><p>  I have not received feedback that foreign landings are undercutting prices in the whitefish sector at the moment.  We must remember that most of this product gets exported anyway and is sold in the same markets it would be sold into if it were being processed in La Rochelle, Brest or Vigo.  However, since the Deputy has asked the question, I will make a few inquiries into it.  Not everybody likes the idea that foreign boats are landing more into Ireland.  Personally, I think it is a good thing for the sector.  It is a way of increasing the volume of fish through our port infrastructure.</p><p>  I was also asked about aquaculture.  The number of licences we have got through so far this year is pretty low.  I do not have an exact figure, but nearly all the licences we got across the line last year - and there were more than 200 of them - were effectively in the last quarter of the year.  Twenty-five licence determinations are expected for Donegal Bay, with 60 for Dungarvan Harbour, another 60 for Clew Bay, 11 for Valentia and the Portmagee channel, 35 for Galway Bay and 70 in Kenmare Bay.  We are trying to do everything we can to progress aquaculture licences when and where appropriate, and to have a transparent and robust system to do that.  The Deputy knows only too well that if one does not do this properly one will be in the courts, and it will be a much longer process.</p><p>  The processing of applications for dairy equipment received in the final tranches under the first targeted agricultural modernisation scheme, which closed on 31 December 2013, is continuing.  All applications are now being examined under the dairy equipment scheme and farmers are being notified of any errors.  In the case of the sheep fencing/mobile handling equipment scheme, fewer than 400 applications remain on hand.</p> <p>These applications should be processed by the end of October.  The final date for completion of work is the end of August 2015.  A new TAM scheme will open in January.  </p><p> TAMS is not as straightforward as one might think.  People apply, get a basic approval, and then sometimes nothing happens.  Then they demand an inspection before they can commence work, at a time that suits them, which does not always result in an inspection when they want it, and so on.  We also have many approvals that have not resulted in drawdown.  Perhaps people are waiting to see what happens with dairy prices before they go ahead and spend money.  Next year we will budget for a significant TAMS spend, particularly in dairy, but also in other sectors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00200"><p>The application process seems to be very bureaucratic.  This is what I am hearing back.  The Minister said himself that many approvals have not resulted in drawdowns.  Not just in the dairy sector, but also in the sheep fencing/mobile handling equipment scheme, for example; from what I hear back, this is particularly bad.  There seems to be an awful lot of red tape between the results and the drawdown not happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00300"><p>We are required to do certain things before we spend money that is co-financed from Europe.  If farmers start work before getting approval, we cannot give them any money.  There is an initial approval process and then there is an inspection and a whole series of form-filling, and quotations are needed from multiple contractors to ensure that farmers are getting value for money and so on.  It is a bit tedious, but many farmers have worked the TAMS system well and it has worked well for them.  We will look at it again next year to see if we can improve the pace of turnaround, but sometimes people get approval and they sit on the approval without doing anything for quite some time.  Then, when they decide they do want to move forward, they contact the Department and want an inspection straight away so that they can get on with the work.  We will review it and see how we can do things more efficiently for farmers before we open up new TAM schemes in January and February, but for many farmers the system has worked reasonably well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00400"><p>Very briefly, Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00500"><p>The Minister mentioned aquaculture licence approval in Galway Bay.  I asked a written parliamentary question, which I thought was reasonable, and got a very vague answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00600"><p>On what?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00700"><p>I asked about the timeframe in which we can expect a decision on the application by Bord Iascaigh Mhara in Galway Bay.  I am not asking the Minister to pre-empt a decision; I am just asking what the timeframe is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00800"><p>I cannot give the Deputy a timeframe because until I get a timeframe for recommendations on my desk, I cannot make decisions and I am reliant on others to do that.  That project has complications.  It is a very big application.  It is a new departure in some ways for salmon farming in terms of scale, and so it is coming under much scrutiny.  I have said to the Deputy and to others in the D&aacute;il that I would not grant approval for a project of that scale unless I was absolutely satisfied of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R00900"><p>Will we have a decision this side of Christmas?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01000"><p>Hopefully we will make some decision on it this side of Christmas, but the project has moved very slowly.  To be honest, it has been very frustrating from my perspective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01100"><p>Are there any observations or questions on programme D - direct payments and effective delivery of schemes and services?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01200"><p>The main component here is the disadvantaged areas scheme, DAS, but it is relatively straightforward.  There will not be much change; it is moving from one CAP to another.  However, the assessment of land under DAS will change in the coming years.  Farmers who have genuinely disadvantaged land are the ones getting the payment.  We will have some flexibility on that, as obviously there will be regional stresses, and it will not be easy because nobody likes losing and everybody wants to gain.  We will manage it as best we can and we will work with farming organisations in a very open way on that.  That does not take effect until the end of 2016, as far as I remember, in terms of the land-based assessment, which will be measuring moisture capacity, quality of soil, depth of soil, etc.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01300"><p>There are three levels of payment on DAS at the moment: less severely handicapped or less favoured areas, more severely handicapped or severely disadvantaged areas, and mountain areas.  When one looks at the productivity of the land in the three areas, there is not much difference between good land and less favoured areas, and the difference between that and the more disadvantaged band is relatively marginal in terms of livestock units per hectare.  The big jump is that productivity in the areas designated as mountain areas, which are not all mountain tops, is about half that.  Many people say that with the disadvantaged area payment, if one can only produce half the volume one should get double the payment.  Is it intended to move, even in the present context, to a system under which the payment would reflect the disadvantage?  In the new areas of natural constraint scheme, ANCS, under which system it is all done by district electoral division, will the payment be relative to the natural constraint?  That would seem the rational thing to do.  If my constraint is twice your constraint, one would think I would get the extra payment to make up for it.  That is not how it works at the moment.  I know there has been a reluctance to change this, because I had to correct the Minister before.  At one stage there was a lower payment for mountain areas, which was quite extraordinary, and which was agreed with the Irish Farmers' Association for some amazing reason.  When I came in as Minister of State I changed it and made the mountain payment higher.  This is an issue on which the Minister should make his own decision, and the criteria should be objective and fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01400"><p>If I could correct myself, Chairman, the new biophysical criteria for what we call the DAS but which will in future be called ANCs, must be in place by the end of 2018, so there is a bit of time, but there is a huge amount of work involved in assessing land plots.  There are also many difficult decisions to be made.  One of the things I hope people will welcome in terms of differentiating between the challenges faced by farmers is the new island payment, whereby farmers living on an island will get an additional &euro;150 per forage hectare.  The original recommendation to me was for much less than that, but I thought we needed to give a decent chunk of money to farmers who farm on islands, or else we will not see a new generation of farmers on these islands.  For farmers who are not resident on islands but who have stock on them, there is a rate of &euro;75 per forage hectare.  We are trying to give considerable top-ups to farmers who are operating in difficult conditions in many cases on islands.  It is really important that we keep farmers on islands.  Otherwise we will see the vegetation there changing and they will become unfarmable if we do not keep them stocked.  Whether it is the south west, the west coast, or the north-west coast - there are probably a couple on the east coast as well - this is a new departure for island farmers and it seems to have gone down well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01500"><p>As a sub-committee, we welcome the fact that one of our recommendations was actually taken up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01600"><p>That is true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300012#R01700"><p>That creates a very interesting precedent.  Some islands are very fertile and some are not so fertile.  Some of those in the lake near me are well farmed, while some are in the sea.  The Minister has just taken them as a group, viewing them as disadvantaged, with feed, etc., having to be brought in by barges or by boat.  I welcome this, but the reality is that in many cases the mountain areas, as the Minister's own statistics would show, are also at a massive disadvantage compared with the rest of the country, but there is not much difference when one looks at livestock units per hectare.</p> <p>Why does the Minister not follow that up with the same methodology in the short term for 15 to 17, inclusive, relating to mountain areas?  This would mean that there would be a double payment in the mountain areas. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300013#S00200"><p>We have not differentiated between individual islands.  Cape Clear is probably quite different from the Aran Islands, which are different from Beara, which is different from Sherkin.  If we were to assess all of those islands and vary the payment depending on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300013#S00300"><p>The Minister is missing the point.  He has accepted one payment for islands because generally they are a very disadvantaged group.  We know, based on livestock figures from his Department, that on average the output of livestock in mountain areas is half that of anywhere else in the country.  Therefore one would expect that people farming designated mountain land would receive twice the DAS payment for that land for the next three years.  People often have land in both disadvantaged and non-disadvantaged areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300013#S00400"><p>That does not necessarily follow because there are lands that are not designated as disadvantaged at all, that are not overly productive either.  We will first assess the level of disadvantage of land on the basis of biophysical criteria as we are required to do.  Once we have this done, we can make further decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2014092300013#S00500"><p>The budget for the areas of natural constraint should remain intact.  When the assessment of biophysical status is carried out, the broader question of how land is divided should be regarded as another argument.  The assumption that disadvantaged land can be divided per hectare as a percentage of the national total is a dangerous one.  It is most important in the context of today's discussions about budgets, outturns and projections that the approximately &euro;200 million is a protected budget for the people who are farming in areas of natural constraint, so that they can be compensated for what they cannot produce at the farm gate.  The objective of many of the other schemes that are in place is to improve and enhance productivity.  On land that is defined as an area of natural constraint the compensation should be able to make amends for that to some degree.</p><p>  I appreciate that Members have stayed back until 6.30 p.m.  I thank the Minister and his officials for coming in.  Perhaps this can become an annual feature of the joint committee's ongoing scrutiny of expenditure.   We need to allocate ourselves a little more time in future and try not to schedule a meeting or priority questions to the Minister in the same week as the national ploughing championships.  It would have been fairer on everyone if we could have started at two and gone through until six.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.115" nospeaker="true" time="17:25:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 6.30 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Tuesday, 30 September 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.116" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.117" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:15</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Ruth Coppinger, Senator Fiach Mac Conghail, Deputy Robert Dowds, Senator Labhrás Ó Murchú, Deputy Michelle Mulherin, Senator Ned O'Sullivan. Deputy Catherine Murphy, Deputy Brian Stanley,</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL MCCARTHY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.118" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 3.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.119" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300003#O00100">Commercial and Domestic Property Supply and Demand: Property Industry Ireland</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300003#O00200"><p>As we are in public session we shall consider the topic of commercial and domestic property - supply and demand, with representatives of Property Industry Ireland.<br/>I welcome the following witnesses: Dr. Peter Stafford, director, Mr. Aidan O'Hogan, chair, Mr. Tom Phillips, chair of the planning and regulation committee and Ms Marian Finnegan, member of the market supply and demand committee.  I thank everyone for their attendance.  <br/>I draw attention to the fact that, by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the joint committee.  However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  I also wish to advise the witnesses that the opening statement and any other material supplied to the committee may be published on the committee's website after the conclusion of the meeting.<br/>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.<br/>I call on Dr. Peter Stafford, Property Industry Ireland, to make his presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Stafford" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300003#O00300"><p>I thank the Chairman, Deputies and Senators for the opportunity to brief the committee on some of the supply and demand issues facing the Irish residential and commercial property sector.</p><p>  My name is Peter Stafford and I am accompanied by some of PII's committee members.  We have submitted to the committee, in advance, a briefing note on the state of the sector.  I hope it gives an overview of some of the issues that we would like to talk about today.  </p><p>  By way of background, Property Industry Ireland works as a not-for-profit think tank to co-ordinate discussions among businesses which have an interest in the property market.  Our member firms who lead our policy-development process cover the entire spectrum of interests and range from banks and financial institutions and asset managers to contractors, developers and builders, and property professional service providers such as architects, surveyors, engineers and planners.</p><p>  Let me turn to the residential sector first.  The period 2002-17 falls into two distinct eras.  During the first era, which ended in 2007, we often built the wrong properties in the wrong locations at the wrong time and we are all living with the consequence of those errors.  Those consequences are negative equity, ghost estates and a collapse in new building activity.  The recent rise in house prices and rents in some parts of the country are a direct result of complexities in the supply chain which often makes it difficult for the market to switch back on supply to meet a recovery in demand.</p><p>  The second era - up to 2017 - begins now.  It is PII's belief that we need to make sure that we only build the right houses in the right place and ahead of the right time.  A clear vision for success for the property sector will ensure that the errors of the past are rectified and sustainability and high standards are met.  We believe we need a data-driven, evidence-based property sector so that supply and demand mismatches are identified, understood and rectified.  Recent increased building standards should now be coupled with a reformed planning process so that viable and sustainable new projects are supported through the planning system and into construction and will drive employment in the sector.</p> <p>Improving supply to the market will calm the market and will provide security to those who own houses and confidence to those who wish to own houses.  It is the easiest way of controlling rents.  Development of new houses, however, will not happen while the cost of construction and development is higher than the market price of the house.  That is why, despite the growth in prices in some areas, there are still no cranes on the skyline.  Two options are open to us: we can allow prices to rise or we can tackle the non-construction cost of development.  VAT at 13.5%, the windfall tax on profits from rezoned land at 80%, and high local development charges all add to the cost of development and mean that in many parts of Ireland, commencing new buildings, despite any increased demand, is not yet viable.  My colleague Mr. Phillips will talk about the recommendations of Property Industry Ireland for planning reform.</p><p> Since the crash, the volume of new commercial property across Ireland has dried up for many of the same reasons as in the residential sector.  High costs of development and low rents, as well as an absence of bank financing, has meant little viability for new development.  Vacancy rates in the commercial property sector are falling, and as employment - especially office-based employment - grows, demand for commercial property space is increasing, driving rents and lowering vacancies.  Ireland has struggled in recent years to regain its international competitiveness.  We attract some of the biggest and best firms to locate and invest in Ireland and we know the reason behind the attraction, but we must be careful that once we set up a tax base and invest in an education system to attract the firms, we have places in which they can work and in which their workers can live.  If we cannot accommodate firms and house their employees in the locations they demand, they will simply relocate - not necessarily to a different area of Ireland, but to another country where there is space.</p><p> In our cities, including Cork, Galway and Limerick, the priority must be to support the building of offices in city centres.  The infrastructure is in place and it is where the bulk of demand lies.  Increasing employment in city centres will have the most immediate knock-on impact on supporting other businesses, especially in the retail sector.  Four issues will drive the ability of the industry to supply new commercial property to the sector: first, access to domestic sources of finance and bank lending to support construction activity and the availability of equity financing;  second, the capacity within the construction supply chain to build out large office and commercial property developments; third, the future direction of NAMA and the speed and nature of decisions on access to finance and sales by NAMA; and fourth, the speed of bringing new developments through the planning and appeals process, especially in the strategic development zones, where the bulk of development will take place in the short term.</p><p> Property Industry Ireland believes the property sector can help to underpin Ireland's economic recovery without a fear of repeating past mistakes so that all micro-sectors can function together in a wider sustainable sector.  The forthcoming planning Bills, the next budget and the budgets after that will provide an opportunity to ensure we have a property sector that is well resourced and informed, working to support an economy that is sustainable and fair, and serving a society that is housed in the highest-quality built environment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300004#P00200"><p>Dr. Stafford can invite his colleagues to contribute to the discussion as it develops.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300004#P00300"><p>I read the document that outlines some of the issues.  I do not disagree with some of what was said.  We most definitely have a serious problem with supply, which is driving up rents and making us unattractive.  This week there was a news item in which some industries said they would have difficulty in attracting people in the absence of appropriate accommodation at a reasonable price.  How to deal with this is the issue.  I accept that there must be a return for building, but sometimes I wonder.  I have examined the matter of development levies over the years.  I am based in Kildare, which had quite high development contributions.  We did that because it was the only available means of delivering infrastructure that would permit the development to take place.</p> <p>A 50% or 75% local contribution was required towards national capital investment.  However, it seemed quite obvious that the development contribution was almost factored into the cost of the building land rather than the cost of building the houses.  The price of building land went down when the development levy went up, and the houses were then priced at what the market could bear.  It may well be the case for people who have bought land that it is not good for it to be factored into the process because the land is already purchased.  However, in the case of future land purchases the development contributions will have an impact on the cost.  I am keen to hear what the witnesses have to say about the price of building land.</p><p> Let us consider all of these things in terms of reductions.  I believe there will be changes to the development contributions on foot of the establishment of Irish Water.  We have had a discussion about that in any case.  There will be needs where there are new developments, but they cannot be funded out of the property tax because the property tax is only a replacement for what was the Local Government Fund.  In fact, it is pitched at 2013 levels, which is an unsustainable level because, for example, the amount of money that has been allocated for regional and local roads is one third of what it was in 2008.  That can only go on for so long before we start ruining our infrastructure.  This is one element that I am keen for the witnesses to address.</p><p> The other issue relates to the planning system.  I had a planning Bill debated in the D&aacute;il and then it came before this committee.  I met the officials in the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  Some elements of that Bill will be included in the legislation due to come before us soon.  The Bill sought to rebalance the legislation from a consumer perspective.  I maintain that the construction industry, particularly house-building, is divided into in three parts.  There are people who are very good.  They go in, build it out and finish it off, they are proud of what they do and we never hear another word from them.  The second group have to be cajoled into finishing work in compliance with planning permission.  The third group is made up of those who should not be building at all.  Essentially, the consumer is a big problem in all of this.  I am keen to hear the view of the witnesses on the matter.  Let us suppose someone buys a house in a housing estate but the developer does not finish it and goes off to build in other areas.  That reflects badly on the industry.  It breaks down trust if such people seek further planning permission.  This side of the sector must be examined from the industry point of view, because a trail of destruction has been left in some locations.  It is not simply about building; it is a question of building in the right locations with the right number and size of units.  Furthermore, we need to consider other infrastructure that should go with this building naturally, such as transport and land use.  All of these should be planned together.  The industry should examine not only the efficiency of getting planning permission but also how problems that have emerged in the sector can be overcome in terms of initiatives that can be included in the planning legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.126" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300005#Q00200"><p>I will address the question of building land.  Deputy Murphy is correct in that future land purchases will reflect the levies as they are.  Our focus in the short term has been on facilitating the delivery of supply to address the shortage, the supply that is currently needed and identification of the constraints in that scenario.  In most of these cases the land is already held, some of it by NAMA and some of it by various other bodies.  We are looking at what could be varied to improve the feasibility to allow these matters to go ahead.  Obviously levies are only part of the equation that we have identified, but it is a big issue at present and it is a serious impediment.</p> <p>The adjustment of levies may have to be just a temporary measure that allows matters to progress at a later stage and, ultimately, land prices will reflect what they are.</p><p> Tom Phillips will talk about the planning issues that were raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.128" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Phillips" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300006#R00200"><p>On the issue of financial contributions, I agree it is something that was going to happen in the future.  At present, however, there are 31 planning authorities and 31 different types of levy.  In Donegal, for example, it is &euro;2,600 per unit, while in Wicklow it is &euro;16,800 per residential unit, so there is a big disparity between local authorities.  The development levy is only one part of the equation.  Peter Stafford spoke about the windfall tax, which is a big issue.  It was introduced in 2009 and it appears from our research that no money has been paid under that tax.  We are seeking to have that reduced from 80% to 33%, because it is a big disincentive.  It does not just apply to the zoning of land but also to the sideways zoning of lands, where there is a material contravention of a development plan.  Everybody might agree that it is a good thing to do, but because it is technically a material contravention of a plan, an 80% tax is applied.</p><p>  Then there are situations where there are special levies.  For example, the metro in Dublin adds a levy to certain developments.  The metro is on hold, but the levy is still in place.  The levy is there for a 30-year period.  If the money has not been spent in 30 years, it can be refunded to the developer.  I can think of no other levy that has a 30-year life span.  There is another special levy in Kilternan.  To build an apartment in Kilternan, one pays a levy of &euro;11,000 per residential unit and then a special levy of over &euro;40,000.  It works out at &euro;55,000 per unit in levies.  That is apart from a potential windfall tax, Part V social housing and other costs.  There are many costs.  That is the situation for people who have land at present.  It is a tricky point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300006#R00300"><p>The Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government made a comment recently about social housing.  There appears to be a housing crisis, although it might have different manifestations at some levels.  There is a huge demand for residential houses in Dublin, but not enough supply.  Students are suffering and families are being made homeless.  There are obviously issues with access to finance and so forth, but there was a statement from the Minister last week with regard to something similar to Part V or a reincarnation of that, with perhaps 10% on this occasion.  If there was a national policy in respect of future development to retain some of the units for social housing, how would you fit that in?  I know it is akin to asking how long is a piece of string, but in your informed view, would you consider that a realistic policy objective?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.130" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Marian Finnegan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300006#R00400"><p>The challenge is to look at the total quantum that is required.  Some of it will be social housing, some will be student accommodation and some will be private housing.  The challenge we face at present is the complete dysfunctionality of both markets - on the new housing construction side, which we have discussed in terms of development, and on the second-hand side, which is dysfunctional because of a hangover from the recession whereby people are tied because of negative equity, bridging finance or tracker mortgages, so they are not bringing their properties to the marketplace.  The entire market has ceased to exist correctly.  As a result, there is an abnormally low quantity of product being put on the market for sale and, equally, an abnormally low quantity is being developed.  The solution for the future is obviously to increase the total quantum, and social housing clearly forms part of that.  A significant proportion in the regional centres being devoted to social housing is critical, but we must get the package right to make it viable.  Just as it is not viable to build apartments in most, if not all, of the country at present, it is equally still not financially viable to develop social housing in the current structure.  It will require a capital injection.  That will be a challenge.  It is certainly one area that must be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300006#R00500"><p>You referred to domestic finance.  What is your experience with the domestic banks in terms of meeting requirements for finance?  It is an important part of the process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.132" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Marian Finnegan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300006#R00600"><p>What has evolved over the last couple of years is that while cash is still a very significant part of the marketplace, it is almost by choice.  Of the transactions that took place in the first six months of the year in Ireland, 51% were with cash and the rest were with finance.  That still appears to be absolutely abnormal, but the cash transactions are being driven by investors buying with cash, because the banking finance that is available is not attractive.  People who sold in the last number of years, because the market fell by 50% or 60%, have come back in with cash and they are reinvesting in the marketplace.  There is bank lending.  There is no doubt that the banks are willing to lend and there is more competition, with more attractive financial products being made available, but they are still only facilitating half of the marketplace.  The other half is being directly facilitated with cash.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300006#R00700"><p>A total of 51% of all transactions are cash.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1070" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300007#S00100"><p>Mr. Phillips's final point related to development levies and the disparities with regard to having 31 planning authorities throughout the country.  To what extent does he agree that where there is provision of services, infrastructure, etc., this is levied?  Is he stating that, on the basis of the existence of Irish Water - which has responsibility in respect of providing water supplies and sewerage facilities - this should be dealt with in a different way and should not be levied by means of planning permission?</p><p>  NAMA is becoming involved in constructing residential properties, in respect of which it has great plans, and commercial units.  One of the points which has been made is that the way to plan for the future is to respond to data.  What is the position with regard to empirical data?  A few years ago we were informed that entire swathes of housing estates would have to be pulled down and that there would probably never be a need to construct new houses again.  Our guests have explained how the market is not operating and outlined the fact that properties are not being brought onto the market.  Is there solid empirical data available in this regard, not just in respect of Dublin but for the remainder of the country, including the west and to locations outside the major urban centres?  What is the position and is more property required?</p><p>  Another point in the context of NAMA is the existence of land banks.  I am aware that land banks built up by a number of developers involved with NAMA are tied up with that organisation.  Those individuals with whom I am in contact have reported that their dealings with NAMA, in the context of having these sites developed, have been very unsatisfactory.  The sites in question are located in the Dublin area and they would be suitable for housing and other types of development.</p><p>  There was previously a large body of experts - that is, those who were developers during the boom years - operating in this area in the past.  Many of these individuals, particularly those who operated on a larger scale, became involved in NAMA, even if this was through no fault of their own.  In the judgment handed down in the O'Flynn case recently, NAMA was very much chastised.  Are out guests in a position to outline the experience the developers with whom they are involved have had with NAMA?  We are quite restricted in terms of the type of information we can seek from NAMA.  Initially, it was envisaged that a parliamentary committee would have oversight in respect of the organisation's activities.  However, that has not proven to be the case and we are operating on the basis of hearsay.  I would propose that some of the developers involved should come before the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform or whatever.  What are our guests' views on the experts in development to whom I refer who have been brought to their knees and who are not being dealt with fairly by NAMA?  I accept that might not be popular to refer to these individuals in the way that I have, particularly as anyone who was involved in property development - whether good, bad or indifferent - in the past has been demonised in recent years.</p><p>  The final issue in which I am interested is that which relates to social housing.  To what extent can private financing be leveraged and used to build social housing?  I accept that the way in which the social housing system operates is different and that people might be able to eventually purchase their council homes.  In other words, the sales involved are not immediate.  What sort of scheme would our guests envisage being put in place in order to encourage private investors to become involved in the development of social housing in order that we might address the housing problem?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Stafford" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300007#S00200"><p>I will discuss the statistics and perhaps my colleagues will comment on the issues relating to NAMA and social housing.  One of the legacies of the Celtic tiger is that when the crash occurred, we realised we had very poor data in respect of the property market.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government collects some data on house-building activity and the Central Statistics Office collects certain other data.  Various agencies examine different parts of this data but it is extremely difficult to mesh it all together in order to obtain an overall picture of the position with regard to supply and demand at any one time.  The Construction 2020 report, which the Government produced a couple of months ago, has at its heart an evidence-based property market.  This is something that we have absolutely been calling for all the way through.  We are of the view that there should be task forces, forums and committees established and that everybody responsible for collecting data on anything to do with the market should contribute to these in order that said data might be analysed in real time.</p> <p>There are two practical problems.  First, the data from the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is often very slow to be released.  We do not yet have commencement notices for -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Marian Finnegan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300008#T00200"><p>Since February.  It is now almost October, but we do not know what has commenced since February because the Department is reviewing its processes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.138" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Stafford" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300008#T00300"><p>Therefore, when we are making our estimates for the number of houses that will be completed in 2014, at best we only have official data from February, and it is now September.</p><p>  The second factor is that tomorrow, the Central Statistics Office will release house price data for August, but as Ms Finnegan mentioned, with half the transactions taking place in the cash market, these are not included in the CSO data.  Again, at best we have a snapshot of what is happening in a market which is moving very quickly.  The CSO is doing good work in trying to improve the basis of its statistics and this will help.  If we can consolidate all of the data, this will help us identify where any supply and demand mismatches are emerging.  Once we identify these, we can resolve them.  Currently, we are sometimes trying to resolve these in an information vacuum.  Construction 2020 creates important forums to help us do this, which is vital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300008#T00400"><p>I would like to come in on the NAMA issue.  The principal constraint in regard to NAMA is the lack of equity these developers have.  While there is finance available, they no longer have any equity.  They have the skills and ability and it is clear that NAMA has already financed a number of ongoing house building developments.  A number of schemes are operating successfully, but within the borrowing constraints of the NAMA legislation.  Further development will emerge over time.  The land banks are there and while  NAMA has been looking at some of the existing borrowers, it is also looking at other developers or construction people who can deliver and are not constrained by the NAMA legislation and are outside of it.  It is a challenging situation, but the biggest challenge arises where developers no longer have any equity.  They have the skills and experience and it would be great if they could get the resources to get building.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.140" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Stafford" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300008#T00500"><p>Does Mr. Phillips want to speak about social housing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Phillips" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300008#T00600"><p>I want to mention financial contributions.  I believe it is right that developers should pay a levy, because development must be paid for.  During the Celtic tiger years we had developer-led planning, but my concern is that we now have a push for plan-led development.  I argue we should have viable plan-led development.  We should have a situation where the planning system is aware of the market, because there is quite a push among my fellow planners to ignore the market, as if it is irrelevant, and to look only at proper planning.  We must look at both together and ensure we have viable plan led development.</p><p>  If we produce a planning scheme, the financial contributions should be tested to ensure the scheme is capable of being delivered.  Certain lands have been zoned for particular purposes, but they are non viable because the financial contributions that would be payable are so large one could not carry out a viability test.  Therefore, at the time of the writing of a local area plan, financial contributions should be provided for it. </p><p>  Let me give two prime examples.  Both Dublin Docklands and Cherrywood strategic development zones have provisions in the planning schemes for developers to contribute towards the delivery of infrastructure to ensure these developments happen.  However, in last year's development levy guidelines, the then Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, said that development levies should be reduced by 50% in strategic development zones, SDZs, to incentivise development in these areas where a plan has been agreed as to what happens.  However, in both Dublin city and in Cherrywood, the planning authorities, which act as development agencies, have increased the levies because so much infrastructure is required to make them happen.  While the Minister has said that we will reduce the levies in an SDZ and make developers outside that area contribute more to incentivise development in these places, delivery is going in the opposite direction.  We cannot, for example, open a book and find out the development levy in the case of every one of the 31 areas in the country.  One can do this as a personal exercise, but there is no central record of the information where we can see what we actually need.</p><p>  In regard to the question on social housing, a report by DKM Economic Consultants looked at how the issue of social housing could be addressed.  The development market is still waiting for delivery of the planning Bill to see how it will be addressed.</p> <p>One of the options DKM put forward - the public was invited to make submissions - was inclusory zoning whereby a local authority would determine where social housing was required and zone land there to incentivise the bringing forward of development schemes.  Of the six options, that is a very good one.  It would be good to determine where housing is needed and how its development could be expedited.  This could be done by incentivising developers to develop the lands identified, not necessarily by tax breaks but by reducing financial contributions in the areas.  It would make development not only attractive but also viable.</p><p> Last week, the chief executive of NAMA was quoted as having said at the meeting in the Convention Centre that NAMA did not really develop between 2010 and 2013 because it was non-viable.  It is only now becoming viable for people to carry out appraisals on land.  We must ask what it takes to make the delivery of housing viable.  It is not achieved by going back to the old days but by making sure that the financial contributions lead to viable plan-led development.  I repeat the example of Kilternan.  Having to pay &euro;54,000 to a local authority to contribute for infrastructure for one apartment makes it completely and utterly non-viable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00200"><p>What was the price of the apartment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.144" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Phillips" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00300"><p>It could be &euro;100,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00400"><p>It could be but it was not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Phillips" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00500"><p>I am talking about now, 2014.  It is still very high.  One could actually ask how much land we have zoned for development in the country but, while one might regard it as part of the equation, one would have to conclude on analysis that it cannot be developed because it is non-viable.  NAMA has said it would not enter into the market where land is non-viable because it would be wasting taxpayers' money.  The same is the case with developers.  One cannot develop speculatively, nor can one go to the banks; even if the banks were lending, one could not get the money if the scheme were non-viable.  The planning system has to step up to the plate and say we need viable plan-led development.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1070" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00600"><p>If I understand Mr. Phillips correctly, he is talking about local area plans being more nuanced with regard to development contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00700"><p>There is a vote in the Seanad.  I call on Senator Landy to make his contribution, after which I will call Deputy Michelle Mulherin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300009#U00800"><p>I thank the witnesses for attending.  I will be very quick in making my observations and asking my questions.</p><p>  On development levies, the delegation is correct that each local authority sets a development levy.  However, it is the autonomous role of elected members at local level, and I do not subscribe in any way to the view that this process should be centralised.  It would be taking away the local knowledge of what is required in local authority areas.</p><p>  I have a couple of questions.  I will not be present to hear the answers but they will be on the record.  Everyone referred to the windfall tax.  Mr. Phillips suggested the levy should be reduced from 80% to 33%.  Will he advise us as to why he made that decision?  Would he not accept there is a windfall tax because the people who now own the land are going to make a major profit when they release it on the market?  This is because it is rezoned land.  From where was the figure of 33% plucked?  There will be profit made on the land no matter what price it is sold for, even at this stage in our economic cycle.  I would like an explanation as to why a levy reduction would kick-start development.</p><p>  My second question concerns derelict sites across the country.  There is currently a levy on derelict sites and, quite obviously, it is not working.  It is not incentivising the development of sites.  The sites are a blight in every rural town and across the city.   There are certainly some unsightly locations.  What do the delegates believe can be done about the derelict sites other than imposing the levy?</p><p>  It was suggested that local authority land be released for development.  Could the delegates elaborate on their view on the release to the market of private land, not just local authority land?</p><p>  With regard to dereliction, what is the proposal to deal with the issue?  It seems most of his contribution to the committee today concerned the Government, local authority or State reducing taxes in one way or another to kick-start house-building.  I come from a rural area where there are many builders still in operation.  They were in operation throughout the recession because they built at a reasonable rate and sold at a reasonable rate.</p> <p>There was a market for what they were building.  In the main, the people who went out of business were those who put their prices up in the sky - prices that people could not meet - and who then borrowed on the strength of not being able to sell houses.  There is still a market for people to build and sell houses if they do so at a reasonable rate.  That seems to be lost in Mr. O'Hogan's contribution today and I would like to hear his comments on that.  I must leave but the answer will be on the record and I appreciate the Chairman's understanding.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300010#V00200"><p>Does Deputy Mulherin wish to conclude?  We will then return to our panel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1070" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300010#V00300"><p>My point concerns the development contributions.  From what Mr. O'Hogan has described, if one was to make it more nuanced around the place looking at market conditions, one would still have disparity.  That seemed to be an issue, yet what he described would create it.</p><p>  My next point concerns zoning, as was referred to by Senator Landy.  Where we are interested in zoning agricultural land, should we not be looking at a new model because we are basically enriching people?  We are zoning their land, they have not done anything with that land and we need it.  Should the State not in some way acquire it and say that it now has the land and will decide heretofore?  It probably sounds a bit like communism but in the past, whole areas of land were zoned, the person selling it were enriched and it had a knock-on effect yet it was by virtue of councillors zoning land and bestowing a gift on people.  I know the land was needed but surely there must be a better system that benefits the general public than the one we have?  I know that certain things are set and we have certain zoning but I am talking about agricultural land or brownfield sites.  It is just a thought or comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.153" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300010#V00400"><p>Could I start with that question?  We have no opposition to a tax on the benefit or value that is attached to the land through the zoning.  We are not opposed to that in principle.  The point we are making is that there is a disincentive because the windfall tax at 80% is so great.  Even if people's land is rezoned, the level of tax is so great that it stops people selling.  What we are trying to advocate, and the reason we picked 33%, is that it is the CGT rate.  That is the only reason we picked that figure.  It was to get to a level at which people feel it is worth their while to sell, particularly agricultural land.  If people are going to pay 80% of the added value in tax, they will ask why they would bother doing that and whether it might be better to hold on to it.  In particular, if it is rezoned, one is better off holding on to it.  There is no incentive to sell it.</p><p>  We want to flush more land into the market and that will help reduce prices and land prices by reducing that tax, which has apparently generated no revenue since it was introduced.  Certainly we have not been able to get any figure from the Revenue Commissioners regarding any tax generated by this levy.  Hence we are saying that we should reduce it to a significant level and the CGT level seems to be a proper one.  There will still be levies so the local authorities will be getting money once it is developed.</p><p>  Deputy Mulherin also asked about social housing and the funding of social housing.  Unquestionably, there is or would be funding available from the private sector for social housing but it will have to be in fairly large tracts of land.  It will not be available within the context of Part V where somebody is developing two or three houses.  However, there would be institutional funding or funding through real estate investment trusts for, say, 100 social houses which are together but that must be managed by leasing through a housing agency or by a local authority.  However, the capital funding in this market is definitely available if it is packaged in the right way.  There is no question about that.  </p><p>  The reason derelict sites are not being developed is because it is either not viable to develop them, namely, the economics do not work, because most of these sites are in very poor locations, and I have some direct experience of this, or frequently there are problems with titles that are unresolved in many cases.  Local authorities have compulsory purchase powers under the Derelict Sites Act.</p> <p>However, they rarely seem to exercise those powers and, frankly, they could easily exercise them at almost no cost by compulsorily purchasing the land and re-selling it with a clean title where there is a title problem, because a CPO starts the title with a clean folio from scratch.  It wipes all the defects instantly and, therefore, there definitely is scope for local authorities to get in there.  By the time they have to pay for the land under the CPO, they could have it resold to a developer.  If the Derelict Sites Act 1990 were fully operational under local authorities, it would have the ability to sort out many of these issues.  I will leave the other issues to my colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.155" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Phillips" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300011#W00200"><p>On the issue of the windfall tax, Mr. Justice Kenny in his 1973 report talked about the betterment of land and the windfall tax, and we agree with that.  The key point is that 80% was too high.  It is not just about zoning agricultural land as residential land; it can be a rezoning from industrial land to residential land or land for different purposes.  It does not have to be agricultural and it can have a commercial zoning use.  Going sideways and not even upwards in terms of different zoning attracts the windfall tax.  A material contravention whereby the local authority and a quantum of the councillors might agree it is good idea to grant permission to a particular scheme that is technically non-compliant with the development plan would attract the windfall tax.  It is catching development in lots of ways.  For example, a few years ago local authorities realised that too much land was zoned residential and they down-zoned it, but in the next year or two when they start rezoning land, the land that was zoned residential, bought at residential prices, down-zoned to agricultural land and then rezoned to residential because of a housing shortage will attract an 80% windfall tax.  Many people say it should be zero, but we say a realistic taxation rate is 33%.  This has been around as an idea since 1973.  That is where we are coming from on it.</p><p>  On the issue of derelict sites, one would have to look at the question of who owns them, because in Dublin city the State authorities own many of the sites.  Dublin City Council and the OPW, for example, have probably the largest land banks of derelict sites in the city.  We made representations to the former Lord Mayor about this.  The levy is in not place at the moment.  It was an idea that it should be put in place.  One needs to look at why the land is derelict.  Is it because people are land-banking, which would fulfil the media attachment to having a definitive reason, or is it because people cannot get the funding or the land is non-viable?  There are greater issues than people simply land-banking because there are plenty of people who want to develop land but either cannot get the finance or are finding that it does not stack up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.156" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300011#W00300"><p>I would like to make one correction.  The Senator is correct that levies are payable under the Derelict Sites Act.  If sites are left derelict, they are levied.</p><p>  The Senator also referred to houses elsewhere in the country and people being reasonable about the prices, but outside Dublin, the prices at which they are being sold are below the construction cost alone in most cases, ignoring site costs and so on.  It is not, therefore, a matter of whether builders are reasonable in the current market; it is a question of what one can get for them, and more often than not it is less than they cost to construct new.  I am not sure how the way the Senator is thinking could resolve the situation unless somebody is building a one-off house for themselves.  Outside Dublin, Cork and the other urban centres, one can buy a house for far less than it would cost to build it, even leaving the site value out of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300011#W00400"><p>What is the breakdown of construction costs nowadays for a three-bedroom semi-detached house?  At one time, it was labour, materials and so on.  What is the ratio nowadays?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.158" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300011#W00500"><p>It used to be that the site would be a third of the total cost.  It is difficult to express the building cost of a house now because it is relative to value, but it is approximately between &euro;100 and &euro;150 per sq. ft.  If the Chairman builds a 1,000 sq. ft. house, it will cost between &euro;100,000 and &euro;150,000 to construct.</p> <p>In counties Cavan, Leitrim or Monaghan, one can buy houses of 1,000 sq. ft. for &euro;50,000 or &euro;60,000.  This is way below the construction cost and takes no account of the cost of the financing, site costs and levies for development.  That is likely to continue.  We will see those prices increase significantly this year once people have confidence that prices are moving.  Whether one pays &euro;50,000 or &euro;55,000 for a house is not the issue, because when one goes to build a new house one is talking about &euro;110,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300012#X00200"><p>There is a recovery.  The talk in the past couple of weeks has been about avoiding another boom-to-bust market.  There is also the focus on homelessness and other aspects of housing.  There is a natural appetite to avoid what happened in the past.  Does Mr. O'Hogan envisage that the market will be positive in a couple of years' time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.161" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300012#X00300"><p>I think it will be good.  Much of what is happening is the result of concern among people that if they do not get into the market the houses will not be built and prices will become unsustainable.  Recently we saw people queueing to buy houses, but in reality there was no need to queue because, while there is some demand, it is not that crazy.  Ms Finnegan will suggest that even in recent months, as more and more houses have come onto the market one can see the price rises decelerating a little bit.  People are concerned that they will not be able to afford a house.  The certainty of delivery, even if it were 18 months to 24 months ahead, would do a great deal to calm the market.  Potentially, prices will continue to rise over the next four or five years, but at a much more graduated rate than they have.  In the next two years, when there is very limited supply, we are likely to see an unusual level of growth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.162" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Marian Finnegan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300012#X00400"><p>I will also comment on that point.  All we are advocating is that we address the supply-and-demand imbalance.  A normal functioning marketplace will address that itself.  Our concern is that the market will take too long to address it, simply because of the constraints that are there, and as a result prices will rise too dramatically in a short period.  In the 12 months to June 2014, prices in Dublin were up by 21.5%.  That said, the stock available for sale in January was at the lowest point ever.  In January 2014 there were just over 3,000 units advertised for sale in Dublin, while in the previous 12 months there had been 10,000 transactions.  One should have at least one year's supply and ideally two years' supply.  The market should have had 20,000 properties advertised for sale, but it had 3,000, so prices rose by 2% a month, which, given the context, was not an exceptional level.  It was undesirable, but we must take into account how low the stock was.  By July the quantum of available properties had gone up by just 1,000 units.  When we did the survey again in July there were 1,100 units available for sale.  Prices are now rising by 1% a month rather than 2% a month.  If one get the supply balance correct, the market will function normally.  The challenge is that people are now focusing on this, and there have been ridiculous media headlines about queues when three people are in a line to buy a house.  That is nonsense.  It is not what makes the market.</p><p>  We need to establish how many houses are required in Dublin and the mid-east in the next ten years.  How many houses will be required in Galway, Cork and Limerick?  For much of the rest of the country, there is no issue.  Prices will not change that significantly in much of the north west or the south east because there is ample product.  There are local economic challenges and it is not a market that will suffer from a supply-side shortage in the short term.  We should be planning for the future; it is not a problem for this year or next year.  However, in the regional centres where IDA Ireland has done a phenomenally good job, where local economies are doing much better, we have a significant shortage of product.  We have not been building units and we have not been supplying them on the second-hand market.  Unless we do something to change that pattern, we will have price inflation of 20%.  The other part of that equation is that, as a hangover from the recession, half of the available properties are buy-to-let-type properties, but three quarters of purchasers want to buy a home to live in.  They do not always meet the same requirements.  There are many buy-to-let properties available for sale.  People are looking to buy family homes, and therefore when a family home becomes available the price rises dramatically.  Forty people come to view the property and suddenly that is all over the newspapers.  We are trying to address that situation.  Rising prices will bring some people out of negative equity and will allow their properties to come to the market.  Rising prices will address a great many problems.  It will make development more viable and we will begin to build more, but in the short term, prices will rise and make our economy more competitive.  We are looking at key locations, albeit from a nationwide perspective.  We are looking for development in the key locations to prevent this spiralling of prices.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300013#Y00200"><p>I apologise for missing the delegates' presentation due to having another meeting to attend, but I studied their document.  </p><p>  Deputy Michelle Mulherin spoke about a communistic solution to the housing crisis, but I think it was with tongue in cheek.  We have a housing emergency which has never been so acute.  Some 100,000 families need homes, but the solutions being put forward not only by the delegates are token and would not deal with the issue.  Their document indicates that it is expected there will be 8,400 completions in the private sector this year and obviously very few of those units will be allocated for social housing.  That number will not go anywhere towards dealing with the housing catastrophe.  During the height of the boom 80,000 houses a year were being built, yet all the Government and the agencies are talking about is the provision of a few thousand units a year in a piecemeal fashion when we know that if the necessary resources were provided, the housing crisis could be solved much quicker.</p><p>  At the weekend we heard that container homes were being put forward as a solution for people who were homeless; meanwhile, on the other side of the spectrum, the price of mansions is rocketing, in Dublin in particular.  The pattern is not uniform throughout the country.  </p><p>  I served as a councillor in Fingal for 11 years.  I sat through discussions on many development plans; there was probably more development in that area than in any other in the country.  Planning permission has been granted for the building of 17,000 houses in the area, while land has been rezoned for the building of 30,000 plus houses.  The availability and zoning of land are not the problem in many cases.  The dysfunctionality is evident from practices in the banks and the actions of the developers who are still reeling from the results of their speculation.  I do not see any resolution of the problem unless the State plays a massive role, although I do not think that is the opinion of the delegates, but the only way we will solve the problem is by public intervention.  </p><p>  I do not believe the private sector has an interest in the provision of social or affordable housing.  In their document the delegates seek tax breaks in terms of VAT and a windfall tax to incentivise developers, but it was the availability of tax breaks that led to the last bubble.  Developers were given huge incentives and we all know what happened as a result.  In terms of public and social housing provision, the delegates speak about the provision of 1,100 extra units per annum.  In terms of giving developers tax breaks, under a model that was in place in the 1930s and 1970s, thousands of social and public houses were built every year.  What has happened is that there has been an ideological opposition to the building of public and social housing by successive Governments, leading to a situation where there has been a collapse on the supply side and people are finding themselves on the streets, including two pensioners whom I saw in their nightclothes.  </p><p>  What the delegates are advocating is a continuation of the same policies, but there is an emergency and the Government must intervene to invest and build social and affordable houses.  It would be best to allow councils to do this, not housing agencies which are new to this and also have a private sector ideology in that if one is given a house, it is like being given charity, rather than having an entitlement to a house.  Councils built houses before and they should be allowed to build them again, but, unfortunately, they are not allowed by EU and troika rules to borrow money.  This is one of the most inhibiting factors in solving the housing crisis.  It is not being highlighted by any of the housing agencies, many of which are being given grants and paid by the Government; therefore, they do not criticise it.  A crucial factor is that councils be allowed to borrow money, but this has been ruled out under EU rules.</p> <p>Since the Deputy mentioned communistic solutions, certainly the private sector is not particularly interested in providing social housing but only houses for profit.   In fact, some are happy with the shortage of housing because it is a chance for them to sell houses they have on their books.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.165" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00200"><p>We would be delighted if the State were to intervene and provide social housing.  Our policy would be 100% behind that.  We genuinely believe it is the only way to solve the problem, particularly in the next few years, as it needs a huge intervention.  Even in the private sector, if 20% of the volume were social and public housing it would still be a drop in the ocean relative to the need.  If we have given the impression that we are opposed to that, we absolutely are not, but we have had to recognise the constraints that are being imposed on the national Exchequer.  If that solution could be provided then we would advocate it tomorrow morning and would be delighted if it happened.  It would be wrong to assume that the private sector is not interested in providing social housing.  I think it would be interested in providing anything as long as it can get some return.  I do not mean an excessive return but one that allows the industry to be financed and to get some return on its investment.  The private sector and the construction sector would be delighted to go into that sector, and there is definitely capital available in the private sector that would fund it.  There are the logistics of grouping it and making the size viable in terms of the investment required, but it would be completely wrong to think that Property Industry Ireland would not be supportive of that policy.  We would be 100% behind it; if the Government can get the money we would see that as a major part of the extension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00300"><p>It is not written down here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00400"><p>We have to recognise the national constraints on the record.  We would be 100% behind it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00500"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Stafford" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00600"><p>By way of context, Exchequer funding of social housing in 2009 was &euro;1.5 billion, while this year it is &euro;300 million.  We cannot switch on that tap and get back to &euro;1.5 billion; therefore, we must look creatively to see what we an do.  Our presentation opened with the idea that we are in a housing crisis and that the crisis in the housing market has lasted longer than the Second World War, in the sense that we went from crisis to crisis.  The challenge now is to rebuild and put together a programme that ensures that the mistakes of the past never happen again.  Our previous budget submission, entitled "Towards a National Property Strategy," highlighted the need for a strategic approach to decide what the success rate appeared to be for the housing market, for building social housing, for communities and for planning.  One of the ways in which Property Industry Ireland tries to stimulate a debate is to look at the different models that are available.  That is what we are trying to.  We recognise that there is a crisis that needs to be solved; the difficulty is solving it in an absence of money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.170" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00700"><p>May I refer also to the windfall tax?  Members are looking at it from a slightly different point of view from us.  We are not opposed to the windfall tax, but the quantum of it is a disincentive for people to release land.  We are anxious to see more land released into the market which can be developed, so that if it is rezoned it will be released.  If one is a farmer and one's land has increased in value from &euro;10,000 per acre to &euro;100,000 per acre, one has an incentive or an added value of &euro;90,000.  As the tax rate currently stands, one will pay &euro;70,000 of that in tax.  That does not make any sense.  Any farmer would ask why he would sell the land.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00800"><p>There is a lot of land already zoned.  That is not the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.172" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300014#Z00900"><p>It does not apply.  This is only in respect of land that may need to be rezoned in the future.  We may need to try to get more of it, which would help to reduce the overall price of land.  We suggest that it should come down to a third.  Roughly, one third of it is taken.  It is with great reluctance that we have advocated any tax reductions.  We are very conscious of what the tax incentives did.  The same applies to VAT.  We are suggesting that it be reduced from 13.5% to 9%.  We have seen what that has done in the hospitality industry.  We reckon that if 10% to 15% more houses are delivered as a result, it will be more than self-financing.</p> <p>This will be more than self-financing.  The people on whom it impacts most are first-time buyers.  It is in that sector of new housing that this has its biggest impact.  It would be honest to say that we are trying to look at sustainable models.  However, as the Deputy stated, there is a crisis and it needs some facilitation to drive the market in the short term.  All we are seeking is the means by which we can oil the wheels in order to have this delivered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.174" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Phillips" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300015#AA00200"><p>The windfall tax was introduced in 2009 under the NAMA Act and it went straight from 0% to 80%.  It was not incrementally increased all the way from 20% to 80%; it came from nowhere and was immediately imposed at a level of 80%.  We are not seeking a tax break, what we want is an equitable tax.  Many people would like it to be reduced to 0% but we are suggesting that it should be reduced to 33%.  We are not seeking a tax break, what we are pursuing is a balancing or a correction of the tax.  In 2009 this appeared to be a good brake on the system but it has not worked and the proof of the pudding is that it appears to have brought in no money.  All it seems to have done is act as a disincentive.</p><p>  In the context of planning and social housing, the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is exemplary.  It has a major workload with which to deal - including implementing the recommendations relating to the Mahon tribunal, establish the office of the planning regulator, etc. - and has only a limited number of planners on its staff.  One of the Department's other duties is to oversee the position with regard to Part V social housing.  Between 2000 and 2011, some 3.5% of all houses, excluding one-off dwellings, were social and affordable houses.  Part V did not deliver 15%, it delivered a much smaller percentage.  It would be useful, from our point of view, if the introduction of the planning Bill could be expedited.  There is a great deal of ground to be covered by that legislation and the position with regard to Part V social housing is only one aspect.  If it could even be done in stages and if Part V could be expedited rather than there being a need to wait for all the other items to be dealt with simultaneously, this would at least provide some certainty.</p><p>  We know that affordable housing has been taken off the table but social housing is still in play.  It is very difficult to advise someone who wants to develop land exactly what the position is likely to be.  This is because there is an expectation that a planning Bill is going to be introduced but this eventuality always appears to be three or four months away.  If we could obtain an indication with regard to when the Bill is going to be introduced, this would provide some certainty to the market.  When it appears, the Bill will then provide us with a way of working out how we can deliver social housing.  I agree with Mr. O'Hogan to the effect that we are supportive of the delivery of social housing.  However, we must be able to see, from our point of view, that it will be viable and that there will be ways of delivering it.  We are not talking about tax breaks, we are seeking an equitable tax situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300015#AA00300"><p>I thank our guests for attending.  I accept that they do not have a crystal ball and cannot tell us the way forward.  However, the interaction we have had with them is very important in the context of what we propose to do.  We will hopefully be meeting the Minister in late October or early November.  The issue of homelessness is of critical importance to the committee, as are the other aspects of general housing policy.  The position in this regard has never been static and it has changed continually, sometimes for the worse.  The exchanges the committee has with the people from the various sectors are extremely important.  I thank our guests for their input and for engaging in a very robust exchange of views.  They are free to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.176" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Aidan O'Hogan" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300015#AA00400"><p>I thank members for their time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1195" speakername="Ruth Coppinger" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300015#AA00500"><p>Housing is the most critical issue for this committee.  Is there a facility whereby we might invite representatives from Dublin City Council to come before us in order that we might discuss with them the proposal relating to containers and the placement of people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2014092300015#AA00600"><p>I suggest that the Deputy write to the clerk officially in respect of that matter.  We discussed an issue in this regard when we dealt with correspondence earlier.  As a result, we are going to invite the Minister to come before us, as a matter of priority, in order that we might discuss housing and other issues relating to the Department.  If the Deputy wishes to put forward a particular suggestion, perhaps she might send an e-mail to the clerk and we will then deal with it as correspondence at next week's meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.179" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 4.24 p.m. until 2.15 p.m. on Tuesday, 30 September 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.180" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Transport and Communications</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.181" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Timmy Dooley, Senator Sean D. Barrett, Deputy Dessie Ellis, Senator Terry Brennan, Deputy Noel Harrington, Senator Eamonn Coghlan, Deputy Seán Kenny, Senator Paschal Mooney, Senator Ned O'Sullivan.</p><p>DEPUTY JOHN O'MAHONY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.182" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300002#A00200">Dublin Bus: Chairman Designate</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300003#B00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Senator Terry Brennan.<br/>The purpose of the meeting is to engage with Mr. Ultan Courtney, chairperson designate of Dublin Bus, in order to discuss the approach he proposes to take when appointed to this role and his views on the challenges facing the company.  Members will be aware of the Government's decision in 2011 to put new arrangements in place for the appointment of persons to State boards and bodies.  The joint committee welcomes the opportunity to meet the chairperson designate to hear his views.  We trust this will provide greater transparency in the process of appointment to State boards and bodies.  On behalf of the committee, I welcome Mr. Courtney.  <br/>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l) </i>of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against a person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  I advise that any submission or opening statement submitted will be published on the committee's website after the meeting.</p> <p>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or any official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p> Mr. Courtney is very welcome and I invite him to make his opening submission.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.185" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300004#C00200"><p>I am honoured to have been asked by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Donohoe, to become chairman of Dublin Bus.  I also wish to thank the Chairman and members of the committee for the invitation to come before them today.<br/>To give some background information, I am a native of Dublin and grew up in Artane, where I attended Chanel College.  I joined C&oacute;ras Iompair &Eacute;ireann in 1979 as a bus conductor and qualified as a bus driver in 1985.  During my time in CIE I became a full-time student in Trinity College and graduated in 1987 with a BA (Hons) in economics.  In my final year I studied transport and labour economics and in my undergraduate thesis I examined how economically efficient Dublin Bus was against a basket of other bus operators.  I left CIE in 1987.<br/>I have been awarded postgraduate diplomas in corporate legal governance from the Law Society of Ireland, in employment law and arbitration law from the school of law in UCD, and in strategic management and executive coaching from DIT.  I am a qualified mediator and arbitrator, master trainer and executive coach.  I am currently a member of the Central Bank disputes resolution tribunal and a lay member of the client and complaints committee of the Law Society of Ireland.  I am a former board member of the Equality Authority and a current member of the Institute of Directors.  <br/>In 1987 I joined IBEC and started a career in HR and in industrial relations.  I have held senior management positions in Glanbia, Superquinn and C&amp;amp;C Group plc.  I was the group HR director in C&amp;amp;C Group plc for seven years until 2008.  For the past seven years I have been managing director of Courtney HR, which provides management consultancy services to many leading Irish companies.  I have an interest in history, sports and the theatre. <br/><b></b>With regard to the strategic priorities, Dublin Bus is a vital transport network and is a key component in enabling economic growth and the creation of jobs.  In 2013, its 3,200 staff and its fleet of 932 buses were responsible for transporting 114 million passengers over 56 million km.  As the economy starts to grow again, so also are passenger numbers.  Our priority is to meet that customer demand and provide the services the city needs when it needs them.  The strategic imperatives are to develop the network to meet the needs of the city and county; to ensure a safe, continuous, reliable and efficient service for our customers; to establish a sound financial footing for the company; and to develop the skills of all the team in Dublin Bus. <b></b><br/><b></b>Moving on to operations, the Dublin Bus Network Direct review has transformed the service.  Consultation with the users was key, and 110 routes, including 19 high-frequency routes, now crisscross the city.  The network is now simpler, more direct, better integrated and more user-friendly.  However, the work goes on, and the priority is to work with the NTA, Dublin City Council and other transport networks to provide a truly integrated system, of which Dublin Bus forms an integral part.  Full accessibility, the introduction of hybrid buses and safety are also priorities. <br/>Dublin Bus is striving to keep its existing customers and attract new ones.  Dublin commuters now have travel options.  They include walking, cycling, and using scooters, cars, buses, trams and trains.  At present, 61% of all public transport trips into Dublin city centre are on the bus.  Our aim is to continue to make the bus option the most attractive.  This is achieved, first, by having a modern clean, reliable fleet of buses, second, by giving value for money, and third, by providing more on-board services. <br/>Dublin Bus services include real-time passenger information and passenger displays at stops, and on-bus real-time passenger announcements are next.  All of the Dublin Bus fleet have free Wi-Fi access for all our customers.  The introduction of the Leap card is one of many steps towards a truly integrated transport system, and Dublin Bus is committed to this process through the National Journey Planner.  Leap cards will be used more than 30 million times in 2014.<br/>With regard to the financial aspect, Dublin Bus has had a very difficult few years and much hard work has been done by the management team to make the most of the reduced revenues available to it.</p> <p>This has meant making some very tough choices about reducing costs, fleet size and changes to routes and schedules.  All of the staff in Dublin Bus have made their contribution to these changes and the company is now heading towards a more stable financial position.  However, capital investment is also a priority and has to be renewed and sustained. <br/>Significant challenges still remain and the careful and prudent management of the limited financial resources available to the company remain a top priority for senior management and the board.  Areas of focus include the ageing of the fleet, the nature and size of the subvention, continuing to give customers value for money and getting value for money from our suppliers. <br/>The staff of Dublin Bus are our greatest asset and provide an essential economic service for the city.  One of our highest priorities is to develop all of our team members and continue to make Dublin Bus a great place in which to work.  The challenge for us all in Dublin Bus is to accept how critical our service is to the people of Dublin and ensure at all times we provide for continuity of this vital service.  This is the one of the highest priorities for the board.  <br/>In three years time Dublin Bus will be an integral part of an integrated transport network, providing a safe, reliable, efficient and continuous service for the people of Dublin.  It will be seen as an alternative to all other modes of transport that customers elect to use by choice both as a means of transport and an experience in itself<b>. </b>I look forward to making my contribution to that change and in my role as chairman to provide strategic support, for supervision and value for money as the changes happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300005#D00200"><p>I thank Mr. Courtney for a comprehensive contribution on the challenges ahead.  While I had never him until he appeared before the committee today, I am impressed by the way in which he has worked his way up through the company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300005#D00300"><p>I wish to share my time with Senator Paschal Mooney.  </p><p>  I welcome Mr. Ultan Courtney and thank him sincerely for appearing before the joint committee.  I, too, have just had the opportunity to go through his background.  As the Chairman said, it is fantastic that a person who started out in the company as a bus conductor has gone on to become chairman.  That speaks volumes for the skills and qualities he has developed.  That he has been through a period of additional learning in that time will stand to the company extremely well.  I wish him well in his endeavours.  We will certainly support him in every way we can.</p><p>  I wish to set out some of the important issues from my party's perspective.  Maintaining a public transport network is hugely important.  This is challenged by the capacity of the State to provide subvention for the company.  Mr. Courtney was appointed by the Government and at the same time as he becomes chairman he takes on a completely different role.  I would have thought there would some be friction between him and the Government in that he has to continuously pushing for more resources, not just to maintain the same level of service but to expand it in line with growth in the economy and also to deal with the competition.  How does Mr. Courtney intend to respond to that dynamic?  How does he intend to develop a public transport system at a time when part of Government policy looks towards privatisation, something of which I am not in favour, but it is the reality?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300005#D00400"><p>I will wait for my turn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300005#D00500"><p>I can allow the Senator in briefly if he wishes, otherwise I will move on to Deputy Se&aacute;n Kenny who will be followed by Deputy Dessie Ellis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1021" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kenny" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300005#D00600"><p>I welcome Mr. Ultan Courtney to the joint committee and wish him every success in his role as chairman of Dublin Bus.  I am impressed by his CV.  That he has a background in public transport should be an asset and give him an insight into how the public transport service works.  </p><p>  A number of questions have been raised about the level of subvention and how it compares with the subvention provided in other European capital cities where public transport is provided.</p> <p>Of particular concern is the impact on Dublin Bus and bus passengers of the current disruption being caused by the Luas cross city works, which is affecting many streets, bus routes and journeys.  How does Dublin Bus propose to manage this year-and-a-half-long disruption and ensure people can utilise buses to travel to work?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300006#E00200"><p>I propose to also allow questions from Deputy Ellis at this point, following which Mr. Courtney can respond to the questions of the three members in this round.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300006#E00300"><p>I thank Mr. Courtney for his presentation.  His curriculum vitae is very good.  I would like to discuss a number of issues with him.  The proposed off-loading of 10% of Dublin Bus routes in 2016 is, in my view, a move towards privatisation.  Dublin Bus should remain publicly owned and operated.  I am interested in hearing Mr. Courtney's view on that issue.  I understand the NTA is currently putting pressure on in this regard.  Can that proposal be rowed back on or is it, as appears to be the case, written in stone?</p><p>  Perhaps Mr. Courtney would offer his opinion on the plans regarding bus rapid transit and say whether he will have input in that regard and what it entails.  This plan will hugely affect Dublin Bus and its routes, particularly the main routes.  On bus lanes, we hear constantly from people about the need for fewer restrictions on the use of bus lanes and that they should be opened up more to use by other traffic.  In some areas, there is awful congestion during times when bus lanes are empty.  I would welcome Mr. Courtney's view on this.</p><p>  Dublin Bus recently recruited a large number of people, which is a positive development.  On the other hand, it is reducing its Dublin routes by 10%, which will mean a loss of passengers.  I welcome the fact that Dublin Bus is recruiting and that its passenger numbers have stabilised.  Mr. Courtney might inform the committee of the proposed remuneration, if any, that he will receive for this post.  I acknowledge his reference to other companies with which he has been associated.  Perhaps he would elaborate on his involvement as chairman or member in other companies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.195" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300006#E00500"><p>On the public transport network, the first priority for Dublin Bus is always to provide an efficient transport service to Dublin city and county.  In terms of our current transport service, the NTA has put forward the proposal that 10% of Dublin Bus routes be put out to tender.  That is a reality that we may have to face.  It is a policy decision, which may also be required under EU legislation.  This will have an impact on Dublin Bus, but we will deal with it as we move forward.  The bigger issue for Dublin Bus is how to increase the business regardless of what market we are in, be that public or private.  Currently, revenue growth is hugely important.  Dublin Bus has shown over the past year or two that it can increase revenue.  It is necessary that we look at opportunities to increase revenue, because we cannot sustain a bus service on constantly cutting costs.</p> <p>Any of us who has been involved in this kind of process knows that there is only so much one can do.  There have been three rounds of it in Dublin Bus and now we want to look to a more positive future where we are growing the service and becoming more efficient.  We will operate in whatever market we have to operate in, whether it is the public market, which we are in currently and which will be the predominant market for a long period, or some other.  There is competition and I have no control over that.  CIE or Dublin Bus has no control over that but if there are routes out for tender, we will compete for them.  Dublin Bus has provided an effective transport system in Dublin.  The challenge is to become more effective.  Many of the initiatives taken in terms of the service in recent years have been to do that and to make it more customer-friendly, usable and to attract people onto the bus, which is very important.  </p><p> Deputy Ellis asked whether people should be allowed to use bus lanes.  I have a slightly different way of looking at it; I want to get people onto the buses if I can.  I have learned over the years that the use of bus lanes - if a route is a priority one on a bus lane and there is no competition in terms of its use - are probably the most effective way of moving a large number of people from A to B.  The real competition is to persuade the person commuting by car by bicycle or walking that the bus is an option that can be used in conjunction with healthy exercise such as walking to travel to and from work.  We want to get people onto the buses and to make travelling by bus an experience with which they are satisfied and that they are prepared to pay a reasonable rate for it, but that will always be the challenge.  I believe the bus lanes work but they should always be under review.  There should always be opportunities to discuss whether they are working and how well they are working.  </p><p> That brings us back to the rapid transport system.  I do not know how that will work in Dublin.  We will have to wait and see.  It is well worth trying to see how it will work because it has worked in other cities and it is a model that can work.  The issue is to make sure that it works well.  The last thing we want is to have a satisfied group of people travelling on the rapid system and another group of people who are dissatisfied.  A key point I have learned over the years is to listen to one's customers because they will tell one what they want and if one does not listen to them, they will vote with their feet and go elsewhere.  We do not want that to happen.  </p><p> There is a bigger focus in that as it is a public service, it also has a commercial element to it.  We want customers to be satisfied.  We want them to travel by bus and on getting off the bus to say that was a good experience, they had access to Wi-Fi, they used their Leap card, the service is better than it was and it is going to be better as we move forward.  The challenge for us as we move forward is to balance the public and the private, the idea of the passenger against the customer - I prefer to call people customers rather than passengers - and to make it a very good experience for them. </p><p> That brings me back to the question that was asked about the subvention paid.  The subvention is a part of the revenue of the business.  I would like to grow the other side of the revenue stream, which is to generate as much income as possible from the business we do on a daily basis and to explore other opportunities.  From my initial reading of the material, I wondered if we had examined all the opportunities to raise revenue.  I do not have the answers here today.  From a board perspective, that is an area we need to examine in detail and to ask if there are other ways to make money that we have not thought of because we often view the bus service as simply that, a bus service, but there are other opporutities we should examine.  It is a question of trying to get that balance right.</p><p> In terms of public transport system, there are people who rely on the bus service, who choose to travel by bus and there are people who are marginal whom we want to target.  Everybody accepts that we have to provide a service in a city of this size, which, geographically, is very spread out.  The argument often arises as to how we should do that.  At present the Government has decided to do that by way of providing a subvention, other people would say direct support should be provided to the people concerned but that is another argument.  The service is provided by way of subvention and that is part of the social contract between Dublin Bus and the Government.  We take that and our responsibilities in that regard very seriously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300007#F00200"><p>Mr. Courtney mentioned that there was an opportunity to examine raising revenue in a different way other than by subvention.  Will he expand on that?  There is great concern that the way Dublin Bus, or the general group of CIE companies, has dealt with the loss in revenues in recent years, in line with a reduction in fare revenue, in passenger numbers and in subvention, has been made up, to some extent, by cost-cutting, which is fair enough, and an increase in fares.</p> <p>Everybody accepts that there is an elasticity around the whole fare structure.  If there is anything to suggest that is the model Mr. Courtney intends to pursue for the increase in fares, that would be a matter of deep concern.  Alongside that, we have got to see a situation where we get a modal shift, which has not been as successful as had generally been expected.  If we are to encourage people onto the public transport system, we certainly cannot go down the road of increased fares.  So, can Mr. Courtney-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.199" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00200"><p>Absolutely.  I am sorry if I gave the impression that I was talking about increased fares; I was not, because at the end of the day customers have to get value for money.  It is within the environment of a bus network as to what it can do to generate revenue.  I do not have the answer to that question today but I want to look at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00300"><p>It is better to have no answer than to say there will be fare increases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.201" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00400"><p>I do not think that is the answer <i>per se</i>.  At the end of the day, people will pay for value for money if they are taken to where they want to go when they need to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00500"><p>What about charging for Wi-Fi?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.203" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00600"><p>I do not know.  It would be wrong to speculate on that issue.  It is too early in a tenure that has not started yet to speculate on that issue.  On thing business has taught me is that one should always examine the model one has to see if there are other opportunities to generate revenue - something for which people are happy to pay.  At the end of the day Wi-Fi is free, and I do not foresee any change, but one should have a look as to whether one can generate income.  One never knows where one will do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00700"><p>Deputy Kenny raised the issue of the destruction of the streets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1021" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kenny" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00800"><p>I asked about the disruption to bus services caused by the Luas Cross City works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.206" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G00900"><p>That is a big concern for Dublin Bus.  I spoke to the CEO.  In one of his initial briefings to me he outlined in detail what Dublin Bus was doing to ensure such disruption was minimised.  The last thing we want is that people are left at places which are too far away from where they want to go.  Some very good work is being done in that area and is ongoing.  We do not know for certain what impact it will have.  It is important from our perspective to know exactly what the proposals are, that they suit the customer, and, if they are not working, to move quickly to try to work around that.  In an ideal world it would not happen, but it will happen, and we will try to ensure it will not have an impact on our customers and, if it does, that the disruption is minimal as far as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1021" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kenny" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G01000"><p>I believe the maintenance of free Wi-Fi is very important.  Most cafes, restaurants and hotels provide free Wi-Fi.  I accept that Dublin Bus has to raise revenue in other areas, but customers would be annoyed if it was to consider charging for Wi-Fi.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.208" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G01100"><p>I do not believe I said we would charge for Wi-Fi.  I do not think there is any plan or proposal to charge for Wi-Fi.  It has been too successful for us and we want to keep our customers happy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300008#G01300"><p>I welcome Mr. Courtney and acknowledge that his is a strong curriculum vitae.  Anyone who has listened to his presentation would have to say that his background in CIE, his studies and his work experience through IBEC in both the private and public sector give him a huge range of experience, and I can only conclude that his appointment is absolutely based on merit.  I am confident that Dublin Bus will benefit hugely from the experience he will bring to the position of chairperson.</p><p>  Perhaps I can take Mr. Courtney back to this time last year, when Dublin Bus went on a three-day strike.  The Government, ICTU and IBEC task force which was appointed was led by Mr. Courtney and Mr. Dowling.  Will Mr. Courtney provide an outline of the work he did to achieve a breakthrough in the industrial relations impasse at the time, his role at that time and how he sees his role changing from that of task force leader to the position he has today as chairman of Dublin Bus?</p> <p>How is the relationship with the Government and the unions?  Was it enhanced by that process?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300009#H00200"><p>I welcome the remarks made about the proposed appointment of Mr. Courtney.  He and I share a common background in that I was a bus conductor, but not with Dublin Bus.  I come from County Leitrim where there were not many jobs and I ended up in London Transport.  I could give him route directions for some of the routes on which I worked if he is interested, as I am sure he could about his.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.212" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Uttan Courtney" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300009#H00300"><p>I probably could.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300009#H00400"><p>He would be too modest to say so, but our colleague, Senator Barrett, was our lecturer in TCD, I understand.  There is a common interest there.  </p><p>  I wish Mr. Courtney well.  If anybody was to headhunt a chairman of Dublin Bus he would be at the top of the list in terms of his CV.  It covers all the bases.  Given the fact he has worked his way up through the organisation I do not think anybody other than somebody like him would have a proper understanding of how the culture of Dublin Bus works.  Deputy Harrington referred to industrial relations.  I know from my time in London that transport workers tend to get a bad name and seem to always give the impression that they are going on strike.  Maybe it is because the public impact of what they do is much greater than in other areas of service.</p><p>  I was curious to explore with Mr. Courtney his views on industrial relations in Bus &Eacute;ireann between the workforce and management.  I want to add a caveat.  I am fully aware that a lot of sacrifices have been made by the workforce since 2009.  There have been severe cuts and that may have been the catalyst for the more recent industrial relations breakdown.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300009#H00500"><p>There is phone interference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300009#H00600"><p>People felt that enough was enough in terms of pay cuts.  Is Dublin Bus out of the woods in that regard or will it always be a question of balancing the books by the amount of money given by the Government?  I would be very supportive of the view expressed by Deputy Ellis.  I am a strong supporter of public subvention for the transport industry because I do not think any public transport organisation in the developed world pays its way as it is, by its nature, a public service.  I am sure that view will be part of Mr. Courtney's ongoing discussions with the Government. </p><p>  I do not share the view that even in times of austerity the first area to be examined should be the subvention for public transport, especially as I am someone who comes from rural Ireland where public transport is relied on to a great extent.  In a city the size of Dublin people rely on public transport for a variety of reasons.  To me it is a no-brainer that Government should provide subventions.  However, there is the argument that subvention is fine but there has to be a responsible approach from those working within the industry.  </p><p>  My question concerns the industrial relations relationship between management and the workers.  Does the workforce support Dublin Bus and see it as more than just a job?  Does it share the vision of what public transport is about as outlined by Mr. Courtney?  I would like to explore that with him.  I wish him every success.  I have no doubt he will bring a very unique dimension to this job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300009#H00700"><p>I welcome Mr. Courtney.  As Senator Mooney said, it is ideal that someone who has been a conductor and a driver and took courses in transport economics is appointed to the role.  In the lectures I gave I referred to the fact that if we can get things right a bus lane can, as someone said earlier, move large numbers of people very quickly without the kind of capital investment required by underground and railway systems, which took over the glamour end of this business.  The bus is still the workhorse.  I hope Dublin Bus will be seen as a higher priority.  </p><p>  The committee recently held negotiations with Mr. Keegan on a different matter.</p> <p>Dublin Bus buses go up one-way streets, have priority at junctions and so on because they carry more people.  Can the success of the Stillorgan quality bus corridor, which was impressive, and the one on the Malahide Road, which had a very high share of the market at one stage, be repeated?  </p><p> As Mr. Courtney said, the staff are very important.  Something I note when I bring tourists on the city tours is the incredible wit of the drivers.  When we passed by the Rotunda on one of them, the driver said, "That is the best hospital in the world.  I am saying that because more people come out of it than go into it."  The Dublin Bus driver's wit is one of the company's great assets, and everybody was delighted with it.  We had to translate it into German for some people but that kind of Dubliner, as a tourist investor in the open top buses, is brilliant for the city.</p><p> I wish Mr. Courtney every good fortune and share the appreciation of everybody else around this table.  He could not have been better chosen in terms of his recent human relations background, all the courses he did and from where he started.  If there is anything we can do in the Seanad, and I am sure in the D&aacute;il also, that would be of use to him he can come back to us because everyone wants the type of transport service he is seeking to develop.  In engineering terms it became less fashionable than much more expensive solutions but we still have a debt to GDP rate of 120%, so some of the expensive solutions might have to wait.  Mr. Courtney is welcome aboard, and congratulations on his appointment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300010#J00200"><p>Mr. Courtney is very welcome.  It would be remiss of me not to comment by way of asking a question but Senators have already made reference to what I had intended to say.  The only association I had with Dublin Bus was jumping on the 23 bus to go down to the Phoenix Park for a run or hitching a lift when I was injured on the way back from Palmerstown.</p><p>  People would ask me about the mindset of an athlete or a sportsperson in the 1960s and 1970s compared to the mindset of an athlete in 2014 or recent years when we have seen the performances increasing.  Mr. Courtney has a phenomenal background in that he was involved in the nuts and bolts, so to speak.  He probably knows every nook and cranny in the engines, besides being a conductor and a bus driver.  What is the difference between the mindset in Dublin Bus now and the mindset at the time he was working there?  The experience he gained academically through arbitrations, human resources etc. places him in the role of a very good visionary, particularly because of his experience of the nuts and bolts aspect and in terms of where we are now.</p><p>  I agree with the subvention and a social contract between Dublin Bus and the Government but, ultimately, it is the taxpayer who pays for that subvention.  Is the taxpayer aware that if there was no subvention it would not be a very attractive buy commercially?  Based on that observation, how does Mr. Courtney, as a visionary who is coming in as chairman of Dublin Bus, intend to get that balance right to satisfy both Government and, ultimately, the taxpayer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.219" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300010#J00300"><p>It is a very good question and it is extremely difficult to answer having been put on the pedestal of a visionary.  It will be a balancing act in regard to that but I am looking forward to that challenge because it probably requires a fresh pair of eyes, a little experience and a little expertise.  I am not just talking about myself but about the board of Dublin Bus, which is made up of capable, commercially-minded and public sector minded people who know that things are changing and they must change with them.  They also know they have to lead it and therefore they have to come in before people like the members and have a vision in regard to that.  They have to tell the population of Dublin what they intend to do for them.  They also have to tell the workforce what they need them to do for them, and outline what the board will do for them.  It is a hearts and minds process.  The Senator has asked a very good question, and it is often forgotten in discussions in Dublin Bus on finances and subventions that we are talking about a very good group of people, many of whom have long service.</p> <p>They are very dedicated and committed to providing the service.  I met a man recently with whom I worked 30 years ago.  He is still driving the bus and still committed to doing the job, and he wants to be out there.  As we sit here and when we go home this evening the buses will still be running; guys will be getting up at 4 a.m. to take the buses out and they will be working until late at night on Nitelink and everything else.  They will be doing the business and they are committed.</p><p> In my view, industrial relations have improved.  We all faced a very difficult set of circumstances over the past number of years when, due to economic circumstances, everybody had to take a cut.  We have all taken various cuts in bits and pieces.  It is difficult to go to any workforce and ask them to take a cut, and in the case of Dublin Bus the last round was the third round.  People are genuinely fearful as they wonder whether this will ever stop and whether a turnaround will come.  Trust became somewhat damaged in that process.  The excellent management in Dublin Bus worked really hard to convince people that if we did this we could get ourselves on a proper footing and be able to start to grow again, to grow with the city and to grow with the economy.  We all bought into that hope; we took all the cuts in the hope that the economy would start to turn around.  There are signs that this is happening and the shoots are there.  We still have problems; Senator Barrett will be able to enunciate those economic problems far better than me.  We still have them and we confront them.  The guys and people driving the buses want to see a future as well, and that is the prize.  </p><p> I was heartened by the process in which I was involved, although it was a very difficult process.  The Labour Court had issued a recommendation, and I and Mr. Dowling - who is an excellent mediator - worked hard over many hours.  We talked to people and we tried to understand why people were rejecting the recommendation - in many cases out of fear or mistrust, or because they held the view that this was an excuse to take money away.  The current proposition is a bargain between the management and the workforce that was freely entered into and agreed, and that bargain has been honoured.  People can now see that passenger numbers are going up and Dublin Bus revenue is starting to increase.  We have stabilised the subvention and we are in a position in which we have a proposition.  We are going to grow with the city and we will face anything that comes our way, whether that be in the public sector, to do with the subvention, or a decision to open the market.  Whatever happens, Dublin Bus will be there and will face anything that comes its way.</p><p> What is sometimes missed is that Dublin Bus has very good staff who are fully committed; they are the last people who want to be in dispute.  People only go out on dispute when they feel they have no option; the day of going out on dispute as an option is long gone in any of the CIE companies.  People go on dispute now because they see it as the only option.  My role and that of other people in the company is to provide an alternative.  That is what we did in the proposal; we offered an alternative way forward, and they bought into it.</p><p> The green shoots have appeared and Dublin Bus is fighting back.  It is a completely different job from what I remember in the past.  There were good men in those days too - and women - who were on the buses and who provided a great social service.  Senator Paschal Mooney will be very familiar with the service provided by bus conductors.  A much wider range of services is being provided now.  They are dealing with the younger population who are looking at Dublin Bus services on Facebook and Twitter and accessing real-time passenger information and apps.  I struggle with some of this, but these things are natural to the young and we want to capture the young population and keep them.  We are hoping to catch the marginal customer.  We have people who will always use our services and those who occasionally use our services.  Other people will make a choice.  For example, I had a choice today as to how I would travel to this meeting.  The best choice for me today was public transport; I arrived by public transport and I will go home by public transport, because it is the best choice for me.  I am one of the marginal people because I have a choice: I can use the car or I can walk.  I admit to Senator Eamonn Coghlan that I cannot run.  I elect to make the choice to use public transport because the service is available.  However, the demand from the customer is that we must be there when we are needed and we go where they want to go.</p><p> The network review is a major change.  Up to a couple of years ago I used to be able to say where every bus went.</p> <p>Up to a couple of years ago, I did; now I do not have a clue because the service is across the city and citywide; it goes everywhere one wants to go.  It has changed and we are constantly challenged by it because Dublin is very spread out and a low-density city.  It is a major challenge for us to provide the service and we will continue to examine it.</p><p> Industrial relations are better and will continue to improve because there is a process of engagement and we have all learned that the only way we will solve problems is through discussion and engagement.  There is always negotiation and, at the end of the day, we do business.  My job, as chairman of the board, is to help management to consider alternatives and suggest better ways.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00200"><p>Mr. Courtney mentioned the ageing fleet.  What percentage of the fleet needs to be replaced and will it have an impact on the financial position of Dublin Bus?  Is the fact that drivers cannot give change an inhibiting factor?  I am thinking of tourists in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.223" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00300"><p>Whether drivers can give change is always a question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00400"><p>Has Dublin Bus considered using debit cards, in respect of which the process is very quick?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.225" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00500"><p>I cannot answer that question today, but I will return to the Senator.  We will always examine the issue.  </p><p>  Because working buses have not been replaced for a couple of years, the fleet is slightly older.  The newest bus is six years old.  It is slipping and we do not want it to happen because if it continues to slip, problems will arise.  It could be marginal, affecting just 1% or 2%, when a bus does not turn up, breaks down or goes in for repair.  There is no better statement about a modern city than it having a modern, clean, efficient, effective and continuous bus service, where when a bus pulls up and people see it as something good and opt to go on it.  In general, despite the few years when we did not receive replacements, the fleet looks good.  In the past two years there have been 160 buses provided and there is a commitment to provide approximately another 90 per year in the next few years.  We will push hard because people say we have surplus revenue which we should return to the Government.  It is very important to argue that it should be put into a modern fleet, which we need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00600"><p>Nitelink used to be a major service, but it is virtually gone.  After midnight or 12.30 a.m. we have a taxi service for the whole city.  There were many problems such as anti-social behaviour and attacks on staff, who have been magnificent over the years.  Will the issue be revisited?  For the capital city not to have a public transport system after hours is an indictment of the city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.227" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00700"><p>An integrated transport system should be provided when people need it and if there is a service at night, it should be examined.  However, we must consider the operational impact.  If there is anti-social behaviour and drivers need to be protected or if the service is not being used, the issue is always going to be revisited.  It will always be in the mix of public transport in Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00800"><p>On behalf of the committee, I thank Mr. Courtney for coming before us and engaging with us in a very open and transparent way.  He has demonstrated that he has been a practitioner and has the theory, expertise and vision.  We wish him well in his new appointment and will send a transcript of today's discussion to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.229" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ultan Courtney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014092300012#L00900"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for their courtesy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-09-23a.230" nospeaker="true" time="15:05:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 2.55 p.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 24 September 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>