<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.2" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="">Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine: Joint Sub-Committee on Fisheries</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.3" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.5" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800002#A00100">Business of Joint Sub-Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800002#A00200"><p>We have a quorum and will commence the meeting.  I have received apologies from Deputy Thomas Pringle and Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill.</p><p>  The minutes of the meetings of 20 and 21 March were circulated to the committee.  Are they agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.8" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00100">Aquaculture and Tourism: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00200"><p>I welcome the following: Mr. Francis O'Donnell, chairman, and Mr. Gavin Power of the Federation of Irish Fishermen; Mr. Eddie Sheehan, chairman, and Ms Caitl&iacute;n U&iacute; hAodha, Irish South and East Fish Producers Organisation from the Irish Fishermen's Organisation; Mr. John Walsh, chairperson, and Mr. S&eacute;amus &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute;, board member, Comhdh&aacute;il Oile&aacute;in na h&Eacute;ireann/Comhar na nOile&aacute;n Teoranta; Mr. Jerry Early and Mr. John O'Brien from Donegal Island Fishermen; Mr. Richie Flynn, executive, IFA Aquaculture; and Mr. Jerry Gallagher, chairman, North West Shellfish and Irish Shellfish Association from IFA Aquaculture.  I thank the delegates for appearing before the joint sub-committee.</p><p>  The joint sub-committee was established to focus on communities and the socioeconomics and promotion of sustainable industries.  The main industries identified by the sub-committee are aquaculture, island and coastal fisheries, inshore fisheries, with a particular emphasis on sea angling, and tourism.  We are here to hear the views of the witnesses on the issues relevant to their organisations.</p><p>  Before we begin, I wish to draw the witnesses' attention to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009 they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they are to give this joint sub-committee.  If they are directed by the sub-committee to cease giving evidence with regard to a particular matter but continue to so do, they will be entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise nor make charges against a person outside the House or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>  We have a large number of groups and I understand that each group will make a five minute presentation and the members offering will be allowed put their questions.  Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v is caught this morning, as the Animal Health and Welfare Bill is being discussed in the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00300"><p>I am in the same position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00400"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh na finn&eacute;ithe.  Beimid in ann l&eacute;amh c&eacute;ard a bheidh le r&aacute; acu agus beidh deis againn ansin scr&uacute;d&uacute; a dh&eacute;anamh ar an m&eacute;id sin.  I join the Chairman in welcoming the groups to the joint sub-committee.  One of the problems that can arise is that one may be required to be in two places at the one time.  I am taking Leaders' Questions this morning on behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party.  Unfortunately I cannot stay for the duration for the meeting but, as the delegates are probably aware, a record is kept of everything that is said and I will make it my business to read the full debate that will take place today.  When we are making our recommendations as a committee, I will give full cognisance to the contribution that will be made today.  This is a very important subject and we need to hear what the people on the ground are saying and to listen with particular care to what has been said.  The establishment of this sub-committee - which focuses on inshore and island fishing, among other issues - by the Chairman is very important.  I apologise to the delegates for my absence but the debate today will form part of my contribution to policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00600"><p>We have approximately 45 minutes until the start of the Order of Business in the D&aacute;il.  I call on Mr. Francis O'Donnell to make the opening presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.13" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Francis O'Donnell" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00700"><p>Good morning Chairman, Deputies and Senators.  I offer apologies on behalf of Mr. Sean O'Donoghue of the Killybegs Fishermen's Organisation, KFO, and Ms Eileen O'Sullivan of the Irish South and West Fish Producers' Organisation, who cannot be present today.  I am accompanied by Mr. Gavin Power and Mr. Ted Breslin of the KFO.</p><p>  The Federation of Irish Fishermen welcomes the opportunity to present our views on the status and management requirements for the inshore fishery in Ireland.  The federation comprises the Irish Fish Producers' Organisation, the KFO and the Irish South and West Fish Producers' Organisation.  Collectively, we represent a number of segments, including pelagic, mixed demersal fisheries, brown crab, nephrops and inshore fisheries.  We are acutely aware of the importance of inshore fisheries from a socioeconomic perspective.  Sustainable management and regulation is the key to ensuring a healthy inshore fishery in Ireland.  Sadly, this has been lacking to date, even though a number of blueprints have been published at the taxpayer's expense which clearly outlined a roadmap to effectively manage this fishery.</p><p>  Ireland has a significant amount of autonomy when managing its inshore fisheries and is not constrained by total allowable catches TACs for most of the mollusc and crustacean species found in inshore waters.  Inshore fisheries should be given the required support to expand sustainably to support coastal and island communities.  This need has been recognised by the recent amendments to include islands and coastal communities by the European Parliament as part of the reform of the Common Fisheries Policy.  However, Ireland is seriously lacking in policy in this area.</p><p>  It is estimated that more than 80% of Ireland's fishing fleet operates inside the 12-mile limit.  The inshore sector, which concentrates in the main on crab, lobster, shrimp, scallops, whelk, razor, cockles and Atlantic salmon, carries out its activity within the six-mile limit.  The last complete figures available for the economic potential of the inshore fishery in Ireland are for 2005.  Those figures were published by BIM and the Marine Institute.  Landings of wild-caught fish in the inshore fishery were worth approximately &euro;30 million at that time.  The inshore fleet is concentrated along the entire coastline of Ireland and supports around 3,000 fishers.  The vessel sizes are small, with the fleet mainly composed of vessels under 15 m in length.  There are approximately 2,100 vessels registered in the Irish fishing fleet, approximately 1,872 of which are less than 15 m in length.  The latter is reflective of sectors such as aquaculture, polyvalent general, polyvalent potting and specific.  The number of registered vessels has grown substantially since 2005.  This has been driven to some extent by the scheme for the licensing of traditional pot fishing boats in the Irish Inshore fleet.</p><p>  An excellent review of the Irish inshore fisheries sector was carried out by BIM in May 1999, entitled Irish Inshore Fisheries Sector: Review and Recommendations.  That review examined the inshore fisheries sector at that time and provided a roadmap for its development, focusing on partnership and stakeholder approaches.  The report was innovative and identified the key difficulties facing the sector.  It identified avenues to secure sustainability and provide development, addressing socioeconomic needs coupled with good fisheries management practices.  In 2005, BIM published an excellent document entitled Managing Ireland's Inshore Fisheries, which outlined in detail a management framework to realise this for 15 shellfish stocks found in inshore waters.  That framework forms the basis for the future management of all inshore fisheries in Ireland.</p><p>  We need to place a proper value on the significance of inshore fisheries in Ireland for the fishery itself and for those who rely on it for a living.  Coastal communities do not have the same employment opportunities as those in urban environments and have limited potential for economic diversification.  Recognising this is one thing; doing something about it is entirely different.  We do not need a task force to investigate how this can be done.  We simply need to design policy in line with the two reports referred to in my presentation.  I thank the Chairman and members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00800"><p>I thank Mr. O'Donnell.  I call on Mr. Eddie Sheehan from the IFO.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Eddie Sheehan" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800003#B00900"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for the opportunity to make this presentation.  I will deal with fishing in general rather than inshore fishing, but the problems are more or less the same in both sectors.</p><p>  My background is in fishing.  I left school at 16 and went to sea.  I spent most of my time at sea and I am still very much involved in the fishing industry both inshore and offshore.  The review of the CFP, in the IFO's estimation, is the final chance we have to rectify the wrongs of the past.  Ireland's share of its own resources gets smaller and smaller each year.  In the last CFP review the EU's plan to conserve stocks was to impose strict quotas on all stocks and throw back the dead fish into the sea.  The same people who have rigidly enforced the plan of dumping dead fish for the past ten years have now come up with a new plan of no discards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.17" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitl&iacute;n U&iacute; hAodha" time="09:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800004#C00200"><p>I am from the Irish South and East Fish Producers Organisation.  I wish to advise that we will probably repeat some of what the other witnesses have said because, all around the island, we experience the same difficulties.</p><p>  The south and east is a unique part of the country because of the diverse fisheries.  I represent a number of boats in that area.  Following a political decision, we lost our EU status in 2011 but we are hoping to have it reinstated.  We need it because it is a unique area.  We represent all the marine trawlers in the island, all the scallop fisheries and almost all of the boats that target ray that are sold on the east coast and mostly into Dublin. </p><p>  We have many success stories in the south east.  Perhaps I will read what I have prepared.  I am here to pose a few questions because the industry is worth &euro;500 million to the ailing economy.  The whitefish sector alone is worth &euro;183 million.  Some 11,000 people are employed in the industry and it is the hope that it will employ up to 15,000.  Are we in the right place to see that growth continue?  Do we need to look at the EU regulations?  Do we need a plan in Ireland?  I do not think we have ever had a serious fisheries plan on where the industry is going?</p><p>  Once we had a fishing licence.  Now we have licences that are constantly diluted which devalues the licences.  We lost our mackerel entitlement to a handful of people.  We lost our herring entitlement to 18 boats in a particular county.  Is that good for coastal development?  One member lost the right to fish because he did not have the base year.  I would argue that he should not have a base year because he fished in that area as his father and grandfather did.  That more and more of our fisheries are being ring-fenced into the future is not good.  The policy of ring-fencing is very poor.  </p><p>  I represent a large amount of the inshore fleet.  Some 80% of the vessels in the Irish fishing fleet are less than 15 m.  Harbours such as Waterford or Youghal where there should be a local fishery for clams and razors cannot get designated.  It takes two years and nine months longer than for any other member state to have licences issued and the areas classified, which is much too slow.  </p><p>  The closure of the salmon fishery was to be reviewed after three years and we are still awaiting this review.  Small areas around the coast such as Dunmore East, Passage East and Helvic should have a small controlled salmon fishery.  Unlike Donegal, no large factories from America or elsewhere will come to this area.  We have to create our own employment in those areas and it can be done if we get the support.  The salmon fishery needs to be looked at, as well as the eel fishery.  A small controlled fishery would allow people to maintain their livelihoods and engage in processing or smoking salmon or whatever. </p><p>  We have another success story in Dunmore East.  The closure of the Dunmore East box to boats in excess of 18 m has proved to be hugely beneficial and that initiative should be extended around the coast to different species and bays.  For example, trawling in bays for sprats should be protected for small boats which do not have the capacity to go further out to sea.  That is not happening.  Larger boats have the privilege of going after many species into deeper water and can also come inshore.  That is an issue that needs to be examined and preserved for smaller fisheries.  </p><p>  The sentinel herring fishery in Dunmore East has 54 small boats.  When that fishery opens in wintertime our office is alive and so is Dunmore East.  It brings money into the industry, creates employment, keeps young guys away from the aeroplane and brings them into the industry. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Walsh" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800005#D00200"><p>We are delighted to be here today and on behalf of the islands I thank the Chairman for the invitation.  I will set out some background.  I am the chairperson of Comhar na nOile&aacute;n, which is the islands local action group.  We manage the rural development programme, the Leader programme, the local and community development programme, the rural social scheme and the walks scheme on behalf of island communities in 33 islands across four counties, Donegal, Mayo, Galway and Cork, with populations ranging from three to 845 people.</p><p>  The basis of my presentation is three reports carried out by a consultancy firm on behalf of Pobail and Comhar.  One dates back as far as 2007, the next took place in 2009 and the last one was for the Common Fisheries Policy review in 2010.  We are trying to get across the message that special solutions are needed for the islands if we are to sustain the island populations.  The island populations are reducing at a dramatic rate and much of the time legislation and Government and EU policy is the cause.  We are here today to highlight some of these issues.  We hope today will represent the first step to try to make a serious attempt at sustaining vibrant populations on the islands.</p><p>  Sometimes legislation does not take into account the needs of islands.  Sometimes a rule or law is brought in which is seen as good for the country but it actually has a dramatic effect on the islands which was not foreseen at the start.  We call on the committee to policy-proof the needs of islands before legislation is brought in.</p><p>  The primary sources of income on the islands are all relevant to this committee.  They include tourism, fishing, farming, ferries and the public sector, and often it is a combination of some or all of these.  Island people are very resilient and like to live on the island but to do so they need to be able to carry out a number of different trades.</p><p>  Let us consider the licensing system for aquaculture in the country at the moment.  On some islands islanders got together and looked for licensing for aquaculture development.  However, it takes up to seven years to get licensing which, in this day and age, is a disgrace and should not happen.  We want young people to stay on islands but if they have to wait around for licensing for seven years then it simply does not happen and they move on.</p><p>  I will outline some of the challenges.  Before I comment on fisheries I will try to give people an idea of different things that happen because of legislation.  Sometimes the impact on island life is dramatic.  Let us consider the roads.  In recent years no road works were done on the islands because the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government put a limit of &euro;4 per sq. m on fixing roads, but because it costs &euro;7 per sq. m on islands no roads were done.  The islands were boxed into the local and community development programme because there was no other programme for islands.  Certain social and economic committees have been proposed.  However, if there is an attempt to break up the island organisations into bodies under the four different counties it will weaken the structure.  At the moment as a national organisation we have strength in numbers and that is the way we want to keep it.</p><p>  We have an issue with the moratorium on State jobs.  In various islands where council workers were posted as well as different State positions, jobs were lost to the islands because of the moratorium.  One job on an island is worth 100 jobs on the mainland.</p><p>  We have an issue with the legislation relating to fisheries.  We believe island communities should have licences designated for use on the islands.  If a young person wants to stay on an island he or she should have the possibility of getting a licence to try to see whether he or she can make a go of it.  such people should be able to try it out perhaps for two years.  Then, once they make a go of it, the licence should go back to the community where it could be used again.  There are many barriers to entry in the fishing industry.  We believe this must be done because at the moment we are always planning for the short term.  However, we should consider what it will be like in 30 years' time.  The question is who we want to be fishing on the islands and that is what we should be planning for now.</p><p>  Two issues stand out.  First, the issue of bringing in bait onto the islands for pot fishermen.  If island fishermen were allowed to catch bait themselves it would save on the cost of inputs.  If one could go to the island to buy bait or if one could fish for it, it would be very beneficial to the islands.  The problem is a fisherman can only deal with authorised buyers.  People on islands cannot understand why they cannot buy fish off a boat when it lands on the pier.  This is something that should be considered under the tourism brief of this committee.  If island boats could land on islands and sell their fish to restaurants and tourists it would be a big change.  That is how it works in France.  It is always done there.  Why can it not be done here?</p><p>  The salmon fishing ban has had a dramatic effect on the islands.  My colleagues from Donegal will discuss that presently.  We fully support the work of the Donegal islands fishermen in their call for an easing of the ban on salmon and also the restrictions in area 6A.</p><p>  There are challenges for islands with regard to infrastructure.  Islands do not have access to ice, cold rooms or bait storage and this is something that must be addressed.</p><p>  There are opportunities.  We believe that islanders should be allowed to take control of the area around their own islands and manage it because they are the best people to do so.  They are the custodians of the sea and they are the best people to oversee it.  There is a considerable value to the landings in Ireland and all island communities want is their small share of it.  There are opportunities under tourism and sea angling.  It is possible to add value to fish.  If we could land on islands we could smoke and fillet fish.  All of this would lead to jobs on islands and we could build up a food brand on the islands.  We believe this is very important.  Small-scale island-managed aquaculture is the way forward.  We have seen big farms off islands but it does not seem to be the way forward.  I note the submission made to the committee by the Inis O&iacute;rr community outlining the problems they are facing.  There are other opportunities in arts, foods, the marine research area and training and passing on the skills that islanders have.  These are all opportunities that can be used for the benefit of island communities.</p><p>  There were several proposals in the reports.  One was a call for island fishermen to have salmon quota.  This issue was mentioned some time ago by Mr. Eddie Sheehan, who referred to the effects of the salmon ban.  The ban was never studied in detail to determine the effects but I know it had a dramatic effect on my island.  The Donegal fishermen will outline the effects on their islands.</p><p>  There is a need for derogations and exceptions in legislation for small island fisheries.  Filleting on board, fishing for bait and selling on the island are all issues.  Up to now in the case of angling there were dual licences and multi-purpose vessels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800006#E00400"><p>I thank Mr. Early.  He was not here when I read out the apologies.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill has had the 'flu for the past week, there was a bereavement in family of the wife of Deputy Pringle and he had to go home.  Otherwise they would be here.</p><p>  I call on Mr. Richie Flynn from the IFA aquaculture executive. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.24" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richie Flynn" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800006#E00500"><p>I thank the Chairman.  We very much welcome the work of this committee in examining the socioeconomic potential of the coast.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800007#F00200"><p>A non-SAC area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richie Flynn" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800007#F00300"><p>Yes, a non-SAC area.</p><p>  We could increase our export earnings from &euro;100 million to &euro;200 million easily given the demand that exists.  We can increase our supply of raw material to local fish and shellfish processors, keeping more employment there.  We can invest in new technology that is built in Ireland, but to do this we need the State to facilitate us not with grant aid but with a system that can deliver licences with flexibility that are fit for purpose, from which we can raise funds and capitalise on our credibility.</p><p>  New legislation is not the answer.  We are not asking the committee for the introduction of a new Bill.  We just want the willingness to push development.  The industry needs answers as to how key economic and practical questions raised by the targets set in Harvest 2020 and Our Ocean Wealth will be met.  That is the job my chairman, Jerry Gallagher from Northwest Shellfish, has been doing since he took up the job.  How will the State support the industry in practical terms, instead of announcing grant aid schemes such as that announced in the past fortnight by BIM, which 95% of our members cannot access because they do not have a licence that has been renewed within the timeframe required?  Why are the templates for licences we require unfit for purpose, based on outdated upper limits of tonnage and ignoring new monitoring technology, which actively discourages good husbandry?  Why can the licensing system not work with farmers who wish to avoid the risk of algal blooms, which wiped out many stocks in the west and north west last year because of a lack of access to protected sites?  These and many other questions need to be answered through the redeployment of existing resources in BIM and the Marine Institute into the sector's development, a closer working relationship between the Department and licensees and applicants and a better understanding of the needs and limitations of those working with different species.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800007#F00400"><p>I thank Mr. Flynn.  That concludes the presentations, which cover a good cross-section of the issues and provide food for thought.  There are many similarities in the points covered.   An effort is being made to bring together people who have different interests and come from parts of the inshore fishing sector in order that they can all live in harmony.  That is part of what we are trying to do.</p><p>  Mr. Flynn's last point about the licensing regime is worrying because we are constantly told it is the designation under the habitats directive that is the big problem.  If there is such a delay in the process for a non-SAC area there is something really wrong.  I call Deputy Ferris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800007#F00500"><p>I thank all those who contributed.  This is a welcome development.  Their presentations were very informative for those of us who deal with this sector.  On a lighter note, there are two football teams south of Kenmare.  There are Cork ringers who play for Castletownbere, for Kenmare and for Tuosist.  My colleague knows what I am talking about.  One can never trust those Cork fellows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800007#F00600"><p>We will turn them over again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800007#F00700"><p>The most obvious point that jumps out at me from the presentations is that there is no cohesive plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800008#G00200"><p>First, I thank the Chairman for his initiative to establish this sub-committee of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  It was clear that the fisheries side was losing out compared to agriculture, which is the historical experience going back 40 or more years.  I hope the sub-committee will go some way towards redressing the balance.</p><p>  I also thank the representatives of the fishing organisations for sacrificing their time and making the effort to come from coastal areas and islands, which is not easy.  I acknowledge the distance they have travelled and the time they have spent to come here and give their presentations.  While it may appear that only a few members are present to listen to the presentations, what is said is on the record and a report will emerge from the deliberations.  Every word that is said will be taken into account.  From the presentations we have heard it appears there are diverse views and even though they all relate to coastal, community and fishery issues, different backgrounds are represented.  That is one of the challenges with which we must deal in terms of formulating or reviewing policy.  Reference was made to the BIM reviews of 1999 and 2005.  We must revisit the reports and take the positive aspects from them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/977" speakername="Michael McNamara" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800009#H00200"><p>I, too, come from a coastal community, although it is less recognised, for whatever reason.  Clare does have a coastline and there are small fishing communities, which, like all small fishing communities, have suffered a great deal, particularly in places such as Quilty.</p><p>  I have some specific questions.  Sustainability has become an increasingly important keyword in the food industry.  More broadly, Irish agriculture has recognised that, with the possible exception of milk, we will not be able to compete for a mass market and that we are better off competing for the upper end of the market.  The environmentally friendly nature of Irish agriculture is emphasised in marketing by An Bord Bia, and there is a movement towards getting Irish agriculture into high-end restaurants across the world and the entire high-end market.  Is there scope for the marketing of Irish fisheries, particularly the inland fisheries in which the witnesses and their communities fish, and for emphasising their sustainability?  We are talking about small producers in relatively small areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Walsh" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00200"><p>A submission was made to this committee implying that the community on Inis O&iacute;rr has issues with the proposed salmon farm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00300"><p>There were a couple of specific questions, particularly from Deputy Martin Ferris and Deputy McNamara.  Deputy Harrington's contribution was more of an overview.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitl&iacute;n U&iacute; hAodha" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00400"><p>I represent practically all the scallop boats in the country.  Scallops are commercially fished and dredged.  We have very few scallop licences and very few scallop days.  The fishing is based on the number of days allocated.  One can fish only for so many days, and this is based on horse power.  I do not know what happened because France has approximately 7 million days and England has approximately 3 million days, while Ireland has approximately 200,000 or 300,000 days.  We are way down the scale because of the manner in which the arrangement was rigged or sorted.</p><p>  There is a very good scallop fishery and it is very sustainable because only a certain number of dredges can be used.  The fishery is a very important one in the south east.  There is great demand for Irish scallops on the high-end market.  The industry is worth perhaps &euro;5 million or &euro;6 million per year to the south east.  It is very sustainable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Francis O'Donnell" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00500"><p>Deputy McNamara talked about sustainability.  Sustainability and responsibility go hand in hand.  Inshore fisheries, in the main, have a low impact.  The consumer is becoming more aware.  There is no reason inshore fisheries in Ireland, particularly those associated with specific species, could not fish under a responsible brand.  The consumer would be aware of the provenance of the product and of the route from pot to plate.  Breaking into niche markets in emerging economies would be difficult and producers would need a lot of capital to do so.  We are told continuously there is rising demand for food, including seafood, globally.  We must have management and policy in the first instance because that is what the consumer wants.  Consumers are becoming extremely aware.  It will not be long before a consumer will be able to walk into a supermarket anywhere in the world and scan a product using a smart phone app to determine where it was caught.  There are opportunities in this area but we need to have policy and proper regulation for inshore fisheries before we can tap into the market.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.41" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Eddie Sheehan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00600"><p>On Deputy McNamara's question on sustainability, the regime we work to at present involves our receiving a monthly quota.  It is dictated in the first instance by the European Union and then by local government.  The system we work at present is such that one gets one tonne of monkfish and one tonne of megs, for example, for boats working inshore.  With regard to smaller grades of fish, one fishes according to catch composition.  It is absolutely impossible to have sustainable stocks while fishing according to catch composition.  I fished all my life and do not know how well the people in the room can understand my point.  If one fishes according to catch composition or to a very strict quota regime, as we do, one will realise in the first instance that our quota is too small.  Second, we must fish to percentages.  One winds up dumping a lot of edible fish.</p><p>  I agree wholeheartedly with what was said by Mr. O'Donnell.  Putting labelling aside, we need to go back to basics.  One can have all the labelling and scanning in the world showing that fish were caught sustainably, but one must ask how one can have a sustainable fishery with the regime imposed on inshore and offshore fisheries at present by the European Union and local authorities.  The policy must change.  For ten years, we have been throwing dead fish back into the sea.  That is the conservation measure that has been put in place.  Now, lo and behold, the same EU officials who have told us for the past ten years to conserve stocks by throwing dead fish back into the sea are now saying this is wrong and that no more dead fish may be thrown back into the sea.  No thought whatsoever has been put into implementation.  We need to bring a sense of reality to the arrangement.  It is a very complex industry.  I have spent my life fishing and am still totally dependent on it.  We need reality because the system is a sham.  Much of the talk on sustainability is a sham, unfortunately, because there is still no proper regime.</p><p>  I addressed this committee in 2009, at which time the present Chairman was in attendance.  We identified a regime whereby we would regulate the catching sector by limiting time at sea.  We receive inshore and offshore quotas on a monthly basis and we fish within those quotas for the month.  One can keep fishing if one has 15 species to catch.  If, after the first week, one has exceeded the quota in respect of two species, one must discard fish of that species that are caught subsequently.  One is legally quite entitled to keep fishing as long as one keeps discarding.  Our proposal was to have a system that involved the cutting of the number of days at sea by 20% to 25% but the European Union, in its wisdom, and the then Government told us that was impossible because we did not have the scientific evidence to back it up.  My education is fairly limited but one does not need a lot of education to realise that cutting the number of days at sea by 20% will conserve stocks rather than throwing dead fish back into the sea.  I hope that answers Deputy McNamara's question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.42" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Walsh" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00700"><p>On the question of added value, if island boats were able to land the fish directly on the island, there would be great potential to create employment and add value, especially with salmon and shellfish, which are high in product value.  This should be part of the overall fisheries management plan for the islands.  On my island in 1900 there were 13 boats fishing for scallops, each with a crew of three.  They were selling directly to the Billingsgate market in London.  I can see why we cannot do that again.  Our objective is to create an island brand for both agricultural and fisheries products.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/977" speakername="Michael McNamara" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800010#J00800"><p>Is there any movement towards adopting the system of geographical area of origin for island fisheries?  Is there any movement at European level towards applying for brands such as "Island caught"?  I am not sure whether it is possible for fish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Walsh" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00100"><p>I think it is possible to do it, but there are no such moves at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00200"><p>In theory that is technically possible, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jerry Early" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00300"><p>Perhaps Mr. O'Brien could comment on that.  We could perhaps broaden the discussion.  As far as we are concerned, we all have our problems.  However, we feel that our island - and we have all alluded to the islands at particular times - is dead on its feet.  We can change things very fast by what we are proposing.  Deputy Harrington spoke about aquaculture but, unfortunately, it does not work everywhere.  Our geographical situation is not always suitable for aquaculture.</p><p>  The same can apply to sea angling and Mr. O'Brien can explain that situation.  We are hemmed in so far that we can see no way out, so we need immediate help.  All stakeholders have their own concerns, which I appreciate, but as an islander in Donegal I feel that our concerns are at the bottom of the chain.  It is imperative for the survival of the Donegal islands in particular - I cannot speak for the others but I am sure we all have the same concerns - that something is done to consider our proposals.</p><p>  As regards aquaculture, I know different things are being proposed.  There are various arguments regarding the pros and cons, but we will leave that to the scientists, although I have my own opinion.  The situation must be carefully managed so that aquaculture will not impinge or endanger the shellfish sector or the shoreline sector, including periwinkles.  There is a big grey area which must be examined. </p><p>  On our island aquaculture may be the way, although it is not our preferred route.  We could work in conjunction with that sector.  One may ask how aquaculture can save Arranmore, but it will take five years for all the studies and business plans to be completed.  It may be a case of considering something on land, such as a contained aquaculture project. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00400"><p>Yes.  I know what Mr. Early is talking about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.48" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jerry Early" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00500"><p>That may be the answer.  Due to our geographical situation, however, I would be sceptical about the open-sea option.  The scientists and others can bat that around the cage, as we are not experts on that aspect.  Mr. O'Brien has some points that really have to be heard, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00600"><p>Certainly.  He is more than welcome to make the points.  This sub-committee was established to create a forum where we could hear the thoughts, proposals and concerns of various interest groups, specifically including island communities and small rural coastal communities that are not part of the bigger offshore fishing industry.  That is the whole purpose of this sub-committee, so in order for us to feed in something useful we need to hear from the stakeholders.  We will try to come up with a report that acknowledges those concerns and see if harmony can be achieved between them all.</p><p>  Mr. O'Brien is welcome to contribute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John O'Brien" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800011#K00700"><p>I come from a small Gaeltacht island off the Donegal coast called Oile&aacute;n Inis B&oacute; Finne.  I did my first sea journey when I was three days old.  I was taken to the mainland for a christening and I have nearly been at sea ever since.  I started night salmon fishing in 1970 or 1971 at the age of 11 or 12 with my father.  At that time, there was only night fishing.  The boats would leave the harbour at about 7 p.m. or 8 p.m. and go to the fishing grounds until 10 p.m. or 11 p.m.  They would shoot their nets just before dark and haul them in again at sunrise before returning home with their catch.</p><p>  That was going on very well between trying to raise the children, as well as a bit of farming and fishing.  However, in 1976 or 1977 a new type of net came on the market that could catch fish during the day.  That is when the whole thing started to go wrong.  It was welcomed by the mothers and grandmothers who had sons and husbands at sea, and who had waited for them to come home during the night, in that they could earn their living during the day.  However, somebody in some Department, for reasons best known to themselves, decided that this could not be allowed.  The new net could be used for fishing cod, haddock and pollack but it was illegal for salmon.    </p><p>  It was easy to catch fish during the day but since our licences did not cover those nets, everybody went fishing, including garda&iacute;, school teachers, shop keepers and publicans.  If the publican could not go, he would buy a boat and send a few customers out and would get all the money back.  That went on for 20 years probably until 1997 when we had a war with the navy.  When an Arranmore boat was being arrested and taken ashore, the boats from Inishbofin and Tory Island would sneak out while they were taken to the court, so we would land our catch.  Nobody wanted to do anything about it because it was a hot potato.  </p><p>  In 1997, the rainbow coalition Government was in power.  The then Minister of State, Deputy Eamon Gilmore, was in charge of fisheries and he had the courage to legalise monofilament nets.  It was a step in the right direction.  We paid a high price for it, in a way, but at least we were legal.  The fishing limit was reduced from the 12-mile limit to the six-mile limit.  In addition, it was restricted to four days instead of five and eight weeks instead of 12, but at least things were legal.  We were going on the right track.  </p><p>  The subsequent Government introduced tags and quotas.  After monofilament nets were legalised there was a widespread decline in fishing because only licensed fishermen could operate.  There was therefore a big decrease in the amount of boats going to sea.  Up to that date the sector was managed depending on the amount of fish landed.  When scientists saw this big decrease in landings, however, they stated there cannot be any fish left so they started to introduce quotas and tags.  </p><p>  Sea angling had a strong lobby group which approached various Ministers because they wanted the fishery closed down altogether.  They started a campaign to stop driftnet fishing.  Meanwhile, some commercial fishermen on the west coast joined with the anglers.  They were approached by the Nascro group whose chairman came all the way from Iceland.  We hear a lot about Iceland nowadays.  The man from Iceland offered people a lot of money to give up their licences.</p><p>  The driftnet representative - I think he was in the salmon commission - wrote to us asking how much money it would take to buy us out.  Would it be &euro;60,000, &euro;100,000, &euro;250,000 or more?  I think I sent my reply saying "More", even though I had no intention of giving up my licence.  Things moved rapidly from 1997 with the introduction of tags and a decrease in landings due to many people leaving the industry.  There was a wide campaign to get us out of fishing.</p><p>  When it came to the crunch, however, there was no money from Iceland, even though about 50% of people had volunteered to leave the industry.  I was appointed to the board of the national fisheries commission in October 2005, but a lot of decisions had been taken before then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800012#L00200"><p>Essentially, the issue is about driftnet fishing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richie Flynn" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800012#L00300"><p>I will give some of my time to my chairman, Mr. Jerry Gallagher, to discuss scallops in particular.  Deputy Martin Ferris asked a question on Galway Bay, which I will deal with now rather than to have the whole meeting discuss it.  The committee has discussed it and will have BIM and the Marine Institute in to talk about it also.  To be clear, the IFA supports salmon farming in principle but cannot and will not lobby for any particular licence be it public or private.  The IFA believes the application process, no more than a planning permission or other process, must be upheld.  I am sure that legislators agree that the process must be apolitical.</p><p>  The science is sound as far as the IFA is concerned and there is no doubt about it.  We should not let opinion overrule facts.  I am personally concerned, having worked in the sector for 17 years, that there has been a great deal of scaremongering and hype.  Many piseogs I thought were dead in the 1980s have been resurrected.  They have to be dealt with.  I am also very concerned for my existing members.  I mentioned them earlier and the 600 licence applications that have been made.  The IFA has been clear from the beginning that in dealing with the new approach BIM is pursing, which is innovative, there must be a parallel process to deal with existing licence applications for shellfish and finfish by people who have invested a great deal of time, energy and money into this business over the last 20 to 30 years.  There are definitely offshore sites which must be investigated.  We definitely need critical mass.  I explained to the committee before about turning customers away and the embarrassment of going to international seafood fairs and saying to very important international supermarkets and processors and restaurants "Thank you very much for your interest in Irish salmon and Irish shellfish, but, we are very sorry, we are not being allowed to produce what we would like to produce to fulfil your orders.  So, thank you but no thanks".  It is a terrible position for anyone to be put in in this day and age.  It is always the default position of some regulators to kick thorny issues like this to touch by setting up another committee to look at the science all over again.  I have been at this long enough and sat on all the committees.  As far as I am concerned, the case is closed on foot of the new science and there is no need to reinvent the wheel.</p><p>  There are many different types of aquaculture.  It is similar to the case on land.  No one would dream of tillage farming in the Burren but they might set up a very successful salmon smoking company there.  In fact, one was set up in Lisdoonvarna which sells Irish organic farmed salmon around the world.  That brings me to the second question about sustainability.  Irish aquaculturalists realised a long time ago that, with the best will in the world, there was no way to compete with the 1.2 million tonnes coming from Norway so we developed niche marketing on the organic side, particularly with salmon and trout.  The shellfish industry is now getting involved.  "Sustainability" is the buzzword, which we have recognised.  We are getting very good prices for our products.  Bord Bia has introduced the new "origin green" initiative and I am proud to say that two IFA members have been among the first people to embrace it and get involved in the auditing.  It is available for fish and I encourage producers to get involved.</p><p>  I am personally drafting a Europe-wide sustainability charter for the aquaculture sector which will be launched in Dublin in May.  It consists of a five-point plan to hand the aquaculture industry to the next generation on a sustainable basis.  It is very exciting and I look forward to the launch.  Labelling is vital, particularly country-of-origin labelling.  We have said it before to the committee.  Control of labelling is vital also.  The Food Safety Authority of Ireland and the HSE must be involved as must the SFPA  It is very interesting that the branding of special areas of conservation, or SACs, was raised.  We have no problem with SACs, which protect environments and birds or other wildlife.  We depend on the environment for our livelihoods.  The problem with SACs has not been the fact that places have been designated, it has been the way that the system has been mishandled from day 1 by D&uacute;chas, the National Parks and Wildlife Service and the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.55" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jerry Gallagher" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800013#M00200"><p>I thank the Chairman for the invitation to present to the sub-committee.  Mr. John O'Brien and I used to leave the same pier in Mulroy Bay for many years to go fishing.  I even went with his boat to fish for salmon, lobster and crab.  In 1992, I formed North West Shell Fish Limited.  Mulroy Bay in north-west Donegal would be renowned around the world for scallop production.  In the late 1970s and early 1980s people were going into mussel production and put out ropes to collect mussel seed in the bay.  However, they found they were covered in scallop seed.  In Ireland this was not such a big deal but in France, where they had depleted their scallop fisheries, they were looking at wild collection, hatchery production and so on.  A delegation from France came to work with Irish scientists, including Dr. Dan Machin.  They stated if they had Mulroy Bay in France, they would have built a high wall around it and nothing else would be allowed in.</p><p>  In the early 1990s, while we continued fishing, we formed North West Shell Fish Limited.  The scallop settlement would be sporadic in Mulroy Bay.  In 1997 and 2007 we had a good settlement.  We got our first licence in 1995 which was expanded in 1997 but these expired after ten years in 2005 and 2007.  We are awaiting a renewal of our licence.  This is impacting on the whole scallop industry as there is very little scallop production elsewhere but in Mulroy Bay.  The European king scallop, the <i>pectin maximus</i>, is one of the most difficult shellfish species to cultivate.  Oysters, clams, mussels and so forth can be settled in a hatchery but for scallops the water quality has to be the purest.  Even the smallest amount of bacteria will prevent the scallop larvae from settling.</p><p>  North West Shell Fish was the model for the scallop industry.  Anyone interested in getting involved in it who contacted BIM, Bord Iascaigh Mhara, was sent to us.  While the French have not been so involved recently with our industry, the Norwegians have since the late 1990s.  Some delegations have come over to us in Mulroy Bay to see our operations.  We put out spat collectors in Mulroy Bay in what we call an onion bag.  It is a monofilament net that comes in rolls of 1,000 m by 1 m from which we would cut off a strip of 1 m.  We would have over 100,000 of these collectors.  We monitor the water quality and take samples to see when the larvae are about to settle.  There is a lot of science involved.  The Norwegians were not going down that road because they wanted the hatchery model but they wanted to see how the rest of the scallop industry worked.  They went diving with us during the harvesting.</p><p>  In 2007, we teamed up with Valentia Island Scallop Fishermens Association which has a large area within the radius of Valentia Island.  We were invited to invest in its programme but many did not because it was in the boom years and when one was not building houses and selling them one was doing nothing anyway.  A good number, however, did invest and put the funds into predator control and other measures necessary in Valentia Harbour.</p><p>  Spat collection in Mulroy Bay is sporadic.  There is no brood stock in the north water part of the bay.  We have asked BIM to come do a survey on this which it did last year and the previous year.  In both surveys, BIM only found one scallop.  It is a bit like having a hatchery with no brood stock.  We have invested an absolute fortune in this through selling sites on our farms and so forth.  Due to the licensing situation, we cannot seed scallops in that area.  There is a fisheries order in that area from 1980 to protect this part of the bay.  The main element to the collection of scallop larvae is the retention of water within a bay.  The scallop spawns and its larvae will swim around for roughly three weeks before they settle on some structure.  We work closely with our near neighbours who are fishing the Irish Sea along with the Irish fleet.  I will not mention the country.  They see the benefit of what we are doing.  This is the uniqueness of Mulroy Bay.  It goes back to issue of sustainability if we were doing what we should be doing and the licensing regime was in place. </p> <p>We intend to build a hatchery.  The Norwegian people I mentioned came over and they have successfully developed a hatchery process.  They are keen to work with us on a hatchery and we have also secured investors.  We are in a position to build a hatchery on the banks of Mulroy Bay but because it is a special area of conservation and appropriate assessments have not been carried out we are in a situation that is similar to the entire industry in Ireland.  Valentia is not unique.  Numerous co-operatives around the coast see scallop, mussel and oyster production as the only way out.</p><p> As has been noted by the other speakers, it takes all the elements.  Coming from a fishing background I see how the elements can come together.  In all of these species, whether mussels, scallops or oysters, a certain biomass is required to develop a bridge stock.  Aquaculture is the way to go because it is a managed stock.  If it was not for us I suggest there would be no scallops left in Mulroy Bay.  We have been managing the stock in part of the bay but we face a bottleneck in terms of collection.  We depend on a transfer of larvae.</p><p> There is not a problem in sustainability of shellfish from the perspective of aquaculture.  There is an overlap between aquaculture and inshore fishing and Valentia provides a perfect example.  There are niche markets for these products.  We are now supplying live and shelled scallops to the Asian market.  We get &euro;6 per kilogram for the scallops we dive harvest.  The product from the Irish Sea fishery is probably worth less than half that figure.  We are not dealing with the same markets.  Norway also operates a dive fishery.  The aquaculture shellfish sector can flourish if the Government creates an environment that allows people to do things.  That is all I am asking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.57" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Caitl&iacute;n U&iacute; hAodha" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800014#N00100"><p>Mr. O'Brien is lucky he was offered money for this licence.  My salmon licence was revoked in 1985 so they did not have to pay me anything.</p><p>  Whether one is fishing at sea or on the islands, salmon fisheries show how badly we have managed our fisheries.  We lobbied strongly in the 1980s to control salmon fisheries with a certain number of nets but the lobbying to which Deputy Harrington referred is the reason our industry is as it is.  We lobby people all the time and those who shout the loudest get the most.  That is one of the issues we must consider.  I return to the question of how our herring fisheries are ring-fenced, because boats from a certain country have more fishery access to our area than anybody else.  These practices will not create sustainable fisheries or sustainable communities.</p><p>  I imagine it is not possible to fish herring and mackerel from the islands in County Donegal because the EU law that affects us also trickles down to affect the people who live on those islands.  They no longer have the privilege of fishing on their doorstep.  These laws have to change and we have to examine what we are doing to protect coastal people and, by doing so, the rest of us.  We are all in the same boat, whether it is a punt or a large vessel.  Boxes create huge problems and they take from coastal areas which enjoyed traditional fishing rights.  The people on these islands should be able to jig or fish for mackerel or herring.  The pot of fish we owned should have been dished out more fairly but we need to consider the matter carefully so that we do not continue to operate in the same way.  If we continue to ring-fence and box fisheries, the boxes will get smaller because the bigger guys will eventually devour the smaller ones.</p><p>  The island people are also part of us, but they are being squeezed out because of EU law and bad Irish policy which closed salmon fishing to them.  I lost my licence to fish salmon even though we lobbied for a sensible approach.  That is the one thing missing from fishing policy in this country.  In aquaculture, I know someone who is trying to get classification for Youghal Bay.  It has taken him two years to even carry out a study.  There is a fishery in the bay that we are not allowed to use.  Why does the fishing community have to address this committee every year?  Where is the barrier between sense and what is going on?  As I noted in my opening statement, the industry is worth &euro;500 million but we have no security.  None of us can go to a bank with a plan for the next five years because we do not know what the EU or the Department will bring down the line.  There is no way forward unless we come out of the boxes.  We need people who will stand up for the industry rather than simply dealing with those who shout the loudest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richie Flynn" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800014#N00200"><p>The question of protected geographical indicators, PGIs, is very relevant.  PGIs are available for fish and the first PGI granted in Ireland was for Clare Island salmon, which is now a protected name.  There is great potential around the coast, particularly in respect of shellfish, to designate PGIs.  The UK, which has a relatively small oyster industry, highlights the qualities of oysters from particular bays.  There is a lot to be said for marketing and branding on that basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800014#N00300"><p>I thank the delegates.  I recognise the group is not as large as it would normally be due to other business.  However, this discussion will be in the Official Report.  I am conscious that all the witnesses have travelled extensive distances to appear before the committee and for this reason it was fair to give everyone a chance to speak.  I invite Mr. &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute; to make a comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.60" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. S&eacute;amus &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute;" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800014#N00400"><p>I am an islander from Arranmore in County Donegal.  I wish to draw the committee's focus back to the islands in the context of the recent legislation passed in Europe specifically recognising islands and their fisheries.  I fully support what Mr. Early and O'Brien have said.  The island group with which we work support their call for an easing of the salmon ban and the various restrictions in area VIA.  Island fishermen want to fish.  The most recent figures from the Marine Institute indicate that offshore fisheries are worth &euro;1.1 billion per annum.  As Mr. O'Donnell noted, the latest figures on inshore fisheries suggest a value of &euro;30 million.  It is a huge resource and the islanders just want their fair share of it.</p><p>  The European legislation is not accompanied by co-ordinated national legislation.  We would like to see a cross-departmental working group with island representation and a focus on implementation.  Considerable work has been done over the years but many of the ensuing reports are just sitting on shelves.  The time has long passed to put them into practice.  If there is a need to consolidate management structures, that should be done.  The focus should be on providing infrastructure and conservation measures so that fisheries are sustainable in the long term.</p><p>  We need to move away from the current short-term management systems towards long-term management of fisheries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00200"><p>On Mr. &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute;'s last point, that is going through due process.  It is a live application.  We must see what comes out of that but we will not be involved in it.  Did Mr. &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute; say the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government was engaged in a consultation process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.63" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. S&eacute;amus &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute;" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00300"><p>It is closed.  It recently made a call for submissions on an integrated coastal zone management system for all of our marine areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00400"><p>The Departments were before the joint sub-committee.  I mistakenly thought it was the Department Communications, Energy and Natural Resources.  That is taking quite a while but it will be seen as an asset to many things, other than just aquaculture.  The one worry is that in a non-SAC application, it is not looked at.  We should alert people as to why that is the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00500"><p>There is a separate process for the coastal zone management process and the baseline data collection process for the SACs.  It is something we could take up.  As Mr. &Oacute; Cn&aacute;imhs&iacute; said, decisions could be island-proofed.  Decisions are taken which have unintended consequences for islands in all legislation and not just in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.66" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Walsh" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00600"><p>The west Cork islands have an integrated development group on which all the agencies are represented in partnership with the islands.  The only Department which will not sit on it is the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which is ironic since we are dealing with islands.  Ireland has a marine affairs attach&eacute; in Europe who I met in UCC a few weeks ago but she does not cover islands either, which is also ironic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00700"><p>The Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine took the lead in establishing this joint sub-committee, which is a cross-departmental one.  We had to pull together the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, which is responsible for islands, and the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  The joint sub-committee was established to cover all the Departments relevant to our focus.  As it included islands and inland fisheries, we had to pull in three Oireachtas joint committees representing a cross-section.  That is why we were a little slow getting going.  We had to try to get the configuration correct.  We have been given a huge amount of information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.68" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jerry Gallagher" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00800"><p>Could I make a point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O00900"><p>Very quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.70" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jerry Gallagher" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O01000"><p>Perhaps the joint sub-committee is aware of it but under axis 4, FLAGs, fisheries local actions groups, have been set up around the country.  It is a new fund and should have been set up a number of years ago but we, in Ireland, are lagging behind again.  BIM is administering the fund and this is exactly what it is for.  Six have been set up around the coast.  Some take in two counties but Donegal has one.  The islands are involved as well.  The fund is administered to local communities devastated by what is happening in the fisheries sector.  If it has the power to do so, will the joint sub-committee lobby for funding?  There is approximately &euro;1.5 million in total for the coastal communities between 2013 and 2014, which is insignificant, but from 2015 to 2021, there is potential to attract some real money into this programme.</p><p>  The EU documentation explains what it is about as well as who it supports, namely, communities within ten miles of the coast, excluding populations of 10,500.  We have spoken about inshore fisheries, aquaculture, coastal communities and the islands.  This fund could really make a difference if proper funding was available.  It is up to Ireland to look for that money.  </p><p>  There is a central implementation board and we had a meeting in D&uacute;n Laoghaire last week with Michael Keatinge as chair.  As I said, BIM is administering it.  There is a bottom-up approach.  There are 16 people on the board in Donegal and it is community based.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AG32013032800015#O01100"><p>I thank Mr. Gallagher for that information.  This is the second session we have had on this issue and we have three more to go.  The next one will include Alyne Delaney and a representative of Teagasc.  After that we will meet &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta, BIM, the Marine Institute and the Sea-Fisheries Protection Authority.  We will finish with representatives of F&aacute;ilte Ireland and Tourism Ireland.</p><p>  If one looks at the principles of CAP, there is a Pillar 1 and a Pillar 2, which is about rural support mechanisms.  The CAP funding seeks to support rural communities.  As with the Common Fisheries Policy, it is not always monetary, except for initiatives like that which Mr. Gallagher highlighted where money can be drawn down.  The Common Fisheries Policy and European islands policies need to reflect the need to support dispersed rural communities, whether on an island or on remote coastal shore.  We are trying to devise a report which can recommend a model for social and economic support for that.  That is the objective of the exercise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.75" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 10:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.78" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2013032800003#B00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2013032800003#B00200"><p>The committee is in public session.  No. 8 is consideration of correspondence item 2013/462.  It was agreed at the previous meeting to discuss this correspondence item in public at the next joint committee meeting.  Further to the receipt of this item, new correspondence on this subject has been received.  I can confirm that the IBOA has written to the joint committee notifying that it is withdrawing its original request.  In that context, is it agreed that the issue deserves no further consideration as its request has been withdrawn?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2013032800003#B00300"><p>I understood it was deferring it pending discussions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2013032800003#B00400"><p>The correspondence is fairly clear.  The IBOA is withdrawing its request to appear before the committee.  If it wishes to write to us again seeking to appear before the committee it can do so.  I will read the letter.<blockquote><br /><br />  Re - IBOA The Finance Union.<br /><br />  Dear Mr. Lynch,<br /><br />  I refer to our previous correspondence and request to address the Finance Committee.  I wish to withdraw that request on the basis that the Liquidator is now engaging with us more regularly and a number of developments have occurred since our initial request that have provided some clarity to staff. I wish to thank the Deputies who supported our request and who have raised the many issues facing IBRC staff in this forum.  We will continue to work to ensure the Minister addresses these issues to the satisfaction of members.<br /><br />  Yours sincerely, ...</blockquote>The request is withdrawn.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.82" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2013032800003#B00650">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FIJ2013032800003#B00725"><p>Item No. 9 is decisions taken at the Joint Sub-Committee on EU Scrutiny on 13 March 2013, for noting on the public record.  Under the terms of reference which established the sub-committee on EU scrutiny, that sub-committee is required to report to the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform at regular intervals.  The clerk has circulated to members a report of the sub-committee meeting of 13 March 2013 which details the recommendations of the sub-committee as follows.  It is recommended that COM (2012) 280 be scrutinised.  This is a proposal for a directive of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing a framework for the recovery and resolution of credit institutions and investment firms and amending Council directives 77/91/EEC and 82/891/EC, directives 2001/24/EC, 2002/47/EC, 2004/25/EC, 2005/56/EC, 2007/36/EC and 2011/35/EC and regulation (EU) No. 1093/2010.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  It is recommended that COM (2012) 724, COM (2012) 754, COM (2012) 755 and COM (2013) 8 do not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  It is recommended that COM (2012) 377, COM (2012) 475, COM (2012) 654, COM (2012) 661, COM (2012) 677 and COM (2012) 792 be noted as adopted.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  Is it agreed that the report be published on the committee's homepage?  Agreed.</p><p>  As there is no other business I shall adjourn the meeting.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.85" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Health and Children</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.86" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.89" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800003#B00100">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800003#B00200"><p>The committee is now in public session.  We will consider COM (2012) 541, proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on <i>in vitro</i> diagnostic medical devices and COM (2012) 542, proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on medical devices, amending Directive 2001/83/EC, Regulation (EC) No 178/2002 and Regulation (EC) No 1223/2009.</p><p>  Having reviewed the correspondence from the stakeholders, I also propose that the committee request that the Department of Health and Children and the Irish Medicines Board attend a meeting of the committee to answer any questions members may have on the proposals I have outlined and to update the committee on the previous discussions we have had as a committee on PIP implants and DePuy hip replacements.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  We have received apologies this morning from Deputies Ciara Conway, Eamonn Maloney and Regina Doherty.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.91" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800003#B00300">State Dental Schemes: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800003#B00400"><p>I welcome Mr. Fintan Hourihan, chief executive of the Irish Dental Association, Ms Clare Dowling, employment and communications officer of the Irish Dental Association, Dr. Andrew Bolas, president of the Irish Dental Association, and Dr. Peter Gannon, chairman of the general practitioners' committee of the Irish Dental Association.  I thank them for coming to our meeting this morning.  We are glad that they were able to come in at such short notice and we appreciate their rearranging schedules to be here.</p><p>  I remind members and those in the public gallery to switch off their mobile telephones rather than leaving them in silent mode because they interfere with broadcasting equipment and it is not fair to members of staff who have to put up with the interference in their headsets.</p><p>  Our discussion this morning arises from a request from the Irish Dental Association to come before the committee.  In correspondence with the committee the association has stated that it is worried and increasingly concerned about gum disease, loose teeth and extractions where it has not been possible to provide preventative treatments given the recent withdrawal of State support for patients.  I thank Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in for making this proposal at our meeting last week.</p><p>  Before we commence I wish to remind members and witnesses that witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if a witness is directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in regard to a particular matter and continues to do so, the witness is entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of his evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing ruling of the Chair to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>  I call on Mr. Hourihan to make his opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.93" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800003#B00500"><p>I thank the Chairman and the committee for inviting us here.  We are delighted to have the opportunity to address the committee.  We have prepared a submission, which I believe has been circulated.  I intend to speak only on parts of the submission, but we felt that as we had an opportunity to come before the committee we could in the submission address other issues about which questions are often asked.  I intend to speak primarily about the State schemes and the services that the HSE provides for children.</p><p>  In our executive summary we explain the critical importance of oral health and its connection to general health and summarise our main recommendations.  I will start by reminding everyone that there are two State-funded schemes: the PRSI scheme - the dental treatment benefit scheme, as it is formally known - and the medical card scheme, the DTSS.  Approximately 2 million taxpayers are entitled to benefit from the PRSI scheme funded by the social insurance fund.  Since the budget of December 2009 the scheme has provided only one item of dental care, which is the annual oral examination.  Prior to that - we will elaborate on this later - there was an extensive range of routine preventative and restorative treatments provided free or subsidised by the State.  That has all been withdrawn.</p><p>  In the case of the medical card scheme, the eligibility for medical card holders is increasing.  In the December 2009 budget it was decided for the first time to cap the level of spending on the scheme.  Similarly to the PRSI scheme - again, we will elaborate on this later - there was an extensive range of routine preventative and restorative treatments provided free to patients.  That has been severely curtailed.  It is now effectively an emergency pain relief scheme only.  We feel that is causing profound difficulties for a very vulnerable cohort of patients, because oral health is a condition that is inextricably linked to social status.</p><p>  I will talk about the difficulties in the public dental service later, but I wish first to make a point about dental care which we feel is often not properly understood.  Dentists form one of the few groups of health professionals who do not receive any financial support from the State.  They rely entirely on their own funds to set up in practice and to meet their running costs.  Whereas the State spends &euro;3.6 billion annually staffing and equipping hospital medicine, there is no comparable assistance provided for dental care in the community.  Likewise, before a penny is spent on caring for medical card patients, GMS doctors in general practice can receive up to &euro;100,000 per annum in grants towards employing nurses, secretaries and practice managers in rural locations, and there are pension payments available to doctors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800005#D00200"><p>I thank Mr. Hourihan for the presentation.  We hope that members of the association will feel free to interact with committee members.  In the absence of Fianna F&aacute;il Deputies, Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in can take the lead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800005#D00300"><p>I join with the Chairman in welcoming all our guests this morning.  Neither Mr. Hourihan nor I expected we would meet so soon when I made the proposition to accommodate a meeting at the earliest opportunity.  I say "Well done" for stepping into the gap that opened up.</p><p>  I have been exposed, particularly in recent years, to much of what Mr. Hourihan outlined this morning in terms of the impact on ordinary people.  I am particularly concerned at the impact on young children whose lives are being blighted.  It is only a number of weeks ago that I took the opportunity to meet with a senior colleague in Mr. Hourihan&rsquo;s association in my constituency, with whom I have a respectful relationship, to discuss some of these matters.  When Mr. Hourihan&rsquo;s letter arrived it made every sense to follow through.</p><p>  As I acknowledged last week, what I am exposed to is not unique.  All Deputies and Senators recognise what Mr. Hourihan outlined.  It is very depressing.  I welcome the fact that he outlined a number of practical solutions.  They will certainly not be a panacea but they could be pursued to address the difficulties that currently prevail.  I refer in particular to proposed solutions Nos. 1 to 5 on pages 19 and 20.  I propose that the committee forward them and commend them for consideration to the Minister.  I put on record that logic dictates that we follow through on this excellent opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/960" speakername="S&eacute;amus Healy" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800006#E00200"><p>I welcome our visitors and thank Mr. Hourihan for his detailed presentation, which highlighted some of the difficulties and indicated solutions that the Irish Dental Association would favour.  The presentation was very helpful in that regard.</p><p>  The presentation details effectively with what amounts to the destruction of the two dental schemes in recent years.  That was short-sighted, because the curtailment of these schemes affects the most disadvantaged sections of society, and it is necessary to ensure these schemes or improved schemes are put in place as soon as possible.</p><p>  Clients come into my clinics to deal with three different areas, the first of which is the question of children being seen in the public service and, as Mr. Hourihan stated, being seen possibly only once very late in primary school or, in some cases, not seen at all.  Another area is orthodontic treatment for children, specifically the narrow guidelines indicating whether a child is approved for orthodontic treatment and the huge cost of orthodontic treatment.  The third area is the question of emergency attendance, whether at public or private dental services.  It is difficult for members of the public, or myself, to understand what is or is not an emergency.  One of the witnesses might indicate what would be considered an emergency.</p><p>  The point made in the submission that there is no chief dental officer in the Department is important.  On the question of consultation, negotiation and interaction with the Department, Mr. Hourihan stated that the initial contact regarding the schemes was as far back as January 2012.  Has there been any contact, negotiation or consultation since then with the association regarding the replacement of these schemes or issues such as the appointment of a chief dental officer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800006#E00300"><p>I will not repeat the issues raised but I want to echo the concerns raised by the previous speakers.  I thank the witnesses for their presentation and the way they have laid it out in examining the challenges, but also for coming up with possible solutions.  In the context of the position we are in currently, they have put forward realistic proposals.</p><p>  I want to focus on a number of areas.  First, oral cancer is not spoken about to a major extent and because it is not usually visible to most of us, it is only when someone attends a dentist that it is identified.  Have the witnesses seen an increase in the incidence of oral cancer or an increase in the number of people being diagnosed later?  What is the impact of that on their treatment and outcomes?</p><p>  Regarding the schools programme and school screening, we have particular problems in the west.  In Galway the issue has been long-fingered, and the position is not much better in Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800007#F00200"><p>I thank Mr. Hourihan for his very comprehensive presentation.  I want to touch on one or two points.  Was there a dental officer in the Department of Health previously?  How long is it since that individual has gone?</p><p>  With regard to being financially innovative given the current budgetary constraints, a colleague of Mr. Hourihan&rsquo;s was in contact with me recently to outline the system being introduced in the United States, which does not necessarily require the presence of a dentist.  A dental nurse is in attendance and scanning and cloud computing are used, with the data being transmitted to a centre to be reviewed by qualified dental practitioners, who can then identify which cases need to be followed up.  It is about the effective use of money.  The person who was in contact with me goes to nursing homes rather than having residents in those homes come to the dental surgery.  Thus, dental care can be provided within nursing homes.  This is a time in which we need to be innovative and determine how to obtain value for money while at the same time providing a comprehensive service.  We must ensure dental practitioners are remunerated adequately for the work they are doing.</p><p>  I do not know whether we have done much work on education on dental care.  It does not appear to be a priority within the Department.  If there is no dental expert within the Department, the whole education programme automatically falls down.  Perhaps the delegates could comment on the position on education and how Ireland compares with other EU countries, the United States and other countries within the OECD.  Although we talk about education in regard to health issues, I am not sure whether we do so in regard to dental issues.  How far behind other countries are we?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800007#F00300"><p>I thank Mr. Hourihan for his very comprehensive presentation.</p><p>  I have two questions, one of which is on the voucher system.  Will Mr. Hourihan elaborate on it?  Could he also elaborate on value for money?  It is well known that it is much cheaper to avail of dental health services in Northern Ireland, England and the rest of Europe than it is here.  Can better value for money be provided here?  We all acknowledge the country is in recession and that it is difficult to fund various services.  I refer to ordinary dental services.   Orthodontic treatment in this State is extraordinarily expensive.  The cost is almost double or treble that in other countries.  Could Mr. Hourihan comment on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800007#F00400"><p>Deputies &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in and Mitchell O'Connor must go to the D&aacute;il.  Mr. Hourihan may answer their questions first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.105" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800007#F00500"><p>With regard to orthodontic treatment in the north east, I can only guess that the issue is related directly to the lack of dental staff.  As the Deputy will be well aware, there has been a severe shortage of dentists in Cavan-Monaghan, of all places, irrespective of whether children require general or orthodontic treatment.  I can only guess that this is reflected in the waiting list.</p><p>  I will ask my colleague, Dr. Bolas, to respond to queries on the threshold and the criteria for orthodontic care.</p><p>  With regard to clinical dental technicians, ours is not the regulatory body.  The Dental Council is a separate entity so we do not have a role in regulating the profession.  However, as an association, we fully support the registration of clinical dental technicians.  We fully support the fact that they are engaged by the HSE and others.  We, too, are concerned about technicians who do not have the necessary formal training.  It is acquired at the expense of the individuals concerned, who must travel to Canada and elsewhere to obtain it.  We share concerns that the system is not properly regulated.  We hope there will be regulation and that increased enforcement powers will be given to the Dental Council as part of the new dental legislation, on which we expect consultation to begin very shortly.</p><p>  With regard to the administration of the DTSS, we felt we could have spent a lot of time talking about the matter.  General practitioners are experiencing considerable difficulties.  Circumstances vary widely throughout the country.  Essentially, this reflects the lack of resources in the public service to handle the correspondence from dentists.  It also reflects the fact that there is now a budget ceiling for care provided to medical card patients.  The HSE officials are told they can spend only so much so they must spend time exercising discretion in dealing with requests for care and treatment.  The service is now an emergency service, essentially, and consequently some time is spent on deciding what constitutes an emergency.  Deputy Healy asked whether there is a general definition in this regard.  I am not sure that there is.  A dentist may comment on that.</p><p>  With regard to Deputy Mitchell O'Connor's comments on the voucher system, such a system has been introduced in other countries.  Very often, people feel that if something is available free of charge, it is not availed of.  Currently, under the medical card system and the PRSI arrangement, eight out of ten adults are entitled to a free checkup, yet fewer than a quarter actually avail of it.  If people had an actual voucher, they might be more inclined to avail of the service.  It would be easier to administer from the State's point of view and would be more cost-effective.  It would not necessarily mean more expenditure, but we feel the current system, under which people have entitlements that they are not choosing to avail of, is not doing their-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00200"><p>Is there a reason they are not availing of it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.107" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00300"><p>No.  There is no obvious reason other than probably that they are not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00400"><p>Aware of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00500"><p>Part of the reason, since the cutbacks, may be that they are concerned that if they go along they will be told that it will require treatment and they simply do not have the funds to meet the cost of the treatment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00600"><p>How would Mr. Hourihan envisage the voucher system operating?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.111" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00700"><p>Everyone would have an entitlement to a voucher and would physically receive one.  We think it would be seen as a service that they have paid for in the case of PRSI employees and for which, in the case of medical card holders, they have an entitlement.  They would be encouraged to visit their dentist.  It would also have some benefits in terms of the administration of the system.  Other countries have introduced these types of systems.</p><p>  As regards value for money, the reason I spent so much time explaining the fact that there is no State support for dental care and that it must meet its costs fully by generating income, is because there is a perception that dental care is expensive.  It is expensive all over the world.  It is one of the most expensive areas of medical care and treatment.  I would not accept that there are significant differences, although there can be between individuals.  Very often, however, people will get a quotation in one jurisdiction and assume that it will cost the same or far more here, even though they may not necessarily have been to a dentist to get a quotation here.  Even where there are differences, however, it simply reflects the cost of running a practice and the absence of State support.</p><p>  We would tell people that, by all means, if they want to go abroad that is their prerogative but they should at least visit their local dentist first.  From a value-for-money perspective, it is a short-sighted approach when somebody travels far away for treatment because if there are remedial or aftercare issues, they may find that it is far more expensive in the long run.  We have plenty of experience of dentists close to the Border here who say that some of the fees they charge are lower than costs in Northern Ireland.  That also reflects currency exchange rates.  Dr. Gannon might wish to comment on this.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.112" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Gannon" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00800"><p>Can I interrupt just to address the question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G00900"><p>I was talking about Newry, which is where patients have told me they are going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.114" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Gannon" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01000"><p>That is true.  I have been working as a dentist for about 15 years.  When I started working there was a big cost difference between dental treatment North and South.  That gap is very close now, however, and there is very little difference.  In fact, a recent survey I saw in a national newspaper looked at four practices in the North and four in the South to compare prices.  The cheapest one was in Dublin.</p><p>  If one looks at the supports that a general dentist will get in the North in contrast to what I would get here, they do not pay commercial rates and their clinical waste is taken away.  There are allowances for maternity leave and education, and there is locum cover if a dentist is not in the practice.  Naturally, it will be more expensive for me to provide that care, so what I charge is based on how much it costs me to provide that care.</p><p>  Looking across Europe and the world generally, there are huge differences in dental treatment costs.  I have Irish patients who are now living in Canada or Australia and when they are home on holidays they come to me because I am much cheaper.  Two weeks ago, a young man visited my practice from Norway.  He reckoned that the price he paid me for a filling was about half what he would pay in Norway, so one will get that range of prices.</p><p>  Where it is cheaper to provide dental treatment, the costs will be cheaper but the difference between North and South is a good deal less than it used to be.  When people take the opportunity to compare different dentists' prices, they will find a lot more value within the Republic of Ireland than they used to in the past.    </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01100"><p>On a slightly different note, patients have said to me that dental practices are only open during working hours.  Is there any way that their opening hours could be extended to help working people?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01200"><p>In fairness, they are open in Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01300"><p>They are not in certain parts of Dublin where these people have complained to me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.118" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Gannon" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01400"><p>It is quite common for dental surgeries to open in the evenings and on Saturdays.  It would be unusual for them not to do so.  As regards emergencies, I have a mobile phone in my pocket 365 days a year so people can contact me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01500"><p>Is that in Sligo?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Gannon" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01600"><p>Galway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01700"><p>It is a service in Galway.  Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.122" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Gannon" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01800"><p>There is a good train service and a road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G01900"><p>Good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G02000"><p>Does Mr. Hourihan want to go back to the other questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G02100"><p>I was at my dentist at 8 a.m. this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G02200"><p>It is great if Senator Burke can get that service in Cork, but the patients complained to me that they cannot access it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G02300"><p>There were a couple of questions on the eligibility criteria for orthodontic care, and comments about the 13-year threshold.  My colleague, Dr. Bolas, works in the public service so I will ask him to address those queries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.128" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Andrew Bolas" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800008#G02400"><p>The committee will note that the table on page 19 lists two categories: grade 5 and grade 4.  This is a historic way of assessing who needs orthodontic treatment.  It is based on a UK guideline called the index of orthodontic treatment need.  Those in category 5 are usually people who need surgical intervention where they have unerupted teeth or may have a cleft pallet or cleft lip.  These are the extreme cases that need not just an orthodontist but also other inputs from an oral surgeon, such as myself.</p><p>  Those in category 4 are what we would call - if I can use a layman's term - people with buck-teeth or crooked teeth.  These people have a functional need for treatment.  Within the grading system, a number of years ago everybody in category 5 and category 4 received treatment.  The problem, however, was that huge numbers qualified for waiting lists.  Therefore, the Department decided that only certain sub-categories in category 4 would qualify.  People with crooked teeth had to have a very unpleasant condition before they would get past the goalposts.  </p><p>  Many of the statistics for the number of patients on waiting lists, even from anecdotal evidence of working in the HSE, are not strictly accurate.  In the midlands area it is 175, for example, but the consultant orthodontist for the midlands moved to Cork in the middle of this period, so people were not being put on the waiting list.</p><p>  I work in the Sligo-Leitrim region where we hold assessment days when we bring in 150 children on a single day.  The consultant orthodontist will examine each child and decide who qualifies and who does not.  We try to work on the principle that people are not waiting to see the orthodontist to go on another waiting list.  It is much better to do it <i>en masse</i> and get them assessed, so they know whether or not they qualify.  That gives patients the opportunity, if they can afford it, to seek private treatment if they do not qualify.  It also gives a consultant the opportunity to tell us that a patient does not need to go on the waiting list, but that we could do the following treatment which would have a good result.  We do a lot of interceptive orthodontics, taking out teeth to allow other teeth to grow.  </p><p>  As regards many waiting lists, there may be a consultant but he does not have any specialists working under him.  There is an artificially large waiting list due to the manpower issue.  The consultant is dealing with category 5 patients, while category 4 people are put on the long finger.  As Deputy Naughten said, that was the case for a long time in Galway where there was no consultant.  The specialists with orthodontic qualifications will not necessarily tackle cleft lips and cleft pallets, but they will deal with category 4 patients which is their bread and butter, so to speak.</p><p>  I suppose the solution would be to have more orthodontic centres around the country with a consultant here and a consultant there.  For instance, in Sligo we share a consultant with Donegal, so we only have him three days a week and he is gone for the other two days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800009#H00200"><p>Does that refer to the dentist or the orthodontist?  Surely, parents know without having to go to the dentist that providing Ribena or sugar in the doses we are talking about will lead to tooth decay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Andrew Bolas" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800009#H00300"><p>It should be out there in other forums also.  The public health nurse should deliver the message too but the best-placed person is a dentist, who can give the example.  When the first cavity appears, the dentist can say to the mother, "Let me show you what has happened".  Parents will often come in and say their children were born with weak teeth, when it was the bottle they went to bed with every night that was the problem.  Parents do not understand, and the dentist becomes the bad guy for saying it is the parents' fault, not the child's.  The child did nothing to progress the decay; it was what the parents were doing.  We need an investment in the current generation to obtain a benefit for the next.  That is the way forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800009#H00400"><p>Dr. Bolas instanced young males, but I am thinking of young females who are called "Nanny McPhee" at age 11 because of an abnormality.  It is a label that will never be erased.  It is something that requires earlier intervention.  Whatever Dr. Bolas can do to encourage that earliest support saves a child or a young adult's life.</p><p>  This has been a very interesting presentation, and I sincerely thank the witnesses for their work in preparing it.  I commend the recommendations and ask that we forward them for the Minister's attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800009#H00500"><p>I want to bring in Deputies Dowds, Catherine Byrne and McLellan, in that order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1011" speakername="Robert Dowds" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800009#H00600"><p>I thank the witnesses for coming here today.  Some of the questions I was going to ask have been asked, so I will not repeat them.</p><p>  As I expected, the witnesses painted a very bleak picture.  I agree with Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in on forwarding the recommendations to the Minister in the hope that he can respond, notwithstanding the fact that there is a &euro;12 billion overspend this year despite the progress we have made in tackling our economic problems.  Is there any way to construct an argument to say that if a certain amount were spent on dentistry for children, it would save the State money because there would be less intervention at a later stage?  That is the sort of argument that must be put forward to win at the moment.  I had intended to ask the question Deputy Mitchell O'Connor asked on the difference between costs in Ireland and those abroad, but the witnesses have addressed the issue.  Scaling and polishing were mentioned.  How much would it cost to reintroduce them in the schemes referred to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800010#J00200"><p>I acknowledge the good work done on the ground by many dentists in local and primary care health centres.  The availability of dental treatment at primary care centres has made a difference for young children.  I agree with all that has been said about orthodontic services.  In 1999 when I first entered politics, I was on the former Eastern Regional Health Authority when the waiting list time for orthodontic treatment was six and a half years.  We have come some way but I am still concerned about waiting lists.  Some children look different to other children in the classroom because of their teeth and, accordingly, it can affect them.  The waiting time for treatment should be only a few months.</p><p>  Hygiene begins at home and parents are the sole educators in this regard.  I agree it is lacking in some households.  My granddaughter who is two and a half brushes her teeth after she gets dressed every morning simply because she sees her mother doing it.  As Dr. Bolas said, what parents do will be followed by their children.  I do acknowledge that in poorer areas where people have less money there are problems.</p><p>  I was not aware of the oral cancer awareness day.  I have met several people in my area who had oral cancer and the disfiguration of their faces is shocking.  Are more men affected than women and what age group is affected?  How many children coming from schools actually attend their appointments?  When I was bringing my children up, I always put a reminder for the date for a dentist appointment in a prominent place.  I am concerned, however, that many parents miss their children's appointments.  How much does a dentist receive for a check-up for a primary schoolchild?  Is there a set fee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/981" speakername="Sandra McLellan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800010#J00300"><p>I thank the delegation for its informative presentation which highlighted many problems but also offered solutions.</p><p>  The report highlights sixth-class primary schoolchildren are often called for dental appointments only when they are in secondary school.  I know that was the case with my daughter who was in first year in secondary school when she was called for an appointment.  Should the Government take emergency measures to rectify this matter?  The criteria for qualifying for orthodontic treatment are very strict.  Accordingly, many 13 year olds who need treatment do not meet the criteria and have to attend private practices.  Most parents cannot afford the enormous costs that go with the treatment and have to go on a waiting list.  I know of cases where children are not called until they are 18.  The voucher system suggested is well worth exploring.  People with special needs also have to endure long waiting lists before they receive dental treatment.</p><p>  The delegation said it was involved in talks about reform of the public dental service.  Can it elaborate on this?  Its report stated oral health care is now almost privatised.  What would be the best practice model of an efficient and functioning public dental service?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800010#J00400"><p>How does Ireland compare with the number of dentists per head of population internationally?  In every medical specialty we are so ludicrously low we are off the scale.  What are the UK and continental averages for dentist per head of population?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Andrew Bolas" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800010#J00500"><p>We average one dentist per 2,200 people while the UK averages one dentist per 1,700 and in Scandinavian countries, it is one dentist for every 1,100.  We are probably the worst in Europe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800010#J00600"><p>One will find we are the worst among OECD countries because we are for everything else in medicine.  It is all down to successive Governments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Andrew Bolas" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800010#J00700"><p>My suspicion is that the incidence of oral cancer is increasing on a slow but steady basis.  The confounding factors are alcohol consumption and smoking.  I have noticed the patients referred to me are getting younger.  The most recent case I saw a fortnight ago was a young girl 32 years of age.  The beauty of oral cancer, so to speak, is that if it is caught early, the treatment can be done under local anaesthetic and is an excision of the area involved with dissolving stitches.  However, once it gets to an advanced stage where one needs to borrow skin from other parts of the body or ribs or arms to replace bones, it becomes very disfiguring.  When it gets to that stage, the first thing we examine is the patient's face.  There is a social stigma almost attached to it.</p><p>  People are presenting earlier with it.  I have to give the credit for that to the Irish Dental Association and the Irish Cancer Society with its oral cancer awareness days.  Also, with celebrities having it, some even dying of it, people have become more aware of it.  Our biggest problem with the awareness day is that it is not supported by the Health Service Executive, HSE, or the Department of Health.  It is purely down to the goodwill of the dentists doing it.  We need to examine this because the incidence rates are comparable to other forms of cancer which get more air time.</p><p>  School screening depends on the area.  Geography dictates health care.  In some areas, they attend the schools to examine the children in the class.  Time wise that is probably the most effective way because then one knows who to call back to the clinic for treatment.  The problem is that not everywhere has enough staff to go out to the schools so they have to call them to the clinics which takes longer.  It means the children have to be brought out of school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Peter Gannon" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00200"><p>Various types of model exist.  We tend to look to Europe in the main because it seems to provide the best access to the most people.  Generally the European model provides state support for those who need it and people pay more of the cost of their dental care as their means allow.  This is backed up by a public dental service that tends to look after certain age groups, such as children, and special needs groups.</p><p>  We operated a similar system in Ireland until the cuts were introduced several years ago.  I have found that many people tend to come to my practice less often now that the supports are no longer being offered.  The schemes that were formerly in place focused on fairly simple preventive treatments, such as cleaning teeth and fillings.  Despite all the talk of complicated dental treatments, implants and root canal treatments, these aforementioned treatments comprise more than 95% of my work.  I know the patients who take fantastic care of their teeth and young people and teenagers will never need complicated or expensive treatment.  That is where people are saving money.  By offering regular simple treatments we can send a personal message to people in terms of showing them where they may be missing out in cleaning their teeth and pointing out their particular problems.  They are more likely to take on board a personal message than the general message about not eating sweets and brushing teeth.  </p><p>  In regard to the cost of reintroducing scaling and polishing, the cost for the last year in which these treatments were allowed under the general medical card scheme was in the region of &euro;5 million.  That is the most simple preventive treatment we carry out but it makes a big difference to individuals' gum health in the long term.  The prevention of gum disease leads to fewer extractions and dentures down the line.  People are inclined to attend for such treatments because they do not mind getting their teeth cleaned, which allows us to impart a personal message.  If they come regularly they are more inclined to take better care of their teeth.  If they know they are going to see the dentist in a month's time they are inclined to clean their teeth properly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.144" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00300"><p>As regards the chief dental officer, there has not been a substantive post holder since 1994.  It is an appalling indictment that it has been vacant for almost 20 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00400"><p>What would be the benefit of filling that position now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00500"><p>The post holder would give strategic direction and advice to the Minister on the best deployment of resources and offer advice on emerging scientific developments.  A dentist is appointed to look after the HSE and the public service component but that is a limited cohort of the overall population.  In the same way as there is a chief medical officer, a chief dental officer is also required.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00600"><p>How has Mr. Hourihan's organisation allowed the situation to continue without the post being filled?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.148" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00700"><p>We have protested for all of those 20 years.  As the individual would be an employee of the Department of Health, the Department has chosen not to fill the vacancy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00800"><p>What reason did it give?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.150" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K00900"><p>It has stated simply that it must cut numbers.  We argue that the savings for the system and the benefits for patients would be far greater than the cost of employing a chief dental officer.  It is embarrassing when we go to international meetings to admit that Ireland is the only country without a chief dental officer.  There is no justification for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K01000"><p>I suggest that the committee write to the Department of Health to seek an update.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.152" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K01100"><p>We would greatly appreciate that.  We wrote to the Minister of Health about the DTSS in 2012 but unfortunately there has been no engagement.  As with other contracts and schemes, the Department is hiding behind competition law even though the last Attorney General stated there is no reason the Department cannot negotiate with representative bodies.  We would like that to happen sooner rather than later.</p><p>  Dentists are obliged to display their fees.  The association actively supports and promotes this practice and surveys have shown that fees are displayed in 98% or 99% of cases.</p><p>  A question was asked about fees paid for seeing primary school children.  Obviously there is no fee if they are seen by the HSE but the Deputy may have been asking about private visits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/981" speakername="Sandra McLellan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K01200"><p>If they do not meet the criteria they are referred for orthodontic treatment and parents cannot afford the fees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.154" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Hourihan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800011#K01300"><p>The fees are usually four figure sums.  Prioritisation is already being done on the basis of what could best be described as rationing because of the drastic cuts in the public service.  It is difficult to see how any further prioritisation can take place without some relaxation of the moratorium.</p><p>  The backdrop to the reform of the HSE public dental service was that the HSE commissioned a firm of management consultants to examine how the service was structured.  It was previously structured on the basis of what were the 32 community care areas in the days of the health boards.  The ensuing report suggested that certain services be consolidated or amalgamated and that a national oral health office be established within the HSE.  This has happened and we participated in the process.  Dentists have taken on a lot of extra work without additional remuneration.  One of the key components of the report was the recommendation that the moratorium on recruitment be lifted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00200"><p>Could I ask about fluoridation in water?  We have been getting many e-mails about it.  Could Dr. Bolas comment on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.157" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Andrew Bolas" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00300"><p>There is certainly a lot of media interest in it at the moment.  One must really look at the scientific evidence available.  The level at which we fluoridate our water supply is perfectly safe.  None of the studies identify any of the diseases many of the campaigners identify as being the reality.  Why is it so good?  As a dentist, I would say the difference it makes to the prevention of cavities in teeth is huge.  I qualified in Belfast and worked in the hospital for sick children there.  It is a non-fluoridated area and routinely, we would have had 26 children on a theatre list to get teeth out.  That was on a weekly basis.  In Sligo, where I now work - a fluoridated area - we see six children per week to get teeth out.  The benefits from the point of view of dental health are marked.  A recent study showed that 15 year olds in County Donegal had 70% fewer cavities than 15 year olds in County Derry, just across the Border.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00400"><p>Is that linked directly to fluoridation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.159" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Andrew Bolas" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00500"><p>Donegal is a fluoridated area but Derry is not.  The sample was chosen to try to equalise social class and so on.  It is a very cost-effective method of preventing treatment.  I dread to think what the state of our children's teeth would be like if we did not have it.  Areas in the UK where one can match social class, economics and so on show marked increases in dental decay.  As a consequence of that, one may need to use general anaesthetics to remove teeth from children, and there is no such thing as a safe anaesthetic.  One is putting the child at risk to solve a problem that could have been prevented.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/960" speakername="S&eacute;amus Healy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00600"><p>I thank the witnesses for their interesting and informative presentation.  I support the referral of pages 19 and 20 to the Department, as well as the question of the chief dental officer.  Perhaps we should include the dental area in the joint committee's work programme in the future, because it is an area that tends to be forgotten.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00700"><p>That is a fair point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/960" speakername="S&eacute;amus Healy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00800"><p>On a lighter note, Dr. Bolas used a term I had never heard before, namely, "children born with weak teeth".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-03-28a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2013032800012#L00900"><p>Is it agreed that we send the proposed solutions as part of the document to the Department and that we write to it about the vacant position?  We will put this on the work programme after Easter in the context of getting a response from the Department to today's presentation.</p><p>  I thank the witnesses and Ms Elaine Hughes, the assistant chief executive, who is in the Visitors' Gallery, for coming in.  I also thank them for their ongoing communication and for raising the issues with us.  It has been a valuable learning exercise.  We appreciate the work they do in their practices around the country.  Some members raised questions about hours of operation.  I know quite a number of dentists in my area in Cork and they are very much patient-focused.  They have emergency numbers on their answering machines and I had to use one last weekend.  To be fair, the dentist was available if I needed him.  Dentists place their patients at the heart of what they do.  Again, I thank the witnesses for coming in.</p><p>  I remind Deputy Healy that the select committee will meet at 5 p.m. on Tuesday, 23 April 2013 to deal with the Health Service Executive (Governance) Bill 2012.  We will discuss organ donation at our next meeting.  I wish everyone a happy Easter and ask members not to cause too much harm to their teeth by indulging in too many chocolate Easter eggs.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>