<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="">Seanad Committee on the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 10:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Senator Victor Boyhan,* Senator Gerald Nash, Senator Mark Daly, Senator Catherine Noone,* Senator Alice-Mary Higgins,* Senator Niall Ó Donnghaile, Senator Michael McDowell, Senator James Reilly.*</p><p>* In the absence of Senator Gerard P. Craughwell, Senator Frances Black, Senator Michelle Mulherin and Senator Joe O'Reilly. respectively.</p><p>SENATOR NEALE RICHMOND IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#A00100">Engagement with former Taoiseach, Mr. John Bruton</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Senator Craughwell, who is being substituted by Senator Boyhan, from Senator O'Reilly, who is being substituted by Senator Reilly; and from Senator Mulherin, who is being substituted by Senator Noone.  Senators McDowell and &Oacute; Donnghaile have given notice they will unfortunately be arriving a little late.  I remind members and those in the Gallery to ensure all mobile phones are switched off or put on airplane mode as they interfere with the sound system.</p><p>On behalf of the committee, I warmly welcome Mr. John Bruton to the committee today.  I do not really know where to start in terms of an introduction because it is fair to say that Mr. Bruton is someone who probably does not need and introduction to this particular audience.  As a former Minister, former Taoiseach, former ambassador of the EU to the US and former negotiator of the draft European constitution, he has a depth of knowledge and understanding of the EU and how it works, of interacting with our European partners at different levels, and of the intricacies of the relationship with the United Kingdom.  As a result, he has an understanding of many of the issues at play and the challenges that Brexit presents, which are considerable.  We very much welcome Mr. Bruton's willingness to share his insights and analysis.  A number of us followed his extremely impressive appearance before the House of Lords committee quite recently and we took great solace from it.</p><p>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence relating to a particular matter and they continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of the proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p><p>With all that out of the way, I ask Mr. Bruton to make his opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.6" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Bruton" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#A00300"><p>I welcome the opportunity to speak here today and I commend the committee on its work.  I would also like to commend the Government on the way it has ensured, through effective diplomacy, that the particular problems of Ireland have been publicly recognised in the negotiating positions of both the EU 27 and the United Kingdom.</p> <p>  I will go into some of the difficulties that will arise in the Brexit negotiations.  It is important to say that Brexit is a British initiative, for whose consequences Britain must take primary responsibility.  It was not forced upon them.  In fact, as I will show, numerous concessions have been made by its EU partners to keep the United Kingdom within the EU treaties, which it freely adhered to in 1973 and which its people overwhelmingly endorsed by referendum in 1975.  The context of the Brexit negotiation is changing all the time.  In recent weeks, the EU economy has been improving.  Election results in the Netherlands and France are more positive than many feared.  Even the Trump administration is beginning to see value in doing business with the European Union.  The EU has remained united in its response to Brexit, a matter for which the Irish Government can take particular credit.</p> <p>  While it may seem impossibly naive or optimistic today, I believe conditions can be envisaged in which, eventually, UK voters decide either not to leave the EU at all or, after it has left, to rejoin.  Ireland should try to keep that possibility alive.  The terms for Brexit, as set out so far by Mrs. May, will do incalculable damage to this island, politically, emotionally and economically.  We cannot simply wait for this to happen.  While seeking to mitigate the effects of Mrs. May's chosen hard Brexit, we must also do everything we can to ensure that, at the end of the day, there is no Brexit.</p><p>Apart from a few open questions, Mrs. May has said what she wants.  She wants to be out of the Single Market, to be out of the customs union and have control over immigration<br/><br/>The open questions she has avoided so far are about the financial terms of the divorce, the status of EU citizens living in the UK and <i>vice versa</i>, and two aspects of a future trade agreement, if there ever is one, namely, arbitrating disputes and third-country imports getting into the EU via the UK.  The Article 50 letter, sent to Donald Tusk, did not tell us much more about the UK negotiating position than the Lancaster House speech did, although it does not repeat the pledge to leave the customs union.<br/><br/>How the EU will respond to Mrs. May's letter?  The European Council is meeting this week to agree the orientation it will give to the EU negotiators for the discussions with the UK that will start formally in June and in earnest after a new German government is formed in September.  As these orientations will be agreed by consensus, each EU Head of Government will have to be satisfied.  In working out the orientation to be given to the negotiators, it will be crucial for the European Council to have in mind its best alternative to a negotiated agreement - BATNA for short.  It is important to have such an alternative ready because there is every possibility that no agreement will be reached within the two-year timeframe for negotiation and ratification of a withdrawal agreement.<br/><br/>Mrs. May has said that, for her, no deal at all preferable to a bad deal.  Her BATNA, so to speak, is no deal at all.  No deal would mean the UK simply crashing out of the EU overnight, sometime before the end of March 2019.  This no-deal scenario could lead to an overnight halt to flights, to trade and to commerce.  There would be immediate, massive currency instability.  As pure negotiating tactics, maybe it not surprising that Mrs. May would pretend that no deal would be better than what she would call a bad deal but she is hardly serious.  No deal is something the UK simply cannot afford.  This no-deal scenario put forward by Mrs. May will, I expect, be probed during the UK election campaign to discover what it actually means.  The fact that it was put forward by the Prime Minister vindicates Tony Blair's description of the UK Government, at the time of the Lancaster House speech, as not driving the Brexit bus, but rather being driven by partisan and ideological forces it had not tried to control.<br/><br/>The EU country that would be worst affected by the UK crashing out of the EU with no deal would, of course, be Ireland.  Ireland, along with its EU partners, must use all its imagination and ingenuity to ensure that a better alternative to no deal is available in the event of a deal not being agreed.<br/><br/>If, because of domestic politics, the UK Government is unable or unwilling to work out a responsible best available alternative to a negotiated agreement, BATNA, then the EU side should do so for it.  It should adopt it, alongside its line-by-line response the UK's negotiating demands its own best alternative to a negotiated agreement.  Having such a BATNA would also strengthen the EU's negotiating position.  It would provide something with which an emerging deal could be compared.  It would also provide a basis on which the UK electorate could reconsider its decision of 23 June 2016, if it ever wants to do that.<br/><br/>As Tony Blair said, UK voters have a right to change their minds.  After all, politicians are allowed to change their minds, so why not voters?  If it was the UK voters who, in a referendum, sent their government on a mission towards Brexit, it would be reasonable that the same voters, rather than Parliament, should adjudicate on what will or will not have been achieved by their delegates.  However, if UK voters ever do change their minds about Brexit, it will happen slowly and incrementally.<br/><br/>Parts of the Brexit scenario, obscured during the referendum campaign, will become clearer during the negotiation.  The unavoidable interconnections between EU freedoms and EU rules will emerge.  For this to happen, it will be in the EU side's interest to ensure that there is maximum public understanding of the unfolding negotiation at every stage.  Transparency will work in the EU's interest.  A running commentary is exactly what is needed in the interest of public education.  When the UK public comes to see that the alternative to a single set of EU rules is either no rules at all or multiple sets of contradictory rules for different jurisdictions, citizens in both the EU countries and the UK may come see EU membership in a different and better light.  They may, for the first time in many cases, see the EU as something that actually simplifies their lives, rather than the reverse.<br/><br/>In my view, the best available alternative to a negotiated agreement, BATNA, that the EU side should adopt is an offer of continuing UK membership of the EU broadly on the basis that the UK was a member in 2015 before David Cameron's ill-fated renegotiation.  The terms obtaining then were generous to the UK.  They allowed it to opt out of the euro, of Schengen, of justice and policing co-operation, of the Stability and Growth Pact, and of the justiciability in the UK of the European Convention.  Furthermore, the UK itself had also decided, without Brexit, that it would have a referendum of any new EU powers.  In that sense, the UK was already having its cake while eating it before it ever decided on Brexit.  These pre-2015 terms should be left on the table by the EU side but without the unjustifiable UK budget rebate.<br/><br/>The President of the European Parliament, Mr. Tajani, made such an offer when he met the UK Prime Minister recently.  That was a very important initiative and underlined how central the European Parliament will be in this whole process.  Of course, at this stage, the UK would reject such an offer out of hand.  However, as the inevitable consequences of Brexit become clearer, UK public opinion might begin to see merit in it, particularly when it is compared with the costs of simply crashing out of the EU overnight with no deal at all, which is supposedly still Mrs. May's fall-back negotiating scenario as compared with what she calls a bad deal.<br/><br/>The resistance to keeping such an offer on the table is more likely to come from some existing EU member states.  Some of them will point to the UK's insatiable demands when it was a member for opt-outs, rebates and exceptions.  Arlene Foster's analogy about feeding crocodiles may come to their minds if they are well informed about Irish politics.  They will also recall General de Gaulle's original veto of UK membership and his foresight that the UK would never settle in as a member.  They might also argue that offering the UK a way back after it has triggered Article 50 might encourage others to try it on too.<br/><br/>However, if they sit back and think about it, they will, I believe, conclude that a UK inside the EU is better for the EU than a UK outside it even with a trade deal with the EU.  Keeping the offer of resumed UK membership on the table would be good politics and good economics for the EU.<br/><br/>I mention, in passing, that Article 6.8 of the Vienna Convention, which sets out the general international law on treaties, explicitly allows revocation of a notice of intention to withdraw from a treaty.</p><p>A political declaration by the EU Heads of Government at some stage in the coming months, along the lines of what the President of the European Parliament, Mr. Tajani, said, in favour of facilitating an eventual UK resumption of EU membership on its pre-2015 terms minus the budget rebate would create a realistic yardstick against which UK citizens could compare the terms of Brexit as negotiated by their Government at the end of the process.</p><p> I do not propose to go into detail about how the EU side should conduct negotiations with the UK.  Obviously, it will keep the 27 member states informed at every stage.  Ireland will need to ensure that any deal guarantees the UK will not engage in unfair or environmentally harmful trading practices, that there will be no unfair subsidisation of UK enterprises competing with Irish enterprises and that assurances will be received that the EU will take immediate action if either of those things happen.  Ireland will have a special interest in the post-2020 agricultural policies of the UK and in ensuring that they do not introduce production subsidies that disadvantage Irish exporters, that the UK adheres to reasonable climate change emission standards and, further, that it does not permit third country imports that would undermine traditional Irish exports to the UK.  We will need to protect our electricity and energy supplies after the UK has left the EU's common energy policy.  Ireland's network is entangled with the UK's, and it is through the UK that we can access the rest of the EU network.  The EU has agreements on this with other countries, including Switzerland, which, although not EU members, contribute to the EU budget.  The EU will have difficulty offering the UK a better deal than it is giving Switzerland on this or any other matter.</p><p> It is important to remember that Westminster politicians have never taken much interest in how the EU actually works, its procedures and rules and the compromises that underlie its very existence.  They have this in common with many politicians in larger European countries who treat the EU as a sideshow to national politics.  Even though the Conservative Party sponsored the idea of holding a referendum on leaving the EU, it did not give much thought in advance to what leaving the EU might mean in practice.  In a sense, it is now finding out about how the EU works for the first time - just as the UK is leaving it.  Mrs. May's first priority immediately after the referendum was party unity.  This may be why she told the Conservative conference last year that she would go beyond the mere terms of the referendum.  She would not just leave the EU.  She would also refuse to join the European Economic Area, unlike non-EU member Norway.  She would also refuse to join the EU customs union, unlike non-EU member Turkey.  She would reject the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice.  This has kept her party quiet for the time being.  However, now come the actual negotiations.  This is where Mrs. May's rhetoric at the Conservative Party conference meets the reality of a rules-based international trading system.</p><p> In a rules-based international trading system, unpleasant compromises are essential if one is to persuade others to open up their markets to one's exporters, bankers, planes and people.  In a rules-based international trading system, one cannot unilaterally make, amend, interpret and enforce the agreed rules in ways that only suit one's own state.  There must be a common system, which involves some concession of sovereignty.  One often has to accept an external enforcer such as the European Commission or an international court.  This is a concession of sovereignty.  One often has to accept an external body, such as the European Court of Justice or a disputes panel of the WTO, interpreting the meaning of the rules one has agreed.  This is another concession of sovereignty.  This is unacceptable to those who have made a religion of national sovereignty.  It is unacceptable to some of Mrs. May's euro-hostile MPs and some supporters of Donald Trump.</p><p> Some have argued that if Ireland is in the EU and the UK is out of it, a special "bespoke deal" for the island of Ireland, or for the UK and Ireland, could be envisaged.  I do not see how this could work as far as trading standards and tariffs are concerned.  The European Court of Justice, ECJ, would be the final arbiter of Irish standards, while the UK Supreme Court would make the final arbitrations as far as UK and Northern Ireland standards would be concerned - a recipe for divergence.  Ireland would be obliged to collect EU tariffs and enforce EU standards on any goods entering the EU through Ireland, and to do so at the Irish Border, unless we wanted to exclude ourselves from the EU Single Market.  Any precedent established for the UK and Ireland in this matter will be examined by the countries in EFTA and the EEA.  They will want to be sure that their existing deal is better than anything offered to the UK, which has refused to join either EFTA or the EEA.  This will be the case especially if those EFTA and EEA countries are, as they now are, contributing to EU funds on an ongoing basis and the UK is not doing so.</p><p> The EU side in the negotiations will also have to respect the long-standing "Interlaken principles" of 1987 which state that, in negotiating privileged relations with non-EU states, the EU will prioritise integration between its own members over relations with non-members and will safeguard its own decision-making autonomy.  This reference to decision-making autonomy may mean that EU rules and the ECJ must take precedence over decisions by any joint bodies the EU might agree to set up with the UK.</p><p> I have been reading publications of Conservative-supporting think tanks such as the Bruges Group and Leave Means Leave.  They are discovering now how much extra bureaucracy will be involved in the UK decision to leave the EU customs union and the Single Market.  The UK will have to introduce customs controls on the goods bought and sold between the UK and the EU.  This will involve checking where the goods came from, whether they are properly labelled, whether they are safe and whether the tariffs due have been paid on all components included in those goods.  The delays will be substantial - at the Border in Ireland and at ports in the UK, in Ireland and on the Continent.  Customs clearance alone, without tariffs, will add 8% to the cost of goods arriving in the UK by sea from Ireland or the rest of the EU.  At present, 90 million customs declarations must be checked in the UK for goods arriving from outside the EU.  Once the UK leaves the EU customs union, UK customs officials will have to check 390 million documents.</p><p> Some may think the UK could reduce these difficulties by being in the customs union for some goods but not others.  This is impossible under WTO rules.  A customs union restricted to some countries is a departure from the WTO norm of non-discriminatory trade policy among all WTO members, the most-favoured-nation principle.  A customs union is allowed by the WTO rules only if it covers substantially all trade.  If the UK were to seek to have a customs union with the EU on some but not all of its trade, that would breach this rule.  I do not expect, given that the UK will have to try to join the WTO with the agreement of all its existing members, that it will start by breaking the WTO rules.  At least, if it does, it would not be acting wisely.</p><p> Even if the UK eventually decides to stay in the customs union but leaves the Single Market and tariffs no longer have to be collected, the origin of goods will still have to be checked, as will compliance with EU safety and labelling rules.</p><p>This will take a lot of time regardless of whether it is done at the border or in a depot, electronically or on paper.  The cost of doing business will increase, but for no productive or constructive purpose.</p><p> By leaving the EU customs union, the UK will not only exclude itself from duty free access to the EU market, which represents more than 50% of UK trade, but it will also lose the benefit of trade agreements that the EU has negotiated with 60 other countries, which account for a further 17% of UK exports.  For example, since the EU negotiated a trade agreement with Korea ten years ago, UK exports to that country have increased by 110%.  Leaving the EU means giving that up temporarily, perhaps permanently.  There may be opportunities for Ireland to replace some of that UK trade with Korea.  Japan has more investment in the UK than it has in the rest of the EU combined but a great deal of that is there to get access to the Single Market.  Again, this is an opportunity for Ireland.</p><p> Mrs. May is also beginning to discover that her hard line on immigration will have costs.  A total of 20% of employees on UK farms and 29% of employees in UK food processing plants are EU nationals who will lose their right to live and work in the UK.  When the UK tries to negotiate trade deals with countries outside the EU, for example India, it will find that it will face demands for more Indian migration to the UK, as Commissioner Hogan pointed out earlier this week.</p><p> UK airports will find themselves losing business when the UK has to leave the EU open skies agreement with the United States.  More transit traffic will be routed through Dublin in that situation.  The UK will also have to try to join the European common aviation agreement as a separate member if UK-owned airlines are to have the right to fly passengers between EU airports.  Rival airlines anxious for that business will not make it easy for them to join.  A sudden "no deal" Brexit would leave the UK outside the European Aviation Safety Agency's jurisdiction without a ready replacement.</p><p> After Brexit, the UK will have to set up and staff 34 new national regulatory bodies to do work now being done for the UK by EU agencies, from which the UK will have excluded itself because those agencies fall under the jurisdiction of the European Court of Justice, ECJ.  An example of this is EURATOM, a body confined to EU members that regulates nuclear safety, which is not a trivial matter for some of us who have represented the east coast of Ireland.</p><p> UK farmers and food producers will find themselves facing tariffs of 35% on dairy exports, 25% on confectionery and 15% on cereals.  UK lamb production will be hard hit.  These tariffs will have to be collected at the Irish Border and in Irish ports trading with Britain.  This foreseeable consequence will be the direct result of the sovereign UK decision, not any EU position.</p><p> If Mrs. May wants to be able to make deals to extricate herself from some of these bad outcomes, she will need much more negotiating flexibility.  Much will depend on what the Conservative manifesto says.  If it repeats the promise of a low cap on immigration, then Mrs. May will have less negotiating flexibility after the election than she has now.</p><p> Even if the UK decides to stay in the customs union, additional barriers to trade will go up at the Border in Ireland and between Ireland and Britain.  Ireland must use every legal means available to prevent this damage, including making full use of the institutions set up in the Good Friday Agreement, to persuade the UK to continue to adhere fully to EU standards within the UK even after it has left the EU.  For example, were the UK to decide as part of its agenda of taking back control to develop new British standards for packaging, plant safety, pharmaceutical safety or food safety, the disruption to North-South trade and to trade between Ireland and the UK would be immense.  Even slight differences in product or packaging standards can add significantly to costs and can require expensive duplication of testing and production lines.  This will be the case even if there are no tariffs.  Similar regulatory barriers could arise for the provision of services sold between Ireland and the UK.  Increasingly, international trade agreements are about standards rather than tariffs.  As the only EU country with a land border with the UK, keeping harmony between EU and UK standards will be disproportionately important for Ireland.  Since 1973, both parts of the island have been following identical rules interpreted identically by the ECJ.  All of this may change on the day the UK leaves.</p><p> The UK Prime Minister has announced that she will, later this year, introduce what she calls a great repeal Bill to repeal the European Communities Act 1972, under which EU laws automatically apply in the UK and are given primacy over UK law.  This great repeal Bill would come into full force on the day the UK left the EU.  This proposed Bill is misnamed because it will not actually repeal the EU laws, but simply declare these same laws to be sovereign and UK laws, independent of the EU but without altering a single comma.  What happens after that?  The great repeal Bill will go on to provide a mechanism whereby the UK can then quietly repeal or amend these laws one by one without reference to the EU or anyone else.  This will be done by ministerial orders, which cannot be amended and are rarely even debated.  If these orders unilaterally change the standards to be met in the UK market, this could overnight erect a new barrier to trade with Ireland and across the Border.  The same will happen if a UK Supreme Court decision interprets a rule the UK has inherited from the EU in a manner that differs from the interpretation of the same rule by the ECJ.  Overnight, we would have another new trade barrier.</p><p> It will take many years for UK Ministers to go through every inherited EU directive and regulation, every amendment to them and every court judgment interpreting them and then to decide which to keep, amend or replace.  All of that will be done behind closed doors and under pressure from special interests.  It could happen with no discussion with Ireland or other EU countries.  That is the logic of the Brexit rhetoric about taking back control.</p><p> Ms May has promised that this process will be subject to full scrutiny and parliamentary debate, but that seems impractical, given that many EU laws are involved.  Scrutiny and debate, if there is any, will be confined to Westminster.  She said nothing about scrutiny in the Parliament in Edinburgh or in the assemblies in Belfast or Cardiff, let alone any consultation with Dublin.  This problem will get more severe as time goes on and the UK seeks to justify its decision to leave the EU by introducing new rules and regulations of its own.</p><p> The British-Irish Intergovernmental Conference, set up under the Good Friday Agreement, must make this possible divergence a permanent agenda item.  It will have to meet much more often than it now does to keep up with the rapidly moving EU and UK regulatory agenda and to spot divergences that might create new trade barriers.  It will need a substantially enhanced secretariat and, as the initiator of Brexit, the UK Government should make concrete proposals on this.</p><p> Some of the laws being repatriated from the EU by the UK will deal with matters that fall within the competence of the devolved assemblies.  These assemblies would theoretically be able to make new rules of their own that differ from one another, which raises the possibility of new barriers to commerce within the UK itself.  The exact same former EU regulation could be interpreted in one way north of the border and in another way south of it.</p><p> What can do to prevent these disruptive and costly trends?  In my testimony to the House of Lords, I suggested that the proposed great repeal Bill contain a special Ireland clause.  This clause would require any UK Minister or devolved UK assembly that was contemplating making any unilateral amendment to inherited EU-UK law to give public notice of its intention to do so and to consult the Irish Government and the Northern Ireland Assembly.</p><p>Such an Ireland clause should also provide for the monitoring of any divergences between the interpretations by the ECJ and the UK courts.  In this way, one could identify anything that might cause a problem for any part of Ireland or for Anglo-Irish relations.  This would help the work of the British-Irish Intergovernmental Conference, to which I referred earlier.  It would not avoid all the problems that will arise from Brexit, but it should ensure that every step is taken with proper deliberation and foresight and that further damage is not inflicted by accident.<br/><br/>Another aspect of Brexit to which I must refer is its impact on the Good Friday Agreement.  The consent principle in the Good Friday Agreement provides that the constitutional status of Northern Ireland - defined as its status as either part of the UK or part of a united Ireland - could not be altered without the consent of the people of Northern Ireland.  This is not affected by Brexit, but it is arguable that Brexit changes the constitutional status of Northern Ireland in another sense by taking it out of the EU.  This type of constitutional change was not envisaged at the time the agreement was being negotiated.  Had Brexit been on the cards then, I am sure the negotiators would have attempted to deal with this matter in the original agreement.  Brexit will impact living standards in Northern Ireland.  The CAP provides 60% of the cash income of Northern Ireland farmers.  The 57% of exports from Northern Ireland, which go to the EU, will suffer.  The per hectare support of farmers in Northern Ireland by the EU is the highest in the entire Union.  Strand Two of the Good Friday Agreement covers North-South relations.  A strong North-South dimension was important in ensuring the overall balance of the Agreement.  The three-stranded approach is the key to the Agreement.<br/><br/>One of the key elements of Strand Two is the Special EU Programmes Body, which helps spend EU moneys on projects that promote closer North-South relations.  When the UK takes Northern Ireland out of the EU, all this will change and, in the absence of EU moneys, Strand Two will lose an important part of its content.  The UK Government, which is the initiator of Brexit, must take responsibility for all of these issues and propose alternative ways forward to strengthen Strand Two and Strand Three of the Agreement.  This will require the continued use of the review procedures in the Good Friday Agreement and the St. Andrews Agreement as Brexit evolves.  This is a matter the committee might wish to explore.<br/><br/>In making its preparations, Ireland should act on the assumption that the UK will leave the customs union and the Single Market.  While it should work for the best, it should prepare for the worst.  In our efforts to get the best outcome, and, indeed, to help the UK, we will only get the support we deserve from the other EU states if we show that we are fully committed to keeping the EU together.  We cannot allow a perception to develop that we are half-hearted about preserving and strengthening the EU.  As a member of the euro, we are necessarily in the EU for the long haul.<br/><br/>Acting on the assumption of a hard Brexit, Ireland should adopt an aggressive strategy to improve its overall competitiveness - in other words, to improve its ability to survive the worst outcome.  To deal with a bad Brexit outcome, Ireland must become hyper-competitive.  The right action agenda is to be found in the<i></i>Ireland's Competitiveness Challenge, a report presented to the Government by the National Competitiveness Council.  As the report points out, we start from a good position.  Ireland has the fifth highest productivity in the OECD, after Luxembourg, Norway, the US and Belgium.  In terms of ease of doing business, Ireland is in fifth place in the EU after Denmark, Finland, Sweden and Germany.  It should aim now to be in first place in both of those tables.  The National Competitiveness Council shows exactly where there is room for improvement.  Our immediate competitor in many areas will still be the UK.  Comparing Ireland with the UK, using the World Bank rankings measures of ease of doing business, the National Competitiveness Council report shows that: in regard to a business wanting to obtain electricity, Ireland is in 33rd place, while the UK is in 17th; in the context of obtaining construction permits, Ireland is in 38th place, while the UK is in 17th; and in the area of enforcement of contracts, Ireland is in 90th place in the world, while the UK is in 31st.  The case clearance rate in our courts is the worst in the EU.  In respect of trade across borders, Ireland is in 27th place, while the UK is in 13th.  In terms of businesses obtaining credit, Ireland is in 32nd place, while the UK is in 20th.  The remedy to each of these problems will be different and will require action by several Departments.  A whole-of-Government approach will be needed, with a narrow focus on dramatically improving Ireland&rsquo;s competitiveness position.  From my experience, the Taoiseach's office is in an ideal position to get all Departments working on this issue.<br/><br/>If our aim is to be is to hyper-competitive, that must influence our policy on public sector pay.  This strengthens the case for a rainy day fund to meet unexpected fiscal eventualities and that for a strong independent parliamentary budget office in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  We should not spend today what we are unsure we will earn tomorrow.  As our population ages and the retired population inevitably expands, costs in this area will increase and we will not be able to afford any work disincentives.  We cannot afford to have so many households where no one is working, an area in respect of which Ireland is apparently worse than any other EU country.  We will also not be able to afford to narrow our tax base, as some propose.  In fact we should be broadening it.<br/><br/>Ireland must work to make the EU more effective and more visibly democratic.  It must help the EU to shake off its pessimism and defend it from unfair criticism.  However, Ireland must also come forward with ideas for the reform and improvement of the EU.  There is no doubt that there was a risk that Brexit would lead to individual countries pursuing separate agendas within the EU but thanks, in particular, to Ireland this has not happened.  EU states must now work hard to strengthen both EU-wide democracy and the effectiveness of the EU.  As a first step, the EU's ability to conclude trade agreements must be improved.  As matters stand, the parliament of one country - the Walloon Parliament in Belgium - could block a trade agreement.  This should be changed.  If the EU does not have the ability to conclude and ratify trade agreements, others will make trade agreements to our disadvantage.  Likewise, we must ensure that the EU becomes more visibly democratic.  This could be done by having the President of the European Commission elected directly in a two-round election by the entire electorate of the EU; having the president of the Eurogroup similarly elected by the eurozone countries and by giving national parliaments of the EU, if a minimum number of them agree, a power to require the Commission to put forward for consideration a legislative proposal within the EU competences in the treaties.  National parliaments can already delay EU legislation so why not allow them to make positive proposals in respect of such legislation?  It is vital that EU rules are respected by all countries.  I was shocked to learn that France had said it would not enforce the postal workers directive if an amendment it proposed was not conceded.  It is an existential threat to the EU if countries threaten to act in that way.  I was surprised that the Prime Minister of a founding member state of the European Union made such a threat.<br/><br/>Likewise, we must not accept that the EU treaties cannot be amended, which seems to be the political consensus at present in the Union.  A club that does not have the ability to change any rules will fossilise and die.  The EU must accept that treaty changes to make it easier to conclude trade agreements, allow for democratic elections of EU leaders and permit national parliaments to urge proposals on the Commission would be supported by the public and should be entertained.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00100"><p>I thank Mr. Bruton for his extensive, informative and enlightening address which is greatly appreciated.  A number of Senators have indicated their desire to speak, the first of whom is Senator Catherine Noone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00200"><p>I thank Mr. Bruton for attending today and for providing a very insightful, detailed and interesting presentation which shows his wide knowledge of and interest in the issues at hand.  I am interested to know Mr. Bruton's feelings about the UK election.  Who knows how it will play out?  I believe that Prime Minister May feels very confident that she will come back with a larger majority which will strengthen her hand, which is understandable, given what opinion polls are showing.  What does Mr. Bruton think about that situation and how it might impact?</p> <p>  Mr. Bruton said earlier that if they were to sit back and think about it, they would conclude that " a UK inside the EU is better for the EU than a UK outside it", even with a trade deal.  While I understand Mr. Bruton's optimism, and I would also tend to be optimistic by nature, I get no sense from what I am hearing from the UK that is realistic.  I ask Mr. Bruton to enlighten me further on that point.</p> <p>  How does Mr. Bruton think the evolving situation with regard to Brexit will affect Scotland?  Does he think Scotland freeing itself from the United Kingdom is inevitable or likely, once the UK formally leaves the EU?  On Northern Ireland many people, including the Taoiseach, have commented that if the UK leaves the EU, which it is on target to do, we could see a united Ireland in the future.  I ask Mr. Bruton to give his opinion on that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00300"><p>I thank Mr. Bruton for appearing before this committee and sharing his insights, not only on domestic matters but also on matters related to the EU and further afield.  I particularly welcome his insights on competitiveness, which is one of the areas over which we have some control.  There is much we can do to limit the effects of Brexit, which will grow and worsen over time.  Brexit is an issue that only gets worse because the more one learns about it, the more one realises how difficult it is for us to address.  </p> <p>  My colleague, Senator Noone, has spoken about the issue of a united Ireland and the Taoiseach has said that the EU needs to prepare for a united Ireland.  What does Mr. Bruton think we should seek to have included in the final agreement between the EU and UK on the issue of Northern Ireland?  Do we require a protocol to be inserted to the effect that if the people of Northern Ireland vote for a united Ireland, that would become automatic?  Is it Mr. Bruton's view that it would be like the precedent set by East and West Germany?  What does he believe we should do now to prepare for the issue in terms of a referendum on the question of unification?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00400"><p>I welcome Mr. Bruton and thank him for his very comprehensive report which clearly demonstrates his vast experience.  I would like to tease out a number of issues with him.  If he was the plane on Saturday morning, what approach would he be taking on our behalf?  We sent Mr. Bruton out to bat for us on many occasions, successfully, I might add.  I am seeking his opinion here and do not seek to undermine the negotiating position of those who will be representing us.  There is a feeling or a perception out there among the remaining EU member states that our efforts to get the deal we need because of our unique position mean we are looking for a softer Brexit for the UK.  They are interpreting our endeavours on our own behalf as working to the advantage of the UK in terms of achieving a softer Brexit than some of them would like to see.  When Mrs. May said it would be a hard Brexit, many of our European partners formed the view that if she wanted a hard Brexit, she would get one.  Then we came knocking on the door, quite genuinely because of our situation, and some of our EU partners now think that we are working more on the side of the British, albeit for our own benefit.</p> <p>  Mr. Bruton began his contribution by complimenting the Government on the work that has been done to date.  Given the importance of this issue, which is possibly the most pressing faced by the State since its foundation, does Mr. Bruton think that we should have a Department and a Minister for Brexit to deal with the negotiations and to prepare for the potential outcomes?  While we are all hoping for the best, as Mr. Bruton said, we must prepare for the worst.  If Mr. Bruton was Taoiseach when this happened, would he have considered appointing a dedicated Minister for Brexit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00500"><p>Senator Paul Daly stole one of my questions but that is fine; we are all working together here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00600"><p>Great minds think alike.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#F00700"><p>I thank Mr. Bruton.  Clearly, he has vast experience in this area.  When I was coming in this morning, someone said "he does go on, you know" but, as I said, he has much to say and a lot to offer.  As I was reading this presentation, I was reminded yet again of the number of people who have asked about a simpleton's guide to Brexit.  How can the punters understand it?  I spoke to a number of people on the DART earlier today who expressed the view that Brexit is going to happen, that there is an inevitability about it and we should stop resisting it.  We must accept that it is going to happen in some shape or form and determine how we can best protect ourselves.  Several speakers referred to the impact on Northern Ireland but Brexit will have a devastating and catastrophic impact on the Republic of Ireland and indeed, on the island of Ireland.  I spoke to an Ulster farmer the other day who said that he was not sure if he was loyal to the crown at all anymore.  He said, "I am loyal to that crown; not the Majesty's crown".  I thought that was a simple but strong and clear message.  Money divides people but it can also unite people.  The economy brings people together.  Prosperity brings people together.  We prosper in a safe, prosperous economy and country.</p><p> I am someone who never envisaged the possibility of a united Ireland but I think it poses great possibilities and opportunities for this country.  When we look at Northern Ireland, the Good Friday Agreement and the commitments that have been made, if Britain pulls Northern Ireland out of the EU, it changes Northern Ireland's constitutional position.  That has a huge impact in terms of the Good Friday Agreement.  We know that we will have the land border between the EU and the UK, but there are complications to all of that.  Look at Scotland.  Scotland chose to remain in the EU.  That is going to gather momentum because the economy focuses people.  Funds and money focus people.  The majority of the people of Northern Ireland voted to remain in the EU.  That is really important.  Some people may call that narrow nationalism or whatever, but at the end of the day it is about their lives and their families.</p><p> We have to keep this whole Brexit debate simple.  We must have brevity and keep it simple.  How is it going to impact on people's lives, their families, their economy and their business?  That is really important.  Sinn F&eacute;in is not here today, but it is interesting that its members have talked about a new Border poll.  I think we are going to move towards that, which is no surprise.  Mr. Bruton might be shocked at this, but I think there is a greater momentum for all of that.  It could be argued, as the British Government of course will, that there is no tangible evidence that the people of Northern Ireland want that to happen, but I think it is coming closer and that is possibly a good thing.  Mr. Bruton talks about opportunities.  I see that as a real opportunity.  I do not want to dwell on that point but I think it is important.  Brexit threatens the key principles and objectives of the Good Friday Agreement.  I want Mr. Bruton to talk about that and how he sees it.  Does he accept or agree that it will have a serious impact on the constitutional position of Northern Ireland?  With his experience I know he would have very strong views on that.  I would like to hear them.</p><p> We also have to recognise that there has always been what I like to term a porous border between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland.  Some of that has not been regulated and there are other arguments about that.  They are for another day.  There is however a transfer of money, business and economy through the porous border between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland and that needs to be recognised and understood.</p><p> The Taoiseach outlined four key areas at the beginning of this process.  He talked about minimising the impact on trade and economy, protecting the Northern Ireland peace process, maintaining the common travel area and influencing the future of the European Union.  I want to start with that last one.  Mr. Bruton talks about greater democracy within the Union.  Why is France in this situation at the moment?  Why is Britain in this situation?  Mr. Bruton accepts, and has clearly outlined, the need for greater power, functions and engagement with national parliaments.  That is a problem that has arisen.  We need greater democracy within the European Union.  I would nearly make a bet with Mr. Bruton that the next European elections in this country will throw up some very interesting results.  There will be resistance, anger, discontent with the standard parties and also reactionary responses, which are not always good in politics, in respect of the European Union and the European institutions.  I would like Mr. Bruton's comments on that.</p><p> Mr. Bruton's document was not numbered, but it has 22 pages in it.  I see my colleague, Senator Reilly, is similarly numbering the pages.  I want to reference two points in the document for Mr. Bruton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Bruton" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#G00200"><p>Now we are all counting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#G00300"><p>Does Mr. Bruton have the numbers himself?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.21" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Bruton" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#G00400"><p>I have no numbers on it at all.  I am afraid I am my own secretary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#G00500"><p>That is the joy of being one's own secretary, is it not?  On page five, Mr. Bruton talks about how keeping the offer of resuming UK membership on the table would be good for politics, the economy and the EU.  That is really interesting.  It is something that is not being pushed out there as an option.  I would really like Mr. Bruton to tease that out more and speak about how he would envisage it.</p> <p>  People do not clearly understand enough about the revocation of the notice of withdrawal and that the UK can revoke a decision of withdrawal from the EU.  That may perhaps be a very lengthy process.  I do not know a lot about it.  It is all news to me so I am glad to be here to listen to what Mr. Bruton had to say about it.  Will Mr. Bruton tease out the revocation process?  That is really important.</p> <p>  On page eight, Mr. Bruton states that "Some have argued that if Ireland is inside the EU and the UK is out of it, a special "bespoke deal" for the island of Ireland, or for the UK and Ireland, could be envisaged".  He says "I do not see how this could work as far as trading standards and tariffs are concerned."  He goes on to explain that, but he might tease it out for us.</p> <p>  In concluding I again thank Mr. Bruton.  The big message for us all in this forum is that we must make this Brexit message very simple.  Yesterday, we saw Donald Trump's new arrangements for taxation.  There are huge, enormous challenges facing the island of Ireland as regards the economy and our new road to recovery.  These times present major challenges for us and they are not unlinked.  They are all interconnected.  I thank Mr. Bruton for his very comprehensive paper.  I would appreciate it if he would touch on some of the issues I have raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#G00600"><p>I welcome Mr. Bruton who, as others have pointed out, has huge experience.  I thank him for all his service to the country in all of the different roles that he has played, and indeed his service to the EU when he was ambassador to the US.  He mentioned competitiveness.  It is really important that we discuss that a bit further and address the issues that are affecting our competitiveness.  Mr. Bruton has been very fair in showing that, overall, we are much better than the UK in terms of competitiveness but that there are areas such as legal costs where we are weaker, not just in terms of the fees charged but the duration of the process.  I have seen deals fall asunder.  People in America can close a house sale in two weeks, very often on the Internet.  They come over here and are just flabbergasted at the amount of time it takes and they become very suspicious that something is awry.  That is certainly something we have to look at.</p> <p>  Mr. Bruton mentioned the Good Friday Agreement, how there will clearly be implications for it and how it is going to sit within any deal done.  It has to be respected as an international agreement.</p> <p>  I agree with Mr. Bruton entirely when he talks about the need for the EU to be dynamic, able to change and, therefore, able to bring in new rules, regulations and treaties.  At the same time however, that cannot be done at the expense of minority views.  Smaller countries such as ours must not be made to feel that we would be sidelined by a number of bigger countries who would make decisions without regard to our concerns.  I am not saying that is the case, but it is a delicate balance to strike.  I would warrant that Mr. Bruton would know more about that than anyone in this room.</p> <p>  I am absolutely delighted to hear Mr. Bruton talking about rules being enforced equally.  I do not mind putting some comments on the record here.  If one wants to set up a small food outlet in this country there are all sorts of rules and regulations imposed by the EU, yet I had an experience where I passed through France and Monaco and into Italy.  I stopped in the third village down the coast for lunch.  It was a lovely lunch and very reasonably priced.  I thanked the staff and asked where the toilet was.  I was told to go the train station as the restaurant did not have one.  One just could not do that here.  Mr. Bruton is absolutely right when he talks about the big things, but it is the little things that drive people mad as well.  Enforcement does not seem to be equal across the EU.  Let us call a spade a spade.  As Mr. Bruton quite rightly implies, that is what undermines people's faith in Europe.  In fairness, politicians in this country too are guilty of blaming the EU for things they do not like and then expecting people to have a love of the EU, when in fact much of what we heap blame on the EU for is our own fault, due to the way we have imposed and interpreted certain rules.</p> <p>  I really welcome Mr. Bruton's proposal to the House of Lords.  It is really important that there would be some sort of heads-up arrangement before any legislation is passed so that it does not cause untoward or unintended consequences.  It was really useful to hear him point out many of the problems.  If we had any doubt about how a change in law can impact hugely on businesses, we should look at an amendment that was recently discussed in the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, the Seanad and D&aacute;il.  It was an amendment to a Bill to allow for a further extension of a derogation for international companies under accountancy rules that apply here in Europe and accountancy rules that apply in the United States.  The sums of money that it was going to cost companies ran to the hundreds of millions, purely because of a rule.  In fairness to her, the Minister took immediate action and extended that so that companies can now relax, but the impact it was going to have was just astonishing.</p><p>That is going to be multiplied a thousand times over through the course of Brexit if great care is not taken.  Mr. Bruton spoke about leaving open the possibility of revoking the decision.  I imagine he will agree it is far too early to be making noise like that.  As he has rightly demonstrated, the longer this goes on, the more people will realise what the impact of it is and understand the negative effects it will have.  In such circumstances, the slightly gung ho approach that has been adopted might diminish and a different view on this matter might be taken in the UK.</p><p> I think we will find out this weekend, when we see what comes out of the meeting, just how effective the Government team has been in making Ireland's case.  I would like to congratulate all of those involved because they have done an excellent job.  As Mr. Bruton has pointed out, there are many problems and many opportunities in this context.  As a country, we need to deal with the problems we know of, anticipate the problems we know about in part and be prepared for problems that have not been thrown up yet.  We need to take every opportunity we can, including those highlighted by Mr. Bruton in his paper.  I refer, for example, to the possibility of bringing the European Medicines Agency to Ireland, and to Dublin in particular.  There are many opportunities in our capital city, especially in the area around the airport.  There are many other opportunities out there for Ireland.  Many countries, including Brazil, Russia, India and China, see Ireland as a wonderful place where they can access the EU market of almost 500 million people.  That market will decrease when the UK leaves the Union.  As Mr. Bruton has pointed out, many companies are based in the UK so that they can access the EU market.  Obviously, that will change.  I thank Mr. Bruton again and ask him to expand on how he envisages that the option of the UK revoking its decision might be retained.  How would that work in real terms?  Will Mr. Bruton set out the timelines within which that might happen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#H00200"><p>I will ask one or two questions before I hand back to Mr. Bruton.  I would like to build on what Senator Reilly has said about the opportunities presented by Brexit.  Mr. Bruton mentioned the positive impact of the recent EU trade deal with South Korea, which has been beneficial to the UK and is presenting opportunities for Ireland.  There is a need for Ireland to diversify its economy and create options beyond Brexit.  What regions or areas present the next best opportunities?  I refer not only to areas with which the EU does not currently have trade deals, but also to existing trade deals, such as the Mercosur deal, that need to be improved and brought up to speed.</p> <p>  Many of the questions I had intended to ask have been asked by my colleagues.  I would like to ask about the scope and role of Anglo-Irish relations after Brexit has happened.  Obviously, we are tied through the EU and we will negotiate as one of 27 member states.  I fully agree that this Saturday's meeting will be extremely important.  We are able to work with the UK outside the structures of the EU through existing bodies like the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly and the British-Irish Council, even if they do not meet as often as they could.  Does Mr. Bruton believe the potential exists for those two bodies to further strengthen Anglo-Irish relations and to facilitate new forms of access?  I thank all Senators for their contributions and invite Mr. Bruton to respond to the questions that have been asked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.26" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Bruton" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#H00300"><p>The EU is negotiating a number of trade agreements at the moment.  I do not have a list of them in my head.  We have had difficult experiences in ratifying agreements with Canada and Ukraine.  In the latter case, a relatively small number of people in the Netherlands were able to bring about a referendum in which a relatively small number of people rejected by a narrow margin a treaty that had been negotiated on behalf of all 28 member states with Ukraine, which was under threat from Russia at the time.  The ability of the EU to negotiate trade agreements, and conclude and ratify such agreements, is weakened by this sort of eventuality.  This needs to be remedied.</p> <p>  Some people might argue that the rights of minorities have to be protected in a situation like this.  That view has been reflected in some of the questions that have been asked by Senators.  I suggest that the interests and rights of majorities also need to be protected.  I believe that the EU, by its very nature as an organisation based on rules that apply equally stringently to big and small countries, to the rich and the poor and to the economically powerful and the economically weak, is the best organisation for a smaller country.  The over-riding reason I believe it is in Ireland's interests to be at the heart of the EU is that the relationships of power within the Union are mitigated by the existence of rules.  If the EU were to break up and we were to revert to pure power politics in Europe, the smaller countries would be the big losers and the bigger countries would be unrestrained.  That is why it is so important for us to remain not just in the EU, but in the lead in the EU along with other countries that have similar interests.  It is a great support for us that the biggest country in the EU - Germany - is so committed to the European ideal and indeed to the rights of smaller countries within the EU.  Germany is the great bulwark for the preservation of peace in Europe, partially as a result of its bad conduct in the past.  That has now been turned into a tremendous asset in terms of German political support for Europe.  I think that is a very positive thing to reflect on.</p> <p>  I will respond to the specific questions that have been asked by the members of the committee.  I agree with the Chairman that the British-Irish Intergovernmental Conference has a great deal of work to do.  It should probably meet once a month as soon as Brexit occurs, if it occurs.  The conference should monitor court judgments and regulatory changes that are being made to identify anything that could add, however infinitesimally, to the burdens faced by those who do business between this island and Britain and across the Border on this island.  It is fortunate that the Good Friday Agreement has an east-west dimension as well as a North-South dimension.  The east-west dimension was originally included in the Agreement to reassure Unionists, but it is now in our interests to make it very strong because it has the potential to protect our interests in the context of Brexit.  On the other hand, the North-South strand was what was important for Nationalists when the original agreement was being put in place.  That has been partially mitigated by the doubt that has been put over the continuance of EU funds.  It is up to the British Government to come forward with proposals to strengthen the North-South and east-west strands in a way that maintains the balance of the Good Friday Agreement, which from the outset was a balance between varying interests.</p> <p>  On the points made by Senator Reilly, it is interesting that one of the areas of competitiveness in which Ireland is among the worst performers in Europe is legal delays.  I do not know the reason for this.  I am not a Member of the House anymore.  I think the experience in Europe generally is that vested interests in the professions are better than their counterparts in the trades at resisting change.  Vested interests in trade and manufacturing find it less easy to resist harmonisation and competition.  Resistance to putting the consumer first is easier in some professions, perhaps because the changes involved are so complex.</p><p>That means that legislators have to do more work in the professions than other areas.</p><p> With reference to Senator Victor Boyhan's suggestion that we try to make Brexit simple and easy to understand, by their nature some things are complex and any attempt to simplify them can lead one into great error.  For example, Boris Johnson tried to simplify the Brexit issue by saying the British people could have their cake and eat it.  It was a memorable phrase, but it irresponsibly misled people in Britain.  In the context of referenda, there is a very big obligation on citizens as citizen legislators not to look for simple explanations but to attempt to understand complexity because this is a complex issue.  The United Kingdom got itself into its current position because it oversimplified what the European Union was about.  It has not studied it in the way smaller countries like Ireland have had to do because of the nature of our position.  We understand the European Union because we have to.  Until now, the United Kingdom felt it did not have to understand the European Union but that it could make a simple decision to leave and that the consequences would be light.  It will find that they will not be.  That is the price it is paying for the search for too much simplicity in the description of complex issues.</p><p> I was invited to speculate on what Scotland might do.  I am tempted to say we have enough problems of our own without worrying about Scotland.  As the Scots are probably quite good at looking after their own interests, I will not address them.</p><p> In 2015 a poll showed that only 32% of Northern Irish Catholics and 14% of the total population wanted a united Ireland.  Those figures would now be somewhat different but not radically so.  For the past 200 years Irish nationalists, both constitutional nationalists and nationalists who also entertained the use of other means, have tended to wish away the substantial resistance to a united Ireland among a significant, concentrated and deeply convinced section of the Unionist community in Northern Ireland.  Asking Unionists to change their position on this issue is akin to asking them to change the way in which they have defined their identity.  We may not define our identity in that way, but they have defined theirs as including allegiance to the Crown.  It is not something they will easily change and that a 51% majority in a Border poll in Northern Ireland would change.  The financial and security practicalities of imposing the wish for a united Ireland of a 51% majority on a recalcitrant 49% would fall entirely on the shoulders of this state.  The British would no longer have any part to play and we would have to shoulder the burden on our own.  It is important that we be honest with ourselves about this.  </p><p> I may be wrong, but I do not believe there is a need for provision to be made in EU law to facilitate a united Ireland.  As Senator Mark Daly pointed out, Germany was reunified without any change to the treaties.  If both communities in Northern Ireland were to decide that it was in their interests to have a united Ireland, the European Union would facilitate that overnight, as would we.  It would cost us money, but if that is what both communities wanted, we would have no difficulty in paying for it.  However, it is more difficult to try to do it when only one community or a narrow majority of one community and an overwhelming majority of the other want it.  Members will probably be glad to know that I am no longer a practising politician.  How to work this out is now an issue for current Members who should not underestimate the difficulties involved.</p><p> To keep the option open of Britain resuming membership of the European Union at some stage in the future, all we need to do is what the President of the European Parliament, Mr. Antonio Tajani, has done and say that option is open.  It does not have to be discussed any further than that.  Should the British Parliament come to consider the outcome of the Brexit negotiations, it will look at this and might consider that that option might be better than what has been offered to it.  That is all that is needed.  No further elaboration is required.</p><p> Senator Paul Daly asked about having a Minister with responsibility for Brexit.  As I indicated in the section on competitiveness, meeting the Brexit challenge involves every Minister.  There is no part of government which is exempt from the responsibility for meeting the challenge.  It is a collective challenge for the entire Government.  Having been a line Minister, there is always a risk that one can become completely immersed in one's own agenda.  A Minister may attend Cabinet meetings but not become involved and perhaps not even encourage himself or herself to become involved in the affairs of other Departments.  I fear that if there were to be a Minister with responsibility for Brexit who would be the bag carrier in dealing with all of the problems, the rest of the members of the Government would sit back, consider that issues were for the Minister with responsibility for Brexit and leave him or her to deal with them.  It is better for Ministers to have collective responsibility.  However, I acknowledge that the suggestion of a Minister with responsibility for Brexit was put forward in good faith and with the best intentions in terms of the interests of the country.  I do not criticise anyone for putting it forward.  It shows seriousness, but I do not think it would be the right thing to do at this point.  However, again, that is for others to decide.</p><p> I share Senator Mark Daly's concern on the issue of a vote in the House of Commons on the Good Friday Agreement.  The UK Government has approached Brexit with little active interest in the impact in Northern Ireland, Scotland or Wales.  It is being dealt with with the English electorate in mind, which is a pity.  There is an interesting contrast between the European Union and the United Kingdom.  In the European Union no treaty change can be made and no new member can be admitted without every existing member agreeing to it.  However, in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland two of the four constituting nations can decide for the other two.</p><p>That shows the difference between the two unions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#K00200"><p>We have covered a great deal and are very appreciative and grateful to Mr. Bruton for giving us so much of his time and the benefit of his insight and experience.  I thank all Senators for their engagement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.30 a.m. and resumed at 12 noon.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.31" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#N00100">Engagement with former Minister, Mr. Dermot Ahern</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#N00200"><p>On behalf of the committee, I welcome Mr. Dermot Ahern to present to us this afternoon.  There is no need for an introduction but in the context of this afternoon's discussion, we are keen to hear from him how the current issues facing us have informed his opinion based on his experiences during his time as a Deputy representing a Border constituency as well as his more than 14 years as a Minister and his considerable involvement at that time at EU Council level.  We had a very good informal discussion outside the committee room.  We value his understanding of the situation and any observation he may bring to the committee.</p><p>Before we begin I will read the notice on privilege.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence relating to a particular matter and they continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of the proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p><p>With all of that out of the way, I ask Mr. Ahern to make his opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Dermot Ahern" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#N00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and the members for their kind invitation to me to say a few words on an issue that will affect our country for many years to come.  The Chairman mentioned the Defamation Act 2009.  I was the one who sponsored that legislation and I remember many long sessions in one of the committee rooms in Leinster House going through the legislation line by line on Committee and Report Stages.  Therefore, to a certain extent, I am back in the corridors where I spent such a long time.  I am delighted at least to give some of my thoughts on an issue which will affect this country for a considerable period ahead.  I will keep my words focused on a number of issues and then I will take questions from the members.</p> <p>  As the Chairman said, I was a Border Deputy for more than 24 years.  I live virtually within a stone's throw of the Border, some ten miles from it, and that area within which I live was the focus of most of my political career.</p> <p>  The foundation of the Irish peace process has been based on the three main relationships within these two islands.  First is the relationship between the two communities in Northern Ireland, then the North-South focus, and finally the east-west axis. The great improvements we and I, as a person from a Border country, have witnessed during recent decades have been derived from our concentration on those three aspects.  The various efforts over the years, culminating in the Good Friday Agreement and the St. Andrews Agreement, were all based on this three-way focus.  Complimenting all those initiatives was the fact that both the UK and Ireland were equal members at the European Union table.  The Brexit decision has potentially reversed, or, at the very least, slowed down the improvement in our dealings, within and across these two islands.  Now, we must pick up pieces from this decision which was not of our making and which was taken without much regard for the implications for this island.</p> <p>  As someone who attended European Council of Ministers meetings virtually every week for more than 14 years, I am acutely aware of the challenging negotiation road ahead, not only in the run-up to the UK leaving the Union but also thereafter.  With the UK leaving, I can foresee huge difficulties.  We will lose our main allies into the future in negotiations within the EU.  Across every specialty with which I dealt, whether it was social welfare and pensions, communications, energy, marine, foreign affairs or justice, we generally had an incredibly close common interest with our neighbouring island.  In future, it will be necessary for us to cultivate new alliances, and we have tried to cultivate those in the years since we became a member of Union, but none of these will be as close to us as our erstwhile UK colleagues were.</p> <p>  By its nature, the European Union is a compromise.  When I attended my first a Council of Ministers meeting in 1997, there were 15 members around the table.  By the time I left in 2011, there were 27, and that number has increased in the meantime to 28.  Getting an agreement on a negotiating stance among so many member states with different and differing national priorities will be extremely difficult, and that is even before the negotiations start with the UK.  I welcome some of the reports in today's newspapers on the conclusions for next Saturday and I hope that continues.  I congratulate everyone involved, if that is to be the case.</p> <p>  For me, there is a danger that we will be caught in the crossfire between the UK and the wider European Union.  Despite all the assurances from both sides, we as a sovereign nation must maintain our absolute right to decide what is best for our own people.  While I fully appreciate that we must rely on the negotiating skills of the various European institutions, which we hope will keep our national interests in mind, we should continue to articulate strongly the very particular circumstances that affect us on this island.  We should insist that nothing is agreed, until everything is agreed.  I was long enough around the corridors of Brussels to know that, ultimately, when the hard bargaining comes down to the wire, the interests of individual member states, especially the smaller ones, can be conveniently glossed over if the ultimate price of an overall agreement is in sight.  It can end up being everyone for themselves, and this is where Ireland could lose out hugely unless we adopt a constant hard bargaining stance from the very start.</p> <p>  Given that Ireland is deemed to be in what are called exceptional circumstances, we should ensure that we can continue bilateral discussions with the UK, which the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, recently referred to it as, "the strong sharing of information" between our two nations.  This should be undertaken especially regarding the micro issues which will not necessarily be dealt with in any overall agreement.  While I have no doubt our embassy in London is doing its level best to highlight issues with our UK neighbours, I do not get the sense that we are, on a sector by sector basis, at least at this time, discussing with them the practical effects on us of their decision.  We need to ramp this up in the next few months, despite the fact the situation unfortunately has been complicated even further by the calling of a snap general election by the British Government and, consequently, that no devolved government is present or will be present in Northern Ireland for a good few months ahead.  We can validly conduct these bilateral talks under the umbrella of the Good Friday Agreement.</p><p>For me, one of the critical issues arising from the Good Friday Agreement architecture which needs to be dealt with on a bilateral basis with the UK as soon as possible is that of the future of the cross-Border bodies, particularly the Special EU Programmes Body.  As we know, these were put in place under the Good Friday Agreement and one of the obvious <i>quid pro quos</i>in that regard was the deletion - following a referendum of our people - of Articles 2 and 3 of the Constitution.  These are very important cross-Border bodies and they have particular issues in light of the fact that Brexit is to happen.  Equally, Brexit clearly will have adverse implications for the ability of the North-South Ministerial Council to discuss EU matters, as is provided for under the Good Friday Agreement.<br/><br/>Spokespersons for the European Commission have stated that creative and effective solutions can be found to ease our difficulties, and I welcome that.  The practical reality is that, as an island, the Irish Sea could well become the de facto Border.  Given that it seems to be accepted that the common travel area regime is to apply, surely some creative and effective solution can be arrived at in that respect.  However, I am of the view that customs clearance would be a much more difficult issue with which to deal.  New technology, which was not present when we had customs checks at the Border in bygone years, can probably help with the movement of large consignments North and South, but what happens to individual citizens travelling normally across the Border on a daily basis, as they do in large numbers?  How can a new post Brexit customs regime deal with that particular aspect?  Unless some practical arrangement can be arrived at in this respect, I foresee smuggling of the past resurrecting its ugly head.  One favourable aspect of our joint EU membership has been a significant reduction, particularly in the past number of years, in the possible avenues for cross-Border smuggling.  Alas, Brexit may change all this back to the bad old days.  The British Brexit Minister, David Davis, referred recently to the possibility, although he said it was a suggestion from one of the lead negotiators in the EU, of joint customs checks taking place on either side of the Border, in a similar way to the arrangement which apparently obtains between Sweden and Norway.  Given our recent history on the island, I am particularly surprised that anyone could even countenance such a solution as being workable.<br/><br/>The Border areas in Ireland will be most affected within the EU.  While the focus of the EU and Irish negotiators will be on the overall impact nationally, unless some special attention is paid to those areas immediately contiguous to the Border, those communities, whether from an economic, cultural or societal point of view, will lose out.  For example, one aspect, which may not be dealt with specifically in an overall agreement, may be the issue of mobile phone roaming charges.  Members may say that this is an insignificant issue.  It is not insignificant for people who live on the Border, as I know.  From 15 June this year, there is due to be, in effect, free mobile phone roaming across the EU.  However, for those of us living and doing business in Border areas, there will be a significant additional financial imposition as our phones roam between North and South, unless some special bilateral arrangement can be arrived at in this regard.  As I said, as the crow flies my house is about ten miles from the Border.  When mobile phones were introduced in the late 1980s, my phone used to roam depending on the room of the house I was in.  If I went into the kitchen I was welcomed to the UK service and when I went into my sitting room I was welcomed to the Republic of Ireland service.  On Clogherhead pier, which, even though it looks directly out over the Mourne Mountains, is approximately 25 miles from the Border, one is welcomed to the UK service.  If some special arrangement is not made regarding the issue of mobile phone roaming charges across the Border, we will be in a very difficult position and face an additional financial burden, particularly people who do business on a day-to-day basis in that general area.<br/><br/>What will be the position of the many hundreds of cross-Border workers who live and work on either side of the Border?  Will their pension and social welfare rights, as laid down by EU directives, be preserved?  When I was in the Department of Foreign Affairs, I was involved in the setting up of the cross-Border bodies and I remember the huge difficulties we had regarding wages and pension rights.  When we were setting up InterTradeIreland, which is based in Newry, there were quite a number of people from the South working in that body and I recall there were significant differing levels of income and pension entitlements between staff who were sitting side by side in that particular location.  It caused the ramping up of those bodies to be slowed because of the difficulty in that respect but there are many other cross-Border issues which need to be specifically dealt with.  For most of my earlier career as a backbencher, time and again my constituency was the focus in terms of people who were to be extradited to Northern Ireland being physically dragged across the Border between garda&iacute; and members of the RUC at the time.  This gave rise to huge upheaval and unrest in the area.  The European arrest warrant set all of that at naught.  What will happen in that regard?<br/><br/>How will cross-Border health co-operation, which has been very good in recent years, continue?  With regard to tourism, unfortunately, during the Troubles there was always a sort of divide regarding tourism.  Thankfully, that is much better but what effect will Brexit have on the initiatives that are taking place across the Border between North and South on a micro rather than an overall level?<br/><br/>Television without frontiers allows free transmission of television programmes across frontiers.  Will the position in this regard be affected in Border areas?<br/><br/>Fisheries is a huge issue, and specifically in terms of Carlingford Lough in my constituency and Lough Swilly, to name but a few.  Some of the best prawn fishing areas in the world are along the coast off north Louth and south Down.  What will happen to the prawn fisheries in that respect?  I do not see anything being talked about in that respect.  Perhaps something is being done behind the scenes; I do not know.<br/><br/>There has been a recognition of the special Border area difficulties, both internationally and from the EU.  For the past number of decades, the International Fund for Ireland, which, if my memory serves me correctly, started in 1986, and the various EU PEACE funds, have helped the six Northern and six Southern Border counties.  I believe that a continuation of the special EU funds should apply to these areas, especially during any transitional period for the implementation of Brexit.  I read in today's media some reference to the possibility that this might happen.  I would like to see more of the detail of that and whether it would apply to the six Northern counties as well as the six Southern Border counties.  This might be a long shot but perhaps consideration could be given to some relaxation of the state aid rules for Border areas.<br/><br/>Over the years, in all my discussions privately with Unionist representatives, I have always maintained that while we may not agree on the political and constitutional issues pertaining on the island we should always proceed with dealing with the practical sectors on an all-island basis.  For instance, it makes absolutely no sense that an island as small as ours should have two distinct electricity networks.  I was in the Department responsible for energy when that initiative started, which I believe was finalised after I left in 2007.  Thankfully, we now have an all-island electricity market but I read in recent media reports that there is a report questioning the effect of Brexit on the all-island electricity regime.  Where stands that and many other such cross-Border initiatives as a result of Brexit?<br/><br/>Undoubtedly, a good deal of preparatory work has already been carried out by our diplomatic officials and Government.  Interest groups also have focused on their own particular spheres.  However, the general public needs to get some direction as to how likely they will be affected.  It will be said that it is far too early to go into specifics but I believe the Government should prepare a national plan outlining the macro and micro issues it believes will need to be focused upon in any future discussions with the United Kingdom and the EU.  I fear that too much focus may be made on some of the more headline issues to the detriment of practical issues which affect ordinary people in their daily lives, particularly people living in the Border areas.  There will be many unknown unknowns cropping up over the next few months and years.</p><p>These are things we have not even thought about but which must be added to any national plan that is put in place.  The general public should be able to interact with a specific Government-sponsored website on the issue.</p><p> It was no coincidence that we joined the EU at the same time as the UK.  Indeed, we stayed out of Schengen because it suited our relationship with the UK.  There were a lot of issues on which we found common cause around the EU table with our neighbours.  It was in our own self-interest to go in at that time in step with the United Kingdom.  Now that it is leaving, we need to strongly articulate our national interest in these negotiations.  One way or the other, the result will be a political compromise.  As such, it will be necessary for our political leaders to keep our particular difficulties at the top of the EU agenda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#P00200"><p>I thank Mr. Ahern for that thoughtful and detailed address which is greatly appreciated by all members of the committee.  We will go straight to questions with Senator Victor Boyhan having indicated first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#P00300"><p>I thank Mr. Ahern.  It is good to hear his comprehensive perspective as someone who lives close to the Border and has represented the people in the Border region and as someone with vast ministerial experience.  I told the previous speaker, Mr. John Bruton, about meeting an Ulster farmer who talked to me about the crown.  He said he was more loyal to the crown, as in the monetary denomination rather than the one worn by her majesty.  The analogy he was making was a simple one.  His point was that economics can divide or unite us.  Money can divide or unite us.  That is becoming a big focus now on the island of Ireland and that is rightly so.</p> <p>  While there are inevitabilities about Brexit, it is great to see Mr. Ahern's emphasis, which was very different to that of the previous speaker.  Mr. Ahern seems to realise to a greater extent the realities of it.  While Mr. Bruton talked about the possibility of revocation and Britain changing its mind, that is a long way away.  While the Government has to be prepared for what is going on, I am more interested in the emphasis Mr. Ahern placed on Northern Ireland and, I presume, the protection of the peace process and all of that.  That is a very important part of Brexit for the island of Ireland as are the difficulties around all of that.  The constitutional position of Northern Ireland will change if Britain brings the United Kingdom out of the EU.  How will that impact on the Anglo-Irish Agreement?  From his experience, what does Mr. Ahern see?  I see that as a major constitutional change to the position of Northern Ireland.  What is the potential impact for the people?  Mr. Ahern referred to the importance of the North-South dimension but now we have the east-west dimension in all of this.  That is a good thing as long as there is dialogue.  Mr. Bruton touched earlier on a really good point.  He said there was a united Europe but in the case of the United Kingdom, one has the position in relation to Scotland.  We know what the position in Scotland and Northern Ireland is.  They both voted to remain within the EU.  I would be interested in Mr. Ahern's comments on that.  Of the four countries in the UK, two are for and two are against.</p> <p>  Referring to Northern Ireland, Mr. Ahern said he believed the continuation of the special EU funds should apply, especially during any transitional period.  While that is important, what are the practicalities and the reality of that happening?  Of course, I agree on all of that and on the relaxing of state-aid rules in the Border counties.  In his experience, what does Mr. Ahern think is the reality?  As someone with huge ministerial experience, what would be his red line in negotiations?  As he is not part of the negotiations, that may be an unfair question to ask him.  What are the red line issues, however, from the point of view of the EU negotiating with the UK or, for that matter, the Irish Government negotiating on our special interests?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#P00400"><p>Mr. Ahern is very welcome.  I appreciate his contribution in which his many years of ministerial experience within the European project was very evident.  His on-the-ground knowledge as someone who lives so close to the Border also came across strongly.  As much as we have studied Brexit, he has been able to identify through personal experience things which have not been mentioned in the previous meetings I have been at.  Simple things like roaming charges are examples of the many things that will come up as the thing progresses and which nobody can predict.</p> <p>  From 23 June, the day after the vote was taken, people started to suffer consequences immediately in Border areas and in specific industries, in particular the mushroom industry which exports across the Border and across the sea to England where it is tied into sterling contracts.  They will continue to suffer as long as the negotiations continue.  There is a great deal of prediction about hard and soft Brexit and what the outcome may be, but what is guaranteed is that while this is all going on there will be an air of instability and currency fluctuation.  Predictions left, right and centre will influence Mr. Ahern's area.  As someone who lives in the Border area, how should we be directing that?  What changes to state-aid rules should we seek and what supports should be available from the EU in the immediate here and now rather than post-Brexit for situations like this?  I am a regular visitor to Dundalk through my passion for horse racing.  When one is there on a Friday night, every second accent one hears is a Northern Irish one.  As such, how is the tourism industry going to be affected given the fluctuations in sterling and so on?</p> <p>  As someone who has been out there for so long negotiating, what is Mr. Ahern's opinion of the following?  When David Cameron went to the EU to get a package to put to the English people, was the EU too hard?  Did the EU not think the English would follow through on this?  If it got a second bite of the cherry in the current situation with the English having voted for Brexit, might the EU provide a bit more flexibility so that the referendum could be revisited?  I am interested in Mr. Ahern's views as someone who lives on the Border, wearing both the political and the local caps.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#P00500"><p>I thank Mr. Ahern for coming before the committee.  His experience of dealing with the EU on various issues made him realise much sooner than some of our Westminster colleagues the consequences for them of leaving.  The effects of Brexit will get worse as time goes by.</p> <p>  Mr. Ahern's idea of a national plan on a micro and macro level is one at which all Departments should look.  That is something that is lacking.  We have had many statements about the effects and what we would like to see on a macro level, but we have not had a detailed analysis down to the nuts and bolts of roaming charges.  There will be a cost to business in future if something is not about that.  These should all be policy positions and they should be lined out by each Department as the issues we need to address in Brexit.  We do not have that.  We have been told by many EU representatives that they want solutions from us and that if we do not provide them, they will have to come up with their own.  We have a very limited window in which to set out those solutions.</p> <p>  Mr. Ahern referred to the funding programmes for Northern Ireland and we have suggested in our report on Brexit and the future of Ireland to the Good Friday Agreement committee that in the absence of an agreement, the British Government should continue to pay for all the EU programmes which are in place as well as for those which are to come in future.  In essence, they broke it so they have to fix it.  It should not be for the people of Northern Ireland who voted to remain in the EU to bear the brunt of a decision made by Wales and England.</p> <p>  The Taoiseach has said since the MacGill summer school last year that the EU needs to prepare for a united Ireland.  What should we be doing as a country to prepare for that along with those preparations for Brexit which Mr. Ahern outlined in his presentation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#P00600"><p>Like other speakers, I welcome Mr. Dermot Ahern.  We spent a long time around the same table dealing with many of the problems we face here today in a different context.</p><p> Two things occur to me.  I do not know whether Mr. Ahern had the opportunity to see the contribution of his namesake, Mr. Bertie Ahern, to this committee recently.  The latter suggested that, in addition to a common travel area, we should consider a common trading area recognising the special status of Northern Ireland.  It occurs to me, and the point has been made by a number of contributors in this process, that if there is to be a new customs regime between the UK and the EU of a hard kind, it would probably make more sense to have it between the island of Ireland as a whole and Great Britain rather than along the Border.  It appears that there is a very strong case to be made for regarding Ireland and Northern Ireland in particular as a special economic area.  Senator Mark Daly mentioned that when Germany was divided, East German-West German relations were regarded as being inside rather than outside the Community under EU law up to the time of German reunification.  There is a real opportunity for Ireland to come up with an imaginative and flexible approach to propose to our EU partners for agreement with the British.  I think Northern Ireland will be extremely marginalised within the UK by the Brexit experience.  The post-industrial base of Northern Ireland has been in decline, which has had a very significant effect on Protestant Unionist working-class people.  Protestant Unionist farmers in Northern Ireland will now find themselves on the wrong side of a revised CAP regime if Tory instincts for cheap food policies are advanced.  The fact that Northern Ireland's agriculture and milk production are so heavily integrated into Southern production is yet another reason we should take on board the idea of regarding Northern Ireland as a special exception to the normal incidences of being inside or outside the EU.  I would be interested in hearing Mr. Ahern's view about the possibility of special economic rules for Ireland and whether he thinks the Irish Government should be coming up with these now, putting them on the table and making them part of the 27 states' negotiating agenda.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#Q00200"><p>I welcome Mr. Ahern and thank him for his presentation.  Obviously, we are all very appreciative of his attendance here because he has particular knowledge nationally, internationally and locally and has highlighted many of the practical local issues people will face on a day-to-day basis.  These issues must be dealt with.  One thing nobody wants to see return to the Border area is smuggling and criminality.  How might this dealt with?  I am not putting Mr. Ahern on the spot but does he have ideas about how this could be dealt with?</p><p>I am also interested in the fact that Mr. Ahern mentioned many other areas like tourism and health.  Health is in the news this week with the announcement that funding for the new national paediatric hospital has received the go-ahead by the Government.  It was very important to me and, I am sure, to others like Mr. Ahern that we had representation from Northern Ireland on both the development board and the board itself so that it would be an all-Ireland hospital.  How does Mr. Ahern feel it might impact on that?  </p><p>Mr. Ahern alluded to pension rights and social welfare rights.  The arrangements we have historically with the UK ensure that its citizens who fall ill here and need to see their GP are covered under our medical card scheme and <i>vice versa</i>.  Obviously, this will need to be addressed and looked at.  </p><p>I think Senator Paul Daly mentioned giving more to the UK during the negotiations and whether the EU have done that.  I come at it from the other side and, following Mr. John Bruton's contribution, wonder whether the UK will come to take a different view as the realisation dawns of the full impact of this decision to leave with all the consequences for the day-to-day lives of people in Northern Ireland and Great Britain, as well as the complications for business, employment and their exchange rate.  What is Mr. Ahern's view on this?  </p><p>I will finish on a positive note because although it is important that we highlight all the problems and challenges, we also need to look for all the opportunities.  In the context of his local knowledge of the Border area and international experience, could Mr. Ahern tell us where opportunities we can exploit might lie?  </p><p>In respect of North-South co-operation and the Good Friday Agreement, I agree with Mr. Ahern that there are huge opportunities for those British-Irish Council ministerial meetings to explore and deal with many of the problems.  I welcome his idea that we should have an interactive website so that the ordinary man and woman on the street can highlight the issues as they see them and reduce the number of unknown unknowns.  This is a very good idea that should be taken on board.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#Q00300"><p>I thank colleagues for all those contributions and questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Dermot Ahern" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#Q00400"><p>I thank the Senators for their questions.  Senator Boyhan raised the issue of two for and two against in the UK.  I cannot really say.  To be honest, I do not think views expressed by me in that respect will change anything.  It is what it is.  Some Senators asked whether there would be a rethink.  I do not think we can even proceed on the basis that we are hoping that the voters will be given an opportunity to rethink.  We just have to continue on the basis that this is going to happen.  There will be adverse implications for all of us, including north, south and east.</p> <p>  In respect of red line issues, I do not think we should be adamant about anything, particularly when we are negotiating within a bloc of 27 states.  What I would say is that we should be very strong and put Ireland first in any of our negotiations.  I will not go as far as to say that we should reserve our position, although that would be a knee-jerk reaction to the situation where we are clearly going to be the worst affected across the EU.  We must accept the bona fides of the people with whom we want to continue to be members of the EU.  If there is any red line issue relating to the negotiations, it must be any adverse implications for the Good Friday Agreement.  At the beginning of my presentation, I spoke about the three-way relationships.  I always used to say that the Good Friday Agreement is only as good as the paper it is written on.  What is really important is the type of relationships built up between people North and South from an economic and societal perspective.  I said to a Senator over a cup of coffee earlier that one of the most embarrassing meetings I had when I was a Minister was when a group of clearly Unionist businesspeople came to me in this complex to talk about energy and the need for an all-island electricity market.  They were decrying the fact that things were not happening quickly enough and they were coming to me to lobby to make sure the Irish Government did its damnedest to promote that.  This is why in any discussions with Unionist politicians, particularly the DUP, I would tell them that we were never going to agree on the issue of the Border and the constitutional issue, and the Good Friday Agreement in effect parks that anyway, but that we should get on with the all-island aspect - all-island, not all-Ireland - across all the sectors.  One finds common cause with these people.</p><p>At the end of the day, they are representatives who are responding to their communities.  They want issues sorted out at a micro level.  As I stated in respect of electricity, it makes no sense that we had two separate grids on the island of Ireland.  It makes no sense that on the island of Ireland we have separate telecommunications.  These were the specialties I was involved with, other than some of the more high-profile ones in the Department of Foreign Affairs and so on.  It went right through into those Ministries, particularly in the Department of Foreign Affairs.  I maintain that right across, whether it was health, tourism, education, telecommunications or energy, there is so much commonality between us that we should get on with pooling our resources.</p><p> Unfortunately, whether we like it or not, there is Brexit.  Whoever devised it - reference was made to Mr. Cameron going over to Brussels and not getting a good deal and all of that - I cannot say because I was not around at that time.  The former Minister, Senator McDowell, may well confirm this but when I went to Brussels, I very rarely came across a British representative of any political party who was favourable to Europe.  There were a few exceptions.  Tony Blair was extremely European in his outlook but I would be hard pressed to name others - maybe Douglas Alexander, I remember.  Indeed, Theresa May was my opposite number when I was in the then Department of Justice and Law Reform and I cannot remember ever having a conversation with her about the EU.  Generally speaking, I cannot remember the UK representatives who I met, both when I went to the UK and when they came here and when I went to the EU, ever being enthusiastic about the EU project.  It was always, "We are paying in more than we are getting out."  In my earlier years, when I was a member of the then British-Irish Inter-Parliamentary Body, it used really grate when some of the membership, who were very friendly to us, used to come and say, "Oh, we are coming over to see how our roads are getting on, how you are developing our roads with our money".  They were decrying the fact that we were a net beneficiary and they were a net contributor, while forgetting about the original aspect of the European project, which was to bring peace and to stop countries fighting on the fields of Europe.  While dealing with it across a table, there was a transfer of funds to bring all the nations up.  Thankfully, we are now a net contributor, as are many of what were net beneficiaries.  From that point of view, the British people were fed on decades of negativity and by putting something to a referendum in that respect, in my view, the result was always going to be negative.  I would not be optimistic that this matter will be turned around quickly and I believe we have to get on with it and put our best foot forward in the negotiations, both within the European Union and with the United Kingdom.</p><p> Senator Paul Daly mentioned the currency fluctuations.  Those of us from the Border areas have dealt with those over the years.  They have been an added difficulty for us.  People will get on with their lives and will deal with whatever is thrown up.  Despite the difficulties, one will not stop the transfer of people, whether they come for the horse racing in the fine horse racing stadium that we have in Dundalk or for something else.  The Senator is correct in that at least 50% of the patrons there every week are from the North.  They are great betters and they bet with sterling.  Those traditions will continue.</p><p> As I said, what I try to focus on - one could get bogged down in the macro issues of the European institutions - and what we need to be aware of are the micro issues, in that these are the issues that ultimately will affect ordinary people in their daily and business lives and small businesses on the island, North and South.</p><p> Senator Mark Daly referred to the aspect of a united Ireland.  The issues are too complex to even visualise that but I think we need to make some provision for the possible entry at some stage of the North into the European Union similar to the way in which it was done in Germany.  I do not give in to this issue a Border poll, even though I would love to see it successful.  It is far too early for that, to a certain extent.  I was telling Senator Daly that, not my maiden speech in Leinster House in 1987 but in my second speech as a young backbencher, I spoke on the issue of the Troubles at that time and I referred to the fact that there is a body of opinion which says that, eventually, the Catholics will outbreed the Protestants, and I had occasion to look back on that speech, find it - in fact, in the archives of Leinster House - and look at it.  I decried the whole issue of 50% plus one, which is now enshrined in the Good Friday Agreement, that is, basically, when 50% plus one of the population in Northern Ireland wants a united Ireland that will happen.  I stated in that speech that long before that will happen, we must have an accommodation and an understanding with the Unionist tradition on this island because we cannot force them by dint of numbers into a united Ireland.  That is why, in all of my political career, I focused on all-island initiatives in order to show those people who do not necessarily agree with the issue of a Northern Ireland that it is necessary we live on this island.  As John Hume said, it is not uniting the territories of Ireland; it is uniting the people who live on the territories of Ireland.  I very much subscribe to that.</p><p> Senator McDowell referred to the issue of a common trading area and a customs regime.  I was first elected in 1987.  The day of my second election, in June 1989, was a lovely day and I tried to get out to some of the polling booths to see how things were going close to the Border.  I could not get out of the town of Dundalk.  There was at least a five or six mile tailback of lorries and cars stuck at the Border, backing up right into the town of Dundalk.  I had to give up.  I could not visit the polling booths on election day out at the Border.  Literally overnight, particularly with the passing of the Single European Act subsequently, or in and around that time, those checkpoints disappeared.  Much more than the military installations that were across the Border which caused obvious difficulty to people traversing the Border, the customs regime was debilitating to the economic development of our area.  I would love to see the European Union agreeing to some sort of special arrangement, a special economic area within the island of Ireland, to deal with our difficulties.  I am not particularly sure, given my experience, that the EU would allow something like that, but I would say we should ask for it.  I would not be particularly hopeful.  One will find that there is some other area in Europe which has a similar problem and it will want similar arrangements, and of course once one gets into that at a negotiation with 27 around the table one is back to square one.  That is not to say that we should not continue with asking for that if there are examples such as East Germany in that respect.  Without being overly cynical about it, I have seen circumstances - we all have seen one of the most high-profile circumstances - where the strength of a small nation within the European Union was evident.  I am a supporter of the European Union but my support for it has been somewhat dented in the last number of years.</p><p>When we voted "No" in a referendum on a treaty, we were told to be good little boys and girls and vote again whereas when the French and Dutch voted "No", the reaction was that they were founding members of the European Union, so what was wrong?  They were not told to go back and vote again on the same thing.  That is why I have some cynicism about the negotiation sphere in Europe and the difficult we have as a nation in putting our best foot forward in regard to having our position clearly articulated as a key priority of the EU.  There are reports everything will be pretty good in the conclusions next Saturday, and I hope that will be the case.  Ultimately, I hope that will be the case also in the final hard negotiations.</p><p> I was involved in negotiations on the marine in Brussels which went on for 48 hours.  We got no sleep and I understood how at the very end of negotiations people would give in to anything because they were so tired.  In 2005, when I was Minister for Foreign Affairs, I had to console the Cypriot Minister, a man in his 70s, who was in tears after he, as representative of his country, was, in effect, forced, because he was the only one holding up the agreement, to agree to accession talks on the possibility of Turkey joining the European Union.  There was so much pressure on that poor man.  He told me he did not want to go home because he would have to face his people but, ultimately, he had to agree.  That is why I say that at negotiation level, we need to be very strong and to insist that nothing is agreed until everything is agreed.</p><p> On smuggling, some people might say I am overstating the issue because smuggling has gone on despite the North and the UK being in the European Union but the avenues for smuggling have been substantially reduced.  However, they have not obliterated because when there is criminality, people will always look for new outlets.  Once there is a border of some sort, in particular a customs border, I fear we will be back to the bad old days of smuggling and it will give new avenues to criminals to exploit.</p><p> Senator Reilly referred to the area of health, which is close to my heart.  For many years we have spoken about cross-Border health initiatives.  Some have worked and others have not but I believe Brexit will slow down those initiatives and make it more difficult for people on the ground.  That is not only in health but in every area, especially in tourism.</p><p> Will opportunities come from this?  Yes, there will be opportunities.  Recently, a company from Craigavon announced it had set up in Dundalk.  It wants an EU presence.  That is great but it is robbing Peter to pay Paul within this island, and I do not think that is good.  I understand its decision and we will be cheering in Dundalk when the jobs are there but those jobs are not going to Northern Ireland, which, as Senator McDowell mentioned, has a less robust economy that is much more reliant on the UK crown, which was referred to earlier.  I think I have answered all the questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/WUS2017042700002#S00200"><p>Mr. Ahern has covered them in great detail.  It is wonderful to be able to draw on Mr. Ahern's many years of experience and personal knowledge of the Border.  I thank him for making his submission.  It is vitally important to our ongoing work.  This committee will only meet for another six weeks.  It will not meeting for too long.  Again, I thank Mr. Ahern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-04-27a.48" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.55 p.m. and resumed at 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>