<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.2" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" url="">Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.3" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 18:40</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Heather Humphreys (Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation), Deputy James Lawless, Deputy Lisa Chambers, Deputy Tom Neville, Deputy Billy Kelleher, Deputy Maurice Quinlivan.</p><p>DEPUTY MARY BUTLER IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.4" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#A00100">Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) (No.2) Bill 2018: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#A00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, and her officials.  Before we begin, I ask members to switch their phones onto flight mode as it is not enough to keep them on silent as that interferes with the recording equipment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.6" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 7, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.7" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>SECTION 8</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#B00200"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 6, lines 6 and 7, to delete &ldquo;may, in its discretion&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>There have been parliamentary debates for years on the difference between &quot;shall&quot; and &quot;may&quot;.  Our intention is to ensure there is an obligation on the judicial system to sanction in some way persons who do not co-operate with the system.  While I accept the Minister's argument that it would interfere with the independence of the Judiciary, I would like to hear why she cannot accept the amendment.  </p><p>We are trying to send a message that people must be more co-operative with the system itself, which was set up to ensure there would be a seamless, less adversarial and less costly system in place.  As I said, there should be some sanction for people who do no contribute in a co-operative way to the system when they assess damages or make their case.  We made the point in the D&aacute;il earlier during parliamentary questions that there seems to be no sanction for people who engage in a process to scam people, fraudulently secure money by false means, present false evidence to courts, lie under oath or view the system as an opportunity for scams.  In my role as spokesperson in this area, I will seek to ensure measures are put forward that oblige the Judiciary, the prosecution services and the investigative services to be as hard as possible on persons who are non-co-operative or who use the system in an abusive way to secure funds through fraudulent means or the pretence of being injured.  That is the purpose of the amendment but if the Minister can convince me otherwise, I will revisit it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#B00300"><p>I understand what the Deputy seeks to achieve.  The effect of the amendment is to remove the discretion of the court as to what order it may make on what costs, if any, it will allow a claimant or respondent, taking into account the failure by the claimant or respondent to comply or submit in the manner specified in subsection (1).  It raises constitutional concerns because it would cut across the constitutional principle of the separation of powers and the discretion of the courts to make an order for costs.</p> <p>  Section 8(1) lists the circumstances under which the court can consider an adverse costs order: where the assessors have requested the claimant under section 23(1) to furnish additional information or documents relating to his or her claim for special damages and the claimant has not complied with the request; where the assessors have requested the respondent or respondents under section 23(2) to furnish additional information or documents and the respondent or respondents have not complied with the request; where the assessors have requested the claimant or respondent or respondents under section 23(4) to assist or co-operate with retained experts, and the claimant or respondent or respondents have not complied with that request; or where the assessor has requested the claimant to submit himself or herself to a medical examination arranged by the Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB, and the claimant has not submitted himself or herself to the medical examination.</p> <p>  The section provides that the court may order certain matters, taking into account the failure to comply or submit in the manner specified in subsection (1).   The word "may" in the section refers to the order a court may make on what costs, if any, it will allow a claimant or a respondent.  The making of an order is, and must remain, a discretionary matter for the judge.  The court must take the matters referred to in subsection (1) into account when deciding on whether to make an order.</p> <p>  When the general scheme of the Bill was published in June 2017, it was proposed under head 7 that a court shall have regard to the failure to respond to a request for further information, documents or medical reports in determining the admissibility of evidence in subsequent proceedings and that a court shall have regard to a failure to attend an independent medical examination in determining what medical evidence is admissible in the court case.  </p> <p>  The Bill was drafted in consultation with the Office of the Attorney General, which was involved directly in the wording of the section.  It was decided that a proposal to limit a court's discretion as to the admissibility of evidence would raise constitutional issues because it would cut across the constitutional principle of the separation of powers.  It is the function of the court and the constitutional duty of a judge to hear all the available evidence, arrive at a decision on foot of that evidence and determine issues of liability and quantum.  Furthermore, the plaintiff has a right to tender evidence before the courts.  The court must retain discretion in any given case to ensure constitutional rights are vindicated and fair procedures are followed.  By providing for potential financial consequences to be applied for non-compliance with requests by PIAB assessors, the section, as drafted, should have the desired effect to change behaviour and encourage parties to adhere to the requirements set out in the Act.</p> <p>  For the reasons I outlined, I ask the Deputy to withdraw his amendment because I cannot support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#B00400"><p>I asked a question in the D&aacute;il earlier about the Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy's, proposals to bring forward next year a constitutional referendum to allow for a cap on awards.  It gives an indication that this Government is not always in favour of the autonomy and independence of the Judiciary.  I am not trying to hamstring the Judiciary into having to do something but rather ensure it must, at the least, take into account the non-co-operation of a claimant, which is the purpose of the amendment.</p> <p>  The Minister said it runs contrary to the advice of the Attorney General because it would be in breach of the separation of powers, a principle I support, although the Minister of State may not.  I will, therefore, withdraw the amendment, reserving my entitlement to reintroduce it on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.11" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#B00600"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 6, to delete lines 23 and 24 and substitute the following: &quot;(2) The amendment effected by subsection (1) shall apply to &mdash; <blockquote>(a) an application under section 11 of the Principal Act made on or after the date on which this section comes into operation, and <br /><br />(b) an application under section 11 of the Principal Act made before the date on which this section comes into operation, where &mdash; <blockquote>(i) the assessors have not, before that date, requested the claimant to furnish to them additional information or documents pursuant to section 23(1) of the Principal Act, <br /><br />(ii) the assessors have not, before that date, requested the respondent or respondents to furnish to them additional information or documents pursuant to section 23(2) of the Principal Act, <br /><br />(iii) the assessors have not, before that date, requested the claimant or the respondent or respondents to provide assistance to retained experts or furnish information or documents or co-operate with those experts pursuant to section 23(4) of the Principal Act, or <br /><br />(iv) the assessors have not, before that date, requested the claimant to submit himself or herself to a medical examination pursuant to section 24(2) of the Principal Act.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>The purpose of the amendment is to delete section (8)(2) and substitute a new subsection.  Section 8 applies to applications made to PIAB on and after the enactment of the section, and applications made to the PIAB on enactment of the section where the assessors have not requested information or documents from the claimant, respondent or respondents regarding special damages, or where the claimant, respondent or respondents have not been requested by the assessors to co-operate or assist retained experts or where the claimant has not been asked by the assessors to submit himself or herself for a medical examination arranged by PIAB.</p><p>The amendment was drafted by the Parliamentary Counsel in consultation with the Office of the Attorney General.  I am conscious that where the State sets up a system where people&rsquo;s rights are engaged, it is critical that the procedural and administrative system is clear and transparent.  People need to know what they are and are not required to do.  The amendment makes clear the applications that will be covered by the section on commencement of the legislation.  It is important that claimants fully co-operate with the PIAB process to maximise the model and ensure as many claims as possible are settled in a timely, cost-effective manner.</p><p>This Bill will cover all the new claims and any claims that are in the system, subject to the circumstances that I have just described.  We are trying to capture as many as we can with the new legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.14" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.15" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Section 8, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.16" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.17" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 9 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C00600"><p>From what I can remember of the first reading of the Bill, the book of quantum was to be reviewed every five years, but this has been amended to a review every three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C00700"><p>Yes.  It will be reviewed every three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C00800"><p>In the context of discussions arising from parliamentary questions, we raised the possibility of comparing awards with those made in other common law countries.  We were told at the time that the awards made in Ireland could not be compared with those made in other countries.  I would like an explanation as to why we cannot benchmark the awards made in Ireland across the norms.  We benchmark the cost of medicines in Ireland with the cost of the same medicines in OECD countries.  In the context of personal injuries, we would want to draw a comparison of awards in Ireland with those in common law jurisdictions.</p><p>I make this point because the awards made in our nearest neighbouring country, which has a similar legal system, are much lower.  For example, the award for whiplash in the UK is about &pound;4,000 compared with a figure of &euro;20,000.  I know that we have a problem when it comes to awards <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>other countries.  I wonder at the reason for the great difference in the level of awards.  I would like to see an explanation in the review of the book of quantum as to how a particular figure is arrived at.  It is fine to publish the details as to what awards should be for various injuries, but there must be some broader assessment as to why a specific figure is arrived at as opposed to the arbitrary announcement that an amount should be paid out when a person suffers a personal injury.  The people as well as the Judiciary have a difficulty with the large disparity between awards across jurisdictions.</p><p>The book of quantum will be a discretionary tool for the Judiciary.  There needs to be research and analysis and a broad assessment of the figures that are awarded for specific injuries.  This is an important point and goes beyond the scope of this Bill.  The Judicial Council Bill 2017 is under consideration, which will in effect take its potential instructions from the Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB, in terms of assessing awards.  I am led to believe that PIAB will assist the Judicial Council in assessing what should be the broad benchmark.  I would appreciate clarity on section 9 in respect of a benchmark which is not self-explanatory in terms of advising and helping the proposed Judicial Council</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C00900"><p>PIAB has offered to help the Judicial Council, but it will be up to the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, to deal with this during the passage of the Judicial Council Bill 2017.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C01000"><p>Would it not be up to Parliament?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C01100"><p>Yes, it will be up to the Parliament to decide.  It will probably be up to the Judicial Council to decide when it has the power to do so.</p> <p>  At the time of the publication of the Bill, the second and final report of the Personal Injuries Commission had not been published.  This report was subsequently published on 18 September 2018 and a key recommendation of the report was that the Judicial Council, when established, should be requested by the Minister for Justice and Equality to compile guidelines for appropriate general damages for various types of personal injury.  When the judicial guidelines are in place, it is intended that they will supersede the book of quantum.  The intention for the future is that the Judicial Council will take ownership of the judicial guidelines for personal injury compensation and it will recalibrate them when it considers it necessary.  That should be better because the Judicial Council can change it easily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.24" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.25" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Section 10 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.26" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>SECTION 11</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.27" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 11 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C01600"><p>I am opposing this section.  Section 11 seeks to reconstitute the nomination process to the board of PIAB.  As it stands, two members of the board are nominated by the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU, one person is nominated by IBEC, and one person by the Irish Insurance Federation or any successor of it.  The proposed change contained in section 11 would remove the power of ICTU to nominate two people to the board and replace it with one nomination from Insurance Ireland and one nomination from the Central Bank.  The balance of the two nominations from ICTU and one from IBEC reflects injured parties and premium paying policyholders who should be the principal stakeholders in PIAB.  I do not see the need for the composition of the board to change in this way and I think it would affect the balance on the board.  Therefore, we are opposing section 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#C01700"><p>Section 11 amends the composition of the board of PIAB in line with Government policy to have more board members appointed through the Public Appointments Service, PAS.  Section 11 removes ICTU and IBEC as bodies designated under the Bill to nominate members to the board.</p> <p>  As I mentioned during the Second Stage debate, it will be open to members of ICTU or IBEC to apply through the PAS process when vacancies arise.  Seeking expressions of interest for board appointments through the PAS process allows for appointments to be made from a greater number of potential candidates with the desired skill sets, which can vary over time, depending on the skills available to the board.  Board members are appointed as individuals by the Minister where, in the opinion of the Minister, they have the expertise in a field relevant to the board's functions.</p> <p>  The code of practice for the governance of State bodies published in 2016 provides that board members should have the appropriate skills and knowledge appropriate to the activities of the State body to enable them to discharge their duties and responsibilities effectively.  The code of practice also requires that, in determining the criteria for board vacancies, the Minister consult the chairperson of the board to identify the appropriate and collective mix of experience, knowledge and skills required to oversee the board's performance of its functions successfully.  All applicants who meet the criteria may apply to PAS and be assessed.  Corporate governance standards require that the board members act in good faith and in the best interests of the State body.  The duty of the board member is owed to the agency and not to any specific stakeholder.</p> <p>  Under the Bill, it was proposed that five board positions would be filled through PAS, through open advertisement operated by PAS, which since 2014 has been responsible for putting in place an open, accessible, rigorous and transparent system to support Ministers in making appointments to State boards.</p> <p>  I wish to clarify for the Deputy that the current board consists of a Chairperson, the chief executive of PIAB, and nine ordinary members, of whom six are nominated by external bodies designated under legislation.  The Minister normally nominates a senior departmental official to the board.  The external bodies are as follows: two persons nominated by ICTU, one person nominated by IBEC, one person nominated by the Irish Insurance Federation, one person nominated by the Central Bank, and one person nominated by the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission.</p><p>Under the Bill, it is proposed that the five positions will be filled through the Public Appointments Service, PAS.</p><p> When the board was established social partnership was in place.  The chair of the board, along with the two board members appointed via PAS, decide what skill set is needed.  It is for that reason they will have the flexibility to appoint or recommend an appointment of people with different skill sets.  </p><p> For the reasons I have outlined I ask the Deputy to withdraw his opposition to section 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00200"><p>I appreciate the Minister's response but she has not addressed the fact that IBEC will lose two seats on the board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00300"><p>ICTU will lose two seats and IBEC will lose one seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00400"><p>Yes, I apologise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00500"><p>Insurance Ireland can still nominate somebody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00600"><p>I am concerned that the proposal makes the board more corporate Ireland because Insurance Ireland, the Central Bank and another entity will have a nomination each but ICTU loses two places and IBEC loses one place.  If there is no support for my proposal then I shall withdraw my opposition with the proviso that----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00700"><p>As other members wish to comment, the Deputy can come back in afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D00900"><p>To follow up, it is open to them to apply through the PAS system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01000"><p>I wish to understand the amendment in order to assess it and then in turn understand Deputy Quinlivan's opposition to it to enable me to adopt a balanced view on what might be the right course of action.  We must be careful not to be overly prescriptive about these boards.  Sometimes we can get into the habit of saying there must a representative from "X" sector, "Y" sector, the voluntary sector, the business sector, the corporate sector and the regulatory sector and then, before one knows it, there are 20 people on a board and we start asking why the board is so big and suggesting that something be done to reduce its size.  One can become trapped in that mindset.</p> <p>  I am unfamiliar with the original composition of the board.  Deputy Quinlivan has said that ICTU and IBEC almost mark each other on the board.  I understand why IBEC would be on the board.  Part of the reason that we seek reform is to reduce the cost to business and make insurance more affordable.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01100"><p>I wish to clarify that ICTU can nominate two persons and IBEC can nominate one person.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1323" speakername="James Lawless" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01200"><p>I am not entirely clear but I am open to discussing the specialist knowledge that ICTU could bring to bear on personal injuries awards.  I can see the benefit of including representatives of the Irish Patients Association and there might be other associations.  It is not obvious to me why trade unions should be included.  Trade union members are not the only people who slip and fall coming out of a shop.  Maybe there is a particular focus on employee and employer injuries but I believe that the PIAB is far more wide reaching.  The inclusion of ICTU and IBEC strikes me as a hangover from the days of social partnership, which the Minister mentioned.  The inclusion of the social partners and every board going was in vogue when PIAB was originally established ten or 15 years ago.  The inclusion of ICTU and IBEC may no longer be appropriate but I am open to persuasion.  I remain unconvinced that we should continue with something just because we always did it like that.  Perhaps the board needs a different composition but I suggest that we do not make it too big or too prescriptive.  The Minister seemed to say that it is open to all parties and none to nominate people, and if they pass the test and get on the board then so be it.  Her suggestion has a lot of merit but I am open to persuasion about nominations.  I would like to understand the issue a bit more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01300"><p>How many members are entitled to be on the committee through the PAS system?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01400"><p>The board is comprised of 11 people in total.  I suggest that we have three nominations, with one person nominated by Insurance Ireland, one person nominated by the Central Bank and one person nominated by the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission.  The Minister also normally nominates a senior departmental official to the board, which brings the number to four.  Therefore, seven positions remain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01500"><p>How will the remainder be appointed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01600"><p>They will be appointed via PAS.  The chairperson, in conjunction with whomsoever sits on the PAS board, would consider the skill set needed.</p> <p>  Corporate governance standards require that board members act in good faith and in the best interests of the State body.  The duty of the board member is owed to the agency and not to any specific stakeholder.  That is what we are trying to achieve with the provision.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01700"><p>Do any members wish to comment further?  No.  I call Deputy Quinlivan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01800"><p>It is not simply a case that we want ICTU to be included in order to represent trade union members.  That is not what we are about at all.  There has been a lot of talk about fraud and people making false claims.  We all agree that has happened and we want to deal with the issue.  We must also remember that people do get injured and they must be compensated.  We want to make sure that someone speaks on their behalf and ICTU could be that voice.  That is why we oppose the section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D01900"><p>The assessors in any of these situations are independent from the board.  The board acts as an oversight for the agency and makes sure that it fulfils it functions.  The Central Bank operates both a regulatory function and consumer protection function, and brings experience of both aspects to the corporate governance of the board.  That is why we have the Central Bank on it.  The Competition and Consumer Protection Commission brings its financial management and information function to the corporate governance of the board, as well as its consumer welfare knowledge.  I believe it is important that the Central Bank and the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission are designated because they bring that experience and aspect to the board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D02000"><p>The Deputy can consider this matter again on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D02100"><p>I am happy to withdraw my opposition to the section and I may restate my opposition on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D02200"><p>Deputy Quinlivan may oppose section 11 on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.52" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.53" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Section 12 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.54" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>SECTION 13</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.55" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 13 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D02700"><p>My party opposes section 13 in its entirety.  This section seeks to give the Minister power to take the financial reserves of PIAB, which currently stands at &euro;19 million.  I oppose the change as PIAB has built up the reserve over years, since its establishment, by continually re-engineering efficient processes and fighting judicial reviews by vested interests.  This money was collected for the purpose of assessing injury claims, as provided for under legislation, and for no other purpose.  Perhaps the reserve should go back to the policyholders who paid it in either directly or through their insurance premiums, which has already happened to an extent.  For example, the fixed fee for an assessment has reduced from &euro;1,500 in 2004 to &euro;600 currently for respondents and their insurers.  In addition, the Exchequer has been repaid a loan of &euro;5 million for set-up costs.  PIAB has been very successful in being self-funding and the reserve gives the board a certain degree of independence.  I do not believe it would benefit PIAB if the reserves were taken.  It is for those reasons that we oppose section 13.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#D02800"><p>Section 13 inserts a new section 74A into the 2003 Act.  The Comptroller and Auditor General recommended to the Department that the Department and the board agree an appropriate level of revenue reserves to be retained by PIAB and the basis for holding such a reserve.  The Comptroller and Auditor General also recommended the introduction of appropriate legislation to deal with excess funds held by PIAB.  Legal advice obtained by the Department is to the effect that legislative change is required to enable the board to remit excess moneys to the Exchequer.</p> <p>  The proposed amendment at section 13 of the Bill implements the recommendation from the Comptroller and Auditor General.  It provides for a reserves policy for PIAB.  It also provides that PIAB shall remit to the Minister, for the benefit of the Exchequer, any moneys in excess of those authorised to be retained by the Minister, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  The Bill specifically provides that the Minister will have regard to the operational, capital and contingency costs of PIAB when determining the sum to be retained.</p> <p>  In 2011, PIAB refunded its establishment costs of &euro;6.9 million to the Exchequer.  PIAB is independent in the exercise of its statutory functions and the Minister is not permitted in his or her executive function to interfere in any way with the day-to-day operations and functions of PIAB.</p><p>Section 74 of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board Act 2003 provides a role for the Minister in the provision of funds to the Personal Injuries Assessment Board, PIAB.  On the basis that this section implements a recommendation of the Comptroller and Auditor General, as I outlined, I ask the Deputy to withdraw his opposition to section 13.<font color="#FF0000"></font></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1229" speakername="Billy Kelleher" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E00100"><p>We may need to revisit this matter on Report Stage.  I have not tabled an amendment but I would like to get some clarity.  While our concerns do not apply to the current Minister, a future Minister may not be as supportive of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board as the current Minister.  Similarly, a future Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform may not be supportive of PIAB.  From my reading of the legislation it will be a matter for the Minister, in discussions with the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation, to decide what are appropriate funds for the running of PIAB, both to meet operational and capital costs.  I am aware that the Comptroller and Auditor General has made a report.  We certainly do not want to have millions of euro in public funds not being used in a fitting manner and there should be remittance to the Exchequer.</p> <p>  Who evaluates the cost of running PIAB and ensuring it can operate in a manner we hope it will operate?  I make this point in view of the fact that in the event of a downturn, public expenditure could be cut without any real evaluation being done of the impact such a cut would have on the capital investment PIAB requires to operate over a period of time.  Should we accept that there may be a role for some form of independent evaluation of the funding required annually for the purposes of running PIAB, both in current and capital costs?  Beyond this, there would then be a remittance to the Exchequer?</p> <p>  The summary account of a report by the Office for the Director of Corporate Enforcement discussed in the D&aacute;il today is a case in point.  We all know that the reason the office did not function was that it was starved of resources.  We need to have some independent evaluation as to what is required to run an entity.  Assuming always that the Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform is the person responsible for public funds, it would be reasonable to provide for an independent evaluation to be carried out to determine how much funding PIAB would need to operate and the funding threshold below which the board would be unable to guarantee a service.</p> <p>  We may revisit this section on Report Stage to ascertain whether we can provide for an independent assessment that would determine how much funding would be needed to ensure PIAB can function, both in terms of current expenditure and capital investment requirements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1327" speakername="Maurice Quinlivan" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E00200"><p>Again, I reserve my position.  We may return to this section.  The reason I want PIAB to retain unspent money is to allow it to do other things.  We are talking of changing the book of quantum every three years and PIAB would require funding for this task.  As Deputy Kelleher said, a future Minister for Finance may decide not to provide the funding needed.  Fees have come down already in recent years and may reduce further.  The reason we want PIAB to retain unspent money is to help it work more efficiently.  I will withdraw my opposition to the section with the proviso that I may oppose it on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E00500"><p>For clarification, the Bill specifically provides that the Minister will have "regard to the operational, capital and contingency costs" of PIAB when determining the sum to be retained.  The Department and PIAB must agree an appropriate level of revenue reserves.  The Comptroller and Auditor General has recommended this.  The funding it requires is also a matter for the PIAB board, which will establish what it needs.  This will be agreed with the Minister of the day.  The Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General, which also audits PIAB, has made this recommendation.  That is why we are following through on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E00600"><p>I thank the Minister.  Deputy Quinlivan has withdrawn his opposition to section 13 and both he and Deputy Kelleher have flagged that they may revisit this matter on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.63" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.64" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Sections 14 and 15 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.65" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.66" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E01200"><p>As the Bill has now completed Committee Stage it is recommended that members submit Report Stage amendments to the Bills Office without delay as Report Stage may be tabled at short notice.  I thank the Minister and her officials for attending today's meeting.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.68" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E01300">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="18:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JES2018120400002#E01400"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 90, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation has completed its consideration of the Personal Injuries Assessment Board (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 and has made an amendment thereto.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.70" nospeaker="true" time="18:40:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 7.25 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Wednesday, 5 December 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.71" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="">Select Committee on Social Protection</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.72" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 13:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy John Brady, Deputy Regina Doherty (Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection), Deputy Joe Carey, Deputy Willie O'Dea. Deputy Joan Collins,</p><p>DEPUTY JOHN CURRAN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.74" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#A00200">Estimates for Public Services 2018<br />Vote 37 - Employment Affairs and Social Protection (Supplementary)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#A00300"><p>As we have a quorum, we will commence in public session.  I remind visitors and members to turn off their mobile phones.  This meeting has been convened to consider the Supplementary Estimate for Vote 37 - Employment Affairs and Social Protection, which was referred by the D&aacute;il to this Select Committee on 21 November 2018.  I welcome the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, and her officials and thank them for the briefing material provided, which has been circulated to members.</p> <p>  Before we commence, I must dispense with one housekeeping item.</p><p>Two sets of imeachta&iacute; were circulated to members, those relating to Committee Stage of the Employment (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2017, which we considered on 17 May 2018, and those relating to Committee Stage of the Social Welfare Pensions and Civil Registration Bill 2018, which we considered on 22 November 2018.  Are they agreed?  Agreed.</p><p> I propose that the following arrangements apply: the Minister will be asked to make a brief statement to the committee and after that members will have an opportunity to raise any issues.  I remind members that, in accordance with Standing Orders, discussion should be confined to the items constituting the Supplementary Estimate, which are: subhead A1 - administration - pay; A2 - administration - non-pay; A3 - State pension non-contributory; A4 - jobseeker's allowance; A5 - one-parent family payment; A6 - widows' and widowers' pension non-contributory; A7 - deserted wife's allowance; A8 - basic supplementary welfare allowance; A10 - exceptional and urgent needs; A11 - other working age supports; A12 - community employment programme; A13 - rural social scheme; A14 - T&Uacute;S; A15 - job initiative; A16 - back to work enterprise allowance; A17 - youth employment support scheme; A18 - back to education; A19, gateway; A20 back to work family dividend; A21 - JobsPlus; A22 - wage subsidy scheme; A23 - other working age employment supports; A24 - disability allowance; A26 - carer's allowance; A27 - domiciliary care allowance; A28 - carer's support grant; A 30 - child benefit; A31 - working family payment; A32 - back to school clothing and footwear; A33 - school meals; A34 - other child-related payments; A35 - rent supplement; A37 - household benefits package; A38 - free travel; A39 - fuel allowance; A40 - grant to the Citizens Information Board; and A41 - miscellaneous appropriations-in-aid.  Members should please indicate the subhead to which they are referring when contributing.  </p><p> I invite the Minister to make her opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#B00200"><p>I thank the committee for the opportunity to present a Supplementary Estimate for the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  I am seeking a Supplementary Estimate of &euro;139 million for 2018.  Primarily, the purpose of the Supplementary Estimate is to fund the Christmas bonus for Vote 37 social assistance recipients.  The Christmas bonus will be paid this week.  For the first time in many years, it is being paid at 100%, which we all very much welcome.  It is being paid over the course of this week to approximately 1.2 million customers.  The bonus is a welcome contribution for people in receipt of long-term social welfare payments in the run-up to Christmas - because it finds its way into communities, local businesses and economies - and for families and individuals to allow them to prepare for the festive season, which is its overall aim.</p> <p>  The Christmas bonus is estimated to cost approximately &euro;266 million.  This cost is broken down into just over &euro;120 million for Vote 37 recipients and nearly &euro;146 million for Social Insurance Fund recipients.  The Social Insurance Fund is providing for the cost of the bonus being paid to people on contributory payments such as the State pension contributory, invalidity pension, and so on.  Accordingly, this element of the bonus does not impact in any way on this Supplementary Estimate application.  The Social Insurance Fund is in surplus this year.  In contrast, the bonus paid to people in receipt of payments from Voted schemes is met entirely by the Exchequer.  The bonus is not included in the original Estimates for the Department and, unless savings are made that will meet the entire cost, a Supplementary Estimate is required in order to ensure that the bonus will be paid.</p> <p>  The Chairman suggested at a previous meeting that it is difficult to compare like with like when comparing the original Estimate with the Supplementary Estimate because of the inclusion of the bonus in the outturn position for the relevant schemes.  For this reason, I have included an additional table, beginning at page 3 of the committee's brief, which shows the variance before the bonus is paid and the effect of the bonus on the outturn position.  I hope the committee finds this approach helpful.</p> <p>  The income from pay-related social insurance, PRSI, receipts during 2018 will result in a Social Insurance Fund income of an estimated &euro;10.6 billion.  This will be &euro;252 million or 2.4% ahead of profile for this year and will be &euro;793 million or 8.1% ahead of the position in 2017.  This position is a reflection of the continuing improvement in employment levels in the economy and continues the welcome trend that I presented to the committee here last year.</p> <p>  Expenditure on Social Insurance Fund schemes and administration, including payment of the Christmas bonus, is expected to cost approximately &euro;9.5 billion.</p><p>This is &euro;187.6 million, or 2% above profile, and &euro;145.5 million of this is due to the payment of that Christmas bonus.  Even with the payment of the Christmas bonus to social insurance schemes, the surplus of the fund is still expected to be around &euro;1.1 billion at the end of 2018.  The accumulated surplus in the fund at the end of the year is estimated at &euro;2.32 billion.  While all of this is good news, and it is welcome to see the social insurance fund in such a healthy state, it is worth noting that the fund was also running a significant surplus of &euro;3.6 billion at the end of 2007, but that surplus was exhausted by 2010 when Exchequer subvention was again required because of the economic climate of the time.</p><p> The overall expenditure of the Department's schemes, services and administration in 2018 is expected to be &euro;20.33 billion and this will be &euro;320 million, or 1.6%, more than provided for in the original 2018 Revised Estimates.  As I mentioned earlier, &euro;266 million of this is due to payment of the Christmas bonus.  The total expenditure for the Department, which includes expenditure from the Vote and the social insurance fund, comprises overspends on some schemes and underspends on others.  For example, on the social insurance side there has been higher than anticipated expenditure on treatment benefits, which is very welcome, but lower than expected expenditure on invalidity pension.  On that Vote, there has been higher expenditure on administration and on illness and disability payments but lower expenditure on the working age employment supports.  When taken together, and excluding the Christmas bonus, the Department's expenditure on such schemes and services is expected to be &euro;54 million ahead of the profile, less than 0.3%.</p><p> The live register is expected to average at around 221,300 in 2018, a reduction of over 39,000 on the average for 2017.  Most of the estimated costs of paying the Christmas bonus of &euro;25 million to jobseekers is being offset by an underspend of over &euro;22 million in the jobseeker's allowance allocation.  The ongoing strong performance of the live register is evidence that growth is continuing and that more people are continuing to make the move into employment.  The live register is now well under 200,000, the first time it has been at that level in ten years and the CSO figures that came out this morning are welcome indeed.  We will continue to work with jobseekers to ensure they are adequately prepared to enter the workforce and can benefit from the recovering economy.</p><p> In 2018, the Supplementary Estimate referred to the committee and the briefings provided to committee members list the schemes for which additional sums are being sought, as well as some of our underspends.  We can go through the positions of individual schemes as required by members.  The amount of the Supplementary Estimate is derived by estimating the outturn across all voted schemes, which includes underspends on some schemes and overspends on others and adds in the cost of the Christmas bonus.  Nearly all the Department's expenditure is demand led and, as people apply for income supports when they meet particular circumstances such as ill health or unemployment or when they reach pension age, demographic trends, economic and societal changes and developments in the labour market all play a role in expenditure incurred by our Department.</p><p> Any estimate of expenditure for any scheme for the following year is published in December as part of our annualised Revised Estimates volume.  The individual Estimates are constructed on a scheme by scheme basis using data on trends in recipient numbers, average payment values and other relevant information that is available at the time the Estimate is calculated.  It is appropriate to note that the outturn position of the Department in the absence of the payments of the Christmas bonus would be &euro;20.7 billion, or just 0.3% above our original Estimates.  In this regard, I am satisfied that the Estimates process is working well.  It takes account of all key trends and expenditure patterns and provides an accurate picture of the following year's expenditure.  Trends can and do, however, change over the course of a year, resulting in expenditure being higher or lower than originally provided for.  The actual expenditure on most of our schemes can probably never be precisely predicted and the extent of an overspend or underspend only becomes fully apparent at the end of a year when the outturn of the year has been confirmed.</p><p> I hope my opening statement, along with the briefing material which I sent over yesterday, provides the necessary information to the committee and supports the reasons given for the Supplementary Estimate.  I am happy to take questions from members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister for her opening statement.  I will make two comments before opening up the discussion to members of the committee.  The changes the Minister made to the presentation on pages 3 and 4, showing the figures with the Christmas bonus stripped back, are very useful because they mean we can see exactly what is happening.</p><p>I thank the Minister for that.  It is also worth acknowledging the work of the staff in the Department who are tasked with preparing the Estimates.  As the Minister rightly said, the variance in terms of the output in comparison to the Estimates across most subheads is very small which means that somebody is doing a good job of work.  That being said, I am sure that colleagues will have issues and questions.  In general terms, in the global figures presented there is close correlation between the Estimates and the outturns.  Those working on the figure and the projections have been doing a good job.  </p><p> Deputy O'Dea is first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#D00200"><p>I reiterate what the Chairman has just said.  I also welcome the 100% return of the Christmas bonus, which is made possible by the lower payouts under the jobseeker's allowance and jobseeker's benefit schemes thanks to the increase in the number of people working.  However, that is offset to some extent by increases in payments of illness benefit and so on.  There seems to have been a marked increase in payments under the different disability and illness headings and while I know that all of these things are demand led, I would like the Minister to comment on that.</p><p>On page six of the briefing note there is a payment of &euro;21.3 million for agency services.  I ask the Minister to outline what exactly is involved there.  I note that under the exceptional and urgent needs payments category, the number of such payments is 16,000 over profile, which is a significant number.  While that has been provided for, it indicates that the Department seriously underestimated the demands on that particular fund.  On the other hand, the back to school clothing and footwear allowance is around<b></b>5,000 below profile.  I appreciate and accept that there have been some changes to that scheme around rates and so on but does the Minister have any plans to change or relax the rules?  I have been contacted by a significant number of people who are just on the margin and who do not qualify for the allowance.  There are 3,000 fewer people availing of the school meals scheme and I ask the Minister to explain that.  Spending on community employment is slightly below profile.  I made the point to the Minister in the D&aacute;il last week during Question Time that the rules relating to community employment, CE, schemes should be relaxed.  I do not say that because I want people to spend 12 years on a CE scheme but because some people in their mid to late 50s find it hard to get work and it would be better for them to be doing something.  Furthermore, sometimes it is easier to get a job when one is actually doing something.  On T&uacute;s, I note that the decline in numbers has been reversed and the reason for that is that in most of those community type schemes, increasingly T&uacute;s members are replacing CE participants.  </p><p>Spending on rent supplement is down by &euro;9.5 million.  Does the Minister have any figures for the corresponding increase in spending on the housing assistance payment, HAP?  I know that the latter payment comes from a different Department but it would be useful to have that data to get the total picture in this area.  The back to education allowance payments are 579 over profile.  A report was prepared in recent years on the back to education allowance scheme which indicated that it was not working particularly well and that the results were not very impressive.  On carers, I note that the Minister can make more than &euro;13 million in savings due to the fact that there are 1,300 fewer people qualifying for the carer's allowance.  The figure for the carer's support grant is approximately &euro;2,500, which is surprisingly high.  All of the statistics show that the number of carers in Ireland is gradually increasing.  What I detect from these figures is that because of the rules, a bigger percentage of people who are actually caring are not entitled to the carer's allowance or carer's benefit.  Certain changes have been recommended by the various organisations representing carers that would make quite a significant impact and introduce much needed flexibility into those schemes.  </p><p>The back to work family dividend payments are 541 below profile.  The working family payment, previously known as family income supplement, FIS, is just short of 3,000 below profile.  There were suggestions that a lot of people were not aware of their entitlement to FIS.</p><p>Has any action been taken by the Department to increase awareness of this scheme?</p><p> On illness benefit, I refer to the figures for disability allowance in particular.  Disability allowance is nearly &euro;2.4 million above what was anticipated.  Is there a proposal to employ additional medical assessors in the Department?  If so, how many and at what level and salary scale will they be employed?</p><p> I take it that the increase in treatment benefits is due to the extension of the benefit to those who are self employed.</p><p> On pensions, I noticed that the figure for non-contributory pensions is only up 3%, even taking the actual increase into account and it is something similar for contributory pensions.  Does the Minister have any actual figures on the extra number of pensioners we had to pay over and above last year and over and above the previous year?</p><p> Has the Minister studied the recent Supreme Court decision on pension entitlements for somebody who is incarcerated and what are the implications of that decision for the system?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#E00200"><p>I welcome the Christmas bonus payout of &euro;266 million to 1.2 million needy people.  It has to be warmly welcomed.  It also has to be welcomed from the point of view of the injection of money it brings to local economies because I said it at a previous committee meeting - probably last year's Estimates - how important the Christmas bonus is for individuals and for the local economy because very few, if any of those people will be heading abroad to spend that money.  Every penny of that money will go directly into the local economy.  It is an invaluable injection into businesses and retailers at this time of year.</p> <p>  On the figures and community employment, CE, under heading A12, there is a massive underspend of &euro;7.2 million in 2018.  I went online today and I saw that there are 1,678 vacancies for CE places across the State.  I have said before that this is a serious problem and I will say it again.  I ask the Minister what her views are on why there are so many vacancies on CE schemes across the board.</p> <p>  On heading A31, which is the working family payment, again there is a really large fall in the spending for this.  Could the Minister give additional information on why exactly that is the case?  Has there been a fall in applications or has there been a serious change in people's circumstances which means that they are no longer entitled to the working family payment?  It would be useful if we could get that information.  I appreciate that the Minister might not have all of the information to hand today but it would be useful.</p> <p>  I refer to heading A32, which is on the back to school clothing and footwear allowance.  Again, there is a fall in the number of recipients and the money being paid out for this allowance.  Given the increasing cost of sending a child back to school which is only going up, does the Minister have the actual number of applications that were refused to hand?  I know we have the numbers that were granted and I know that many people do apply and there are many criteria that have to be met.  Does the Minister have the exact figures for how many people have been refused?</p> <p>  I raised it with the Minister that there were a lot of delays in people getting payouts and I know she said that it was because people applied late but that is not the full reason there were late payments.</p><p>People were getting payouts in September and October when kids were long back at school.  There are problems there.  </p><p> The underspend on school meals is a little strange.  The Minister said it is due to a lower uptake from schools.  Is there an explanation for that?  Has she considered that?  Is there a reason schools are not drawing this money down?  It is badly needed and if there is a reason, that needs to be examined.  Will the Minister elaborate on that a bit? </p><p> Under subhead A2, administration non-pay, there is a sum of &euro;4.2 million for "Office Equipment and External IT Services".  Over the past few months, there have been major difficulties with the payout of illness benefit for many thousands of people and it transpired that there were problems with the IT system being rolled out by consultants.  Was some of that money for the roll-out of that system supposed to be for illness benefit or where are those figures to be found?  There are issues in this regard and the Minister said they related to the IT system.  Has that money been paid to consultants for the roll-out of that system, which caused massive difficulties for many people? </p><p> There is a reduction in the amount for rent supplement, which is understandable because people are being moved onto HAP.  That falls under a different Department but the intention is to ultimately move everyone off rent supplement onto HAP.  Is there a timeframe for that?  How many people have transferred from rent supplement to HAP?  There are difficulties with some landlords who refuse to sign the HAP lease.  That is putting people in serious difficulty because their rent supplement payment is being cut.  Claimants are being told their landlord has no choice, he has to sign HAP or the rent supplement will be cut.  Could the Minister give an overview of that?  There are concerns that there are higher standards for HAP, which is brilliant because a minority of landlords have been getting away with blue murder in respect of the conditions they have been providing through rent supplement.  Much of that goes back to local authorities that failed to carry out inspections.  Landlords do not want to go to the additional cost of having to carry out refurbishment and upgrade works to meet the HAP criteria.  I would appreciate it if the Minister could outline the figures in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1306" speakername="Joan Collins" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#F00200"><p>The Christmas bonus is welcome.  People have been struggling in recent years and it is a significant boost to their income at this time of the year.  It will be welcomed by millions of people in the State.  It is great that it has been reinstated in full.  We know that many thousands of people are caring for parents or siblings in the home and the Minister referred to the "lower number of recipients than estimated - 1,294 lower than profiled".  The carer's allowance by its nature is difficult to get.</p><p>There is no information on how to go about making an application for the allowance.  Many people are refused and they appeal but that takes time.  I have a case where a claimant was awarded carer's allowance in September but, two months later, they have still not been paid.  It will be backdated but the system is slow.  I would have expected many more people to have applied for the allowance.  Is there any reason it has not happened?  Perhaps the application process should be examined.</p><p> It is disappointing that more schools do not have access to school meals.  The Minister stated that the lower take-up by schools in the 2018 budget is due to applications on hand that may not be processed by year end and to applications yet to be received.  Is the Department expecting many more applications?  Have the Estimates taken into account the possibility of more people applying?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1273" speakername="Joe Carey" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#G00200"><p>I welcome the reintroduction of the 100% Christmas bonus, which is a measure every member of this committee called for over many years.  It is significant that this is the first time in ten years that a 100% Christmas bonus payment will be made.  It will be made this week and that is welcome for the people who receive it.</p> <p>  There was higher than anticipated expenditure on treatment benefit, which is probably good news because it means a big take-up of the scheme.  Has the Department examined the numbers involved?  Deputy O'Dea asked if it was down to the self-employed taking up their entitlement.  Does the Minister foresee a greater take-up in the coming years?</p> <p>  It is welcome that the live register continues to fall, with 39,000 fewer people on it this year.  What figures are anticipated for the coming year?  Is the figure expected to reduce further as more people return to work?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#G00300"><p>I welcome the 100% Christmas bonus.  Last week, the papers reported that retail spending would increase this Christmas.  People are dependent on social welfare payments.  It is not that they get wealthy from them but they help keep people out of debt and away from moneylenders.  It also gives them the opportunity to have a decent Christmas.</p> <p>  Deputy O'Dea's contribution was comprehensive and he went through most of the subheads so I will not add to that.  However, there are two figures in subhead A2, administration non-pay, which I would like the Minister to explain.  One is payments for agency services at an additional &euro;21.3 million.  That is a lot of money.  What was the original Estimate and what additionality did the Department get for the &euro;21.3 million?  Under the same subhead, there are allocations for training and development and incidental expenses.  There were savings of &euro;6 million under training and development   What had the Department intended to do and what training programmes were forgone to make that saving?  It is also a substantial figure.</p> <p>  Members referred to savings in the carer's allowance.  More and more people are presenting at our clinics seeking supports for caring for somebody, though I do not suggest everybody is eligible for the allowance.  However, while many of the target Estimates have been good, there has been a saving in this area and the figure is lower than the profile figure.</p><p>Could any of that be attributed to the time it takes to process those applications rather than the number of applicants?  Carer's allowance can take quite a period to be processed.  Rather than saying there are fewer people on it, are the savings more attributable to other factors?  The Minister knows what I am getting at and I ask her to comment on that.</p><p> As an example, the working family payment was lower than expected with 2,800 fewer people on it.  There was also a smaller number in receipt of the back to school clothing and footwear allowance.  This is a bugbear of mine.  Does the Minister future-proof existing schemes when she is doing her Estimates and budgets?  Are people falling out of some of the schemes from an eligibility point of view based on increases they might have received from the Minister or tax increases or whatever else?  Does the Department use future-proofing?  In our clinics we do not notice a significant reduction in people who are looking to join such schemes.  When the Minister increases social welfare payments, are people falling through the cracks?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#H00200"><p>It is called the step-up effect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#H00300"><p>Yes.  I have one further question.  This is a small point but it is interesting.  I refer to subhead A40, the grant to the Citizens Information Board, CIB, which made a small saving.  Despite the rationalisation, the budget year-on-year for 2018 versus 2017 is still up a couple of million euro.  Are there any efficiencies to be generated given that the Minister is no longer servicing 90 or so boards?  However, the savings are in areas where we might have expected to see pressure for increased spending.  There was an underspend of &euro;400,000 on the mortgage arrears services being provided by the Money Advice &amp;amp; Budgeting Service, MABS.  Another &euro;100,000 was saved on Abhaile staff.  The figures are not significant, but at a time people are having difficulties in this area, I am concerned whether those organisations have evolved quickly enough to meet the existing demand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#H00400"><p>Would the Chairman if I go backwards?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#H00500"><p>The Minister may do it any way she wishes.  We will listen to all the responses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#H00600"><p>I will start with the Chairman.  The first point relates to the step-up effect.  There is a bit of work to be done with regard to some other Departments in terms of changes that are made in the budget and the impacts of those changes.  In the main, there were increases.  If payments under any scheme increase by &euro;5 or &euro;3.20 or whatever it happens to be, then the qualifying conditions have to be cognisant of that.  One cannot suddenly no longer get access to a back to school allowance just because an increase has been provided.  That is called the step-up effect and that is reflected in the legislation.  Everything gets stepped up in line with the increases provided by the Department.  However, that is not true of some other Departments.  The Chairman and I have had conversations about medical cards and Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, and a body of work needs to be done in that regard, in particular in terms of positive changes that can be made to welfare payments.</p> <p>  One of the reasons the CIB's budget has increased is it has been asked to provide additional services.  One of the Chairman's party colleagues was responsible for increasing the services provided to the deaf community.  I put in a few million euro more to ensure the CIB could through its funding streams give money to the organisations that provide additional signing services and additional access to information, and to increase the availability of the service on a daily basis to people in the deaf community.  That is very welcome.  I accept that there are some reductions in the anticipated spend on the CIB and it is because there is genuinely not the same requirement for them that we anticipated.  One can reflect on that and conclude that, thankfully, the number of people in long-term arrears on their mortgages are reducing.  That means we must now change and reflect the services to suit the needs of the people.  One of the changes that has been made in the past year is that to provide mentors to attend court sittings with people.  That is  positive and has been well received and we might further roll out that service.  Some of the Abhaile services and the work with PIPs in the community have not entirely fulfilled some people's expectations of getting a deal and providing them with a long-term route to deal with their longer-term debt.</p><p>It might be time to consider putting in place some internal performance improvement plans, PIPs, in that service to ensure they do not have to use vouchers, but the Chairman is right.  Some of the underspend is due to the fact that the number of people accessing the services is reducing.  It is time to examine those services and make small changes and tweaks so that we can help the people equally as well as we have done in recent years.</p><p> I will come back to the training shortly.  </p><p> On the administration, the original Estimate for 2018 was &euro;119,820,000.  The actual Estimate is &euro;141,141,000, so it is an increase of &euro;21,321,000.  That is to pay our agents who carry out the work on behalf of the Department.  To give some examples of that, An Post is paid for making scheme payments to customers and, thankfully, that is up this year.  I believe we are the largest customer and user of An Post, and long may that last, and its services with us have increased this year, which is very welcome.  Doctors are paid for certifying illness in respect of illness benefits and that figure is up this year, notwithstanding the difficulties we experienced.  They did not come from the certificates but there is an actual increase in the number of people making applications for illness benefit this year and therefore the doctors have to be paid.  I have the figures now if they are any good to the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00200"><p>Yes, please, for An Post.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00300"><p>I have told the Chairman a dirty lie; the figure for An Post is actually down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00400"><p>Now, Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00500"><p>I am sorry.  The figure for An Post agency fees was &euro;32,000,000, and it came in at just over &euro;31,000,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00600"><p>It got less from the Minister than anticipated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00700"><p>It got less than anticipated.  Our spend with An Post went up this year, so I hope that will be reflected in next year's figures.</p> <p>  The figure for the medical certificates is &euro;22,250,000.  The figure for JobPath was estimated at &euro;48,800,000, and the Revised Supplementary Estimate is &euro;71,698,000, which is the increase of &euro;22,895,000.  Therein lies the increase in that one.  We probably did not anticipate JobPath being as successful as it has been in the past year.  If the Chairman looks at our job figures, which were only released by the CSO this morning, he will see they are down significantly year on year than we would have anticipated.  That is reflected in the number of people who are getting work using our JobPath programme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00800"><p>Effectively, the bulk of that &euro;21,000,000 is the JobPath figure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J00900"><p>It is actually more than that.  It is &euro;22,898,000, and then there is the underspend.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J01000"><p>Yes.  Some savings were made on An Post and whatever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J01100"><p>Yes.  It reflects the success of that particular programme.</p> <p>  The training programme was estimated at &euro;17.5 million and it came in at &euro;11.4 million, which is an underspend of &euro;6 million.  Approximately 40% of the savings under this subhead relate to the Department's contingency fund.  This fund is reserved for unforeseen circumstances.  We did not have any unforeseen circumstances to be able to draw down that money this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J01200"><p>The Department did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#J01300"><p>Nothing that cost us money.  The primary savings related to bank charges, which was &euro;2.8 million.  I am not sure why bank charges are under the training subhead.  I am informed it is the training and incidental figure.</p> <p>  The Department also incurred savings in other areas including training in customer communications and advertising, PeoplePoint charges and the higher of rooms charges.  It is difficult to extend those subheads with 100% or even 99% accuracy.</p> <p>  Training savings of &euro;665,000 were incurred in this particular area.  That was primarily as a result of lower costs than were initially anticipated.  We got our training courses last year for less than what we thought we would have to pay.</p> <p>  With regard to additional information on learning and development, savings were incurred.  The Department has provided extensive training for all our staff in 2018.  To date, there have been 13,416 staff attendances at instructor-led classroom training, and 2,678 staff received this training in 2018.  There have been 2,447 e-learning modules and front-line serving training areas were completed in 2018.  Other internally delivered staff training outside the scope of these programmes was provided to 2,796 staff and another 1,799 staff received an externally delivered training programme.  The Department arranges approximately 100 one day learning courses across a range of subjects, and those are available to all our staff.  Those are the training and administration figures.</p> <p>  Deputy Joan Collins raised the issue of school meals, as did the other two Deputies.  Most, if not all, of our schemes are demand led.  We can put out an offer, as we did in this year's budget, to extend a hot school meals pilot scheme, which we hope to take on board at the beginning of next year, but we cannot make schools take up that offer.</p><p>A significant amount of additional money was provided, at a sitting of this committee at which I was present in October or November 2017, for the year 2018 but there was not the level of uptake that we expected for which there is a variety of reasons.  I would not have viewed the matter in the same way as the Deputy concerned who sounded  frustrated and wondered why schools would not avail of such a good scheme.  </p><p> We had an issue with one particular area.  I refer to instances where school meals were distributed by staff or volunteers who were over and above the staff in the school.  In the past year something happened to the provision of those staff members so schools could no longer deliver the school meals programme.  Thankfully, we have resolved the issue but it would have meant the non-delivery of school meals for a number of months in a small cluster of schools.  There are other schools where the staff are not available in the schools to take in meals and distribute them on a daily basis over and above the normal day-to-day running of the schools.  Again, we are trying to work with individual schools to break down whatever barriers exist that prevent schools from availing of the programme.  When we added the extra money last year, it was probably before we addressed the matter and we added people to the list thinking nobody would say "No".  Some schools have different issues.  We have to break down those barriers school by school because the barriers are not the same in each school.  Again, we are working with people.</p><p> Let me give the example of a school that has difficulties with the items listed on the school meals programme as suggested by Healthy Ireland in its health eating guidelines.  The school is a special needs school.  Some of the children will not eat what is listed on the school meals programme and, therefore, pulled out of the school.  We worked with the school and decided that we needed to be more flexible about recommendations.  We brought in a nutritionist and considered what should be provided to the children to ensure that we can continue to deliver.  Reasons vary in schools.  We have an incredible division located in Sligo that looks after the scheme and they are very proactive.  If there are issues, we visit the schools and work with them to make sure that we break down the issues, where we can, and bridge any gaps.  We are intent on ensuring that the school meals programme is fully up to spend.  We will also add the hot school meals pilot programme next year.  Please God it will go well and we can add another string to our bow in terms of school meals.  </p><p> In terms of the carers' allowance, there has not been a decrease in the number of people applying for the allowance.  I know it probably looks like there was a decrease.  Last year, we anticipated that more people would apply than applied because there had been an increase year-on-year.  For example, at the end of last October as many as 17,406 applications had been received and we received 20,852 last year.</p><p> There is a new carers' form planned.  Deputy Joan Collins suggested that it is a very difficult scheme to apply for and the Chairman suggested that one of the reasons for a reduction in the number of applicants is due to the process taking so long to complete.  My answer is no as the process took equally as long the year before and the year before that, unfortunately.  As a result we have worked very closely with the Carers' Association of Ireland in the past year and come up with a new application form.  As Deputy O'Dea will be aware, particularly with our work with the domiciliary care allowance and DCA Warriors in the past number of years, we have similar issues because it is a very similar scheme.  Obviously, one scheme is for adults while the other scheme is for children.  It was a difficult application to navigate and we did great work with the DCA Warriors.  The organisation and the parents helped us enormously to make the application a much simpler process.  We have done exactly the same work with the Carers' Association of Ireland and we will release a new form at the beginning of next year.  I hope that the new form will mean that far more people will be successful with their first application.  </p><p> To answer the question posed by Deputy O'Dea, we have a new recruitment campaign for medical assessors planned for January.  It is not just to extend the service.  A  number of medical assessors left over the course of the year and we got new replacements this year.  The new recruitment campaign will help us to continue and extend that employment recruitment drive.  We want to make sure that the application is as easy as possible and people give us all of the information.  The reason it takes a while to process applications is not that the qualifying, from a condition perspective, is onerous.  One must meet the conditions outlined in the means test, which are relatively simple.  Out of all of the schemes, they would have the highest conditions to reach.  One's income threshold and all of that kind of stuff on the carers' allowance would be much higher than some of our other schemes.  Due to the fact that people need to be medically assessed and the bar for a full and half carer's allowance - the threshold of the care that has been given has to be fully detailed and examined by medical assessors, which takes a little bit of time.</p><p>We all accept that it has taken too long, but I hope the new application form and the employment of additional medical assessors next year will bring a drastic reduction in the numbers.  I believe, and management share my view, that there is a need for more staff in that area, and we are awaiting staff arising from efficiencies in other areas to move into this area.  It will then benefit from a double whammy of getting the attention and new initiatives it deserves.  The annualised figures for the number of carers at the end of October 2018 were 78,681 an increase from 74,881 in the same period the year before.  The rate of increase has slowed down.</p><p> Deputy Carey raised the issue of treatment benefits.  We increased the allocation for treatment benefits this year and allowed both the self-employed and employees to claim under this scheme.  We expected the uptake to increase, but never to the level received.  This is good, as it means that people perceive this scheme as a genuine benefit.  When people think about their social insurance contribution, all they think about is the pension that comes when they reach 66 years, which in their case is donkey's years away.  We wish to instill the value of the social insurance contribution and treatment benefits are one clear way that resonates with the people and there has been a significant increase in the number of applications this year.</p><p> Deputies Brady and O'Dea raised the issue of the CE scheme.  There are 1,600 and odd vacancies on this programme.  The scheme is entirely different from T&uacute;s, the community work placement initiative.  Under T&uacute;s, the employment official in consultation with the unemployed person and with his or her co-operation send him or her on a T&uacute;s scheme whereas under the CE scheme, one has to apply for a place on the scheme.  People on the live register visit the Intreo office on a weekly basis and they choose to apply for the CE opportunities.</p><p> The number of people applying for places on a CE scheme is reducing for two reasons.  First, there are fewer people on the live register than there used to be so fewer people are available to apply for the scheme in the first instance.  Based on the contributions of the members who were of the view that JobPath was hampering people in applying for CE places, we allowed anybody who was on JobPath this summer to do both.  That has not resulted in a significant increase in the number of people applying for the CE programme from this summer.  The only factor I can put my finger on is that because there are jobs in the community, people are looking for full-time employment as opposed to work experience.  We work with all of our CE sponsor schemes which do tremendous work on a monthly basis and we try to improve their access to people and help them to advertise their positions</p><p>.  As unemployment numbers reduce, the number of positions on CE schemes should reduce by a percentage in line with the reduction in the live register because the CE programme is purely an activation model.  I do not subscribe to the fact that it is an activation model because a raft of people on community programmes are not there just to be trained to move on to the next job as they see what they do as a fulfilling and worthwhile activity.  Members share my view that this work is of significant value to our communities.  We need to reflect on that and change how it is viewed.  Sometimes it is more than just a work experience or training opportunity for people but the reasons the numbers are falling is that the unemployment figures are reducing and it is reflected in that.  The falling numbers is not due to anything we are doing differently in the Department, as the scheme is entirely demand-led.  The places are available because of the reflected numbers that we expected to be on the live register this year.  That number will reduce next year as the number on the live register comes down again.  Nobody is preventing anybody from applying for a place on a CE scheme anymore.  Anybody who is on the live register can apply to be on a scheme.  They are choosing not to and we will reflect on that.</p><p> The working family and the back to school allowance payments are demand-led schemes.  People are benefitting from the fact that the economy is recovering.</p><p>This relates to the back to school allowance as well.  Nothing has changed.  I view the changes in the back to school allowance and the working family payment as positive for those who receive these payments.  We introduced a disregard into the working family payment.  People who rely entirely on the working family payment to top up their incomes now have a weekly disregard for their rent payments.  Back to school payments for next year were increased significantly in the budget.  I know we have not finalised that yet.  Deputy O'Dea is right when he says that this increase reflects the fact that the cost of going to school is increasing.<br/><br/>The number of people who are accessing both of these schemes is a reflection of the fact that the economy is recovering.  Many people are moving into full-time employment at a level where they do not reach the means test, do not need the working family payment or do not qualify for the back to school allowance anymore.  The number of new applications for the working family payment received so far this year - the figure was 23,803 at the end of October - is relatively similar to last year's number.  I have mentioned the introduction of the disregard.  It is a good thing that the numbers are slowly decreasing.  It is not something to be worried about.  As I have said, this will always be a demand-led scheme.  I want to be able to allow people who are currently on the scheme to earn more and to take home more of the money they are actually earning.  I hope this will incentivise and encourage them to earn more and keep more of their own money.  The scheme will always be led by demand.  If there is an increase in the need for the scheme next year, we will respond to that.<br/><br/>I have spoken about school meals.  I will come back to illness benefit in a second.  Deputy Brady mentioned the overspend of &euro;4.2 million under the heading of Office Equipment and External IT Services.  Our list of ongoing schemes is continuing to grow.  Every time I introduce a new scheme, I have to get into the queue to get an entirely new platform developed.  Thankfully, we are introducing new schemes.  We introduced the paid parental leave and the self-employed jobseeker's schemes this year.  These brand new schemes need brand new IT platforms.  We are investing in our online digital services.  We are about to go live with <i>mywelfare.ie</i>, which is a new and hugely positive method of interacting with the Department.  It is so user-friendly that even I am totally impressed by it.  This new system is incredibly easy to use.  We have 6,000 staff and 70 schemes.  This means that our IT platforms are constantly being upgraded and new systems are constantly coming on board.  The only difficulty we have as a society, a country or an economy at the moment is that there are so few software developers on the Government procurement list.  They are all busy.  They are already doing stuff for all the other Departments.  This will probably slow down our ability to deliver on some of the new schemes we would like to deliver on.  It is possibly something that needs to be looked at.  That accounts for the &euro;4.2 million overspend.<br/><br/>I think Deputy Brady is under the impression that there is a programme to move people off rent supplement and onto HAP.  I say that because I am making an assumption.  I hope I am wrong.  No one in the Department is working off a list with a target of getting 100 people off rent supplement.  Rent supplement is a short-term measure to bridge a gap in the housing need of a family or couple.  The State has to make sure it provides long-term sustainable solutions for people.  Ideally, we would like to see people not being on rent supplement for any more than about a year.  That has not been the reality in recent years because we have given people rent supplement for more than 12 months.  It was always intended to be a short-term stop for people as they come in and out of need.  Over recent years, HAP has been introduced, there has been a move away from RAS and a long-term requirement for HAP leases to be five or ten years has been introduced.  As a result, people have moved gradually from rent supplement to HAP.  There is no agenda of getting officials to hurry through a list of 10,000 people.  It will happen as people come.  Therefore, I am disappointed to hear from the Deputy that people are being told they will lose their RAS if they do not take up HAP.  It is definitely not coming from the Department.  People will get RAS for as long as they need it.  Rent supplement is provided because there is a need for it.  When somebody moves onto HAP or into a social house, or wins the lotto and buys his or her own house, he or she will come off rent supplement because it is no longer required.  Nobody is actively pushing people off rent supplement.  All of our schemes are led by demand.  If someone has a need and the conditions apply to him or her, he or she will get what comes from the Department.  There is nobody telling that person that he or she should or should not be here.</p><p>I have just been given the figures.  At the end of October, we had 25,654 people on rent supplement, 19,196 people on RAS through the local authorities and 41,693 people on HAP.  I might be wrong, but I think the Deputy is asking how many people came off rent supplement and went onto HAP.  Is that what he is asking?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#N00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#N00300"><p>I do not have that figure with me, but I will come back to the Deputy with it.  It will take me a couple of days or weeks to get the figure because it is not something we would have.  I will give it to the Deputy as soon as I get it.  The Department will need to correspond with the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government.  I will get back to the Deputy.  Again, nobody is pushing anybody out the door.</p><p>We are recruiting medical assessors to work across a number of schemes, including the illness benefit scheme.</p><p>Deputy O'Dea asked about the FIS or working family payment awareness scheme.  We have a new interactive platform for engaging with our clients, customers or citizens.  There is a conversation that I would love to have around this table one day.  I am going off script slightly at the moment, not that I have a script.  I am going off on a tangent.  Every time we announce something, we get a barrage of responses from people asking why we have a &quot;customer&quot; charter.  We decided to draw up the charter a number of years ago because we wanted to provide the most excellent level of customer service.  That irks people because they are not really customers.  Then we called them &quot;clients&quot;, but they are not really clients.  We cannot call them &quot;citizens&quot; because we look after many people who are not citizens.  I am not sure what the correct language is.  Someone told me one day that I should just call them &quot;people&quot;, but sometimes that does not quite fit into what I am talking about.  I would love some advice on this.  The last thing we want to do is to upset somebody by saying &quot;citizens&quot; when we look after people who are not citizens or by saying &quot;customers&quot; when they are not really customers.  If I could get some advice on this issue, that would be deadly.  Similarly, it was noted this week that some people do not like the idea of us calling the Christmas bonus a &quot;Christmas&quot; bonus.  It was suggested that we should think about calling it something else.  We are all gone very politically correct lately.</p><p>We are making people aware of the new <i>mygovid.ie</i>and <i>mywelfare.ie</i>platforms, which are very interactive.  All of our people in the Intreo offices and all of our front-line staff are well aware of the conditions around FIS.  The idea behind FIS when it was introduced a number of years ago was to try to encourage people who depend entirely on welfare to go out, take a chance and try to do work.  We were trying to give them comfort that they would not lose the supports they previously enjoyed.  We are trying to make sure the transition period is well supported by the Departments of Health and Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  That is what is there.  We are consistently trying to help people to get into employment.  We are certainly not shy about telling people that FIS is there.  The new &euro;95 disregard for rent payments will certainly be well advertised in all of our offices next year.  It is not something that we are keeping secret.  I genuinely believe that it is because people's fortunes are improving that these schemes are not required anymore.</p><p>I have covered the issues of community employment, school meals, back to school payments and agencies.</p><p>I have not yet responded to Deputy O'Dea's question about the court ruling during the week which deemed that our withholding of contributory pension payments to a particular gentleman under section 249 of the Social Welfare (Consolidation) Act 2005 was unconstitutional.  The report from the court is very lengthy.  We are probably still assimilating it without jumping to any conclusions.  I know what my gut is telling me to do, but obviously I have to get some advice before I can do that.  The Attorney General has the report.  I expect to have a meeting before the end of this week, or early next week, at which a final decision can be made.  The Deputy is well aware that this is not something that can be put on the long finger.  We need to decide soon whether we are going to appeal or make alternative arrangements.  I will be looking for the co-operation of all parties in the House when the time comes to rectify the position we currently find ourselves in.  Even if it is not of our making - I hope it is not - it is not very satisfactory.</p><p>The final point I would like to make in response to Deputy O'Dea relates to pensions.  He was looking for the actual numbers for the year-on-year increases.  This year, an additional 17,300 people are receiving the contributory State pension, an additional 500 people are receiving the contributory widow's pension and an additional 130 people are receiving the non-contributory State pension.</p><p>The total pensions additional this year are 17,930.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00200"><p>Which brings the total to what?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00300"><p>I do not have that figure.  I will have it in a minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00400"><p>I have one or two brief comments.  On the agency services, the JobPath figure which the Minister gave was-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00500"><p>It went up &euro;22 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00600"><p>What did it go up to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00700"><p>It went up to &euro;71.698 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00800"><p>What was the original estimate then?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O00900"><p>It was &euro;48.8 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01000"><p>In comparison to everything else that the Minister has presented here today, this is a very significant increase, about 40% more.  That went among those JobPath companies to administer the scheme.  Is it because they dealt with more people or did they retain people in employment for longer?  It is a phased payment but it strikes me, from the point of view of doing an Estimate, that if &euro;48 million is estimated and the outcome is nearly &euro;72 million, that is a substantial difference.  Something happened that was not predicted, which may not have been bad, but that is what I am trying to get to because it is a significant figure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01100"><p>It is both.  Not only are more people staying in work longer, but they have the capacity to take more people as well.  The schemes with both of these organisations are entirely demand led so they only get paid when there are successful outcomes.  They do not get paid just for showing up to work, they have to take people, work with them and then they get approximately &euro;300 for working with people for the year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01200"><p>They get &euro;311.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01300"><p>Good man.  That is what they get for working with somebody but then the bonus payments obviously kick in when somebody gets a full-time job for 13 weeks, 26 weeks and 52 weeks.  That increase is purely down to the success of the project so maybe we should have been more ambitious when we made our Estimates last year that they would be more successful.  Also, that is reflected in the fact that the live register numbers are lower than we would have expected and there are 13,000 to 14,000 more people working than I would have expected at this time last year.  It is all based on positive outcomes because people are getting jobs and the two agencies that we have employed to help us get people jobs are doing a great job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01400"><p>They hit the jackpot in terms of where they thought they might be and where they have ended up.  It is significantly different.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01600"><p>Some 60,000 people were referred to JobPath last year.  How many of those were going in for the second time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01700"><p>This year, 15,000 people have been sent a second time.  There were significantly more referred in the first instance than the first number the Deputy mentioned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01800"><p>Can the Minister give us her idea of what, if any, future there is for JobPath?  I understand that the contract runs out next year or the year after.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O01900"><p>The end of next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O02000"><p>Could the Minister give us an indication as to whether there are any proposals to renew the contract?  Did the Minister also commission a report on the future of the local employment service network, LESN?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O02100"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O02200"><p>Has that been published yet?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O02300"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1227" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O02400"><p>When can we expect to see that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#O02500"><p>There are two issues.  The econometric analysis is being finalised and I hope to have it in January but the preliminary findings are looking good and that is the report, alongside the position on our projected targets, that will determine what we will need going forward.  I do not know right now what the needs of those 127,000 people who are full-time unemployed, as announced this morning by the CSO, are going to be in a number of years but we will have to devise schemes to make sure that they are as successful as JobPath has been for us in recent years, but that might change.</p> <p>  Any changes in that route will come from the econometric review that we have done on JobPath but the Deputy is aware that I have also commissioned an Indecon report on the review into LESN's and our jobs clubs.  I am currently assessing that and I only started reading it last week.  All of that will feed into the State's service and provision of activation for some 86,000 people who are unfortunately long-term unemployed and the entire 127,000 people who are full-time unemployed.</p><p>If the figures on the unemployed and underemployed are looked at, there are 197,000 people, so there is still a big body of work to be done.  I know that we constantly say that when we get to the magic number of 4% we will have reached full employment, as if we should nearly give up, say that is grand and the job is oxo, but there are 197,000 people in this country who are unemployed or underemployed and we will not stop trying to help them get full-time employment until they do.  We have a lot of work to do and there are big decisions to be made next year, but it is to be hoped members will play a role in those decisions next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00200"><p>In playing that role, will members have access to that Indecon report that the Minister referred to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00300"><p>They will of course.  I apologise because I have so many reports at the moment and I like to finish one before I start another one.  I have finished reading the report and I have a meeting with the team on the local employment support networks, LESNs, and jobs clubs this week.  I need to fill them in on my good news from the report on what we should do and they will temper me and tell me to do something else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00400"><p>Then the Minister will come and tell us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00500"><p>As soon as that meeting has happened, we will issue the report and it would be valuable to have the committee's input into the recommendations before we make final decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00600"><p>I refer to reports and I hear what the Minister is saying about finishing one before commencing another.  Two years ago she promised a report on young unemployed people.  She indicated on Report Stage of the Social Welfare and Pensions Bill that it was imminent, so when exactly is it expected?  Is it next month or in two months?</p> <p>  I refer to the housing assistance payment, HAP.  I am surprised that the Minister is saying that there is no drive to get people off rent supplement onto HAP because that is not the case in Wicklow.  The county council is actively writing out to people in receipt of rent supplement telling them that they have to talk to their landlord and that their landlord has to sign up to the HAP payment or otherwise it will impact on their rent supplement payment-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00700"><p>Get me a copy of the letter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00800"><p>-----and staff are saying they are processing 20 to 30 of those applications a week.  That is happening as we speak and I am sure that is being replicated in every local authority in the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P00900"><p>The local authority's job is to provide long-term, stable housing for people, and HAP is far more stable on a five or ten-year contract than rent supplement where people are normally only on an annual contract.  They are obviously writing out to them offering to put them on a long-term footing, but there is no implicit threat that if they do not, it will affect their rent supplement.  If the Deputy says there is an implicit threat, then I need a copy of that letter because the Department is demand led and if somebody has a need, we fill that need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01000"><p>People are being told that the landlord has to sign up to it or else the payment will be stopped.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01100"><p>The local authority has absolutely no truck with anybody in our Department.  They do not have a magic button that they can press.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01200"><p>I will get the Minister a copy of the letter because it is concerning for many reasons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01300"><p>Yes, give me the letter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01400"><p>That would be helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01500"><p>On the additional spend of &euro;22.8 million for Turas Nua and Seetec, the figures that were finally produced at the Committee of Public Accounts last week after several years of asking, with the cover of commercial sensitivity being given, are startling.  I do not know how the Minister can come here and say that JobPath is the most successful labour activation scheme-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01600"><p>Because it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01700"><p>-----and stand over that.  We know that 190,000 people have been referred over and it has cost &euro;149 million.  Only 17% of those people who engaged in employment lasted as far as the first sustainment payment of 13 weeks.  If we take the last sustainment payment, only 9% of people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01800"><p>So far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P01900"><p>-----have been sustained in a job for 52 weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P02000"><p>That is so far.  The Deputy is giving the impression that people get a job for 13 weeks and then lose the job.  The numbers are reflective of the position we are in today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P02100"><p>Allow Deputy Brady to make the point and I will afford the Minister an opportunity to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#P02200"><p>The Minister initially said that this is demand driven, but it is not.  We know people are referred over from Intreo.</p><p>Some of the massive increase from &euro;48.8 million to &euro;71.69 million might be those sustainment payments.  Something else happened during that period in 2018.  Was there renegotiation around the contract with Turas Nua and Seetec to see an increase in numbers being referred over?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00200"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00300"><p>It would be very useful at this point, and I do not expect to hear it, if there was a full breakdown of all of those figures because they were only produced last week at the Committee of Public Accounts.  The figures are alarming, to say the least.  This scheme has been in place for three years.  I do not buy what the Minister is saying so it would be useful to get an up-to-date picture on all of those figures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00400"><p>Could the Deputy afford the Minister time to respond to him?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00500"><p>When I responded to the Chairman, I said it was demand led but I corrected myself so I would rather not see the Deputy misquote me again because I did correct myself.  Turas Nua and Seetec get paid on outputs.  When they have a successful outcome, they get paid the extra bonus money for that successful outcome.  The numbers we shared last week were never hidden beforehand.  Commercial sensitivity relating to the State being able to ensure it gets good value for money does not necessarily mean that we bare all.  Everybody knowing exactly what everyone else is getting paid does not do the State any service.  What we can clearly see-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00600"><p>It is a taxpayer-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00700"><p>The Deputy will see that if we go to tender next year for the new JobPath.  What it does show clearly is that,  for the hundreds of thousands of people who have had the experience of going through it, a very large percentage - an enormously successful percentage - with the exception of JobBridge,  which people in Deputy Brady's party did not appreciate for a number of years, it has been the most successful activation programme we have ever run in the State.  I know the Deputy does not like it and that is fine but it affects tens of thousands of people who have got jobs because of the interaction, assistance and help from the great staff in Turas Nua and Seetec, who are all Irish people by the way in case there is an ideological difficulty there.  They are Irish people helping Irish people to get work and they are succeeding, which is great.  It is wonderful to see the extra money that is being paid to those companies because it means they are actually being effective, which is what we want to see.  If the Deputy does not want to take my word for it, the live register and CSO figures were issued this morning and they are going down.  The reason they are going down is because our activation methods are working.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1252" speakername="John Brady" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00800"><p>The Minister is in denial.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q00900"><p>I thank the Minister and her officials for attending today.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.170" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q01000">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1298" speakername="John Curran" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/SPS2018120400002#Q01100"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 90, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection has completed its consideration of the following Supplementary Estimate for public services for the year ended 31 December 2018: Vote 37 - Employment Affairs and Social Protection .  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2018-12-04a.172" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 2.18 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>