<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Committee on Public Petitions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Shane Cassells, Senator Jerry Buttimer. Deputy Denise Mitchell, Deputy Brendan Ryan,</p><p>DEPUTY SEAN SHERLOCK IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.4" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CPP2019013000002#A00100">Decisions on Public Petitions Received</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CPP2019013000002#A00200"><p>The first petition for consideration is Petition No. P00023/18.  It is proposed that we forward a copy of the response from the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation to the petitioner and close the petition.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  The next petition for consideration is Petition No. P00046/18.  It is proposed that we correspond with the Department of Justice and Equality seeking an update on this issue when work is finalised and leave the petition open.  We will forward a copy of the reply from the Department to the petitioner and inform her that we are leaving the petition open.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1301" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CPP2019013000002#A00300"><p>The petition relates to people with a stamp 3 visa.  The visa is issued to the spouses or partners of workers who have come to Ireland in response to a critical skills shortage and are effectively facilitating the growth of our economy and in many ways keeping the economy going.  There is a very strong case for allowing those with a stamp 3 visa the right to work without having to go through the work permit system.</p><p>That would do justice to the families coming to Ireland and remove some of the related burden from the work permit system.  I agree with the recommendation of the committee that we should keep the petition open.  I note that the responses from the two Departments involved in this matter have been quite positive in terms of seeking to do something about it.  It is important that the committee maintains its interest in this petition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1276" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="13:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CPP2019013000002#B00200"><p>It is the view of the committee that we should keep the petition open as it is a live issue which mainly affects women.  I am happy to await the update from the Department.  It would be appropriate for the committee to keep the petition open on that basis.  I think we are agreed on that.  I acknowledge the visitors in the Public Gallery who I understand may be guests of Deputy Brendan Ryan.</p> <p>  The final petition for consideration is Petition No. P00048/18 relating to motor tax issues.  It is proposed that we forward a copy of the response from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport to the petitioner and close the petition.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.9" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 1.40 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 13 February 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.10" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Health</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.11" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Stephen S. Donnelly, Senator Colm Burke, Deputy Bernard Durkan, Senator John Dolan, Deputy Kate O'Connell, Senator Keith Swanick. Deputy Margaret Murphy O'Mahony, Deputy Louise O'Reilly,</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL HARTY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.12" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.13" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 9.15 a.m., suspended at 9.26 a.m. and resumed in public session at 9.28 a.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.14" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#C00100">Implications for Health Sector of United Kingdom's Withdrawal from the EU: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#C00200"><p>The purpose of the meeting is to engage with officials from the Department of Health, the HSE and the Health Products Regulatory Authority on the implications for the health sector of the decision of the United Kingdom to withdraw from the European Union.  On behalf of the committee, I welcome Mr. Jim Breslin, Secretary General of the Department of Health, and officials from the Department, Mr. Fergal Goodman and Mr. Kieran Smith; Mr. John Hennessy, Mr. John Swords and Ms Paula Keon of the HSE; and from the Health Products Regulatory Authority, Dr. Lorraine Nolan, chief executive, Ms Rita Purcell and Dr. Caitr&iacute;ona Fisher.</p><p>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the joint committee.  If, however, they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to do so, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p><p>I advise witnesses that any opening statements they make to the committee may be published on its website after the meeting.</p><p> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p> I ask Mr. Breslin to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.17" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#D00200"><p>I thank the committee for inviting the Department of Health to engage with it on the preparedness of the health sector for Brexit.  The Chairman introduced the witnesses so I will not repeat that.  I assure the committee that detailed planning for Brexit has been ongoing in the Department and its agencies for more than two years.  As part of the whole-of-Government work on Brexit preparation, the Government is working to secure an orderly and agreed Brexit, but in view of the uncertainty in London and the increased risks of a no-deal Brexit, we will continue to intensify our preparations for any such outcome.<br/><br/>Our number one protection from whatever Brexit brings will be our status as an EU member state, with all the stability, predictability and solidarity that brings.  On 19 December, the Government published its contingency action plan, which outlines the approach to no-deal Brexit planning, and the Department of Health and its agencies are contributing in full to this.  Brexit of any kind will mean change and will impact on all sectors, including health.  It is recognised that managing a no-deal Brexit would be an exercise in damage limitation and it would be impossible in a no-deal scenario to maintain the current seamless arrangements between the EU and UK across a full range of sectors which are currently facilitated by our common EU membership.<br/><br/>It is important to underline that certain measures will allow us to mitigate, as far as possible, the implications of a no-deal Brexit.  Both the Irish and British Governments are committed to maintaining the common travel area in all circumstances and have committed to undertaking all the work necessary, including through legislative provision to ensure that common travel area rights and privileges are protected.  The Department has focused attention on protecting the common travel area with regard to access to healthcare and allowing the freedom of movement we currently have for Irish and UK citizens.  Protecting and maintaining the common travel area and the associated rights and privileges is a key part of our contingency planning and preparations.  This is vital in the context of the Good Friday Agreement and the Northern Ireland peace process, as well as broader UK-Ireland relations.<br/><br/>The Department continues to work closely with other Departments and agencies on all aspects of Brexit planning, particularly the Department of the Taoiseach and the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.  The Department is represented at all cross-sectoral working groups and is co-operating fully with colleagues across Government.  The Department has also strengthened its internal capacity to plan for Brexit.  I meet the heads of the HSE, the Health Products Regulatory Authority, HPRA, and the Food Safety Authority of Ireland, FSAI, weekly to review progress on Brexit preparedness and to consider any new challenges identified.  I have also established a Brexit operations team, chaired by a deputy secretary general in the Department, comprised of senior officials from the Department, the HSE, the HPRA and the FSAI.  This group works to resolve issues and to escalate them to the heads of agency group, which I chair, if necessary.<br/><br/>An inter-agency communications group, chaired by my Department, has been established to plan for all aspects of a communications strategy to ensure that the public is fully informed of the health implications of either a central case Brexit or a no-deal Brexit.  A further working group is working to identify and monitor medicines that may be vulnerable to supply disruption as a result of Brexit.  The Department and its agencies, especially the HPRA, FSAI and HSE, have been in regular contact with stakeholders to assess the level of preparedness for a no-deal Brexit.  It is important to state that while the Department continues to monitor and seek assurances in a number of areas, our current analysis is that there are no immediate risks to the health of the population because of Brexit.<br/><br/>Co-operation on healthcare provision and the protection of public health on the island of Ireland and between Ireland and Britain has developed over many years to the mutual benefit of the all parties.  Some of these arrangements are underpinned by EU regulations while others are on the basis of bilateral agreements or service-to-service arrangements.  Both Governments have repeatedly stressed that they are anxious for these services to continue post Brexit, and the Department of Health continues to be in close contact to facilitate this.<br/><br/>I will update the committee on the progress and the current status of priority issues since the Department's previous appearance on this issue in January 2018.  In the event that the United Kingdom leaves the European Union on 29 March 2019 without a withdrawal agreement in place, it will be necessary to put in place legislative provisions to enable necessary healthcare arrangements, including reimbursement arrangements, to be maintained between Ireland and the United Kingdom.  The Irish and British Governments have committed to maintaining the common travel area and its associated rights and privileges.  These arrangements facilitate access to health services in the UK and Ireland, including access to emergency, routine and planned healthcare.  The draft heads of the proposed legislation therefore seek to put in place an appropriate legal framework in Ireland to ensure the continuation of the common travel area arrangements.<br/><br/>The Department, as part of the cross-Government approach to contingency planning, has prepared heads of a Bill which is consistent with our commitment to provide for these rights and privileges.  The proposed legislation would allow the Minister for Health and the HSE, as appropriate, to cover the cost of healthcare provided in the UK under the same conditions as currently exist, for example, where treatments are not provided under our own healthcare system or for an Irish person who becomes ill while on a visit to the UK and needs immediate healthcare there.  It also makes provision to preserve existing eligibility for healthcare in Ireland for a range of different cohorts of people, including UK pensioners residing in Ireland, frontier workers and for UK residents on a temporary visit here.<br/><br/>As part of our common travel area discussions, key principles have been agreed at official level with the UK to maintain bilateral health co-operation.  There has been very good ongoing engagement with the UK on the technical work needed to ensure continuity of arrangements.  Proposals are now being examined with a view to ensuring the maintenance of the <i>status quo</i>pending the finalisation of longer-term arrangements.  This co-operation will support the objectives of the healthcare legislation proposed in the no-deal Brexit omnibus Bill.  This overall framework will build upon many years of very positive co-operation between the two jurisdictions.  This is true of our administrative systems but it is also true at a clinical level.  There are very strong and well-established relationships at clinician-to-clinician level.  Many of our respective clinicians have trained together.  In all of our preparations we have been able to build upon this very strong spirit of collaboration in the interests of patient care, at clinical, hospital, administrative and political levels.<br/><br/>The Department is working closely with the HPRA and the HSE on the supply of medicine.  Since the UK referendum, industry has undertaken very significant work in modifying supply chains and revising regulatory pathways to guard against Brexit.  This work is continuous and the Department, the HPRA and the HSE are continuing to work closely with suppliers.  As part of a whole-of-Government response to Brexit, the Minister, Deputy Harris, recently outlined a comprehensive set of preparations to ensure continuity of health services and supply of medical products in the event of a no-deal Brexit.  This work involves the Department of Health, the HSE, the HPRA and other agencies engaging in intensive Brexit preparedness and contingency planning.  Significant work has been undertaken together with the pharmaceutical industry to anticipate, as much as possible, potential vulnerabilities, risk assess these and devise contingencies to minimise and address any risks to continuity of supply of medicines and medical goods.  No major supply issues have been identified through the preparedness and contingency planning exercises.<br/><br/>Ireland is unlikely to face serious general medicine supply issues in the period immediately after 29 March.  Any emerging supply issues will, in the first instance, be dealt with from existing supplies held within the domestic distribution chain.  It is important to reiterate that there are already additional stocks of medicines routinely built into the Irish medicine supply chain.  This is different to the wholesaling model which operates in the UK.  The pharmaceutical industry and wholesalers have provided assurance that they are confident that they will have sufficient stocks to bridge any initial issues at ports, should they occur.  There is no need for hospitals, pharmacists or patients to order extra quantities of medicines or for doctors to issue additional prescriptions as doing so could disrupt existing stock levels and hamper the supply of medicines to other patients.  As an additional safeguard, special consideration is being given to those categories of medicines which are considered most essential to public health.  An expert group is examining these categories of medicine and, where the supply chain indicates that Brexit could potentially cause issues, the group is working with suppliers to verify that robust contingencies are in place.  Work on this process is ongoing and will continue for the foreseeable future.</p><p>Both the HPRA and HSE have requested that companies highlight any issues regarding the availability of specific products associated with Brexit and no major issues have been identified to date.  If any potential issue is identified, it will be managed through the existing medicine shortages framework.  </p><p> Medicine shortages inevitably arise from time to time and are a feature of health systems around the world.  The HPRA has an existing medicine shortages framework in place to help prevent shortages from occurring and to reduce the impact of shortages on patients and healthcare professionals by co-ordinating the management of potential or actual shortages as they arise.  This framework is already used to manage and address an average of 45 shortage notifications a month.  There is no current shortage caused by Brexit. </p><p> The mutual recognition of qualifications awarded in the UK and Ireland has been considered in the context of the negotiations on the withdrawal agreement and the framework for the future relationship.  Clearly an EU-UK agreement on the mutual recognition of qualifications, were that to be achieved, would address the issue in the best way possible.  The recognition of qualifications has been discussed as part of the engagement at official level between the UK and Ireland on the common travel area.  Both the UK and Ireland are committed to ensuring measures are in place to allow for the recognition of qualifications within the parameters applying.  The UK has recently published draft regulations, which it intends to enact in the case of a no-deal Brexit.  This legislation will enable Irish qualifications to be recognised in the UK.</p><p> The Irish health professional regulation bodies have been examining the mechanisms in place for the recognition of qualifications with the objective of ensuring efficient processes for recognition for those holding UK qualifications while ensuring that this is done in an objective and non-discriminatory way.  The Irish bodies have been linking with their UK counterparts on this issue.</p><p> The maintenance of food safety standards of food imports from the UK and the efficient flow of food through the ports is another issue for which the Department is planning.  The withdrawal of the UK from the EU and its new status as a third country will have implications for the official food control system in Ireland.  The Food Safety Authority of Ireland is the central competent authority for official food controls, which are carried out by a range of official agencies.  Those include the HSE's environmental health service, which is largely responsible for foods of non-animal origin and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which is responsible for foods of animal origin and plants.  Challenges ahead in this area include import and export issues, as well as potential divergence with EU law over the longer term.</p><p> The importation of food is subject to EU legislation.  Additional resources have been provided to conduct the appropriate checks where Ireland is the first point of entry to the EU.  Preparations are also under way in the event that the UK should decide to require export certificates for certain food products.</p><p> To facilitate these preparations the Department is working closely with the relevant agencies and has approved additional resources for environmental health service staff, the public analyst laboratory and the Food Safety Authority of Ireland.  It is also working with the environmental health service, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, the Revenue Commissioners and the Office of Public Works, OPW, with regard to the infrastructure and traffic management requirements at Dublin Port, Dublin Airport and Rosslare Europort.  The aim is to ensure that the appropriate food controls are conducted from a public health perspective, while being cognisant of the implications for trade.</p><p> In conclusion, I wish to reiterate that the Department, the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, and the relevant agencies under the aegis of the Department are fully engaged in Brexit planning to ensure, as far as is possible, that the health sector is prepared for any adverse impacts as a result of Brexit.  We recognise the valuable work of the committee and I thank members for the opportunity to be here today.  I look forward to the views and questions of members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#E00200"><p>I thank Mr. Breslin.  I now call on Mr. John Hennessy to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.20" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#E00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and members of the committee for the invitation to attend this meeting to discuss HSE Brexit preparedness.  I am joined by my colleagues, Mr. John Swords, national director for procurement, and Ms Paula Keon, assistant national director for the HSE North-South unit.</p> <p>  The HSE has been preparing for Brexit for some time on the basis of a central-case scenario and for a potential worst-case scenario, while at all times aware that negotiations are ongoing to help ensure that the necessary transition arrangements are in place to maintain continuity of health services.</p> <p>  A HSE Brexit planning group has been in place since 2017 and has been working closely with our departmental colleagues on a wide range of Brexit contingency planning and mitigating actions.  The focus of this work has been on Brexit implications across key work streams, including the continuity of patient and client health services; cross-Border and frontier arrangements, including co-operation and working together, CAWT; emergency healthcare, including the ambulance service; public health matters; environmental health; workforce issues and recognition of qualifications; and continuity of supply of goods and services including procurement.  </p> <p>  The focus of the mitigation measures relating to continuity of care is on ensuring that service level agreements and memoranda of understanding are in place where necessary.  This applies to specific service areas such as emergency cross-Border arrangements, cardiac and cancer services, treatment abroad placements and CAWT arrangements.  The EU North-South unit is working to ensure that services currently available to people living in Border areas continue to be available post Brexit.  Examples of those, as I mentioned, include cardiology and radiotherapy services at Altnagelvin and the specialist cardiac services provided on an all-island basis for children at Our Lady's Children's Hospital, Crumlin. </p> <p>  Arrangements in respect of other specific areas of healthcare, such as paediatric organ transplant services, are progressing and agreements are being finalised with the relevant UK hospitals to ensure continuity of service post Brexit.  That includes Great Ormond Street Hospital.  </p> <p>  The national ambulance services, here and in Northern Ireland, are liaising closely to ensure service continuity and agreement with regard to operating procedures.  There are two key memoranda of understanding in place between the respective ambulance services.  The first is a memorandum of understanding on the provision of assistance in the management and resourcing of emergency and urgent calls.  The second covers mutual aid for declared major incidents.  These join the two jurisdictions in their responses to emergency situations.</p> <p>  The environmental health service is engaged in ongoing discussions with the Departments of Health and Agriculture, Food and the Marine about the import and export of foodstuffs and the possible divergence of food regulations and controls over time.  As Mr. Breslin mentioned, additional resources have been made available in 2019 to strengthen the environmental health service capacity in this regard, and those additional posts are being recruited at present.  </p> <p>  The wider workforce implications of Brexit have been examined in detail by human resources department of the HSE and the key risks such as mutual recognition of qualifications and training for professional staff have been analysed in detail in the context of the movement of healthcare workers.  The HSE is liaising closely with the respective professional bodies and the regulators with a view to facilitating the continuation of existing recognition arrangements.  </p> <p>  The key risks for the provision of goods and services, such as medical and surgical supplies and medicines, in the short term relate to potential disruption and delay to supply chains.  As Mr. Breslin mentioned earlier, a joint working group comprised of staff from the HSE, the Department and the HPRA has been engaged in intensive work that involves the identification of suppliers of critical medicines and detailed follow-up with regard to specific product lines.  The key supply chain challenges in the short term are likely to be related to medicines with a short shelf life, those reliant on refrigerated supply chains, compounded products and time-critical logistics.  The HSE-HPRA group is liaising closely with hospitals and community pharmacists to identify short, medium and longer-term concerns regarding the continued supply of drugs and any risks to such supply and the proposed mitigation of those risks.  This work is being done in close collaboration with the pharmaceutical industry and both hospital and community pharmacy stakeholders.</p> <p>  There is currently a two-month stock of vaccines held in the HSE national cold chain service which, along with the stock held by companies in Ireland, gives approximately a six-month supply on the island to ensure the continuation of service delivery.  My colleague, Mr. John Swords, can provide the committee with further details about the continuity of supply of goods and services post Brexit.  </p> <p>  In terms of next steps, the HSE is continuing to work closely with service providers, suppliers and patient groups in relation to Brexit preparations.  This involves identifying, assessing and addressing the necessary contingency measures and actions required to maintain service continuity in the event of both an orderly and a disorderly Brexit.</p><p>The HSE is also continuing to work on awareness of Brexit implications among HSE and health service staff generally along with our colleagues in the Health Products Regulatory Authority, the Food Safety Authority of Ireland, key suppliers, and with patients and the public in consultation with the Department of Health.  This concludes my opening statement.  I and my colleagues we will endeavour to answer any questions the committee may have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#F00200"><p>I thank Mr. Hennessy.  I will start proceedings by asking the witnesses to expand on the treatment abroad scheme and the cross-border directive, both of which are very commonly used by Irish patients seeking treatment abroad.  They involve reimbursement of payments for those services.  How will they continue or will they be affected in any way?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.23" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#F00300"><p>I will ask my colleague, Mr. Goodman, to come in on this.  We have previously supplied to the committee data on the activity under those schemes.  It is notable that while, as EU citizens, we have entitlement to travel for treatment abroad or to avail of the cross-border directive across the EU, the majority of people are accessing care in the UK or Northern Ireland under both schemes.  For the treatment abroad scheme, as I noted in my statement, that is because our specialist links are most developed with the UK.  Mr. Hennessy mentioned Great Ormond Street.  There is a range of institutions in the UK to which we are very connected.  That will continue after Brexit.  We are confident about that for two reasons.  The level of engagement Mr. Hennessy has described with those institutions indicates that they completely understand the patient rationale here.  It is to their advantage that we form part of the catchment area for very highly specialist care and that we are able to feed in our patient to give them a critical mass of treatment within these islands.  If they were to lose some of that critical mass it would undermine their services.  They want to continue that relationship with us not only for altruistic reasons, which are very important, but also for the reputation of their units.  That is the very positive message we have received in our interactions with those facilities.</p> <p>  The heads of the Bill that have been published will give us the legal authority, subject to the drafting and progression of the Bill, to reimburse those facilities for the care they give.  At the moment, that is done completely through an EU-wide process where there is low administrative overhead and pretty well established rules as to how it happens.  In a post-Brexit situation, the UK will no longer be part of the EU-defined treatment abroad scheme but we will have an equivalent arrangement with the UK.  We will reimburse them, not as we currently do through the EU, but directly, for the care that they give. </p> <p>  In respect of the cross-border directive, the legislation also has an enabling provision which would allow the Minister and the HSE to meet the travel costs of Irish citizens to access treatment on an equivalent basis to the cross-border directive.  Currently, if someone goes to an EU member state and pays for their cross-border care, they can come back to the HSE and have that reimbursed.  We would seek to put in place a similar scheme.  It will not be the EU cross-border scheme but a similar scheme that would allow Irish citizens to continue to travel to Northern Ireland or the UK and be reimbursed by the Irish Government.  The UK authorities have indicated to us that they would be interested and prepared to facilitate continuing access under those arrangements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#F00400"><p>On that point, can Ireland enter into bilateral arrangements like that with the UK or would it have to go through the EU?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#F00500"><p>Part of the rationale here is the common travel area, which provides that we are completely fluid in how people and labour move around.  We have such historic links between us in that regard that we have to put an overarching set of entitlements in place.  There is no point in telling someone they have a historic right to work in another country if, when they work there and need healthcare, they are not covered for that.  The common travel area has always covered not just people's ability to work but also the social security that goes with it.  It is through those mechanisms that we will seek to do that.  The cross-border directive is probably going to be an extra bit.  In the heads of the Bill, we have signalled our intention that we would like to provide for it.  We will have to work it through with the Oireachtas as the legislation goes through the Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.26" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fergal Goodman" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#F00600"><p>I do not have a lot to add, really.  The principal distinction between the two schemes is that treatment abroad is very much a service-to-service arrangement, as the Secretary General has said.  As Mr. Hennessy has indicated, the HSE is proceeding on the basis that those service-to-service arrangements are essential in many ways and need to be maintained whatever happens.  The confirmation of the HSE's legal authority to continue with those arrangements is one of the purposes of the Bill.</p> <p>  As people will be aware, the cross-border directive puts the control in the hands of the patient to elect to source a service elsewhere.  That is not something that would otherwise exist in legislation.  The omnibus Bill that is being developed will need to pin that down in particular.  As the Secretary General has said, what we are seeking is the legal underpinnings that will enable the patients to continue to make those individual choices to access services.  That is the policy mandate that Government has given us in that regard.  Both arrangements are essentially dependent on reciprocation from the UK as far as is necessary to enable those systems to operate.  At present our understanding is that we expect that reciprocity to be forthcoming, all other things being equal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#F00700"><p>I thank the witnesses for their presentations and am grateful for all the work that has been done by both the Department and the HSE.  Everyone very much appreciates it.  Both the Department and the HSE played a major part in developing the cross-border directive over a long number of years.  As a result, Irish people have benefitted substantially in being able to travel abroad when treatment is not available here.</p> <p>  The presentation suggests that many of the angles have been covered.  Is there a particular angle of concern that will now change?  The one area I want to find out about is the case of someone who is working in the UK, has private health insurance and ends up receiving healthcare.  Have the health insurance companies engaged in the same way as the Department and the HSE as regards making sure the existing arrangements will still be in place after 29 March?  Have the witnesses had any feedback from the health insurance companies on that?</p> <p>  Much work has been done as regards joint co-operation between Belfast and Dublin and between Derry and Donegal on providing medical care for people travelling between the North and South to receive care.  Will there be any real change in the services that will be available?  Will there be a change in how remuneration is resolved between the parties?  What kind of changes do we expect in that whole area?</p> <p>  On training in respect of medical care, the working time directive has brought in many changes here.  It has been very good for staff as regards working time and the hours they have to put in every week.  However, others would claim that there is less training as a result of the reduced working hours.  Now that the UK is going to be outside the European Union, the likelihood is that it will change some aspects of the working time directive.  How are we going to deal with that?</p><p>We have certain qualifying criteria, for example.  Has there been any indication that there will be changes to these in terms of the training of nurses, pharmacists, physiotherapists or doctors, including GPs?  Has the issue been discussed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his questions.  I will ask people to contribute as we go through them.  The question on what might change was helpful.  People may not have seen it, but I saw a headline in <i>The Times</i>of London<i>.  </i>It summarised, albeit inaccurately, the position outlined in my opening statement by saying that medicines would be fine but cross-Border services would be impacted.  That is not what I said in my opening statement.  I am happy to say that we do not expect the North-South arrangements to be affected by Brexit.  That is not the basis on which either jurisdiction is planning.  When I referred to the general proposition that Brexit would change our lives and have implications for all sectors, it was not the cross-Border arrangements that we operate that I was thinking about.  I can provide examples of what I was thinking about, though.<br/><br/>We have strong North-South relationships.  We have provided capital for the opening of the radiotherapy unit in Altnagelvin.  We were there at the design stage and the commissioning stage.  We pay for the service that we get, as we do for the primary cardiac catheterisation service at Altnagelvin and some other services in the North.  Equally, our colleagues in the North are providing for the capital development of Crumlin so that children from the North with congenital heart defects can be treated at that hospital.  The North will pay the revenue costs of that.  All this is founded on the patient outcomes that can be produced by working together, and we are confident that the arrangements will be sustained through this period of disruption.<br/><br/>The arrangements are largely governed by service-level agreements.  In some cases, we have contributed to the capital costs.  In many cases, we are meeting the revenue costs.  Currently, they do not go up to Brussels and back down to the other jurisdiction.  Rather, they go directly from the HSE to the facilities in Altnagelvin or elsewhere.  We are confident in that regard.  Mr. Hennessy can discuss the detailed engagement that has been happening.<br/><br/>The private health insurers have assured us that they are not planning for an impact on those with coverage.  I will address an important point that did not come across in the question.  I believe I am right in saying that the health insurance policy of an Irish person who is working and resident in the UK will be written in the UK.  The VHI or another insurer would write insurance for people who were resident in Ireland, but if they were non-resident in Ireland, they would either get their insurance from the countries they were resident in or would get international health insurance policies.  This issue is more likely to arise in respect of someone who is resident in Ireland but who, in the course of his or her business or leisure, is in the UK or US when something happens.  That is something with which insurers are familiar.  In general, people do not use their private insurance to access healthcare in the UK on a planned basis unless that care is not available in Ireland, in which instance specific arrangements apply.  We have heard back from the insurers that there will be no change in this area.  They have examined the issue.<br/><br/>Regarding the question on training, a great deal of work has been done by our professional regulators.  This is an example of where Brexit changes the situation.  If someone trains in the EU, his or her qualification is automatically recognised in other EU member states and no one in their regulators can raise an issue about it.  However, the UK will become a third country and there will not be automatic recognition unless an overall deal is done by it and the EU to recognise qualifications.  There have been discussions in the context of the future relationship.  In the absence of a deal, we will put in place an administratively seamless approach between regulators.  The Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland, NMBI, is already informing itself on the qualifications in the UK and will not have to go through a long check when it receives an application from a nurse trained in the UK.  It will deal with that application within the current timeframes.<br/><br/>The Senator asked a good question about what would happen if the UK diverged over time.  That does not relate to the EU's working time directive principally, as the UK could diverge from the directive without it having an implication for the quality of the qualification.  Obviously, Ireland would stay with the EU standards.  However, if the UK diverged in the period ahead - we have no indication that it will, and I am referring to years from now anyway as opposed to just months - and decided to define the qualifications to be a professional in a different way from the EU, rendering them no longer equivalent, it would raise issues for our regulators and we would have to re-examine the situation.  Similarly, if the UK decided to diverge from EU food standards five or ten years after leaving, it would pose a risk for all of our interactions with it and is something that we would have to watch.  It would not be an issue for 2019, but it would have to be examined and is likely to be one of the issues addressed in the future relationship between the EU and the UK.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00300"><p>Many of our training guidelines were developed jointly by Ireland and the UK.  I refer in particular to junior doctors.  If someone does 48 hours per week in Ireland and the UK diverges from the working time directive as regards training and allows someone to work up to 60 or 65 hours per week, the long-term effect on Irish people who have done two or three years of training in Ireland before going to the UK could be that they would not get the same recognition.</p> <p>  Regarding the exchange between Ireland and the UK of people working in medical services, many junior doctors stay in Ireland for two or three years before going to the UK for another three or four years and then returning.  It is important that this co-operation on training continues.  Otherwise, both countries will suffer.  An eye should be kept on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00400"><p>Yes.  The Senator's second issue is the focus of attention, and not just as regards doctors, but also nurses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00500"><p>And physiotherapists.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00600"><p>There is quite a degree of movement.  The Nurses and Midwives Act 2011 provides for the NMBI to enter into agreements with third countries for the purpose of mutual recognition.  That will allow the registration bodies in both jurisdictions to say that there is equivalence and that people can seamlessly move back and forth.  The same applies in the case of the Medical Council.  The bodies involved may need to change their internal rules somewhat, but given the historic linkages and the equivalence that we currently enjoy, the latter is something that all regulators on the two islands wish to continue.</p> <p>  I do not know what the UK's plans on the working time directive are.  I do not mean to disagree with the Senator, but the essential point is not the number of hours, but the quality of the training in the course of those hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00800"><p>So long as we can maintain that our doctors are getting in that 48-hour period the quality of training that would be expected for someone working for a longer period of time in the UK, it is better that our doctors are working 48 hours instead of 60 hours in terms of the performance of their duties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G00900"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#G01000"><p>Where equivalence is concerned, that is where the attention will have to be paid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.38" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00100"><p>Our HR department has been doing extensive work with the regulators in respect of this issue and training.  The feedback from that process does not reveal significant concerns in the short term but, obviously, there is a need to monitor any divergence in standards over the longer term.  That will be a priority.</p> <p>  My colleague, Ms Keon, has been closely involved in dealing with the North-South relationships.  Several joint workshops have been held with representatives of the health services in the North and in the South with a view to ensuring a seamless transition to the post-Brexit situation.  They have addressed specific services such as those I mentioned in the opening statement where extensive agreements are in place.  The agreements relating to cardiac, radiotherapy, paediatric cardiac and other services have been tested to ensure that they would withstand any kind of Brexit and we are satisfied that they will.  We have been working on ensuring a seamless transition on the reimbursement issue and the funding implications in terms of issues such as the cross-border directive such that the current reimbursement arrangements or very similar will be maintained and patients will not be unduly discommoded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00200"><p>Will the Medical Council be responsible for the recognition of qualifications?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00300"><p>Yes.  Similarly, other professional bodies such as the NMBI and CORU will be responsible for recognising qualifications relating to their professions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00400"><p>If a university in England introduces a new course such which involves graduate entry rather than standard entry, will that course be assessed under new recognition processes?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.42" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00500"><p>Initially, the General Medical Council, GMC, in the United Kingdom would have to recognise the new course.  By virtue of its relationship with the GMC, the Irish Medical Council understands where the GMC sets the bar in terms of standards.  Once the GMC approved the course, the Medical Council would recognise that as the course meets the GMC test which it considers equivalent to ours, that is sufficient for us to recognise the course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00600"><p>The discussion of Brexit nearly always relates to the political or economic consequences.  It was late in the day before I started thinking about the impact it may have on our health sector.  How can we ensure that the general public understand what is happening or could happen with regard to Brexit?  As Mr. Breslin is aware, under the Medical Practitioners Act, Irish qualifications must be recognised in other EU countries.  What is Mr. Breslin's view on the potential difficulties in regard to recognising qualifications in England?</p> <p>  He referred to the various groups set up to consider the implications of Brexit.  I ask him to expand on the work of the Brexit operations team.  What issues does it deal with and what actions does it take?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00700"><p>The Minister briefed the Cabinet on this issue recently.  We have issued public statements and it is outlined in the contingency action plan.  We have convened stakeholders for discussions, particularly in the area of medicine supply, on which it is very important that there is good clear public information.  Later today I will write to stakeholders with whom we had a very good meeting last week, including representatives of the pharmaceutical industry, the Irish Pharmacy Union, which represents community pharmacists, and a range of other stakeholders in order to ensure that we are all aware of the exact situation regarding medicine supplies.  As stated earlier, it is very important that people understand that this is a sophisticated industry with well-developed supply chains and some of the largest multinationals in the world delivering medicines to community pharmacists through very well established and resourced wholesalers.  The HPRA, the HSE and the Department are working with the industry to pre-empt any issues.  As per my opening statement, we are confident that there are no current issues.  However, medicine shortage can arise even without Brexit, so we will remain vigilant.  If an issue arises, we will put actions in place to resolve it as quickly as possible.  We are confident that there is adequate provision and that wholesalers routinely hold sufficient stock to bridge any problems that may arise at the ports.  The important message is that there is no need for patients, retail pharmacists or hospitals to increase stock levels or ask for extra prescriptions.  To do so would suck product out of the supply chain, which might produce a shortage and mean a person who needs the medicine would not be able to get it.  That is a very important public message which we are seeking to promote.  We will continue to review this matter with industry representatives.  As Mr. Hennessy outlined, we are considering categories of medicines and product lines.  In addition to receiving the message from the industry that it has done the preparations - and we are very appreciative of its work in that regard - we are verifying the availability of the most critical medicines and asking the industry to be definitive in regard to how the product will be delivered and that there will be sufficient supply.  All of the information to date indicates that the work is proceeding and that there is satisfaction in respect of adequate supply.  That is important information which we are promoting to the public.  It would be great if something sensible could be done in Westminster to conclude an agreement as that would render all of this damage limitation unnecessary.  However, we will continue with it because of the uncertainty.  We will continue to make that information publicly available.  Obviously, as we get closer to Brexit, we will make further information available.</p> <p>  The potential impact on the flow of patients between Ireland and the UK for specialist services is also a source of public concern.  As I stated, we are working to ensure that will continue and are confident that it will.  The authorities in the UK are very anxious to facilitate it.  As Mr. Hennessy outlined, service agreements have been reached regarding individual circumstances such as cancer or cardiac care in Altnagelvin hospital or other arrangements which we facilitate.  We are confident those agreements will withstand any issues that arise out of Brexit.  Those are probably the two most important messages I wish to send to the public today.</p> <p>  On the Medical Practitioners Act, as previously outlined, we envisage that the Medical Council will examine its current rule set.  Should the UK crash out, an EU-recognised qualification would no longer suffice to practice in the UK.  Rather, doctors there would require GMC UK-recognised qualification.  We understand the implications of that.  Once we are satisfied that a person has such a qualification, we will put him or her through an administrative procedure similar to that in regard to recognition for EU qualifications but which will no longer be automatic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1262" speakername="Margaret Murphy O'Mahony" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00800"><p>There will be two channels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#H00900"><p>There will be two channels.  A person with a French qualification will automatically be recognised.  A person with a UK qualification will not have to undergo the same depth of analysis as a person from a third country with which we have no relationship.  There will be a fast-track system but it will differ from the process for holders of EU-recognised qualifications.  Our regulators will put back-to-back arrangements in place with their equivalents in the UK to allow that to function.</p> <p>  I refer to the Brexit operation team.</p><p>I hope colleagues will have a chance to provide the committee with detail of the importance of that team.  The HPRA, the HSE and the Food Safety Authority have been working on this issue for two years and a tremendous amount of work has been done.  After Christmas we decided that the cycle of work and the response would speed up considerably to the end of March and beyond.  Rather than have meetings every three or four weeks, we need a functional team from across the agencies and the Department which has a leadership and meets every week.  In between the weekly meetings there will be constant bilateral engagement.  If the HPRA needs to work with the HSE on a medicine supply issue, it can do so between meetings and report back on the Monday when the operations team convenes again.  The Department is providing the leadership for the team to ensure it will all happen in real time.  There has been very good collaboration over two years, but we have speeded up its intensity and integrated to a greater extent.  It is focusing on the full range of Brexit tasks we will have to undertake under many of the differing headings.  It is providing a central point for the agencies to feed into the Department.  It is also allowing the Department to feed into central government.  When we talk to the Department of the Taoiseach or the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, we will do so having freshly left a conversation with the HPRA, the HSE and the Food Safety Authority and with the most up-to-date information possible.  It also permits a joined-up stakeholder engagement and communications piece.  On Wednesday last Mr. Goodman led a meeting with medicines stakeholders.  It was the full range of the industry, regulators and professionals working in the area.  He did so with representatives of the HPRA and the HSE in the room.  Everybody heard the same thing at the same time.  It is important in responding rapidly to an evolving situation that people move at the same speed.  That is the purpose of the Brexit operations team.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#J00200"><p>I ask Ms Nolan about medicines.  Will HPRA recognition and approval of drugs process change after Brexit?  I presume existing drugs will be recognised.  As new drugs come from the United Kingdom, however, will there be a different process of recognition and approval?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#J00300"><p>In his opening statement Mr. Breslin mentioned the various regulatory pathways by which medicines come to the market.  In the light of Brexit, changes to these regulatory pathways must take place.  Where there are activities which are conducted in the United Kingdom such as manufacturing or the batch release or testing of medicines, in the light of Brexit they must be changed to another EU member state.  In the case of existing licensed medicines, where there is a dependence on the United Kingdom for the activities to be conducted or where the UK agency was the lead agency in the technical evaluation of the medicines, all of these issues have to be transferred.  That is one consequence of Brexit.  Preparations have been under way at European level since 2016 and are advancing.  The vast majority of the changes have been made, but in fairness to the committee, I note that we are aware of some companies within the United Kingdom which supply both that market and the Irish market which have not as yet made the regulatory changes.  The other system is that after the United Kingdom leaves the European Union and becomes a third country, the EU 27 will continue to authorise medicines as it currently does and Ireland will continue to be part of that system.  The United Kingdom will separate from that process.  We are working on arrangements with the United Kingdom for things like joint packaging.  Because we have a common language, for a lot of the medicines supplied here and in the United Kingdom there is joint packaging.  Joint packaging with third countries will be an acceptable process.  We have worked on solutions to maintain the supply of medicines to the market and ensure we will have sufficient contingency plans in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#J00400"><p>Could there be a problem with the companies which have not made their arrangements in accessing the drugs they produce?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#J00500"><p>As Mr. Breslin outlined, an extensive planning process has been in train in the past two years.  At this point, we are working with the companies involved.  In many cases, we will have sufficient alternatives to those medicines and will not necessarily be reliant on them.  This is part of the criticality assessment exercise on which we are working.  If it comes down to dependency on a medicine, we are open to looking at pragmatic ways to transition across the period after Brexit to allow supply to continue to the market.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#J00600"><p>After Brexit the United Kingdom will, effectively, be a third country.  I acknowledge the preparatory work already done and congratulate the delegates on the options they have covered.  Dipping a little further into the food quality controls that will apply, as a third country the United Kingdom will import from and export to third countries and, presumably, the European Union.  If there is no agreement and it is a crash-out, the scenery will be slightly different.  Will adequate controls be in place to ensure the quality and standards applicable throughout the European Union will continue to prevail, given, in particular, that we will be in the European Union, while the United Kingdom will not?  Is it envisaged that an EU standard will be applicable?  I acknowledge the common travel area, but I am a little worried about the extent to which it will prevail if the standards to which we have become accustomed in the European Union continue to apply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#J00700"><p>The common travel area does not relate to products but to people.  It is a different conversation than for product movement between the United Kingdom and the European Union post-Brexit.  Obviously, we have an interest in food safety in that context.  Significant preparations are under way.  The HSE's environmental health service has responsibility for food safety as it relates to food of non-animal origin, while the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine has responsibility for foods of animal origin.  Broadly, that is how the division of responsibility works.  For example, we have approved 61 additional environmental health officers for the HSE.  They will carry out physical checks and checks on documentation in the importation of foods.  Currently, arrangements are in place for third country importation.  If foods come from outside the European Union and land in Dublin Port as their first port of entry to the European Union, the environmental health service personnel at the port go through the products to ensure they are acceptable for supply to the Irish market.  They do this on a risk basis and do not have to go through every product.  They look at the nature of the product and decide what to inspect.</p> <p>  In the event that there is a crash-out, products coming from the United Kingdom would have to be subject to the same regime.  That means taking a risk-based approach where we would look at the nature of the products, while the environmental health service would make a decision, based on the documentation, on what was worthy of physical inspection.  That would involve a logistical operation, in particular at Dublin Port, on the part of the environmental health service of the HSE, officers from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and Revenue customs officials.  While such an operation is already in place, it will have to be beefed up considerably.  If a ship arrives from the United Kingdom, officials will have to look at the cargo details, lorries and importers, of which they will have to receive advance notice.  They will look at the products involved and a determination that might be made would be for the environmental health service to inspect two lorries off that ship.  Revenue will act as the co-ordination mechanism and issue a message to the haulier to the effect that the lorry must be presented for inspection.  It would not get to exit the port without that inspection.  The lorry and its cargo would be presented for inspection by environmental health officers before it could go on its way.</p><p>The Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine could do the same for meat or similarly the Revenue in the case of a customs issue.  The logistical operation in the port has been carefully planned to ensure that, on a risk basis, we have controls in place but the free flow of traffic continues.  It is to ensure that the truck driver who does not have any issues can get off the ship and out of Dublin Port without experiencing traffic jams.  Those who are subject to inspection will obviously experience some delay as their products are examined.  That is one of the consequences of moving out of the EU.  People importing from the UK into Ireland will be subject in some cases to a check of documentation or a physical inspection based on risk.  That is not the case now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#K00200"><p>During the foot and mouth epidemic in the UK, satisfactory arrangements were put in place to ensure no contamination came from the UK or <i>vice versa</i>.  There did not seem to be any great backlogs at ports or airports.  It was done efficiently and effectively.  I presume cognisance has been taken of that to put something comparable in place now.</p><p>I will move on very quickly to the supply of drugs.  I have listened to some of our colleagues in the UK predicting a doomsday situation for this country after the UK leaves.  To what extent has the Department considered their views?  Are there any particular drugs or range of drugs that might be controlled to an extraordinary extent by third countries?  That is what the UK will become.  What has been our experience in dealing directly with third countries heretofore regarding compliance and availability?  How are generic drugs likely to be affected?  I presume that has been examined.</p><p>On access to healthcare for children, in the run up to the provision of our own new national children's hospital, what arrangements are in place with third countries?  I refer to the UK and others.  To what degree is remuneration readily available?  We can still do that after Brexit.  Will Mr. Breslin, however, give us some indication of the other countries besides the UK with which we have such arrangements?  My understanding is that any bilateral arrangements require EU approval because we are, and will remain, a part of the EU.  I would like some clarification on that issue, just in case we find ourselves in some kind of a cul-de-sac at a later stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#K00300"><p>I might ask the HPRA and the HSE to come in on the drugs supply issue as well.  The starting point is that there is a significant routing of medicines from the UK, either originating there and landing in Ireland or being sourced from there.  Up to 70% of medicines on the Irish market are manufactured in the UK or transit through the UK.  When we talk about the supply chain, and modification of the supply chain, individual manufacturers have looked at that.  Some have made arrangements, for example, where the drug is manufactured on the Continent and is moved through the UK landbridge, while some have made arrangements to come directly to Ireland.</p> <p>  Others have decided that where a product was previously contained within a drop for the UK and Ireland, they will now separate out those two loads and send them separately via the landbridge.  Significant supply chain modification is under way.  Much of that depends on the characteristics of the medicine.  If a particular medicine has a long shelf life and little potential for disruption due to a delay at a port, then there is more flexibility on the part of the manufacturer and the distribution chain.  Particular areas examined include medicines with a short shelf life, as Mr. Hennessy referenced.  A delay could lead to a product expiring.  The HSE and the HPRA have reached out to those suppliers in particular to seek reassurance and verification that arrangements in place will not be disrupted.</p> <p>  In general, the arrangements in place in Ireland for the supply of medicines are quite distinct from those in the UK.  We are an island and we have a wholesale distribution system very different from that of the UK.  We also have significant stocks held domestically within our supply chain.  That will be the first port of call if any immediate issues were to arise.  We are working with a range of stakeholders in the medicines industry to ensure they have the proper capability to respond to any disruption that might arise.  The scale of the thousands of medicines involved requires individual level preparation and planning.  In respect of critical medicines, we have an exercise under way to look at alternatives, to look at supply chains and to verify what is under way.</p> <p>  As of today, we have no issue which we are declaring will be a problem or disrupted.  We will continue to engage right up to Brexit and beyond to ensure that stays the case.  There is a background issue.  The Irish market has been very intermingled with the UK market.  Potentially, over the medium term rather than in the next weeks, manufacturers or suppliers may look at the Irish market as a smaller market post Brexit.  We were part of a huge UK-Ireland market.  For some people, we will now be an Irish market of 4.5 million people without a great supply requirement.  We may experience a situation relating to our size, as other countries do, where some suppliers decide it is not worth supplying into such a market or they may want to supply on different terms.  We will have to watch that in the medium term post Brexit.  It is not an immediate issue.</p> <p>  Generic medicines are potentially an issue.  Down the road, some suppliers might consider that extra work is required to get into this market, more documentation is needed and not much is sold.  They might then question what is the point in continuing.  We have to look at all of those situations.  In many cases, because we are dealing with generic drugs, the active ingredients are being manufactured by others.  One supplier, therefore, making a decision not to supply the Irish market might not be crucial if other generic suppliers provide the same active ingredient or the originator is still on the market.  I ask the HPRA to expand on that matter.  I ask Mr. Hennessy to speak about the children's services and existing linkages.  Regarding our ability to conduct bilateral agreements, the EU-UK withdrawal agreement and the negotiations in Brussels specifically recognise the common travel area as a distinct feature of the Irish-UK relationship and gives us a licence to give that expression post Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#K00400"><p>I thank Mr. Breslin.  I call Dr. Nolan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#K00500"><p>I will not repeat what Mr Breslin said.  I will just add some more information.  On Deputy Durkan's question on doomsday scenario predictions in the UK regarding medicines supply, Mr. Breslin outlined very well the logistical preparations the industry is making.  We have to remember that, in most cases, the industry has been preparing for almost three years.  The industry has great expertise in logistics, knows how to split off supply from Ireland and examine different routing for medicines to come into the country.</p> <p>  In addition, the wholesale distribution model in Ireland is very different from the UK.  We hold much larger buffer stocks at the wholesale level than the UK.  In general, we hold six to eight weeks of stock.  We have, therefore, a mechanism within that system giving us the capacity to maintain supply even if there are delays in getting medicines transported to and from the UK.  Our system is more flexible and adaptable because different mechanisms evolved in the UK supply chain compared with the Irish situation.</p> <p>  Mr. Breslin spoke of generic medicines.  The generic medicines industry works on smaller margins in respect of supplying medicines to the marketplace.  Brexit, as we have said, does mean change.  The cost of supply to the market may go up.</p><p>We do not anticipate that there will be a major impact in the aftermath of or at the end of March, but what we may see over time is a rationalisation by the industry of portfolios of medicines that are supplied into the Irish market.  We do have systems for dealing with this.  Mr. Breslin mentioned that the HPRA has a co-ordinating role in respect of shortages of medicines.  We have a framework that has been put in place within the past six months and which is operating very well and has very good capability for managing shortages.  The main thing in all our Brexit contingency planning, which has been ongoing for quite some time, is that we have very close engagement with the industry and receive real-time updates from it.  The operational meeting to which Mr. Breslin referred gives us a mechanism to be able to react to an evolving situation very carefully.  Therefore, with very careful monitoring and with issues occurring over time, the situation has the capability to be very well managed if there is rationalisation of generics.  We also have quite an extensive supply of generic medicines in the Irish market.  The Deputy may be familiar with the interchangeable lists of medicines published by the HPRA.  This is the list of generic medicines that are available in the Irish marketplace.  It is an aid used at pharmacy level for changing patients-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00200"><p>They are available and manufactured here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00300"><p>No, not necessarily manufactured here.  These are medicines that are brought into the country.  What I am saying is that we have adequate supplies and there is no immediate concern.</p> <p>  Deputy Durkan raised a point about third countries, bringing medicines in from them and how the system can adapt to that.  The European system, of which Ireland is a part, is very well used to dealing with third countries.  It is actually set up to allow for importation of medicines from third countries.  There are additional regulatory requirements that must be put in place if we bring in medicines.  This is where the product must go through a process called batch release testing.  The developments in Europe over the past two years in preparation for the UK withdrawal have meant that much of the transfer of these activities into other European countries for certain medicines has transferred to Ireland, so we have good capability to address that situation as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.62" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00400"><p>To add a quick point to that, high-volume, low-priced medicines are a very specific part of the contingency planning.  I echo Dr. Nolan's point that we do not have huge concerns in the short term, but in the medium to longer term there may be issues around continuity of supply and perhaps price implications, seeing as Ireland is such a small component of the market for those products.  My colleague, Mr. Swords, has been working on a number of these areas, including medical-surgical supplies, in order to ensure continuity and availability, but there are no major concerns emerging in the short term.  In the medium to longer term we will need to monitor matters carefully.  As Dr. Nolan mentioned, however, of their nature, there is interchangeability and alternatives may have to be sourced, but we are particularly conscious that there are high numbers of patients, particularly those with chronic illnesses, who are on these medicines who would have become reliant on or used to the same products for perhaps a considerable amount of time.  We are not underestimating the issue for a moment but it represents more of a longer-term concern rather than a short-term one in the context of Brexit.</p> <p>  Deputy Durkan referred to children.  The treatment abroad scheme covers this pretty extensively for both adults and children.  However, children represent a niche in the context of transplant services in particular.  We have a very close relationship with a small number of UK tertiary sites that provide these specialist services.  The numbers would not be sufficient to provide that level of service within the island of Ireland.  Our planning focus - and there has been very extensive planning on this - is on ensuring that this access route remains open and available, and the agreements with the individual sites in the UK are developed in order to ensure that post Brexit.  As I said, though, the particular concern, and where there would not necessarily be readily available alternatives to UK sites, is in the area of transplants for children.</p> <p>  I do not know if Mr. Hennessy wishes to add anything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1322" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00500"><p>Has the HSE revised any of that with a view to an alternative in the event of there being a difficulty gaining access to the UK site, either for children or for adults?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.64" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00600"><p>We have done some work on that.  The concern would be, as I think the Secretary General mentioned, that very close relationships have developed and grown over the years between Ireland and the UK on the basis of consultant-to-consultant referral, and there is a high degree of comfort among Irish clinicians about these sites in terms of the service they provide.  To be frank and truthful, it would be difficult in the short term to develop alternatives across mainland Europe for many of these services.  Therefore, our efforts are on ensuring that continuity remains post Brexit in the short term, at least with the UK sites.  Over time, we will look to develop relationships with alternative providers.  Again, to be fair, there is treatment abroad activity in other continental countries from Ireland that we want to develop, but I do not think any of us would like to be reliant on that in the short term and, therefore, we need to maintain our connections with the UK sites.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00700"><p>Are there any particular concerns about vaccines, as opposed to medication?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.66" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00800"><p>Mr. Swords may wish to comment on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Swords" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#L00900"><p>I might make a couple of points about the supply chain.  The question was asked whether there is any learning from what has happened in the UK and so on.  Over a year ago the UK Government issued a kind of intention, a directive, stating that it wanted to stockpile certain items as far as six months for all the companies.  At that time, we had been in discussions with our supply chain people in the drugs, medical-surgical and food areas.  They are the three key areas on which we have concentrated for Brexit.  Nonetheless, the key to any supply chain is an even flow of product rather than stockpiling because stockpiling actually creates difficulties.  This is evident now in that some hospitals in the UK are finding it difficult to get product even though there is enough product in the country.  There is an abundance of product in some areas.  The hospitals do not have it when they need it, though, which means there is a redistribution and a cost associated with that.  Our strategy has been to keep an even flow of product.  As Dr. Nolan, Mr. Breslin and Mr. Hennessy stated, we have enough stock in the country at any given time to allow us to plan forward.</p> <p>  To give the committee a bit of an idea of this, we have a national logistics plan in the HSE and a national distribution centre with nine hubs around the country, which we use to supply out into community and hospitals.  We have six weeks' worth of stock at any given time across 6,000 stock-keeping units which supply on a regular basis the items that are required and used in the hospitals.  That is one area of security, and we will monitor it as we go forward.  As for drugs, we have met representatives of all the umbrella companies and are meeting representatives of the main distribution companies to see what they have in place and to reassure ourselves that the stock is there.  We have been very encouraged by what we have found.  As Dr. Nolan said, there is six to eight weeks' stock in wholesale.  There is a further number of weeks' worth of stock in the manufacturing process at any given time, and there lies the secret to our success in maintaining that supply in an even way and not knee-jerking across the system and causing peaks and valleys, which could in fact have an effect on employment.  We have manufacturing in Ireland, so we do not want to disrupt any element of the supply chain.  It is a very refined and mature supply chain, and everyone is encouraging us not to overreact.  If we stay sensible on this and stay in communication, which is what we are doing, we will be able to see whether there will be a break on 29 March.  It is later in the year that we will see any real impact because we will start seeing the ports filling up or whatever.  Even allowing for that, and looking for securities of supply, particularly in the short-life areas, we have met the suppliers of products and they have brought in enough manufacturing raw materials for three months in some cases and are upping that in some cases to eight weeks on the overall supply.  We are learning all the time about our supply chains and probably getting more information than we have ever had and more education on how we will deal with any shortages.  The shortages framework has worked very well.</p> <p>  To move from the area of drugs and more into the area of food, there are shortages on an ongoing basis in food supply.  One of our main suppliers of ambient food sources products from all over the world.  They bring shortages to our attention from time to time and we discuss any shortages they have with our catering officers who are on the ground providing the services within health.</p><p>We agree any changes that have to take place to ensure that a spurious product does not get into the supply chain.  That is very closely monitored by our catering officers.  It is a good example of day to day shortages happening within a supply chain.  We have to maintain that and keep an even flow of product, and encourage everybody to be sensible about it.</p><p> There are 1,800 pharmacies which take deliveries 11 times per week on average, through the distribution service.  There are numerous pharmacies in different communities.  They rely on each other, and it is a very mature and well-stocked system.  There is up to four weeks of supply in the individual pharmacies and six to eight weeks in the supply chain.  We do not see shortages arising at the moment.  There is no difficulty with that; it is well managed.  It is encouraging that there is such a large amount of communication going on at the moment.  We have written to more than 300 of our main suppliers and have had 70% of them write back.  Much of the information in that correspondence states that they have examined their supply chain and that they are looking at six to eight weeks, and in some cases three to six months.  Generic medicines were mentioned.  Some smaller companies are actually stocking up to six to 12 months worth of product.  They are making sure that we will not face an interruption of supply.  </p><p> It is important to note that we deal extensively with distributors, and because of that we have options within our supply chain.  We have been rationalising our logistics operation within health over the last number of years and are bringing efficiencies into it.  We are currently extending that process into the Dublin region.  We are reducing our inventory in many areas.  On average we keep two to three weeks of stock in hospitals across all of our areas, but we rely on each other in the event of any shortage in any given area.  We are in control of our information, and we are getting better and better at it.  While Brexit poses different problems and questions for us, we are in a position to answer those questions.  Our one risk, if it can be called that, is that there may be a delay of product, but there is enough in the system to sustain a shock.  </p><p> On the question of drugs that might be required on a short-term basis with a quick turnaround time, customs officials have indicated to us that, where paperwork is in place, it will provide a blue light service.  That is as good as it gets.  We have spoken to suppliers, and instead of just using road, rail and shipping to deliver the products we will also use air freight.  Those arrangements are in place with some of the companies at this point in time.  We are examining the issues and going out to meet our main supplies to ensure they understand where we are coming from and to make sure that we are working together on this issue.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#M00200"><p>What about vaccines?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.70" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#M00300"><p>The level of vaccines in place is fine at the moment.  Population health colleagues have tested the supply chains for all the immunisation programmes.  Most of them come directly to us from Europe and do not touch the UK at all.  All have tested well and we have solid assurances around them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#M00400"><p>Many of my points have been touched upon, but I welcome what Mr. Hennessy said earlier about the organ transplant programme at Great Ormond Street, and also the collaboration between the ambulance services in case of major incidences and emergencies.  My colleague, Senator Burke, mentioned young health professionals going to the UK to gain experience.  That is invaluable; I spent some time in south Wales and completed my GP scheme there.  Young health professionals gain invaluable experience by working in a different jurisdiction.  This is probably an issue for postgraduate organisations, but if a young doctor completed his or her GP scheme in the UK, gained qualification and became a member of the Royal College of General Practitioners, ICGP, perhaps that could be reciprocated with a membership of the Irish College of General Practitioners on returning to Ireland.  We hope they will return to Ireland to address some of the shortages we have here.</p> <p>  We had a long discussion about drugs, and I recognise the collaboration between the Department, the Health Products Regulatory Authority, HPRA, and the HSE.  I also acknowledge the challenges for refrigerated products and products with short shelf lives.  The vaccines were mentioned; are we happy that two months supply is enough?  I presume the witnesses were discussing childhood vaccinations.  Are travel vaccinations also covered under that grouping?  There is also a question about cancer drugs, and immunotherapy and biological agents.  Mr. Breslin mentioned critical medicines, but biological agents fall under that critical medicines banner.  Often with rheumatological diseases, for example rheumatoid arthritis or inflammatory bowel disease, consultants will go straight in with a biological agent to get a patient's symptoms under control quickly.  Previously they might have used a disease modifying agent and built up to using a biological agent.  It is nowadays often a first-line treatment.  The demand for that product is obviously higher.  They are used in such a variety of cases, including gastrointestinal cases or joint cases.  Are the witnesses quite happy that we have enough of those types of drugs available?  I agree that we have good links with multinational companies and that there are excellent wholesalers in the country.  The witnesses correctly said that medicine shortages are an ongoing issue, with or without Brexit, but as a GP on the ground I am beginning to see patients requesting extra drugs because people are seeing the charade and disorganisation in the British Parliament and combining it with the 29 March deadline looming.  GPs are once again acting as gatekeepers in a role they did not think they would have.  We are trying to reassure people, but would the witnesses consider redoubling the efforts to get the message out to the public on the ground in the form of a media awareness campaign, with radio and TV, for example?  People are asking for more inhalers and more blood pressure drugs.  People who are using these biological agents are concerned that the consultants will not be sending the high-tech scripts down to their local pharmacy in order that the local pharmacy would dispense them.</p> <p>  As professionals we can be reassured by the comments made here today.  However, there is a bit of a disconnect on the ground.  People are obviously worried about their conditions, and I believe a public awareness campaign would really help to benefit that cohort of patients.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.72" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#M00500"><p>Coincidentally I signed off on a communication on medicines to go to a range of stakeholders last night.  Included in that is the ICGP.  It is important that networks of GPs are given the knowledge so that when a patient attends, the GP is able to tell them key things about it.  We will look at this issue.  We have a communications team in place to do that.  At the moment we are getting great free messaging out because people are asking questions, like the members present today, and the newspapers are writing about it.  As we come closer to the time we will think about putting our own public messaging out.  We have to think about the best way to do that.  If we tell people what we do not want them to do, they think that is perhaps what they should do.  That is why working through professionals is really important.  We must involve the Irish Pharmacy Union, IPU, and the ICGP so that the local community pharmacist is able to discern the real situation and tell clients what it is.  We will be doing more and more of that.</p> <p>  The point about medicine shortages already being a feature is absolutely correct.  There are 45 medicines on a current list at the moment, but with the HPRA and stakeholders we have put a medicine shortage framework in place to address those.  The last thing we want to happen - but which probably will happen in the period ahead - is that shortages in the near future will be blamed on Brexit.  There is every chance that the problem will be due to a manufacturing issue or an issue that has arisen for a completely different reason.  We must remain clear on what the source of the delays is and to work with stakeholders to explain it, while not allowing erroneous information to make its way into our system.  </p> <p>  I will ask Mr. Swords or the HPRA to talk about the critical medicines assessment process, but we are interested in building on the overall message we have received from manufacturers and wholesalers that there is a plan for this and that there is a sufficient amount of medicine.</p><p>In the case of medicines where, because of their characteristics there could be a critical issue if they were not available, we want an additional layer of verification.  We are doing that by category.  It is important that one has a medicine within the category one would be able to prescribe in that situation.  There would be some interchangeability.  The health professionals are doing this.  Doctors, through clinical programmes, and pharmacists are identifying, say, four medicines of which we need a supply.  If there was a problem with one, we would still be okay with the other three.  That involves more detailed conversations where one is looking for an additional layer of reassurance and verification.  We are going through this process.  It is not completed and we will keep refreshing it as we go along.</p><p> The important point is that just because a medicine is critical, does not mean that it is one about which we are concerned.  It could be critical in coming directly to Ireland from the Continent and there could be no disruption.  It could have features to it which mean even a short delay of a week or two might not impact our supply.  We must not just examine ones that are critical but also examine the current supply chain.  That is the level of analysis we are bringing to bear on this.</p><p> I am not certain if the travel vaccination is in this process.  It is probably in the more general process of checking levels and working with manufacturers.</p><p> It is not just about medicines which end up in hospitals but those that the public will need.  That includes medicines dispensed through retail pharmacy and prescribed by GPs.  We have to take a public health view of this, not just looking at the ones which we order.  We have to understand that some medicines will be critical but will be dispensed in the community.  They can be just as important as medicines dispensed in hospitals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#N00200"><p>The reason I was late was I was on the picket line with the nurses this morning showing solidarity in the same way as I would with any public sector worker or civil servant fighting for his or her rights and entitlements.  I read through the submissions and I apologise for being late.</p> <p>  The evidence suggests there is a struggle to recruit nurses and other healthcare professionals.  Is there any sense within the groups working on this that Brexit will have a negative or positive impact on the health sector workforce?  Much work has been done, which is welcome.  We had an engagement previously where the same level of work or engagement was not obvious.  Is someone examining the implication for workforce planning?  There is mutual recognition of qualifications which has been discussed previously.  My sense is that the British health service has aggressively recruited staff because it has a fear of the implications of Brexit for its staffing numbers.  Is this being countered?</p> <p>  It was stated in the submissions that the HSE is continuing to work on awareness of Brexit among HSE and health service staff generally, key suppliers, patients and with the public.  I appreciate the dilemma because we do not want to panic people.  We have been focused on Brexit for a long time.  However, more people are beginning to focus their attention on it and they are concerned.  I have spoken to people who are nervous and asking whether they should get a six months supply with their next prescription.  There will be an issue if everybody starts stockpiling.  I respect it can be tricky but has any consideration been given to a media campaign?  It should be more than just talking to the professionals and somewhere along the lines of radio, television or newspaper advertisements.</p> <p>  The Department stated it would be impossible in a no-deal scenario to maintain the current seamless arrangements between the EU and the UK across a range of sectors that are currently facilitated by our common EU membership.  There is no such thing as a good Brexit.  We said this repeatedly and nobody majority on the island voted for it.  However, we are where we are.  In the event of a no-deal scenario, where will the first implications hit?  Will there be a requirement at that stage for legislative change or will it have to come in advance of that?</p> <p>  Last weekend, I attended a conference in Belfast and was also at the Border Communities against Brexit protest, where people asked me about cross-Border health services.  For example, GP out-of-hours services operate between Keady and Castleblayney, and Altnagelvin and Inishowen.  They work well because they are geographically close.  In the event of a no-deal Brexit, will these services continue?  Is it anticipated that there will be a break in some services while alternative arrangements are made?  I recognise it is not the fault of any person in this room that we find ourselves where we are.  However, is it anticipated that there will be a break and then it will be necessary to restore those services or is it anticipated that services will continue seamlessly?</p> <p>  I asked if service level agreements had been Brexit-proofed at a previous committee meeting.  It was a year ago and the answer was, "We did not know".  I appreciate that at that stage nobody could have predicted how this would go.  The level of unpreparedness in Britain and its impact on us is a concerns.  It is clear that while we could do all the work to prepare ourselves, we are geographically close to people who may undo any good work that might be done. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.75" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#N00300"><p>It is not anticipated that there will be any break in services.  We have confidence in that.  Mr. John Hennessy has spoken about the Brexit-proofing of service level agreements, which has been completed.  He spoke about co-operation and working together, CAWT, because some of those arrangements are under a co-operation mechanism which we have.  We are not anticipating anything in that regard.<br/><br/>I noted early in the meeting that <i>The Times</i>Ireland edition jumped from a general statement about Brexit at large to Secretary General says medicines will be okay but cross-Border services are going to be impacted.  I did not say that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#N00400"><p>That clarification is welcome but it underlines the need for a media awareness campaign.  I also read that article and it was not correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.77" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#N00500"><p>When I talked about the impact across sectors &ndash; some of the discussion has highlighted some of the areas - there are things which are currently automatic but will not be when the UK becomes a third country.</p><p>We have had two examples so far.  One is in the area of food safety.  When product is moving east-west at the moment, it is moving within the EU.  If the UK crashes out, when product moves east-west, it will be coming from a third country and there will have to be a risk-based decision as to whether the documentation is pulled and there is a physical inspection.  We are putting 61 staff into the HSE to do that.  We are spending &euro;6 million on staff.  If we could have that &euro;6 million to spend on patient care, I would much prefer it, but because Brexit is happening, that is what we are doing.  Going from a situation that was seamless to one in which we have administrative overhead is an example of the impact Brexit has on this country and on the UK.</p><p> The Deputy referred to professional qualifications that are currently automatic.  We will have a procedure that makes it smooth and seamless but it will require an extra procedure.  It will not delay things, but while recognition of EU qualifications is automatic, we will have to have a means of saying we understand the standard of a UK qualification and will have to apply our system to recognise it here.  It is an extra layer that will have to be built in.</p><p> On the question of awareness, we are actively considering our communications strategy.  We are working through intermediaries, particularly health professionals, general practitioners and pharmacists, as well as patient groups.  Mr. Hennessy can speak on that.  There are particular patient groups that would have particular anxiety.  If we can give them information, they will be able to talk to their membership as well.  The Deputy asked about the content and timing.  We are actively considering pushing messaging out in a more visible, public way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#O00200"><p>Yes.  I do appreciate that it has to be balanced but it is something that cannot be ruled out at this stage.  Anecdotally, I have spoken to people who are planning to get a few extra just in case.  It is a question of putting people's minds at rest and assuring them there is no need to do that, and that if they do it, they will contribute to the problem rather than it being any solution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.80" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#O00300"><p>Mr. Goodman has reminded me about the question of legislation.  The Bill whose heads were published is to be introduced before a no-deal crash out, which we hope will not happen.  That is subject to drafting and bringing the Bill through the Oireachtas.  The intention is that the legislation, which would sit above what we have talked about and would allow for the HSE to reimburse services in the UK that are treating Irish patients, for example, would go through before 29 March.</p> <p>  On workforce, there is a degree of speculation and it is not going to impact us immediately in April.  However, it will potentially change the global attractiveness of the UK.  One of the things that may happen is that professionals who are trained elsewhere in the EU may no longer find it attractive to go to the UK.  The UK is seized of that.  They may then find themselves running into shortages in the UK.  They are just as worried about non-professionally qualified healthcare staff such as cleaners, porters and other staff.  There may well be shortages in those areas because traditionally a lot of those posts have been filled by foreign nationals in the UK.  They may respond to that by looking for English-speaking health professionals and targeting us.  Equally, we would be more attractive in that situation because EU-qualified professionals who want to come to an English-speaking country will no longer have the UK to go to and may be interested in Ireland.  It is push and pull and it is hard to speculate.  We are working on getting the professional recognitions in place that would allow us to be able to move in the event of any patterns that develop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.81" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Hennessy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#O00400"><p>I have just a couple of points to add.  I will ask Ms Keon to speak on the North-South dimension because she has been very close to Brexit-proofing the agreements between the various providers.  We mentioned some of them but the Deputy is right that the GP out of hours service is an important part of that programme as well.  We have been very conscious of the need for clear, reliable information for the public and for patients.  The committee is going to see evidence of a lot more proactive communication from this end over the next four to six weeks.  It has already kicked off with some stakeholders in respect of suppliers.  We are meeting the National Patients Forum, which has representation from most of the patient advocacy groups, especially those representing people with chronic conditions.  We are meeting it next week to provide information and assurance where necessary on particular issues like medicines and supplies.  We understand fully how people would be concerned about those things, and with the benefit of good, reliable information, we may be able to prevent the kind of stockpiling tendencies to which the Deputy referred.  We are watching closely at the supplier end as well to see if there are any unusual patterns of ordering from any particular sources.  Included in that programme of communication, as Senator Swanick mentioned, would be general practitioners, pharmacists and prescribers generally to help assure people about supply chains and to try to manage it.</p> <p>  The Secretary General has covered most of the workforce issues.  The HSE HR department has analysed in great detail the Brexit details across the spectrum of qualifications, training, education and recruitment.  We have a good handle on the implications there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.82" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Paula Keon" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#O00500"><p>The Deputy is correct about the GP out of hours service.  It is a very important part and I will get to it in a minute.  In fact, there have been 30 years of intensive cross-Border work between North and South.  For those of us who live on the Border, it is very much the norm to get a service in the other jurisdiction.  Since 1992 there has been a formal arrangement, the Ballyconnell agreement, whereby services North and South set up the cross-Border organisation, Co-operation and Working Together, CAWT.  That was done largely using European INTERREG funding to seed projects North and South to use economies of scale and find solutions that we could not otherwise find because of our geographic distance from the urban centres.  To Brexit-proof our current range of work, which is an INTERREG 5A &euro;30 million project, we have it underpinned by Her Majesty's Treasury.  With the Department of Health, we went to the UK to seek assurance that the current round of funding will be secured until the end of the programme of funding in 2020.  The future of European funding is obviously uncertain and probably part of the future arrangements.  We will have to see what happens there.  The current round of funding that seeds these projects is underpinned.</p> <p>  Outside the INTERREG funding there is a lot of North-South work going on.  The radiotherapy centre is very innovative and the only capital build in health on the island of Ireland with a ratio of two thirds to one third built and the same in respect of patients.  A second one is the primary percutaneous coronary intervention, PCI, which is clinically absolutely the solution for the patients of Donegal.  They only have a 90 minute window for their stents.  It is absolutely the solution for our patients.  We did a mapping exercise to look at all these service-level agreements and memorandums of understanding, including the ambulance service and GP out of hours service, which was the solution for 243 patients in 2018, as was noted earlier.  We have all of those mapped and they are underpinned by the common travel area.  As Mr. Breslin said, it is not anticipated that there would be any break in service on day one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1302" speakername="Louise O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#O00600"><p>Ms Keon mentioned the INTERREG funding for CAWT.  I am very familiar with that organisation and its work.  How long is the current round of funding to last?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.84" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Paula Keon" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#P00100"><p>That funding covers up to 2021.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#P00200"><p>From the publications released by the Commission in December 2018, we know that there is recognition of the importance of those funds in Brussels.  As has just been said, there is a commitment to continue with the current programme but the importance of building upon it is also being looked at.  Even in the context of no deal, I do not believe that Brussels will say that it is over with.  The UK authorities and ourselves are certainly committed to trying to continue with co-operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#P00300"><p>I thank the witnesses.  It is nice to see Mr. Breslin again.  I want to take up a few issues regarding the reality of the situation.  Deputy O'Reilly mentioned the anecdotal evidence.  My understanding is that people on the ground, and older people in particular, are stockpiling drugs, especially drugs with narrow therapeutic indexes and so on.  In the event that a GP has run off a six-month GMS prescription form and it is legally presented to a pharmacy which has stock on the shelf, Mr. Breslin will understand the conundrum of a pharmacist who is faced with a person who is concerned about the future.  Perhaps the person gets his or her news from Sky rather than the BBC or something else might feed his or her fears.  My understanding is that people on the ground are stockpiling and I am concerned about that.  I am sorry for being late, but I have heard various reports that we have approximately ten to 12 weeks of headroom in the supply chain for medication.  If people are getting six months' worth of prescriptions, that headroom will be depleted.</p> <p>  Often when a product is in short supply or is controlled, there is a limit to the number of packs a retail pharmacy can acquire in a month.  I assume somebody puts something into a computer and once a business has its 20 packs, it gets no more.  Has the Department imposed or considered imposing anything like that?  Has it considered limiting the monthly orders of retail pharmacies dealing with one of the big suppliers to 1.2 or 1.1 times what they ordered in the previous month?</p> <p>  There has been talk of a media campaign.  I urge caution in that regard because when one tells people not to stockpile, the first thing they do is get a truck and fill it full of tablets.  That is the nature of people and the survival instinct.  When it comes to supply issues, some of the products we get in through the UK include bespoke feed bags, total parenteral nutrition, TPN, and specials.  In this committee and within my own party I have heard conversations about how the Department has engaged with the manufacturers.  My understanding is that approximately 80% of some types of TPN comes from one place in the UK.  Are we sure that, if there is no deal and the UK crashes out on 29 March, we will be able to feed those people in April?  Do we have the capacity to supply ourselves as a stop-gap?  Does the Department have something in place so that somebody waiting for their nutrition in one of our acute hospitals will not be left hungry?</p> <p>  Regarding the marketing authorisations and dual labelling arrangements we have with the UK - and Dr. Nolan might be the expert on this - my understanding is that we have piggybacked on the UK for a long time in respect of packaging.  Most marketing authorisations are authorised through the UK where the qualified person, QP, is domiciled in the UK.  If there is a hard Brexit and the UK is not in the EU any more, the QPs who are authorising medications and who are responsible for pharmacovigilance will no longer be allowed to sign off because they will not be domiciled within the EU.  This leads to a conundrum where we speak English and nobody else does.  Are there provisions in this regard in the event of a no-deal Brexit?  Have we spoken to the Dutch or other friendly countries which might print the other side of their information leaflets in English?  Is there something in place to deal with the fact that we are piggybacking on the QPs in the UK, which may no longer be possible?</p> <p>  As a UK graduate, I am interested in professional qualifications.  The witnesses have said there will be an additional layer, but that assumes that the standards will stay the same.  With respect, that is only a short-term solution.  With regard to people who have graduated recently, it is unlikely that the UK will have allowed standards to fall too far by summer, but theoretically we can only add in that layer if there is alignment of standards.  Is there any plan for what happens thereafter?  I know we are talking about things that could happen based on whatever happens across the water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#P00400"><p>I will start with the Deputy's final question.  We touched on the recognition of qualifications earlier, but there is a risk of divergence.  We have different scenarios.  We have a regulator-to-regulator arrangement that will be in place in the context of no deal, which is based on the fact that we know the standards are currently equivalent.  The most ideal scenario is an agreement to avoid no deal.  The next most ideal is that, in the future relationship between the UK and EU, something is concluded on recognising qualifications between the EU and UK.  That would be great.  We would then be fairly close to where we started.  In the event that the UK and Ireland have a bilateral arrangement, it will not be a bilateral arrangement so much as the two regulators understanding the qualifications in both jurisdictions and recognising them because they are equivalent.  If UK standards were no longer equivalent, it would be an issue for both regulators.  That will not happen by accident.  The UK would have to decide that it wants its professionals to be different from those of the EU.  That would be a big decision to be made in the UK.  Our regulator would have to make the implications of such a move very clear and plan for it were it to happen.  That is the same for the whole EU rule book.  It is not just about professional qualifications.  If the UK diverges from the EU in any element of standards, it will have implications for trade, movement and so on.  It is a big policy question for people in Westminster who have a lot on their minds at the moment.  If they got that freedom, how would they use it?</p> <p>  Moving on to the other areas, Dr. Nolan will certainly be able to talk on dual-labelling and marketing authorisation holders, MAHs.  She may also be able to talk on the TPN.  On shortages, it would helpful if the HPRA representatives talked about the medicines shortage framework.  From the contact the HPRA and the HSE are having with wholesalers, we know that they are looking at ordering to ensure that there are no artificial reasons for products being taken down.  They will continue to do that up to and beyond Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.88" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#P00500"><p>I will start where Mr. Breslin ended, which was on ordering, and work through questions in that way.  Wholesalers have a process for putting stock in allocation when there is a concern in respect of supply and availability.  As we work through and identify products that could be impacted - and we are not at that stage yet because we have not identified these products - those processes can be activated.  That system of controlling what is supplied to pharmacies exists and can be activated and put in place.</p> <p>  I will start with the TPN and compounded products.  The Deputy is right in that regard.  We have identified these as a category of products in respect of which particular risks will arise from Brexit because many of them have short shelf lives and some have particular storage requirements that it may not be possible to fulfil if there are delays in getting imports in through the ports.  We work with three TPN compounders and suppliers  in the UK.  We have engaged with these and with compounding companies based in Ireland.  In all cases, the companies have told us that their Brexit planning is well developed.  They have increased their stocks of component parts and are looking at the logistics of getting products into Ireland.  Some of this is routed through the UK but the companies are looking at flying it into Ireland directly.  We are engaging with them almost weekly to get updates in real time.  It is an evolving situation.  If we become aware of any concerns, we will take appropriate measures to address them.</p><p>We have not been informed of any concerns relating to those supplies.</p><p> The Deputy mentioned the conduct of regulatory activities, of which there are many because of the United Kingdom's history in pharmaceutical manufacturing, etc.  These include specifically mentioned activities such as QP batch release and pharmacovigilance QP residing in the United Kingdom.  Over the past two years, the regulatory system across the European network has been preparing widely for this and we have also been working with the companies.  It is the case that the vast majority of companies have worked to transfer those activities into the other EU 27 member states.  Some of that work, specifically in the area of quality control testing, for example, has been transferred to Ireland.  Similar transfers have happened with the batch release activities and the QPV.  We do not necessarily have any concerns about that.</p><p> Joint labelling has been an issue that we have been working extensively on, especially as 60% of the medicines supplied in Ireland have joint labels with the UK.  Ms Purcell will speak a little on that.  We have been exploring the possibilities of coming up with joint labelling with other EU member states and we have had quite extensive discussions with Scandinavian countries in that regard.  There are associated challenges because the look and feel of products will change very much for both healthcare professionals and patients but it is something we are developing as a contingency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.90" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Rita Purcell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00200"><p>We recognised very early that for commercial reasons it is very important for companies to treat Ireland and the UK as a common market and joint labels underpinned this for many years.  Having looked at the issue, we have publicly stated since Article 50 was invoked that provided the labels continued to meet the requirements of the EU directive, we will continue to accept UK-Ireland joint labels.  That position was slightly at odds with advice the Commission had given, and we have been lobbying very strongly on that.  I am very pleased that, as of last Wednesday, the Commission has accepted the Irish position.  Provided those labels remain within regulatory convergence, we will be able to accept UK label information on Irish packs.  We will continue to see Irish-UK labels.</p> <p>  Will there be regulatory divergence to address that risk?  The UK has stated strongly that it will continue to apply EU regulations in the foreseeable future.  Given that the UK will become a small market in terms of the EU - with 60 million people as opposed to 600 million - there is a strong incentive, certainly for all the international or global products, to remain largely convergent.  We have also spoken with both the human and veterinary product regulators in the UK and their current position is that they will work with us to ensure we can keep that alignment in place.  We do not know if that will continue five years down the road but in the next number of years there is a good grounding to continue having shared labels and leaflets.  I hope they can continue to make the Irish market more attractive commercially to pharmaceutical companies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00300"><p>It is a bit like the qualifications.  Things will be fine provided things stay the same, but if the UK changes the goalposts, there may be a problem in three years.  If its standards change and they are not compliant with the directives, we would need a new option.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.92" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00400"><p>I will come back to the point on shortages.  Mr. Breslin has just mentioned that we receive approximately 45 shortage notifications per month and it is very important for the committee to understand that less than 50% of those notifications go on to be an issue where medicine supply is short.  In all those cases - we have had 90 of those shortages in the past five months - we have never had a case of a patient being left without a treatment for a particular condition because there have always been alternatives.  It is important to get that point across.  Dr. Fisher can speak about how the shortages framework operates in terms of engagement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00500"><p>There have always been approximately 45 shortage notifications per month.  That has not changed because of Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00600"><p>It is irrespective of Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00700"><p>There has always been such a shortage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.96" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00800"><p>I would not say there has always been a shortage.  The position is well managed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.97" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Breslin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q00900"><p>It is important to say no product on the list is affected by Brexit.  Those 45 notifications would occur regardless of whether Brexit happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.98" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Caitr&iacute;ona Fisher" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q01000"><p>The framework in place for managing shortages was implemented with stakeholders across the range dealing with medicines, including those who market medicines, wholesalers, distributors, manufacturers, healthcare professionals, patient organisations and the HSE.  All these stakeholders came together to develop a framework where we in the HPRA co-ordinate the management of shortages.  It is done with all these stakeholders.</p> <p>  We receive an average of 45 notifications per month.  These come mainly from those who market the products.  Some notifications might go to the HSE and we can share information on potential shortages.  We ask that the company marketing the product would do some impact analysis and make proposals as to how to deal with the shortage.  We then validate it, and as Dr. Nolan states, in some cases it would not be a shortage; there might be a shortage in one part of the country but there is no shortage of the medicine in the system.  Of those notifications that are confirmed, they are designated as potential or actual shortages.  A potential shortage is not happening but it is possible there would be a shortage.  With an actual shortage, we would do a risk assessment on the impact on patients.  We manage all of these shortages and the high-risk examples amount to between 10% and 12% of the total we get.  Most of them are quite readily managed.</p> <p>  We would look at stock in wholesalers and get clinical advice if we need to help prescribers and pharmacists.  We would also consider alternatives and the market share of other companies.  We would see if there could be other strengths, formulations or generic products available.  With the company in question we would communicate to healthcare professionals if required.  If a shortage is confirmed as medium or high risk, a notice is put on our website.  The page on the website describes ongoing shortages at any one time so pharmacists, doctors or patients can see what is short and when the product is likely to come back in.  All the instances to date have been managed with alternative formulations or sources.  In no case to date have we needed clinical guidance to be issued.  There has been no change in the treatment options available to patients.  There is no backlog and we deal with the 45 notifications per month.  We have sufficient resources to deal with those.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q01100"><p>Has the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency - the HPRA equivalent in the UK - commented on allowing EU officials to make inspections?  Are there any preliminary arrangements or is the UK agency staying quiet?  This relates to regulatory alignment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q01200"><p>The UK agency is in quite a different position from us.  It has been very clear about its intention to remain aligned with EU law but there is a caveat.  The Deputy is making the point that we will have to keep a close eye on this with respect to joint labelling and how things move forward.  We may not be able to continue with it so we are looking to future-proof our system and supply channels all the time.  The UK is adopting a position where it will recognise all the EU systems and inspections done by other member states.  I suppose it is in a privileged position where it can be in and out of the system to a certain extent.  We are in a different position because we are one of the EU 27 member states.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#Q01300"><p>On what basis did we choose to pair with the Scandinavians?  Is it just that they were easier to talk to or are we more aligned with them with respect to formulations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.102" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Lorraine Nolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#R00100"><p>To be honest with the Deputy, historically, countries have had alliances.  Not surprisingly, the Benelux countries have arrangements, as do the Scandinavian countries.  We have opened up discussions with other colleagues in the European network on those possibilities but I suppose the Scandinavian discussion is the one that has made advances to date.  That is not to say there are not other possibilities.  Ms Purcell wishes to make a point on the UK situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Rita Purcell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#R00200"><p>In relation to inspection, most big UK pharmaceutical companies are exporting to the European Union and must, therefore, comply with EU law, no matter that they are based in the UK.  They are also subject to EU inspections.  Whether there will be resources is a second issue.  It is not even that there is an incentive to stay aligned, but that these companies must stay aligned if they want to continue to gain access to the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1297" speakername="Kate O'Connell" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#R00300"><p>I thank the witnesses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1275" speakername="Michael Harty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HEJ2019013000002#R00400"><p>That concludes our hearing this morning.  I thank from the HSE, Ms Paula Keon, Mr. John Hennessy and Mr. John Swords, from the Department of Health, Mr. Jim Breslin, Mr. Kieran Smyth and Mr. Fergal Goodman, and from the HPRA, Dr. Lorraine Nolan, Ms Rita Purcell and Dr. Caitr&iacute;ona Fisher.  The meeting stands adjourned until next Wednesday morning when we will engage again with the Department of Health and the HSE on general matters.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.106" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 11.40 a.m. until 9 a.m. on Wednesday, 6 February 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.107" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="">Select Committee on Justice and Equality</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.108" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 09:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Jack Chambers, Deputy Finian McGrath (Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality), Deputy Clare Daly, Deputy Jim O'Callaghan, Deputy Peter Fitzpatrick, Deputy Mick Wallace.</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Donnchadh  Laoghaire.</p><p>DEPUTY CAOIMHGHN  CAOLIN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.109" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#A00100">Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2016: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#A00200"><p>This meeting has been convened for consideration of Committee Stage of the Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2016.  Members are reminded of the longstanding parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against either a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I also remind people, including our friends in the Gallery, to switch off their mobile phones as it interferes with recording equipment in the room.</p> <p>  We are joined by the Minister of State at the Departments of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Justice and Equality, and Health, Deputy Finian McGrath, who has special responsibility for disability issues.  The Minister of State and his officials are all welcome.  Before I invite the Minister of State to make his opening remarks on the Bill and before we begin to address the amendments, the Minister of State and colleagues should note that not for the first time, the Committee on Justice and Equality finds its work being compromised in some way by the fact that questions to the Minister for Justice and Equality are taking place in the D&aacute;il Chamber at the same time.  I do not know how quickly we will get through our work here this morning but members of the committee who are spokespersons on justice are obliged to be on the floor of the D&aacute;il to deal with questions to the Minister.  It is an absolutely unacceptable situation, and it is not the first time it has happened.  This scheduling should not happen.  I appeal to the Minister of State to address this issue after the meeting. </p> <p>  I invite the Minister of State to make any opening remarks on the Bill before we address the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#A00300"><p>I thank the Chairman for the opportunity to address the committee.  I apologise for the delay.  A lot of work has been ongoing in the background in recent months.  I also note the Chairman's point on the schedule and understand the difficulty that it has caused and I will deal with that later.</p> <p>  I am delighted to be here today before the committee, and with its assistance, to complete another stage in the legislative process and move towards enactment of the Bill.  The Bill is being brought forward to give effect to Ireland&rsquo;s ratification of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, which took place in March 2018, and I had the honour of visiting the UN at that time. </p> <p>  It is a small item of legislation but it is a significant part of the overall process of progressive realisation of the convention.  It addresses a number of key strategic issues.  First and foremost, it establishes the independent monitoring framework for the convention, which will be overseen by the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, IHREC, with the support of the National Disability Authority. </p> <p>  This week, the IHREC appointed its monitoring committee for the convention.</p><p>The composition of the committee reflects the importance of involving persons with disabilities in the monitoring process.  This was a very clear statement during the week when we saw the number of people with a disability on that committee.  In addition, the Bill will increase the public sector target for employment of persons with disabilities from 3% to 6% over a number of years.  As Deputies will be aware, the National Disability Authority has the statutory duty to monitor annually the rate of employment of persons with disabilities in the public sector.  In 2017, the employment rate was 3.5% and I am pleased to note the extent to which many public bodies have exceeded the target of 3%, with the overall number of persons with disabilities employed in the public sector increasing.  This Bill will provide a mechanism to ensure a staged increase of this minimum target, reaching 6% by 2024.  This is a welcome development, particularly as leadership within the public sector in this regard is a crucial step in transforming attitudes across the employment market.  I accept that we have a long way to go and we also have to bring the private sector with us.</p><p> The provisions in the Bill regarding jury service are the culmination of a process started by the report of the Commission on the Status of People with Disabilities in 1996.  The Civil Law (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2008 amended and updated the references to persons with disabilities but did not remove them.  The enactment of this Bill will finally clarify the position of deaf jurors.  The public sector duty obligations in the Irish Sign Language Act 2017 will provide the means to make reasonable accommodation for deaf people.</p><p> I am concerned about the funding position of the Irish Deaf Society and this is a matter I am actively pursuing.  I mention it this morning because I am sure many colleagues will raise it.  I hope to have a resolution by the end of the week.</p><p> The Bill will also facilitate the participation of persons with certain disabilities on juries and will remove barriers to their standing for election, improving the standard of reasonable accommodation by certain service providers. </p><p> Many of the issues addressed in the Bill are highly complex and intertwined with other legislation, thus its passage has been slower than I would have liked.  I apologise again for the delays.  For example, a decision was taken last year to remove the deprivation of liberty provisions to feature in a stand-alone Bill to be taken forward by the Minister of Health.  Since then, the Department has organised a consultation process and received more than 50 submissions which are currently being analysed.  In addition, while it was indicated on Second Stage that it was intended to bring forward three heads relating to equality and discrimination matters, I am not proceeding with them at this time because they are not related to disability or the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UNCRPD.  The Department of Justice and Equality is developing an LGBT strategy and it needs to await the outcome of that process before being in a position to determine if legislative change is needed.</p><p> Work is continuing on the reforms needed for an optimum level of compliance with the convention's requirements and the progress of this Bill forms a key part of this work.  In the early implementation phase, it is essential that resources are focused on the improvement and enhancement of services and not diverted into additional areas such as servicing the optional protocol before we are fully ready.</p><p> Five Government amendments are proposed today on Committee Stage.  We will discuss these in due course.  The opportunity is also being taken to make some minor amendments to the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015, which provides a modern statutory framework to support decision-making by adults with capacity difficulties.</p><p> Detailed work is ongoing to finalise amendments on a number of issues for consideration on Report Stage.  These include amendments to address the use of the phrase "unsound mind" in the Statute Book where those references potentially intrude upon the rights of the person deemed to be of "unsound mind".  Deputies will appreciate this is a highly technical, complex and very sensitive area.  The term "unsound mind" appears in many areas of law and the meaning in each case depends on the context so it is not a simple task to replace it with a generic provision.</p><p> The Government also intends to bring forward a Report Stage amendment to align the relevant provisions of the Social Welfare (Consolidation) Act 2005 with the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015 concerning persons appointed to act on behalf of recipients or beneficiaries of social welfare payments where those people have been medically certified as being unable, for the time being, to manage their own financial affairs.  An analogous amendment will be brought forward to amend to the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 to replace the reference to a "person of unsound mind" with language that aligns with the approach taken in the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  Similarly, an amendment to the Criminal Law (Insanity) Act 2006 regarding fitness to plead at trial has been drafted and will be included on Report Stage further to consultation with the advisory counsel and the DPP.</p><p> I will bring forward further amendments to the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  Work is ongoing to establish the decision support service and draft the necessary codes of practice.  In the course of implementation it has been necessary to make amendments to the 2015 Act to correct initial drafting errors and to align the legislation with operational experience.  I look forward to working with the committee to refine the Bill and improve the lives of people with disabilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#B00200"><p>Before proceeding with the amendments, I must advise members that I was given notice by the Bills Office last evening in respect of a number of amendments.  It is the responsibility of the Chair in upholding Standing Orders to sign off on the notification of the disallowance of amendments that are deemed not to be in order.  However, on first perusal, for which I only had an opportunity late last night, I was conflicted about some of the points made in the briefing note directing the Chair to disallow certain amendments.  For example, my experience and knowledge of the provision of polling stations in my constituency is that they are not only schools.  I have some question in my mind in respect of "no rent charged".  Church halls, private halls and so on are all employed as polling stations.  I am not convinced by the argument that some of the amendments presented would subsequently constitute a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p> <p>  As a D&aacute;il Deputy and as Chair of this committee, I am anxious at all times that members, Government and Opposition, have the opportunity to properly play their full part in the construct and passage of all legislation.  I believe I have done so fairly and equitably since I took on the position of Chair of this committee.  However, I believe an inordinate effort is made to find reason to disallow reasonable amendments that could make a critical difference to legislation and, in the case of this Bill, to the daily life of people with disabilities and their reasonable expectations in respect of the affirmation of rights and equality.</p> <p>  Without an opportunity to engage further on the note which I received very late yesterday evening, I am exercising my position as Chairman and ruling that the amendments will be allowed to proceed today on Committee Stage.  The ultimate determiner in all of this is the Ceann Comhairle.  That judgment can be reserved by the Ceann Comhairle on Report Stage.  I have had no facility to engage with the Ceann Comhairle on these matters other than very briefly through the clerk to the committee.  I will not willy-nilly be the puppet for any direction in respect of very important matters concerning a cohort of people, those with disabilities, whom I hold in very high regard.</p><p>Therefore, although one of the amendments before us is quite specific, I am not going to make fish of one and flesh of another.  I propose to proceed and take the amendments as tabled.  I will engage with whoever wishes to engage with me subsequently on the decision I made this morning.  It is up to members to proceed to Report Stage with their amendments, whereupon, when adequate time is given to the Ceann Comhairle and others to peruse and make an assessment - something I did not have - they can make a decision.  It is up to members in the intervening period to make the case as to the veracity and applicability of their respective amendments.  It is the position I am taking and I am putting the Minister of State and members on notice of it.  I would appreciate it if the members could accept the Chair's ruling in this instance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00200"><p>I totally understand the Chairman's position and I know his track record on disability matters.  You mentioned church, community and private halls, and that issue is out there as well.  Ruling on amendments is a matter for the Bills Office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00300"><p>The office can advise but I can quote from the guidelines for Chairs issued in June 2016, as I have taken the time and trouble to read it.  It states clearly, on page three of eight, that the "decision of the Chairman regarding the disallowance of amendments is final".  I have highlighted it and I rest my case on that decision.  I ask members not to elongate or prolong unnecessarily address of the amendments as indicated.  We have much work to do and other members have other responsibilities as the morning will proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00400"><p>I recognise the Chairman has not taken the decision lightly and I recognise it is a serious and probably unprecedented decision.  The Chairman is absolutely right as we have ratified the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UNCRPD, and that comes with a cost.  If we are to ratify it in a meaningful way, we will have to take steps that are meaningful.  What we are seeing is becoming a bit of a trend and we saw it with the recognition of Irish Sign Language, ISL, and now the deaf community is in jeopardy because of finances.  The very mechanism to exercise its access to ISL is being taken away.  I appreciate the Chairman's stance on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00500"><p>This is my final contribution on the matter.  I had no reasonable time to make a judgment on the amendments other than by giving them a cursory reading.  I am in a position to contest the views presented in most of these.  In the absence of the opportunity to engage further, I do not intend, as Chairman of the committee, to thwart an effort to further underscore the rights of people with disabilities in the passage of this legislation.  I intend to proceed on that basis.</p> <p>  Members will note a number of groupings have been advised.  Amendments No. 1 may be discussed with amendment No. 2, amendment No. 6 may be discussed with amendment No. 7, amendment 14 may be discussed with amendment No. 17, and all the others will be taken individually as we proceed.  Without further ado, I propose to commence examination of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.119" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00700"><p>If the question on amendment No. 1 is agreed, amendment No. 2 cannot be moved.  The amendments will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00800"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 3, lines 20 and 21, to delete &quot;have sufficient mental or intellectual capacity to serve as a juror&quot; and substitute &quot;possess the decision-making capacity to exercise the functions of a member of a jury&quot;.</blockquote> <p>The Bill states that a person who does not, in the opinion of the court, have &quot;sufficient mental or intellectual capacity to serve as a juror&quot; would not be eligible for jury service.  However, in the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015, a person's capacity is assessed functionally and on the basis of his or her ability to understand at a time the decision is to be made the nature and consequence of the decision to be made by him or her in the context of the available choices at the time.  It is important that a person would enjoy the presumption of capacity to make decisions.  I know interest groups, such as Inclusion Ireland and others, have said it is important for us to ensure this miscellaneous Bill is consistent with the assisted decision-making legislation.  It is something I recommend and we support.  We need to ensure the legislation fits what will happen in this space.  It is a simple amendment and something we will push.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C00900"><p>This pertains to the Juries Act 1976.  I will refer to section 1(1)(<i>a</i>) of this Bill.  I have not yet tabled an amendment to this part of the Bill but I will do so.  It relates to the provision of Irish Sign Language, ISL, interpreters to allow a deaf person to serve on a jury.  I welcome that greatly.  We should include those who are hard of hearing with those who are deaf.  Additionally, an interpreter is not necessarily the only service that could be provided to a deaf person or a person hard of hearing to perform jury service effectively.  There are people who are hard of hearing or those with cochlear implants who can use technologies like captioning and so on.  The Bill as drafted does not allow for that.  Not all deaf people can read English and not all have ISL, for many reasons.  We must go beyond just ISL and look at the use of technology.  It is the first element of the amendment.</p><p>The second part was explained by Deputy Chambers.  It is critical that language and how we approach these matters is dealt with properly.  The assisted decision-making legislation moves away from a status approach to capacity based on having a disability and moves towards a functional approach in which the presumption of capacity is there until it is clearly not the case.  Capacity is based on ability to understand at the time a decision is made and in context with the available choices at the time.  We are removing the certainty of the statement &quot;does not have mental capacity&quot;.  It is a case of saying it might be the case at a particular time but not necessarily forever that these people might not be in a position to possess the capacity to engage in jury service.  This is key and language is not neutral.  It suggests there is a constant standard for mental capacity before it is needed, which would be the day of jury service.  People may be told they cannot serve because they will not in future have the capacity to do so.  That language is too definite.</p><p>The assisted decision-making legislation is clear about the need to assess capacity and understand what can be done at a particular time.  It is what we are looking at.  There is nuanced difference between our amendment and the amendment proposed by Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire.  I would prefer for ours to be accepted, but if it is not, the alternative should be accepted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C01000"><p>I have no doubt the Minister of State is well disposed to that argument.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C01100"><p>The amendments are similar in their intentions.  The ability to serve on a jury is something most of us would consider an ordinary and democratic right, but we need to improve the presumption in favour of the person being able to participate in a jury.  I will certainly not oppose the first amendment but I have a slight preference for my own because of the specific reference to reasonable accommodation, which is important.  I will listen to the Minister of State's comments and I will not oppose the first amendment.  I will take on board the feedback of other Deputies as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#C01200"><p>My points will be pretty similar to those aired.  The assisted decision-making legislation lists jury duty as one of the exemptions to the provisions of the Act, which is a problem as it contravenes the spirit of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, especially Article 12.2.  It affects the ability of persons with disabilities to participate in all aspects of life.  Section 1 of the Bill before us attempts to address this with respect to jury service but it falls short.  It proposes to amend existing legislation on who is defined as being incapable of serving on a jury and it seeks to ensure compliance with Article 29 of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, which guarantees the right to equal participation in political and public life.</p> <p>  The idea of participation is key and we are supposed to be facilitating participation of people with disabilities.</p><p>People with disabilities should be presumed to have the capacity to serve on a jury, to carry out jury duty.  People with disabilities are rights holders first and foremost and the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, CRPD, is clear that they are entitled to be integrated socially and politically.  While the Bill attempts in section 1 to rectify the problem in the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015 on jury duty, and that is to be welcomed, it is in fact, as I understand it, creating a new problem.  It is undermining some of the very positive aspects of the 2015 Act.  The wording of section 1 on jury duty seems to be contrary to the provisions of the Assisted Decision Making Act (Capacity) 2015 where capacity is defined as &quot;decision-making capacity&quot; and refers to a person's ability to understand at the time that a decision is to be made the nature and consequences of that decision in the context of the available choices at that time.  The Department of Justice and Equality's website describes the Act as follows: </p><blockquote>The Act proposes to change the law from the current all or nothing status approach to a flexible functional definition, whereby capacity is assessed only in relation to the matter in question and only at the time in question.  If a person is found to lack decision-making capacity in one matter, this will not necessarily mean that s/he also lacks capacity in another matter.  The Act recognises that capacity can fluctuate in certain cases.</blockquote><p>As the Department defines it, a person does not lack capacity to make a decision, rather he or she is presumed to have such capacity.  This is the spirit of section 8 of the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  A person may lack capacity to make a particular decision at a particular time or his or her capacity may be in doubt but this capacity may be regained at a different time and for a different decision.  However, the wording we are addressing here, that the person must &quot;have sufficient mental or intellectual capacity to serve as a juror&quot;, brings us back to an outdated understanding of disability rights very much at odds with the positive functional approach of the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  It assesses a person's decision-making capacity simply based on the fact that he or she has a disability which is exactly the kind of all or nothing approach from which we are supposed to have moved on.<br/><br/>The Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015 already provides a statutory framework to support decision-making by adults who have difficulty making decisions without help and to enable them to fully participate in all aspects of public life.  The provision of reasonable accommodation, in Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire's amendment No. 2, is already provided for in the existing Act, from our understanding. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#D00200"><p>This amendment addresses important issues of capacity and participation that go to the heart of the convention, and I thank the Deputies for bringing it forward.  The amendment to the Juries Act 1976 proposed by the Government in section 1 of the Bill as published replaces a provision that prohibits a category of persons from performing jury duty with a functional test of mental or intellectual capacity.  The category of persons currently excluded are those who suffer from, or have suffered from, mental illness or mental disability which either causes them to be resident in a hospital or similar institution or to regularly attend for treatment by a medical practitioner.  This represents a status approach to the determination of capacity, and is precisely what we are aiming to move away from in the implementation of the Convention and the development of the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) 2015 legislation.</p> <p>  In the Bill as drafted there is a Government amendment that changes the exclusion to read as follows: "A person who, does not, in the opinion of the court, have sufficient mental or intellectual capacity to serve as a juror."  The amendments put forward by the Deputies focus on decision-making capacity rather than mental or intellectual capacity in one case.  The other amendment focuses on the provision of reasonable accommodation for jurors.</p> <p>  As regards the reference to decision-making capacity, I welcome this clarification as the term is potentially more relevant in the context of the new approach to capacity and decision-making outlined in the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  However, we are balancing two equally fundamental rights here &ndash; the rights of persons with disabilities to fully participate in all aspects of society, and the right to a fair trial.  For this reason, absolute precision is required.</p> <p>  Furthermore, I am advised by the Office of the Attorney General that a number of legal issues arise from the draft amendment, the most significant of which is that jury duty does not fall within the remit of the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  Section 138(i) of the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015 specifically states that the Act does not purport to change the law in relation to capacity or consent for serving as a member of a jury.  The justice sector working group on jury service is currently examining the issues raised in the report of the Law Reform Commission on jury service published in 2013.</p> <p>  Deputies Wallace, &Oacute; Laoghaire and Chambers have hit the nail on the head about the rights to services, and the debate in the past two weeks about the Irish Deaf Society.  I am aware of the financial difficulties the society is experiencing and the concerns about its future sustainability.  There are several funding options.  I am actively involved in this and I hope to resolve it during the week.  The Deputies' early point is fundamental.  When we talk about people with disabilities and their rights we also have to ensure they have services.  It is also important to note that the largest provider of such services is the National Association for the Deaf which receives significant funding, for example, we gave it &euro;6.7 million in 2018.  There are issues such as that which must be dealt with and I will deal with them.  I take the Deputies' points on the rights of people with disabilities. </p> <p>  I will consider the legal implications of amendment No. 1 for Report Stage because the Assisted Decision Making (Capacity) Act 2015 will require amendments.  I am likely to support it on Report Stage.  </p> <p>  Amendment No. 2 raises a complex legal issue and I would like Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire to let the juries working group consider it because it gives rise to many complicated legal issues.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#D00300"><p>It happens frequently on Committee Stage of various Bills that members are given a commitment about Report Stage.  Would it not be better to insert something now that the Minister of State is potentially willing to accept on Report Stage and for him then to come back with the legal advice on Report Stage and propose an amendment to delete it, if that is his advice?  If he is willing to support a change on Report Stage, he should just accept the amendment now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1259" speakername="Clare Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#D00400"><p>I agree with that.  We should put it in now.  I take issue with the Minister of State's point about a citizen's right to a fair trial as if somehow the measure we are proposing or debating on these issues would undermine a citizen's right to a fair trial by having somebody with disabilities on the jury.  The precise point of the amendment is to remove the wording which states "have sufficient mental or intellectual capacity" as if it were fixed for all time.  We are proposing to insert the words "possess the decision-making capacity to exercise the functions".  With our amendment the person on the jury would have to have the decision-making capacity to participate and therefore ensure a fair trial.  The concern does not arise in this instance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#D00500"><p>I would back up Deputy Chambers' argument.  It is a rational one and I do not see the rationale for not pressing ahead with it today.</p> <p>  Separately, it is good to hear that the Minister of State is hopeful that the Irish Deaf Society funding issue will be sorted this week.  Why are things allowed to get to this point?  The people from the Irish Deaf Society who contacted us were pretty upset about the approach of Government and while I am not saying it is the Minister of State's fault, I wonder if he can explain it.  He tells us now that he will probably sort it this week but I do not understand the rationale of letting it get to this point.</p><p>Can the Minister of State tell me?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00200"><p>On the points made by Deputy Jack Chambers, there are a number of drafting issues that have to be resolved.  I am guided by the legal advice I have been given, and legal advice has to come first for these amendments.</p> <p>  Deputy Clare Daly made a point about fair trials.  It is a very complex situation, and there is a lot of work that has to be done in this area.</p> <p>  On Deputy Wallace's point about the Irish Deaf Society, it is important that people realise that not only were the Deputy and the society upset, but I was upset as well.  There have been a few differences of opinion on this issue in recent weeks.  The Irish Deaf Society had a problem last year and we provided bridging funding of &euro;195,000.  The plan was that that money was to sort it out for 2018 and that a proper plan would be put in place for 2019.  I told people to get on with it, but it did not happen in the way I wanted it to happen, and it then exploded.  The way that happened was unacceptable, and I have made that point twice at two meetings of the Government.  Different sections have to get their act together when it comes to deciding on core funding, which will be decided over the next couple of days.  I am particularly annoyed because the Irish Deaf Society, which the Members here present all supported, was very supportive during the debate on the Irish Sign Language Bill, which was brought through the Houses by Senator Mark Daly, among others.  We worked together for six or seven months, along with Gerry Maguire, my adviser, and the Department of Justice and Equality.  Many compromises were made by all sides.  Part of my agenda was that the Irish Deaf Society be properly supported and funded, but that is another issue.  The matter will be resolved this week, and there will be stable funding in place from now on.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00300"><p>In addition to what the Minister of State has mentioned, the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality held a considerable number of hearings and produced a report.  Indeed, it was the last report presented in advance of the final passage of the Irish Sign Language Bill which recognised Irish Sign Language as an official language of this State.  We are very proud of that work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00400"><p>I recognise the work of the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality on issues relating to disability issues over many years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00500"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00700"><p>Does the Minister of State wish to respond?  Would he like to revisit his earlier indication before we proceed to call-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E00800"><p>I am likely to support it on Report Stage, which is the point Deputy Jack Chambers is making.  It is a matter of head and heart.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.139" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E01000"><p>I have to say no at the moment and seek legal advice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.141" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.142" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 2 not moved</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.143" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 1, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.144" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E01500"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><p>In page 4, between lines 1 and 2, to insert the following:</p><p>&ldquo;(1)The Act of 1992 is amended&mdash;</p><p>(a)in section 28 by the substitution of the following for subsection (1A):</p><blockquote><blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(1A)Each local authority shall, in making a scheme under this section, appoint as polling places only such areas as shall allow the returning officer to provide polling stations which are accessible to wheelchair users.&rdquo;,</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>and</p><p>(b)by the repeal of section 28(5A).</p><p>I appreciate the ruling.  It is wise and sensible.  We have come up against this issue regularly, whether on the basis the the amendments place a charge on the Exchequer, they are not adequate or are irrelevant to the subject of the Bill.  Amendments can be reasonably ruled out of order, but perfectly sensible and relevant amendments are being ruled out of order too often. </p><p>These amendments relate to what I believe to be the most fundamental of democratic rights, which is the right to vote.  It is the case that there are many polling stations that are not accessible to all of the public.  This is not the kind of public service that one can go and get elsewhere.  If one cannot access the polling station to which he or she has been allocated there is no alternative open to him or her.  Unfortunately this is not an uncommon phenomenon.  In the 2016 election there were 15 polling stations in Galway, ten in Kerry, five in Carlow-Kilkenny and four in Dublin which were not wheelchair accessible, and that created considerable difficulty for a number of individuals.  These two amendments seek to put that right and to provide that all polling stations should be wheelchair accessible.  That is reasonable and fair, and very much in keeping with the spirit of the Bill. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E01600"><p>This amendment addresses both articles 8 and 29 of the convention, dealing with accessibility and participation in political and public life.  The Deputy mentioned some examples of polling stations that are not accessible.  That is unacceptable to me as the Minister of State with responsibility in this area.  While I am completely in agreement with the spirit of the amendment proposed I have a number of concerns at the precise manner in which it has been drafted, and I cannot support it as a result.  The proposed amendment cuts across the broader reform of electoral law currently being undertaken by my colleague, the Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Phelan.  As the Deputy may be aware, the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan has recently established a working group on disability voting, the work of which is ongoing.  The group comprises key stakeholders, representing people with disability.  Members of this group include representatives from the National Disabilities Authority, the Disability Federation of Ireland, the National Council for the Blind, the Blind Legal Alliance and the Irish Wheelchair Association.  The working group is dominated by stakeholders.  Its terms of reference provides that its role is to examine and to make recommendations on issues that arise under a number of headings, including improving accessibility to polling stations for voters with physical disabilities, particularly wheelchair users, with the goal for all polling stations to be fully accessible as soon as possible.  The Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, has shown a clear commitment to addressing this issue to ensure that all polling stations will be fully accessible as soon as possible.  Work is already under way to this end.  The expertise available within the group will provide a clear understanding of the actions required to ensure that polling stations are accessible.</p> <p>  I hope the committee will agree that it is preferable not to undertake piecemeal reform in this area but rather to implement a reform process that is solidly rooted in the perspective of people with disabilities who are directly affected.  Reform of electoral law is already under way, and we should let it move along strongly.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E01700"><p>I suggest that we should not press the amendments which were indicated as potentially being out of order.  I use the word "potentially" deliberately.  We have had an opportunity to engage with it today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E01800"><p>May I make a point?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#E01900"><p>I will finish my point.  I am not sure that members are prepared to participate because they were notified that the amendments were not in order.  I am trying to be as accommodating as possible.  I appreciate that the Minister had his speaking notes, in any event.</p><p>I will leave it to members to make that determination.  Critically, they will have the opportunity to retable their amendments on Report Stage when the Ceann Comhairle, who is the final arbiter in these matters, can make his judgment and decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00200"><p>I will support the amendment if it is pressed.  The Government is overburdened with working groups, which delay reform across many areas of disability.  In many cases, it is bureaucracy talking to bureaucracy.  This is a simple amendment to direct local authorities to do what they should do anyway.  It would have positive effects for those who need access.  I do not know why a working group is needed to do something relatively simple.  If local authorities are directed by law to do it, they have enough staff to change their polling schemes quickly and appropriately.  A complex working group is not needed to address the area.  I support the amendment and consider that it should be pressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00300"><p>Does Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire wish to come back on the Minister of State's remarks?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00400"><p>I am inclined to press the amendment.  It is something that comes up every so often but we are always told there is a review under way and that nothing can be done in the meantime.  That excuse can be used to cover a multitude.  We saw it in the context of civil law reform recently where we were told something could not be contemplated as a review was ongoing which might recommend something.  As the Minister of State said and as Deputy Jack Chambers reflected, this should be the position as it stands.  People should not be in a position where they may be denied the right to vote or where voting may be made difficult for them because polling stations are practically or completely inaccessible.  I am minded to press the amendment unless the Chairman is certain it will create a difficulty for the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00500"><p>No.  It is new ground but the Chair is committed.  Either way, I have no issue with that whatsoever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00600"><p>It is an important matter.  In any event, I would be surprised if the review group came back and said it would be fine if some polling stations were inaccessible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00700"><p>Does the Minister of State have anything further to say?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F00800"><p>I do not disagree with the Deputies on the points they raised.  While I understand the frustration with the working group, the problem is also one we had in respect of the capacity issue.  We placed advertisements in newspapers and received 50 submissions.  The more that came in, the more people became involved and the more complex everything became.  At the same time, if we did not consult the Irish Wheelchair Association, the Disability Federation of Ireland and other groups, I would be in the firing line.  On the amendments, I note that local authorities have flexibility to improve accessibility, which some have done while others remain weak, as Deputies pointed out.  My concern is that there are significant legal issues with the way in which the amendment is drafted, which means I cannot support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.158" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F01000"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 4, between lines 2 and 3, to insert the following:&quot;(3) Section 94 of the Act of 1992 is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(a) by the substitution of the following for subsection (1A):<blockquote>&quot;(1A) Polling stations provided by the returning officer shall be accessible to wheelchair users.&quot;,</blockquote>and<br /><br />(b) by the repeal of subsection (3A).&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.160" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.161" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.162" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F01400"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p><blockquote>In page 4, between lines 2 and 3, to insert the following:<b>&quot;Amendment of section 3 of Referendum Act 1998</b><br /><br /><b>3. </b>Section 3 of the Referendum Act 1998 is amended by the substitution of the following for subsection (1):<blockquote>&quot;(1) The Commission shall have, in addition to any functions conferred on it by any other provision of this Act, the following principal functions in relation to the referendum in respect of which it is established:<blockquote>(a) to prepare statements containing a general explanation of the subject matter of the proposal and of the text thereof in the relevant Act and any other information relating to those matters that the Commission considers appropriate;<br /><br />(b) to prepare statements that are as far as practicable accessible to persons with a disability;<br /><br />(c) to publish and distribute those statements in such manner and by such means including the use of television, radio and other electronic media as the Commission considers most likely to bring them to the attention of the electorate and to ensure as far as practicable that the means employed enable those with a sight or hearing disability to read or hear the statements concerned;<br /><br />(d) to promote public awareness of the referendum and encourage the electorate to vote at the poll.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>The aim of the amendment is to insert a new subsection into section 3 of the Referendum Act 1998.  We have discussed the need to make information on referenda properly accessible to people with disabilities.  As such, it is important to integrate provisions in this regard in the Act to give the Referendum Commission a mandate to ensure that occurs.  The amendment proposes to include in section 3 a requirement to publish statements that are as far as practicable accessible to persons with a disability, to publish and distribute those statements to various media and to promote public awareness of a referendum and encourage the electorate to vote at the poll.  It adds to what is there.  In the spirit of disability reform, it is important to ensure information is put out there in an accessible way and to provide the commission with a positive mandate to ensure it reaches everyone.  The commission should be required to go that extra yard to communicate that information to those who may not currently receive it.  It is a simple amendment and one which is in keeping with the spirit of the Bill.  I hope the Minister of State will support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F01500"><p>Section 3 removes the reference to section 41 of the Electoral Acts to "unsound mind" in respect of a person standing for election to the D&aacute;il or Seanad.  This is obviously welcome.  The UN committee on the rights of persons with disabilities has urged that all stages of an election should be made fully accessible, including the political campaigns around them.  Our amendment, as proposed by Inclusion Ireland, will guarantee an equal right for people with disabilities to participate in political and public life.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#F01600"><p>I share the concern of the Deputies who have tabled the amendment that information provided to voters in a referendum should be accessible and easy to understand.  However, this concern is addressed through current practices.  In line with its existing duties under the Referendum Act 1998, the Referendum Commission prepares and provides information on referenda for persons with disabilities, including in easy-to-read format for people with intellectual disabilities.  It is important to note that.  Given that the commission is doing this work, which has become standard practice, I do not consider it necessary to amend the Act.</p><p>There are further technical issues with the proposed amendment.  The amendment proposes the deletion from section 3(1)(<i>a</i>) of the Act of the words &quot;one or more&quot; after &quot;prepare&quot; so that the section provides that the commission shall prepare statements.  This means the commission would be forced to prepare multiple statements when it might not be appropriate or necessary to do so.</p><p>The important issue is that the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government commenced a public consultation process recently on the regulatory impact assessment relating to the establishment of an electoral commission.  The assessment sets out a number of options for establishing a commission, including the functions that might be assigned to it.  Following any Government decision on a preferred option for the establishment of an electoral commission, work will commence on the drafting of an electoral commission Bill.  That Bill would be the appropriate mechanism through which to provide for people with disabilities in respect of electoral matters.  I understand the aim of Deputies in proposing the amendment and support the principles raised by them.  We need to get more people with disabilities in politics, whether in local or national government or in the Seanad, to advocate directly on their particular issues.  However, the Deputies will understand the reasons I cannot support the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G00100"><p>I do not accept that the amendment would complicate the work of the Referendum Commission.  It seeks to go further than what is there at the moment.  If we are trying to keep within the spirit of the Bill, the commission should be mandated to go the extra yard.  None of its work up to now has sought to properly communicate the message to people with disabilities and ensure that voting is promoted properly and the amendment mandates the commission to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G00300"><p>I see what the Deputy is up to.  We must push forward to ensure that more people with disabilities can go forward and get involved in politics and lobbying but the Referendum Act 1998 provides for the preparation of this information on referendums for people with disabilities, including an easy-to-read format for people with intellectual disabilities.  That is something I have seen used regularly in the disability sector, particularly the easy-to-read format for people with intellectual disabilities.  They have found it helpful and that has increased the participation of people with disabilities in elections.  We have a long way to go and I accept the points made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G00400"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.170" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.171" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G00800"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G00900"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p><blockquote>In page 4, line 25, to delete &quot;Every person&quot; and substitute &quot;A person&quot;.</blockquote> <p>I hope I win this one.  The section makes two amendments to the National Disability Authority, NDA.  It makes provision for the NDA to play a role in a monitoring mechanism for the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  It also provides for staff of the NDA to become civil servants of the State.  This is a technical drafting amendment, which seeks to align the current provision better with the section as a whole.  The term &quot;Every person&quot; is replaced by &quot;A person&quot;.  It is a minor amendment that I am making on the advice of the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel to ensure a consistent approach throughout the section.  I stress that the change in the status of the staff of the NDA will not in any way compromise the authority's independence.  As the committee will be aware, the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, IHREC, enjoys full independence in its role notwithstanding the fact that its staff are civil servants of the State.  I intend to bring forward a further amendment to this section on Report Stage, which will deal with the transfer of pension liabilities for the staff of the NDA.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.174" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G01100"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p><blockquote>In page 5, line 38, to delete &quot;applies&quot; and substitute the following:&quot;applies, and in such case, a reference in this section to &quot;appointed day&quot; in relation to a person means the day appointed under this paragraph in respect of the category or grade of staff to which the person belongs&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.176" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.177" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.178" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G01500"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><blockquote>In page 6, lines 38 to 40, to delete all words from and including &quot;unless&quot; in line 38 down to and including &quot;question&quot; in line 40.</blockquote> <p>I shall not press my amendment but I am interested in the Minister of State's view on it.  It seems that in respect of the amendment to section 4 of the Equal Status Act 2000, the final paragraph seems to be excessively qualified.  I am not sure what the Minister of State thinks about that.  Perhaps it allows a bit too much wriggle room.  As I said, I will not press the amendment.  I simply wish to make that point and give the Minister of State the opportunity to respond.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G01600"><p>Section 4, as drafted, deals with reasonable accommodation for persons with disabilities.  Reasonable accommodation are practical changes that service providers have to make so that people with disabilities can obtain and use all kinds of services on an equal basis with others.  The convention provides that reasonable accommodation be provided for people with disabilities in the areas of employment and provision of services provided the cost does not exceed a disproportionate cost.  The amendment proposed by the Deputy seeks to eliminate the standard of disproportionate cost altogether.  This is problematic for a number of reasons, the most fundamental of which is that it is liable to incur constitutional challenge.  The Supreme Court decided in an Article 26 referral of the Employment Equality Bill 1996 that it would be unconstitutional to impose such a requirement where the cost exceeds a nominal cost.  The Supreme Court decision hinges on the private property protection provisions of the Constitution.  The Attorney General has advised that it would not be appropriate to apply the disproportionate burden obligation in the case of commercial bodies whose activities are regulated for quality of service, <i>viz</i>. banks, insurance companies, telecommunications and transport providers and credit unions.  To eliminate the maximum standard altogether would create a substantial risk of challenge and for this reason, I propose that the amendment be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G01700"><p>I am glad the Deputy  is not pressing this amendment because I agree with the Minister of State.  The amendment would make section 4 excessively restrictive.  I acknowledge the Deputy is concerned that it may be too qualified but if the provision at the end of section 2A is deleted, it would be unconstitutional.  It is just stating that it shall not be deemed reasonable if special treatment or facilities are not provided.  There must be some wriggle room for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G01800"><p>I will not press the amendment.  As much as anything else, it is an opportunity to debate this and tease it out.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State would consider it again and see if there is any possibility that it might be made a bit more difficult for people to squeeze out of their obligations - not to the point of being unconstitutional.  If he will examine that, I am happy to withdraw the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G01900"><p>Disproportionate burden is the standard provided in the convention so from my point of view, it would be very risky to remove the standard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.184" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.185" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.186" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G02300"><p>I wish to advise that acceptance of amendment No. 9 involves the deletion of section 5.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#G02400"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p><blockquote>In page 7, between lines 7 and 8, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&quot;Amendment of Disability Act 2005</b><br /><br /><b>5.</b>The Disability Act 2005 is amended&mdash;(a) in section 46(3), by the substitution of &quot;members, within the meaning of section 3(1) of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005, of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na&quot; for &quot;the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na&quot;, and <br /><br />(b) by the substitution of the following for section 47(4):<blockquote>&quot;(4) If no compliance targets stand prescribed under subsection (3) in relation to a public body, the body shall ensure, unless there is good reason to the contrary, that&mdash;<blockquote>(a) for the period from the date of commencement of <i>section 5(b)</i>of the <i>Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2019</i>up to and including 31 December 2019, not less than 3 per cent of the persons employed by it are persons with disabilities,<br /><br />(b) for the period from 1 January 2020 up to and including 31 December 2021, not less than 4 per cent of the persons employed by it are persons with disabilities,<br /><br />(c) for the period from 1 January 2022 up to and including 31 December 2023, not less than 5 per cent of the persons employed by it are persons with disabilities, and<br /><br />(d) on and from 1 January 2024, not less than 6 per cent of the persons employed by it are persons with disabilities.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>This amendment would insert a new section that, if agreed, would replace section 5, as initiated.  The proposed amendment would make two changes to the Disability Act 2005.  One relates to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the other to the public service employment quota for persons with disabilities.  The first change, which was confirmed on Second Stage, brings civilian staff of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na back within the terms of Part 5 of the Disability Act, providing for a public sector employment quota for people with disabilities.  This group of Civil Service staff was inadvertently removed from the scope of Part 5 by the enactment of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005.  In accordance with this amendment, the Disability Act would also be amended to increase the employment target of persons with disabilities in the public sector from 3% to 6% on a phased basis by 2024.</p><p>A staggered approach is now proposed as follows.  From 1 January 2020 to 31 December 2021, the target will be 4%.  From 1 January 2022 to 31 December 2023, the target will be 5%.  From 1 January 2024, the target will be 6%.  The basis for these provisions is a Government decision of 2015 on foot of a recommendation in the comprehensive employment strategy to increase public service employment from 3% to 6%.  The figure of 6% and the staggered approach were recommended by the NDA, which is the key adviser to the Government on disability policy and practice.  The staged approach facilitates capacity building in respect of continued improvements in employment levels.</p><p> The NDA monitors the progress of public bodies in achieving the targets and works with Departments and agencies to advise on ways to improve policies and practices in order to meet them.  It will continue to have this role following the introduction of the new targets.  If the revised targets are agreed by the Oireachtas and enshrined in legislation, they will represent a significant advance for people with disabilities and provide them with significantly more employment opportunities in the public service.  As such, they have the potential to transform the lives of many people with disabilities who can obtain good quality and secure employment.  Like my colleagues on this committee, I feel strongly that while we have made a major dent in general employment, we must also make a major dent on unemployment among people with disabilities.  We have a lot of quality people in the disabilities sector who want jobs.  While we have taken steps to assist them in respect of welfare payments and hours of work, we must also consider the potential within the public and private sectors to provide more employment for them</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H00200"><p>I support the amendment.  What is the remedy if these targets are missed?  There is obviously a macro incentive for the public service to increase the percentage in employment but what is the remedy for a person with a disability on a micro level?  At the organisational level of Department or State agency, they will displace the macro incentive to someone else, as it is a general percentage.  Has the Minister of State considered specifying additional organisational targets so that the macro target can be reached?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H00300"><p>The NDA will monitor and report on progress in respect of employment.  I have also set up a team under the national disability inclusion strategy, which meets every couple of months.  I bring in officials from every Department and we sit around the table and ask what they have done on disabilities over the previous three or four months.  There is accountability to me as Minister of State and it is up to me to drive the process forward.  Some Departments have a good record and are above the 3.5% rate.  Some are in that zone but I want to get them up to 4% and 5%.  The accountability is directly to me and to the Secretaries General of the Departments.  There is also accountability at Cabinet level.  A point I make at Cabinet meetings is that it is not just the Minister of State with responsibility for disabilities who has to be involved in supporting people with disabilities.  Every Department represented at the Cabinet table must bring something to it to develop and support people with disabilities.  We have a couple of thousand people with disabilities working in different Departments, including the Departments of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Education and Skills, and Health.  I want that number increased on a phased basis.  That is the way I do it.  The accountability is to me, Secretaries General and, ultimately, to Cabinet in a broader sense.  It is up to us to drive this forward while the NDA monitors and reports on progress.  It clips our wings every now and again, let us be honest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.192" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.193" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 5 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.194" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H00700"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p><blockquote>In page 7, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:<b>&quot;5. </b>(1) The Disability Act 2005 is amended by the insertion of the following after section 6:<blockquote><b>&quot;Transposition of Article 14(2) of the UNCRPD</b><br /><br /><b>6A. </b>The State shall ensure that if persons with disabilities are deprived of their liberty through any process, they are, on an equal basis with others, entitled to guarantees in accordance with international human rights law and shall be treated in compliance with the objectives and principles of the present Convention, including by provision of reasonable accommodation.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>The amendment seeks simply to transpose Article 14.2 of the UNCRPD into the Disability Act 2005.  It is an important statement.  It is important to ensure there is consistency between the legislation and our international obligations and the provision should be included in primary legislation.  The principles should be consistent with our domestic law and what we are trying to achieve through this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H00800"><p>It is of the utmost importance that the essence of Article 14.2 is adequately provided for in primary legislation.  In this regard, the Department feels strongly about, and continues to prioritise, the development of legislation on the deprivation of liberty safeguards.  While it was initially intended to include a deprivation of liberty safeguard on Committee Stage, the importance of provisions in this regard led the Government to agree early last year to bring them forward in a stand-alone Bill sponsored by the Minister for Health.  This was a response to concerns raised about the opportunity for an in-depth and meaningful consultation on this important topic.  As the Deputy will be aware, a public consultation on the draft deprivation of liberty safeguard legislative proposals concluded in May 2018.  The Department of Health is engaged in revising the draft proposals and working hard to resolve the complicated policy issues that have arisen.  Deprivation of liberty is a complex matter and a great deal of information has been provided in the submissions made.  The Department and I feel strongly that it is necessary to deal with such complexity in a stand-alone Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H00900"><p>As I indicated in respect of amendment No. 9, its acceptance entailed the deletion of section 5.  I am teasing out in my own mind, therefore, the impact of amendment No. 10.  It might be appropriate to resubmit on Report Stage to allow for an examination of that situation.  The decision we have just taken, unanimously, on amendment No. 9 and section 5 could be <i>ultra vires</i>.  I am open to any other opinion and guidance from colleagues on the committee or the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H01000"><p>I would be interested to hear any views.  I take the Chairman's point on board and am open minded about how to proceed.  I am curious to hear if any other member has a view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H01100"><p>Does any other member have a view?  I am not suggesting my reading is definitive, but there is a concern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1296" speakername="Jim O'Callaghan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H01200"><p>The Chairman is correct to be concerned and it may be better to leave the amendment until Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H01300"><p>Just in case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#H01400"><p>I am happy enough with that but emphasise that the issue is important.  I take on board the Minister of State's point about an additional Bill but I do not know what the timescale for it is or whether heads exist.  I ask that in advance of Report Stage any issue is raised as to whether there is anything in the current wording that should not be included or which is not consistent with how people with disabilities are treated in the context where they are deprived of liberty.  It appears that it is a minimal standard.  Perhaps we are not meeting it, but it is the least we should expect.  In that context, I am happy to withdraw the amendment now with a view to tabling it again on Report Stage.</p><p>In that context, I am happy enough to withdraw for the moment, with a view to resubmitting it or a variation of it on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J00200"><p>I will take Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire's views on board and I assure him that the heads of the Bill are ready.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J00300"><p>I appreciate that and the views of other colleagues, which were very helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.206" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.207" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J00600"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p><blockquote>In page 7, lines 19 to 21, to delete all words from and including &ldquo;to keep&rdquo; in line 19 down to and including &ldquo;disabilities;&quot;,&rdquo; in line 21 and substitute the following:&ldquo;to promote, protect, and monitor the implementation of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, and to keep under review the adequacy and effectiveness of law and practice in the State relating to the protection of persons with disabilities.  Adequate funding and resources will be provided to carry out these functions;&rdquo;,&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>This amendment was proposed by the Disability Federation of Ireland.  The federation is of the view that the Bill does not provide a broad enough mandate to comply fully with the UN Convention.  This amendment uses language taken directly from the convention and it tasks the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, IHREC, not only with reviewing the law but also with promoting awareness of the convention and ensuring its continued implementation.  The amendment removes the paternalistic language of this section of the Bill and focuses on empowering people with disabilities rather than on protection.  It goes without saying that IHREC must be adequately funded and resourced if it is to be given new duties.  We often give extra powers to bodies, as with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, GSOC, for example, but if we do not resource them adequately, those powers cannot be used.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J00700"><p>Would Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire, who also tabled the amendment, like to comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J00800"><p>I do not have a great deal more to add.  It is important that this is properly implemented.  Adequate funding and resources are needed.  Good legislation and words as well as high ideals and principles are all very well but they must be properly backed by resources and funding.  I appreciate what the Minister of State said about the Irish Deaf Society and look forward to seeing more detail on that later in the week, but what has transpired there is an example of us signing up to high ideals but not providing adequate resources, which means that we do not meet the standards that the people who are relying on these protections are expecting.  This is a worthy amendment that is deserving of support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J00900"><p>I take the points on board that were made by Deputies Wallace and &Oacute; Laoghaire.  I have consulted IHREC and understand that it has made provisions for its role as an independent monitor in its work plan and budget for this year.  On the question of resources, IHREC receives substantial Exchequer funding each year to support its core activities.  The 2019 Estimates provide an allocation of &euro;6.651 million.  It is possible that matters which may arise over the forthcoming UNCRPD reporting cycle could require extra resources and IHREC is free at any time to present a case to Government for additional resources, as necessary, to carry out its core functions or other functions arising from its statutory role.  As the Deputies are aware, it is the role of Government to determine how resources are allocated and it would not be appropriate for legislation to interfere with that role.  That is the key issue here.  Equally, enshrining the provision in legislation could cut across the role of the Oireachtas in overseeing IHREC's Vote.  Accordingly, I cannot accept the amendment and propose that it be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01000"><p>Deputy Wallace, in my opening remarks, I indicated that my assessment of the wording, in the limited time available to me, led me to determine that some elements or aspects of the amendment might not be in order.  I will leave it to Deputy Wallace's good judgment and that of his colleagues as to whether it is pressed at this point or withdrawn and returned to on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01100"><p>I will consider the amendment further.  I reserve the right to reintroduce it on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01200"><p>If the amendment were pressed and accepted, it would probably overly complicate and potentially delay the Bill.  I have not seen any amendment passed with an open-ended insertion of "adequate funding and resources", which would be impossible to interpret.  While the Deputy's aim in introducing the amendment is correct, I do not think the Bill would pass with this amendment in it.  It would undermine the accountability role that the structures have to the Departments and the Oireachtas.  I agree with the Minister of State on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01300"><p>The essence of the Chairman's remarks are obviously also being taken on board.  I thank Deputy Chambers for his contribution.  Does Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire have anything to add?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01400"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01500"><p>In this instance, Deputy Wallace, can we take it that the amendment-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01600"><p>I realise that we tend to legislate in terms of "may" rather than "shall" and this amendment probably fits into the same category.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01700"><p>Members can resubmit their amendments on Report Stage if they wish.  In this instance, can I take it that amendment No. 11 is being withdrawn?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1355" speakername="Mick Wallace" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J01900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02000"><p>I thank all concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.223" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02200"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p><blockquote>In page 7, between lines 21 and 22, to insert the following:&ldquo;(iii) by the insertion of the following paragraph after paragraph (o):<blockquote>&ldquo;(p) to act as the independent mechanism to promote, protect and monitor implementation of the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities done at New York on 13 December 2006.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>This very simple amendment seeks to insert a paragraph into the section based on the intention in the general scheme of the Bill, which was to provide that the commission would act as an independent mechanism to promote, protect and monitor implementation of the convention.  The additional commission function proposed in the Bill makes no reference to the independent mechanism or to the UNCRPD more broadly.  The function proposed under the Bill should be clearly linked to the commission's designation as the independent mechanism under Article 33 of the UNCRPD.  The amendment would better align the view of the UN Committee on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities that the State must adopt the necessary legal measures to establish the independent mechanism clearly.  That is what we are seeking to do with this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02300"><p>I agree with Deputy Chambers.  This section of Bill creates a statutory basis for IHREC's role in the monitoring framework with regard to the UNCRPD.  IHREC, as Ireland's national human rights and equality body has a function to keep under review the adequacy and effectiveness of law and practice in the State relating to the protection of human rights and equality and so is well placed to undertake the monitoring role with the technical support of the National Disability Authority, NDA.  Having consulted IHREC, I understand that it welcomes the proposed amendment, which links its role explicitly to the UNCRPD.  It is important that Ireland's progress in implementing the convention should be underpinned by robust monitoring.  I am open to accepting this amendment on Report Stage, subject to further legal analysis or tidying up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02400"><p>The amendment will be accepted on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02500"><p>I am not accepting that.  This is a case of <i>d&eacute;j&agrave; vu</i>.  I am going to press the amendment now.  If the Minister of State needs to get legal advice on it, he can provide it to us on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02600"><p>I said that I am open to supporting the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02700"><p>I think it is important that we amend the Bill now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02800"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J02900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.232" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J03100"><p>I may have to come back on Report Stage with some changes to the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission Act of 2014 to make provisions consistent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#J03200"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00200"><p>I move amendment No. 13:</p><blockquote>In page 7, to delete lines 33 to 35 and substitute the following:&ldquo;the committee shall comprise at least 20 members and all members shall have, or have had, a disability within the meaning of section 2(1) of the Disability Act 2005.  Cognisance will be given to the nature of disability to ensure broad representation.  This committee shall receive the funds, resources and facilitation required to effectively execute its duties, with particular reference to the needs of members for reasonable accommodation.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Unfortunately, scheduling means that I have a question in the D&aacute;il in three or four minutes and must leave.  The principle of the amendment is very simple.  There is no reason all the members of the advisory committee should not be people who have or had a disability.  I will press the amendment, but if the Minister of State wishes to comment, I ask that he be as concise as possible.  Unfortunately, I will probably be absent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00300"><p>No, with the indulgence of the committee members and the Minister of State, I will allow Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire to speak to amendments Nos. 15 and 16 in his name now and we will proceed to address them in his absence.  The situation in which we find ourselves is not of our construct.  I want to accommodate members as best I can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00400"><p>Amendment No. 16 is the simplest amendment.  It returns the Bill to its original Title that it be cited as the Equality/Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2016.  Amendment No. 15 calls for a focal point for implementation and that the Department of an Taoiseach will be the focal point for the monitoring framework as set out in Article 33 of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00500"><p>I am in a similar position.  I have a group of disabled people in the audiovisual room waiting for me at 11 a.m. and we have about three other events on today.  It is difficult.  I am prepared to facilitate if the committee wishes to choose a quieter time when we are not rushed to complete this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00600"><p>No, with respect, we will complete our business here now.  The further opportunity will be Report Stage, but we should not defer Committee Stage.  There has been a significant deferral from prior to Christmas to 30 January and, in deference to members and the broader disability community, we should complete our business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00700"><p>That is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00800"><p>Does the Minister of State wish to respond to amendment No. 13?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K00900"><p>The Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, IHREC, has appointed a disability advisory committee under section 9 of the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission Act 2014.  When it was established, it had regard to the Disability Bill 2016 of its own volition.  The disability advisory committee is made up of 14 members, three of whom are commissioners, being the chair, the vice chair and the chief commissioner, as per the requirements of the commission's founding legislation.  Of the other 11 members, nine are persons with a disability and have been appointed following an open recruitment process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1255" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01000"><p>As with an earlier point, amendment No. 13 making it open-ended would complicate and delay the legislation.  There is a proposal to mandate a committee to receive necessary funds but I have never seen an amendment with that type of working language successfully pass through the Oireachtas.  Perhaps Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire might reword the amendment on Report Stage.  I do not disagree with other parts of the amendment but I do not think it will pass.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01100"><p>My question is about to come up in the House but I will press amendment No. 13.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01200"><p>IHREC is an independent body which is directly accountable to the Oireachtas.  Accordingly, it would not be appropriate for me as Minister of State to contradict any determination it makes to the composition of its advisory committee.  Therefore, I propose that the amendment be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01300"><p>Being mindful of how this might go, and weighing up the options before us and the time available, as Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire will not be present, might he withdraw amendments Nos. 15 and 16 and resubmit them on Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1287" speakername="Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.248" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.249" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 6, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.250" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01800"><p>Amendments Nos. 14 and 17 may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K01900"><p>I move amendment No. 14:</p><blockquote>In page 7, after line 35, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Amendment of Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015 </b><br /><br /><b>7. </b>The Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015 is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in section 15(1)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) by the substitution of &ldquo;one or more of&rdquo; for &ldquo;one or both of&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(ii) in paragraph (c), by the substitution of &ldquo;decision-making assistance agreement&rdquo; for &ldquo;co-decision-making agreement&rdquo;,</blockquote>(b) in section 46(6)(b), by the substitution of &ldquo;general visitor&rdquo; for &ldquo;special visitor&rdquo;,<br /><br />(c) in section 75, by the substitution&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in subsection (2)(b), of &ldquo;general visitor&rdquo; for &ldquo;special visitor&rdquo;,<br /><br />(ii) in subsection (7)(b), of &ldquo;attorney&rdquo; for &ldquo;co-decision-maker&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(iii) in subsection (8), of &ldquo;subsection (7)(b)&rdquo; for &ldquo;subsection (7)(a)&rdquo;, </blockquote>and<br /><br />(d) in section 143, by the deletion of paragraphs (b) and (d).&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>The purpose of the amendment is to insert a new section into the Bill to provide for a number of minor technical amendments and corrections to the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015.  Paragraph (a) of the new section relates to section 15 of the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act, which provides for complaints against decision-making assistants appointed under the Act.  The first proposed amendment to section 15 is a technical drafting amendment.  As there are three paragraphs in section 15(1), the reference to &ldquo;one or both of the following matters&rdquo; is incorrect.  The second proposed amendment is a technical drafting amendment to replace an erroneous reference to co-decision-making agreements with a reference to decision-making assistance agreements.</p><p>The director was appointed in late 2017.  The preparations for the commencement of the Act are ongoing.  We are working towards 2020 for its commencement.  The staff are being recruited, codes of practice are being drafted, and procurement is under way.  The Department is working on amendments to the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015 to address the issues that have arisen since the Act was passed.  They are also to remove inconsistencies and clarify provisions.  Much work is ongoing on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K02000"><p>Do any members wish to speak on these amendments?  No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K02100"><p>I will bring forward amendments on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.255" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.256" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 15 and 16 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.257" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 7 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.258" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>TITLE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#K02500"><p>I move amendment No. 17:</p><blockquote>In page 3, line 9, to delete &ldquo;2014&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;2014, the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.260" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.261" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Title, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.262" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.263" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00250">Message to Dil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00275"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 90, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Committee on Justice and Equality has completed its consideration of the Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2016 and has made amendments thereto.</blockquote> <p>I thank the Minister of State and his officials for attending.  The committee is very pleased that it has had a number of representatives of disability organisations in the Visitors Gallery throughout Committee Stage of the Bill.  They are all welcome and I hope they found the proceedings interesting.  We hope that, in joining with them, we can wish the Bill a fair wind in the taking of Report and Final Stages at the earliest possible date.  I hope the Minister of State can take that request on board.  As a committee, we certainly do not wish to see any delay in the Bill's progress.</p><p>In the Minister of State's delivery of his speaking note, as circulated, he jumped a page.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00400"><p>I did, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00500"><p>Did the Minister of State intend to do so?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00600"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00700"><p>In his closing remarks the Minister of State might make some reference to the optional protocol and its ratification which is eagerly awaited.  It is referred to in his script.  I am anxious to hear his additional assurances in that regard.</p> <p>  I appeal to the Minister of State to consider the amendment tabled by Deputy &Oacute; Laoghaire that was not proceeded with.  The Deputy has reserved the right to resubmit it on Report Stage.  It proposes that the Title to the Bill be changed to "Equality/Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2016".  There is a very strong opinion across the committee on the dropping of the word "Equality".  The matter has been referred to and reflected on on a number of occasions.  I urge the Minister of State to consider it before Report Stage.</p> <p>  On the amendments that were indicated as being out of order and on which I ruled accordingly, I was left in what I believed was an invidious position.  Considering that the Minister of State indicated correctly during the deliberations his comfort, understanding and support, in some instances, and that Opposition Members are sometimes precluded from moving amendments that "may" entail an increase in the charge on the Exchequer, he might consider taking on board some of the amendments proposed on Report Stage.  This merits consideration in a number of cases.  The greatest number of the amendments were authored initially by the various umbrella representative groups in the disability community.</p> <p>  Does the Minister of State have closing words he would like to offer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00800"><p>There are further amendments to the Bill that I intend to introduce on Report Stage.  They are being drafted by the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel.  I intend to introduce an amendment to address the issue that arose regarding a person whose fitness to be tried was to be determined in the course of criminal proceedings.</p> <p>  I thank colleagues for their contributions.  I welcome the visitors in the Visitors Gallery and thank them for their submissions on the Bill.  They will have seen the interaction in the debate.  They can see that we have a Chairman and members who are dedicated to the principles behind legislating for disability issues.  We now have a different vision in the country than in the past.  We want people to be treated with respect, which is why all of the Deputies supported me when I went to New York to ratify the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  As colleagues said, it is all very well to talk about having a vision and a plan, but we need to ensure we have the resources.  That is also important and part of the debate.  In budget 2019 I managed to deliver &euro;1.9 billion for social care services for people with disabilities.  What that means in real terms is that there will be 8,568 residential places, 20,000 people in day places and 10,000 accessing 4.7 million personal assistance hours and home care packages.  The work has begun, but we have a lot to do.  In two weeks in County Meath I will be opening the twelfth respite care house to have been opened in the past 12 months.  There is ongoing work, but it is absolutely the case that we have a lot to do.  The committee has supported the ratification of the UN convention which has been a personal commitment of mine and the Chairman for many years.  </p> <p>  I have committed to ratifying the optional protocol on completion of Ireland&rsquo;s first reporting cycle under the convention.  The Government's approach and mine in meeting the terms of the convention is one of sustained and ongoing improvement.  Work is continuing on the reforms needed for optimum compliance with the convention's requirements.  Progress on this Bill forms a key part of that work.  In the early implementation phase it is essential that resources be focused on the improvement and enhancement of services and not diverted into additional areas such as servicing the optional protocol before we are fully ready.  Five Government amendments were introduced on Committee Stage.  I will deal with the optional protocol as quickly as possible.  My focus will be on resourcing the services as quickly as possible.  The Irish Deaf Society was mentioned in that regard.  Sometimes resourcing services leads to many internal battles about which those in the Visitors Gallery would not hear, but the bottom line is addressing the needs of those with disabilities.</p> <p>  On the equality issue, I have listened to the debate very carefully.  I do not want to be distracted by focusing on other areas of equality which I strongly support, as my focus in on disability services.  The members and I want to drive the Bill through.  I am open to constructive amendments on Report Stage.  I have indicated that I will do so.</p> <p>  I thank colleagues and committee staff.  I was saying to Pat before the meeting that I had attended many meetings of the committee as a member of the Opposition.  Now I am here as Minister of State with responsibility for disability services.  I will give one commitment.  I came into the job to do three things: reform disability services; invest in those services; and change the mindset to put the person with a disability at the centre of the services.  That is my objective and what I will be doing during my term of office, depending on how long the Government lasts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1269" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L00900"><p>I believed the Minister of State was going to tell us something seismic, for which we are all waiting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L01000"><p>We might have another year, but Deputy Fitzpatrick has already told us that we will be here until next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1441" speakername="Peter Fitzpatrick" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#L01100"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his contribution.  It is important that the Government create jobs for individuals with a disability.  I am aware that its intention is to increase the proportion of people with a disability in the workforce to 6% by 2024, but that is far too long down the road.  We have been working very closely with the Minister of State for the past few years.</p><p>I thank the Government for funding towards the respite unit in Dundalk for adults with disabilities which was badly needed.  This meeting showed that everyone has an interest in people with disabilities.  I wish the Minister of State the best for the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2019013000002#M00200"><p>I thank Deputy Fitzpatrick for his support.  Many of us have targets that are higher than 6%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2019-01-30a.275" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 10.50 a.m. sine die.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>