<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="">Committee on Education and Social Protection: Select Sub-Committee on Social Protection</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 13:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Ray Butler, Deputy Kevin Humphreys (Minister of State at the Department of Social Protection), Deputy Catherine Byrne, Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh, Deputy Joan Collins, Deputy Willie O'Dea, Deputy Michael Conaghan, Deputy Brendan Ryan. Deputy Jim Daly,</p><p>DEPUTY JOANNA TUFFY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.4" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#A00100">Business of Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#A00200"><p>At the request of the broadcasting and recording services, members are reminded to ensure that their mobile phones are turned off or put on flight or safe mode.  Today's proceedings will be broadcast live on Virgin Media channel 207, eir Vision channel 504 and Sky channel 574 until 2 p.m.  We will now go into private session to deal with any other business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.6" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The committee went into private session at 1.09 p.m. and resumed in public session at 1.12 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.7" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00050">Social Welfare Bill 2015: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00100"><p>This meeting was convened for the purpose of the consideration by the select sub-committee of the Social Welfare 2015 which was referred to it by orders of the D&aacute;il on 5 and 10 November.  The Bill gives effect principally to the social welfare measures announced in the Budget Statement on 13 October which are generally due to take effect in early 2016.  They provide for increases in social protection payments, including certain pensions, child benefit, the respite care grant which has been renamed as the carer support grant and family income supplement.  The Bill also provides for changes to PRSI contributions and credits.  It comprises two Parts, ten sections and two Schedules.  </p> <p>  I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Social Protection, Deputy Kevin Humphreys, and his officials.  I ask members and visitors to switch their mobile phones to silent or flight mode to avoid interference with the broadcasting equipment.  It is my intention to conclude Committee Stage this afternoon.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  </p> <p>  I draw members' attention to the grouping of amendments for the purposes of the debate.  It is proposed to group amendments Nos. 1, 3, 34 to 38, inclusive and 41 together; amendments Nos. 4, 5, 7, 8 and 14 to 21, inclusive, together; amendments Nos. 31 to 33, inclusive, together and amendments 39 and 40.  The amendments which have been ruled out of order are Nos. 6, 9 to 11, inclusive, 13, 24, 25 and 27 to 30, inclusive.  All other amendments which have not been grouped will be discussed individually.  I will give the explanation the various amendments have been ruled out of order when we reach them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.9" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION  1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00400"><p>Amendments Nos.1, 3, 34 to 38, inclusive, and 41 will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00500"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 3, line 10, to delete &ldquo;Social Welfare Act 2015.&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Social Welfare and Pensions Act 2015.&rdquo;</blockquote> <p>These amendments will allow the holder of the office of Financial Services Ombudsman to also hold the office of Pensions Ombudsman.  They will also ensure that where the office of Pensions Ombudsman is held by the Financial Services Ombudsman, no salary or remuneration will be received in respect of the office of Pensions Ombudsman.  Deputy Willie O'Dea has proposed a similar amendment.  The amendments tidy up the Bill and are not controversial.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00600"><p>The proposed subsection (4) in amendment No. 3 states Part 3 will "come into operation on such day or days as the Minister for Social Protection may appoint".  Does the Minister of State have any idea as to when that will happen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00700"><p>The Minister for Finance must bring forward legislation to allow for the merger of the offices of Pensions Ombudsman and Financial Services Ombudsman.  Therefore, I do not have a definite date because it is not a matter within the control of the Department of Social Protection.  That said, I hope it will happen as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00800"><p>It is a matter for the Department of Finance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B00900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B01000"><p>I do not have a major problem with this group of amendments which are technical in nature, but it does seem to be a very clumsy way of putting legislation together.  Previously, legislation made reference to the Acts being "read together as one", but this has been changed to "construed together as one Act".  In some ways, a full restatement would be better.</p> <p>  On the substantive point about the Pensions Ombudsman, it is a little previous including the measure at this stage, given that the amalgamation of the two offices has not yet happened.  It may not happen.  I know that the measure is to be brought into operation "on such day or days as the Minister for Social Protection" decides.  That could be during the lifetime of this or a future Government.  What if it takes a number of  years?  In the past individuals were allowed to remain in position until an amalgamation happened.I</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B01100"><p>It will be a separate office until the amalgamation happens because within the legislation there is a prohibition on the Pensions Ombudsman holding another job.  When enacted, the Bill will improve services for the customer because there will be a one-stop-shop to deal with related concerns.  It is enabling legislation to ensure that when the Department of Finance amalgamates the two offices, we will be able to move speedily.  This is the most relevant time to do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B01200"><p>My own view is that it should be done when the legislation from the Department of Finance is enacted.  The logic behind it is there will be the amalgamation of both offices, but that may not happen.  That said, I am not opposing the changes.  I am just arguing that it seems to be very clumsy and that there must have been a better way to do this.  Perhaps it is the opportune time to do so, but I find the construct of the amendments clumsy.  Amendment No.1 is simple enough and we have dealt with a number of similar amendments in the past.  We dealt with several Social Welfare Bills to which pension provisions were added.  I do not have a problem with this because I have been able to use it to my own benefit to table amendments on pension issues.  Once a Social Welfare Bill is opened in that way it gives us such an opportunity.  I may table amendments at a future date because I have not had adequate time to study the pension related amendments proposed.  Given that the Bill has been opened up to cover pension issues, I may submit amendments on the structure of pensions and so forth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#B01300"><p>The Government has approved the heads of the Bill.  The proposed amendments amount to a bridging measure to allow the holder of the office of Financial Services Ombudsman to hold the office of Pensions Ombudsman pending the passing of the legislation providing for the formal merger of these two offices.  I fully accept what Deputy Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh said about opening up the Bill to deal wit pensions, but it is important that the amendments are agreed to because they will allow the bridging measure to take effect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.20" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C00200"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 3, line 11, to delete &ldquo;read together as one.&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;construed together as one Act.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>This is a minor technical change to provide for the amendment of the Social Welfare Acts and the amendments contained in Part 2 of the Bill to be construed together as one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.22" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C00400"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 3, between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:&ldquo;(3) The Pensions Acts 1990 to 2014 and <i>Part 3</i>shall be construed together as one Act and may be cited together as the Pensions Acts 1990 to 2015.<br /><br />(4) <i>Part 3</i>shall come into operation on such day or days as the Minister for Social Protection may appoint by order or orders either generally or with reference to any particular purpose or provision, and different days may be so appointed for different purposes or different provisions.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.24" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p><p>Section 1, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.25" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 4, 5, 7 and 8 and 14 to 21, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C00800"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 3, to delete line 16 and substitute the following:&ldquo; &ldquo;Act of 2010&rdquo; means the Social Welfare and Pensions Act 2010;&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>In light of the enactment of the Marriage Act 2015, these amendments provide for various references to the gender-specific terms of &quot;husband&quot; and &quot;wife&quot; contained in the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 to be replaced with reference to the gender-neutral term of &quot;spouse&quot;.  They also provide for related changes in the Acts.  All these changes pertain to the recently enacted Marriage Act 2015 and it is just to tidy up and to make sure the references are correct within the Acts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C00900"><p>I welcome these amendments.  I hope all the references contained within the consolidated Act that require change are changed and if not, that any other anomalies will be addressed at the earliest possible stage, given the size of the consolidated Act and other legislation, to give full effect to the Marriage Act as now passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C01000"><p>I thank the Deputy for his comments.  I wish to compliment the staff of the Departments of Social Protection and Justice and Equality on endeavouring to implement the legislative structure arising from the referendum as quickly as they did.  While the Government has endeavoured to make all the amendments changing references to "husbands" and "wives" to "spouses", I accept fully a few references may be encountered that may need to be changed at a further time.  I acknowledge the Deputy will co-operate in so doing at that stage but I thank him for those comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C01100"><p>On that point regarding the legislation, are there issues such as, for example, payments that were more specific to one gender or the other?  I am thinking of the deserted wives payment and while it may not arise any longer, would amendments be necessary to legislation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C01200"><p>Throughout this process, the Department has endeavoured to change as many as possible.  The consolidated Act is under review constantly to ensure the legislative references are correct.  Since I came into the House, I and many Deputies have been finding references that were not up to date.  However, through a review mechanism, the Government will rectify anything that is discovered.  A huge body of work has been undertaken by civil servants in respect of the Marriage Act in an endeavour to rectify everything possible.  I certainly am not stating nothing will be found but if it is, it will be rectified as discovered as soon as practicable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.32" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C01400"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p><blockquote>In page 3, between lines 16 and 17, to insert the following:&ldquo; &ldquo;Act of 2013&rdquo; means the Social Welfare and Pensions (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2013;&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.34" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.35" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C01700"><p>Amendment No. 6 has been ruled out of order as a potential charge on the Exchequer.  Basically, this is because the amendment proposes a further increase in the contributory State pension above the increases proposed in the Bill.  As this amendment could involve a charge on the Exchequer, it therefore must be ruled out of order in accordance with Standing Order 156(3).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.37" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 6 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C01900"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p><blockquote>In page 5, line 28, to delete &ldquo;Act of 2010&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Social Welfare Act 2010&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.39" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p><p>Question proposed: "That section 3, as amended, stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C02100"><p>I note my amendment was ruled out of order on the basis it would constitute a charge on the Exchequer.  Members are debating the rate of increase for pensioners.  Section 3 deals with contributory pensioners and section 4 deals with non-contributory pensioners.  The Minister of State will be aware that pensioners have not had an increase since 2010 and the rate of inflation in the interim period has been 4.5% which, apart from anything else, erodes their purchasing power straight away by 4.5%.  However, I suggest this probably is exaggerated on the lower side because inflation covers everything from the cost of aeroplanes to the cost of drink, the cost of luxury goods, essential goods, etc.  The increase in the prices of essential items, which are more regularly purchased by pensioners, particularly those who are completely reliant on their pension, probably has been approximately 6% or 7% since 2010.  In itself, that is bad enough and constitutes a considerable erosion of purchasing power but in the meantime, pensioners in this category have lost the free telephone rental allowance and the household benefits package has been decimated.  They have lost and subsequently regained half the fuel allowance but carbon taxes have increased.  In addition, tax relief on medical insurance has been severely restricted and this measure particularly affects people in this category.  The drugs threshold has been increased and the limits in respect of the over-70s medical card have been reduced, that is, the payments of the amounts under which one will not qualify for a medical card.  Moreover, the housing adaptation grants, which again are of particular relevance to this group, have been reduced quite substantially.  Mobility grants have been reduced and the bereavement grant has been abolished.  On top of all of this, people - not exclusively but including those in this category - must bear the weight of water charges, property tax and increased contributions towards the fair deal scheme.  In addition, home help hours have been slashed.</p> <p>  Consequently, these people have suffered quite an imposition apart from the erosion of their incomes through inflation.  It is my contention that &euro;3 per week is insufficient compensation for the private nations they have suffered and while I welcome the increase, it is not nearly sufficient to compensate them for what they have lost.  Incidentally, I re-read the T&aacute;naiste's Second Stage speech and she mentioned it was a &euro;3 per week "above inflation increase" but this should be corrected.  It is not an above inflation increase, which would suggest pensions have been increased to provide for inflation in recent years, an inflation rate of a certain amount now is being projected and the &euro;3 is on top of that.  This is not correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#C02200"><p>There are a number of issues and I concur with Deputy O'Dea regarding the litany of cuts to benefits.</p><p>These cuts would affect people who are in receipt of the contributory pension and also some of the other pensions, some of which are already listed, and others which would also have an effect.  For example, if prescription charges increase it would affect people who benefit from medical cards or the reduction of six weeks in fuel allowance would affect people who benefit from a fuel allowance.  Deputy O'Dea referred to the fact that the Minister said that the &euro;3 increase was above inflation and this is what annoyed me most.  Even if one was to take the rate of inflation, which in the last four years is over 4.5%, then there should have been a &euro;10 increase and it is nowhere near that.  Different inflation figures apply to different people in some ways because if one was dependent upon a service and that service increased in price then the cumulative national inflation figure of 4% or 5% in the last few years does not hold and one might have a higher figure.</p><p> In some ways the Bill shows us, in very stark nature, the different rates for qualified adults.  It needs to be tidied up so there is consistency in some way across the board - a later amendment refers to different rates.  I will not suggest rates because we are excluded and prevented from suggesting changes which would incur a cost to the Exchequer.  I have argued here and in the D&aacute;il that this needs to be addressed in a Constitutional convention.  Towards the end of the section relating to when the increases come into operation, and then again in the next section, there are two different dates.  The logical thing to do would be to select 1 January 2016 as the date on which the legislation would come into effect.  Maybe the date of Thursday 7 January is the first day of payment or the Friday 8 January is for the invalidity pension.  Why can one date not be selected and then the next payment can be covered?  I cannot understand why there are different start dates.  The start date should be 1 January and the next payment would then take effect and a person would get the full benefit, or would lose some, based on the person's start date.  When one goes further into the legislation, 1 January seems to be a set date, yet the 7 January and 8 January are selected in this instance.  I could not figure out the logic of this other than it might be the date of the first payment.  I do not think it would make much of a difference if we removed those dates out and enabled the increases to come into effect on 1 January.  When a payment then falls due a person would get the full effect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#D00200"><p>I will address Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's last query first.  This is standard practice for increases and it arises from budgeting for weekly payments.  As it ties into weekly payments it is very difficult to administer payment of partial weeks.  This is why it is based on the different start dates and has been standard practice in payment of weekly payments since I came into the House and probably since the Deputy came into the House also.</p> <p>  In regard to Deputy O' Dea's comments on inflation, it depends on which group of experts are giving the inflation rates.  However, certain items have gone up and others have gone down.  In that regard I accept the point which was made by the Deputy.  In this context I will now turn to the matter of the &euro;3 pension increase.  The Deputy is aware from the Spring Economic Statement of the exact boundaries within which this Government was operating.  The Cabinet decided to not only provide for a &euro;3 increase in the pension, but also to provide for a 75% Christmas bonus and an increase in the fuel allowance and the carers' allowance.  The Deputy wishes to reference just the &euro;3 figure but that increase is significantly more than was suggested by his own party in its pre-budget submission operating within the same constraints as the Government.  We increased the pension by &euro;3 but we also provided for the Christmas bonus, the fuel allowance and the much welcomed change in the carers' allowance.  Those are the constraints within which the Government operated and they were acknowledge by Fianna F&aacute;il when it used the same constraints in making its pre-budget submission.</p> <p>  The Government decided to not only increase the pension by &euro;3 per week but to also bring back the Christmas bonus to 75%, increase the fuel allowance by &euro;2.50 per week and to extend the carers' allowance from six to 12 weeks after the death of a carer, who is often a much loved member of the family.  The &euro;3 increase is one measure in a package which has been universally accepted.  I do not think the Deputy suggested that we should create a &euro;5 increase and not provide all the other increases.  I ask that the Deputy looks at the whole package.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#D00300"><p>I have acknowledged the number of increases that have been made but in many cases they represent a return of what was taken away by the present Government in the first place, but I will leave that to one side.  Fianna F&aacute;il's pre-budget submission indicated that it would implement considerably higher expenditure on social welfare and provide for less in terms of tax concessions than ultimately proved to be the case, but that was just our position and how we wanted to balance it.  I refer the Minister of State to the statement made in the D&aacute;il by his colleague the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, when she said that the &euro;3 pension increase was an above-inflation increase.  Would Deputy Humphreys agree that it is not an above-inflation increase and that it is does not take inflation or projected inflation into account?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#D00400"><p>I do not have the transcripts of the Second Stage debate but I am happy to discuss that with Deputy O'Dea at a later stage when I have read the transcripts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#D00500"><p>While we talk of the &euro;3 pension increase can the Minister of State, Deputy Humphreys indicate the overall cost of the increases under this section and what is the overall cost of the package of measures under the Bill itself?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#D00600"><p>I had the figure on inflation rates and consumer price index buried in my notes here.  The consumer price index, while not necessarily the best example, is the one usually used and accepted as a guide.  It indicates an aggregate inflation rate of 5.08%.  It is not the rate of 1.5% which was quoted by the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton.  She said that the &euro;3 increase was above the rate of inflation.  As the inflation rate for the term of office for this Government is over 5% and if the increase was to be above inflation, then nearly &euro;11 would need to go onto the pension each week.  Other figures show 4.5% growth in GDP last year.  Even if that figure of 4.5% had been used, the increase would be more than &euro;3.  None of the figures which has emerged is below the 4.5% and is definitely not as low as 1.50% or less, which is suggested by the &euro;3 increase.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1193" speakername="Joan Collins" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#E00100"><p>Irrespective of the Minister of State's comments on constraints and although welcome to a small degree, many of the pensioners I have met have said the &euro;3 increase is derisory.  It will cover the cost of an extra pan of bread and pint of milk once a week; it will be known, therefore, in the next period as the pan of bread and pint of milk increase.  A pan of bread costs approximately &euro;2, depending on where a person shops, and then there is the cost of a pint of milk.  This increase will not substantially change people's position.  Given the constraints, it would probably have been much better to target the money elsewhere.  The duration of the fuel allowance could have been extended, with the payments for the six weeks cut from the period being reinstated.  That would have had a much more substantial effect on the lives of old age pensioners and those receiving welfare payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#E00200"><p>I am reluctant to say too much because my blood pressure might go through the roof.  I pause, first, to welcome the Minister of State and the Bill.  </p> <p>  It is interesting to listen to the comments of those who were formally in government.  They say things should have been done differently.  If they had been done differently when the previous Government was in office, we would not find ourselves in the mess we are in.  </p> <p>  I welcome the increase in the State pension.  During the past five years there has been no reduction in the contributory or non-contributory State pension.  Holding this together was an important part of what the Government was trying to do.  I welcome the &euro;3 increase.  We would have liked to have seen it being increased a little more, but we have to start with small steps.</p> <p>  In the previous Government people were leaping ahead of themselves.  They were giving &euro;1,000 to everyone with a child under three years of age.  That approach did not help and because of it we are where we are today.  </p> <p>  It is welcome that the free travel scheme, the free television licence and the living alone allowance are still in place.  I also welcome the return of the Christmas bonus, which will see a 75% restoration.</p> <p>  I do not know to whom Deputies have been speaking, but I have been on the doorsteps and the people to whom I have been speaking welcome the fact that the Government has pulled the country back from the brink.  This is very obvious from speaking to people on the doorsteps and I speak to people in all areas of my constituency.  There are other points I will mention.  </p> <p>  I sat and listened to a former Minister speak about water charges.  The previous Government proposed a charge of &euro;400.  Fresh running water and wastewater services will cost people, in particular old age pensioners, &euro;1.07 per week.  We need to deal with reality.  If money was abundant, as it was in the past, and it had been used appropriately instead of being squandered, we would not be in the position we are in today.</p> <p>  I welcome the changes proposed and compliment the Minister, Deputy Joan Burton, who has made a huge contribution in the social welfare portfolio.  No other Minister made the strides she has made in recent years.  I will speak again later, but it is rich for Members to make statements, given that they had the opportunity to lead the country into a better future, but, unfortunately, they wasted it.  That is my small contribution for what it is worth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#E00300"><p>I will have to keep a careful hold of my blood pressure.  Deputy Catherine Byrne refers to leaking by the previous Government.  That is hugely ironic in view of the fact that the Government has made leaking an art form.  Half of the measures announced in the budget were leaked in advance; it, therefore, ill behoves any member or supporter of the Administration to criticise any previous Administration for leaking.</p> <p>  Deputy Catherine Byrne also referred to the free telephone rental allowance and other household benefits.  The free telephone rental allowance is no more and, whatever about the people she represents, this causes a great deal of angst, anxiety and distress among the people I represent.  Elderly people are living behind barricades, in particular in rural Ireland, with no access to a telephone because they cannot afford the telephone rental cost.  It was the abolition of the free telephone allowance that removed that lifeline from them.  I know one or two cases adjacent to my constituency in which people have been subject to very serious crime.  They would have been helped had they had a telephone and been able to call An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  </p> <p>  A figure of &euro;400 is being mentioned in respect of water charges.  I would never support a Government that would introduce water charges without taking ability to pay into account, regardless of how badly off a person is.  There are people in my constituency living on &euro;188 a week who are paying rent to the city council, yet they have to pay water charges.  Similarly, people in living Moyross, Southhill and St. Mary's Park are living in conditions of abject poverty.  They are dependent on social welfare payments, yet they are paying property tax which is being forcibly deducted from them by Limerick City and County Council.  I could go on, but I do not want to delay proceedings unduly.  </p> <p>  Deputy Catherine Byrne says she is on the doorsteps and that people are extremely happy and content.  Many of the people I represent are in the same category represents.  Good luck to her if the people she meets are happy with an increase of &euro;3 a week, but I know that the people I represent certainly are not happy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#E00400"><p>Earlier this year the ESRI published a report on inflation.  It stated the rate of inflation for low income families was higher than the average inflation rate during the recession and that it was lower for high income families.  When we pick a figure, be it the consumer price index or another, a higher figure applies to low income families during the recession.  These families are usually dependent on the contributory or, more likely, the non-contributory State pension.  If they have another pension, the position might be different.  In its paper the ESRI argues that there should be a monitoring of differences in the inflation rate.  One rate should not be used as a yardstick.</p><p>I share the same constituency as Deputy Catherine Byrne and it is obvious that she is not speaking to the people to whom I speak.  Everyone welcomes an increase in his or her social welfare payments, but that is because they have been hammered in the past.  That does not mean that the end is near.  I will not oppose a Social Welfare Bill when it contains welcome changes.  I did not oppose the Bill on Second Stage, despite the Minister's challenge to those in opposition, nor have I opposed previous Social Welfare Bills.</p><p>Changes might be welcome, but we must have regard to the context.  In this case, the context is that while contributory pension rates were not changed <i>per se</i>, substantial changes were made to social welfare secondary benefits.  Changes were also made to qualifying periods for pensions which, in effect, amounted to a cut in income for those in receipt of contributory or invalidity pension.  There was also the cut to the respite care grant and death benefit, for instance, on which many of the people concerned would have relied at some stage.  We have had a list of cuts and I do not wish to delay proceedings, but their effects should be remembered.  </p><p>Deputy Catherine Byrne cannot turn around and say the charge for water is &euro;1.07 a week.  If true, only &euro;1.93 will be left of the &euro;3 being crowed about to cover the property tax, increased prescription charges and the cost of changes to the drugs repayment scheme.  All of these changes will eat into the increase of &euro;3 which will disappear, without taking account of the effect of inflation, which brings us back to where this debate started.  The Government is not rowing back on anything which was done previously.  In the scheme of things, the &euro;3 increase is minuscule, given what people have gone through in recent times.  The constituents I met in recent times welcome the increase, but they will not thank the Government for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1079" speakername="Ray Butler" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00100"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  We all know that this is a start, that there is a long road ahead and that we have come a long way.  Certain members said that when the crash occurred, it would cost only &euro;6 billion to recapitalise the banks.  Chemical Ali went out onto the plinth and said the troika and the IMF were not in town.  Others wanted to run the country on the pension reserve fund.  They said it was worth &euro;15 billion when, in reality, there was only &euro;5 billion or &euro;6 billion in it.  I have to agree that if we had been left in the hands of the people concerned, we would all be having bread and milk, if we were lucky.  I understand people are not dancing in the street, but I have noted when knocking on doors that the people welcome the increases in the pension payment and Christmas bonus and the reinstatement of some of the payments that were cut.  It is a start and we have come a long way.  I agree that people are not dancing in the street, but they see what the Government has done in managing the economy in the past four years.  They will not be fooled when it comes to the general election.  We see this in the opinion polls.  I talk to people and know what is happening on the ground.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00200"><p>To be fair to the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh should note that she was not challenging Sinn F&eacute;in to vote against the welfare budget.  The comment was directed more at his colleagues sitting beside him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00300"><p>No, she did not single us out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00400"><p>It was quite obvious because Deputy Willie O'Dea ran true to form.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Willie O&rsquo;Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00500"><p>Another version of Walter Mitty.  The Minister of State should read her speech.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00800"><p>Deputy Brendan Ryan asked me about costs.  For pension measures and the qualified adult rate of payment, there is a cost of &euro;93 million to 2016.  The overall package is worth approximately &euro;250 million, which is substantial considering where all of the experts said we would be in budgetary matters at this stage.  They said we would still be taking money out of the economy and making further corrections.  We have certainly come a long way in the past three years.  If one considers the budgets announced last year and this year together, one realises we were able to increase the living alone allowance.  It is the first time it has been raised since the 1990s.  Last year we were able to take the first step towards bringing back the Christmas bonus.  It was restored at a rate of 25%.  At the time, the Government indicated that it was hoped to restore it at a rate of 50% in the 2016 budget, but we were able to restore it at the rate of 75%.</p> <p>  Deputy Joan Collins referred to the fuel allowance.  There is a 12.5% increase on the previous rate.  Its purpose is to get people through the worst weather, or bad weather events.  In the past when there was exceptionally bad weather, the allowance was extended.  I hope we will have no exceptionally bad weather this winter.  The 12.5% increase is significant considering that nobody envisaged in any of the budgetary submissions we received that the Government would be able to increase not only the fuel allowance but also carer's allowance and the Christmas bonus.</p> <p>  I accept Deputy Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh&rsquo;s figures for inflation, but there is a 1% increase on the 2015 rate.  Generally, it is slightly ahead of the projected annual inflation rate of 1% in 2016.  I accept that nobody will be dancing at the crossroads over the increases, but people have recognised that since the last budget recovery has started slightly and that we have been able to put something back.  It marks the end of the period of cuts which is generally welcomed by the public at large.  It is an indication that there is hope and that this and future Governments will be in a position to reinstate some of the payments that were cut.  I hope that in future years we will be able to increase the State pension to reflect the economic recovery.  My party is committed to increasing it as long as the economy continues to recover in the current manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F00900"><p>Does the Minister of State have a figure for the percentage of contributory pensioners by comparison with the number of non-contributory pensioners?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01000"><p>I will get the officials to go through the documentation.  As soon as they find the figure, I will give it to the Deputy.  I will send it to him after the meeting if it is not found while the meeting is in progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01100"><p>What is the overall cost?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01200"><p>The cost of the overall budgetary package is &euro;250 million.  The overall increase associated with the increase in the pension of &euro;3 per week is &euro;93 million.  There are additional costs associated with the fuel allowance and the Christmas bonus.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01300"><p>As water charges were in place last year, the benefits accruing from the budget are such that people will have greater capacity to meet payments this year.  If it were the case that the increases were being introduced this year with water charges, one would accept the argument Deputy Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh is making, namely, that the increases are being eaten into already.  However, the charges were in place last year and will continue.  The increases will help people to pay the charges to their households.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01400"><p>I have the figures for Deputy Willie O&rsquo;Dea.  The figure for the number in receipt of the State contributory pension is 386,420.  The number in receipt of the State non-contributory pension is 94,640.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01500"><p>Obviously, there are those who receive the contributory pension on a <i>pro rata</i>basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01600"><p>Dependants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01700"><p>That would be included in the contributory category.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01800"><p>Is the Chairman asking about qualified adults?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F01900"><p>Some people receive a partial contributory pension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F02200"><p>They are included.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.70" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.71" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F02500"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><blockquote>In page 6, line 12, to delete &ldquo;Act of 2010&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Social Welfare Act 2010&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.73" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F02700"><p>Amendment No. 9, in the name of Deputy Willie O&rsquo;Dea, proposes a further increase in the State non-contributory pension above the increase provided for in the Bill.  As  it could involve a charge on the Exchequer, it must, therefore, be ruled out of order in accordance with Standing Order 156(3).</p> <p>  Amendment No. 10, also in the name of Deputy Willie O&rsquo;Dea, seeks to exempt persons reaching 65 years from the requirement to seek employment actively while in receipt of jobseeker&rsquo;s allowance until they qualify for the State pension.  This would have the effect of relaxing the requirements for qualification for jobseeker&rsquo;s allowance.  As it could involve a charge on the Exchequer, it must, therefore, be ruled out of order in accordance with Standing Order 156(3).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.75" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 9 and 10 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.76" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 4, as amended, stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#F03000"><p>The Minister of State has just given us the figures for those in receipt of the State contributory and non-contributory pensions.  Some people in receipt of the State contributory pension will have alternative sources of income.  Overall, approximately 70% of pensioners rely exclusively on their pensions to survive, but I am open to correction in saying this.  The State non-contributory pension is based on a means test, as members will be aware.  Recipients of the State non-contributory pension are almost guaranteed to have no other source of income.</p><p>What I have said about the rate of increase for contributory pensioners applies with even greater force to non-contributory pensioners because they do not have any alternative source of income.</p><p> My amendment was ruled out of order but I want to ask the Minister of State about those who have reached the age of 65.  As he will be aware, the target age for old age pension is to rise to 67 years in the next year or two.  With the abolition of the retirement pension or as it was subsequently called, "transition" pension, if a person who is compulsorily retired, must retire or is retired aged 65 is now to get jobseeker's allowance, could the Minister of State clarify the requirements he or she must meet?  Have they to prove that they are actively seeking and available for work at 65 years?  Are they subject to these new regulations about being offered training courses, etc., and if they do not take up the training course, will they be penalised in relation to receipt of their social welfare?  What exactly is the position?  Is there any difference in substance between a person aged 65 or over applying for jobseeker's allowance and a person under the age of 65 applying for jobseeker's?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00200"><p>The committee discussed this previously with the Minister.  My understanding was that the Minister stated that those having to retire who were not of the age of the retirement pension would not have to be available for work but that they could get the jobseeker's allowance.  It is the same question.  I realise that it is more due to the rules of the House that this amendment was ruled out of order but I understood the position to be as the amendment suggests.  The Minister of State might clarify that.  Deputy Joan Collins raised it previously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1193" speakername="Joan Collins" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00300"><p>I seek clarification on that as well.  I was quite surprised the reason it has been ruled out of order is that it would be a cost to the Exchequer.  How would it be a cost to the Exchequer if we were of the understanding that one does not have to look for work?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00400"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00500"><p>When the change to the pension ages came about, a number of anomalies were identified but there were also effects on the recipients.  For instance, it is not only that they end up, instead of being on the State transition pension, being on jobseeker's allowance, albeit as far as I know without being forced to look for work.  There was a pre-retirement payment in the past which captured that but we do not have it anymore - it is not called that at least.</p> <p>  If one goes for jobseeker's benefit for a number of months if one retires at 65 and the age criteria changes to 67, that involves two years of a gap that one must make up.  The jobseeker's benefit runs out.  One's partner may still be working.  If so, one ends up with nothing whereas in the past one would have been on a contributory pension.  There are problems.  Some will be caught in a bind because, especially at that age, they will not have the opportunity to plan long enough for that shortfall of one year at present, two years in the future, or three years at some stage, because their contracts were until age 65 and the State transition payment was in recognition that the State pension kicked in at 66 years.  There was a recognition previously, but with that gone there is nothing other than jobseeker's benefit, initially, for six or maybe nine months - I cannot remember now.  It is when it goes beyond that there is a possibility that one will end up with nothing if one's partner is working because jobseeker's allowance is means tested.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00600"><p>Deputy O'Dea asked when the pension age of 67 years kicks in, and it is in 2021.  From age 65 to 66, jobseeker's benefit is paid.  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh stated he was not too sure whether it was for nine months.  Actually, from age 65 to 66, it is paid for 12 months.</p> <p>  The requirements for signing, etc., are all changed and much more relaxed.  It is actually relaxed from the age of 62 onwards, not 65.  At age 65, on which the questions were asked, the job benefit is paid for the 12 months, from 65 to 66 years, and retirement is at 67 years.</p> <p>  The demographics are changing.  Certainly, when my father retired, men's life expectancy was probably five or six years once retired.  Life expectancy is changing.  There is a whole change in demographics, in relation to the length of time people are living and also the length of time people now want to work and want to seek employment.  One of the queries I get on a regular basis in my clinic relates to those who believe they are being forced to retire and who want to continue working for much longer periods and be involved in the workforce.</p> <p>  The pensions area will be a major challenge for all of us in the future because of the change in demographics, such as the change in the number of young people compared to pensioners.  We, as a Legislature, have a significant body of work to carry out in future years to deal with the implications of demographic changes to pensions.  I believe I have answered the specific questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00700"><p>I agree with what the Minister of State says about the demographics, etc.  I mentioned somebody retiring compulsorily at 65.  I should have said - Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh reminded me I was incorrect - they apply for jobseeker's benefit, which they can receive, as, I think, the Minister of State indicated, for 12 months.  Of course, for somebody of a young age to qualify for jobseeker's benefit in the normal course of events, he or she must prove certain criteria.  They must establish that they are available for work, they are actively seeking work, etc.  Is the Minister of State saying that does not apply to a person-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00800"><p>It is relaxed.  I will give the exact circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G00900"><p>Where is it written out?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01000"><p>I have said I will provide that to the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01100"><p>To the committee even.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01200"><p>To the committee.  Sorry, I beg the Chairman's pardon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01300"><p>That would be useful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01400"><p>They still must be genuinely seeking work, from age 65 to 66.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01500"><p>That is what we were told previously.  I understood that at the very least there were plans to have a transition a little like what is there for the lone parents.  When the Minister of State says there is a relaxing of the rules, how is it relaxed if one still has to be available?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01600"><p>They are not activated in the same way.  On the number of times that they come in to sign, for instance, those on job benefit normally sign on a weekly basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01700"><p>It is obviously not as sympathetic as, say, the transition jobseeker's payment for lone parents.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01800"><p>I would appreciate the information as to what exactly the rules are, particularly in relation to activation.  What sort of activation measures are they subject to, in terms of being offered courses, etc.?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G01900"><p>It is voluntary after age 62.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02000"><p>The only remaining requirement is one must be available for and seeking work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02100"><p>Can it be part-time work or does it have to be full-time work?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02200"><p>I will give the details to the committee afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1193" speakername="Joan Collins" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02300"><p>For the purposes of clarification, amendment No. 10 stated they would "be exempt from the requirement of being available for and genuinely seeking full-time employment".  Deputy Humphreys, as a Minister of State, is rejecting it because it could be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02400"><p>It would be the Oireachtas that would have ruled that out of order in accordance with Standing Orders.  It would not be the Minister who ruled that out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1193" speakername="Joan Collins" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02500"><p>It was ruled out of order because it would be a cost to the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1193" speakername="Joan Collins" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02700"><p>Everybody was of the understanding that, from age 65 to 66, a person would not be cut-off from jobseeker's benefit or jobseeker's allowance on the basis of not looking for work.  We need further clarification on that because it is something we would have to challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G02800"><p>The Minister of State said that he will provide that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.106" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.107" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.108" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 5 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#G03200"><p>I welcome the name change that is being brought about.  I also welcome the fact that the Government saw the light and reversed the cut that it imposed.</p><p>The name change is an admission of what we knew, that the respite care grant was not used for respite by the vast majority of carers but was used for other supports such as buying equipment, paying for car insurance, fuel and so forth.  We have had that debate.  This is a welcome change in the budget.  The Government has seen the light and has reversed a cut that was not going to bring in the billions that were required but that targeted those in society who in some cases have given up full-time work to care for loved ones and, incidentally, saved the State money.  Often they were unappreciated to a degree, so it is a welcome change.</p><p> I acknowledge changes that are positive and the carers will welcome this.  In particular, the name change is a reflection of what the payment was used for in the first instance.  In some cases, it is payment for services that should have been delivered by the State.  For example, many people have told me recently that they have used the payment because they have not been able to access the motorised transport grant or the mobility allowance, which is not in this legislation.  In that regard, representatives of the Department of Health appeared before the Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions and they appeared to suggest that it will be a number of months, if not years, before we see the full outline of a scheme to replace that, which affects many of the people who would be cared for and who would benefit from this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H00200"><p>I also welcome the restoration of the respite care grant.  When the cut was introduced we pointed out that it would cause a great deal of hardship.  I can testify to the fact that it has done so in the individual cases I have dealt with.  Carers contribute an enormous amount to this country.  I forget the exact figure but if they were to be paid properly, at the usual rate for the work they do, it would cost the State many billions.</p> <p>  Perhaps the Minister will clarify a matter regarding the old respite care grant.  People who did not qualify for the carer's allowance could apply for that grant.  The position is that if one receives carer's allowance, one is automatically entitled to the respite care grant.  I presume the same applies to this carer's support grant.  Will the Minister clarify that there is no change in the regulations and that if a person does not qualify for the carer's allowance they can still apply for, and receive, this grant?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H00300"><p>It is the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H00400"><p>I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H00500"><p>I welcome this change and the restoration of the grant to &euro;1,700 from &euro;1,375.  I am well aware of the importance of the respite grant.  My mother was ill for a long time and my brothers cared for her at home.  The respite grant paid for the items that were extra requirements in addition to minding somebody who was very ill.  It could be an item such as a clothes dryer.  If somebody is incontinent, having a clothes dryer means one can dry their clothes.  It was important to have that grant available so people could use it for other items and functions, particularly for people are very ill.</p> <p>  This refers back to the issue of trying to spread what we have and to give everybody a little.  The decision to restore the extra money to the carer's support grant is very important.  For many families it is not about the money.  It certainly was not about money in our family when it came to minding my mother.  It was about the fact that we wanted to keep her at home and to give her as much support as she needed in the final years of her life, and being able to support her and my brothers so she could have the comforts of her own home.  It is a hugely important grant.  In the past, when the money was not available, it was difficult when some of the benefit was taken away.  Now it has been restored and, hopefully, in the future we can give greater acknowledgement to people who provide care and support 24 hours a day, seven days a week for 365 days of the year to family members at home, particularly when they are very ill.</p> <p>  The Minister has restored the money that was withdrawn previously and that is very important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.115" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.116" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H00800"><p>Amendment No. 11 is out of order as it is a potential charge on the Exchequer.  The amendment seeks to amend section 6 with regard to the definition of relevant age of a child in respect of entitlement to the one-parent family payment.  The amendment provides for the restoration of the qualifying age for children from seven years of age to 12 years.  This amendment could involve a charge on the Exchequer and therefore must be ruled out of order in accordance with Standing Order 1563.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.118" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment No.  11 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.119" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 6 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01000"><p>On section 6, the two matters are related.  One comes into effect on 1 January and the other commences on 1 June.  I understand that 1 June is when the payment is made and 1 May marks the six months requirement prior to it.  In some ways it would have made no difference if the Minister had left the date as 1 June for when it comes into effect, because the existing payment is transferring straight in.  Again, at some point in the future, we must look at the dates that are set.  As with the figures, the more dates that are provided, the more confusing it gets.  It is bad enough for us who are dealing with it on a daily basis, but many people might have some idea about the social welfare system but do not fully understand it and get caught out by this and that date.</p> <p>  To qualify for the respite care grant, one must have been caring from 1 January until 1 June.  Sometimes people postpone applying.  They might be caring for a parent and postpone applying for it, thinking they will wait until after Christmas.  It is too late if one leaves it too long into January.  One will not get one's full benefits.  It is not for the sake of the monetary benefit.  As Deputy Catherine Byrne said, it might be for a clothes dryer, heating or something else and they should be entitled to it.</p> <p>  I do not oppose the section but am just pointing to the anomaly with dates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01100"><p>I welcome the small increase of &euro;5 in child benefit.  I am sorry, that is dealt with in section 7.  I am sorry for the confusion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01200"><p>Do you wish say anything else on this section?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01300"><p>No.  I think I covered it under the wrong section, but I covered it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01400"><p>You were on the right section, but covered the two.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01500"><p>I could not see the small print.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#H01600"><p>I realise this matter was dealt with under section 5, but section 6 deals with the restoration of the grant.  I welcome the restoration of the respite care grant, now called the carer's support grant.  I congratulate the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Burton, on honouring her commitment to us that she would restore this in full once the resources became available.  It is a strong indication of the recovery of the economy that the resources are now available, and I am delighted that it has been restored in full.</p><p>It would be easy for potential Governments of any hue to just leave the cuts alone and not reverse them.  I am delighted with the restoration of the grant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.128" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.129" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.130" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 7 stand part of the Bill".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J00500"><p>I welcome the small increase in child benefit.  The briefing provided by the Department in respect of the Bill indicates that Ireland has the fifth highest rate of fifth highest rate of child benefit in Europe.  The payment here is &euro;140 per month, whereas the rate paid immediately across the water is &euro;29 per month.  That is a huge benefit for people who have children.  When I had a young family, people welcomed their child benefit at the end of the month and put it towards the little things they could not otherwise afford or used it to pay a bit extra off the ESB bill or gas bill.  It is hugely important for children to get additional benefits from the payment of child benefit.  In the long run, it will benefit those who are poorer.  I hope whatever Government is in place after the forthcoming election will consider another increase in child benefit because it is most beneficial to families, in particular those with very young children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J00600"><p>I wish to put the Chair on notice that I may be obliged to step out just before 2.40 p.m. to respond to a Topical Issue.  I hope it will not happen.  My private secretary is endeavouring to get a substitute to respond on my behalf but if efforts in that regard are not successful, I will have to go to the House.  I apologise to the committee and I just wish to notify members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J00700"><p>If that happens and if members agree, we will suspend for a period of approximately 20 minutes.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J00800"><p>I welcome any change to reverse cuts.  Child benefit has now been restored to the average, if one likes, but there were changes to the payment of child benefit for families with more than four children.  Is there an indication that the Minister will reconsider that matter in the future?  In the past, the Minister said that if money is available some of the cuts would be reversed.  That did not happen in other cases but the restoration of child benefit in terms of the average payment was flagged.</p> <p>  Perhaps the committee as a whole could discuss in future the general direction of such payments.  Child benefit should be a universal payment but it is important to capture those who are most disadvantaged and who are dependent on social welfare.  Rather than have two rates of child benefit, as some suggest, is there an indication that the qualified child allowance would be increased?  That would be a way to capture those who are living in poverty and who are most disadvantaged.  It would be a more targeted mechanism to ensure the transfers from Government would go to those most at risk of poverty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J00900"><p>Deputy Ryan asked about the respite care grant, which cost &euro;30 million.  I very much agree with Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh on what he said previously about carer's support.  The renaming of it is important but what is most important is the principle.  He is correct in that regard.</p> <p>  If we are re-elected and I happen to be in the same position, I would be open to looking at everything,  However, I am not going to comment on the next budget or the next social welfare Bill at this stage.  If I find myself in this position next year, I would be happy to sit down with Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh and discuss the matter with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01000"><p>I will remind the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01100"><p>Or <i>vice versa</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01200"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01300"><p>We could grant it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01400"><p>Or<i>vice versa.</i></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01500"><p>None of us might be here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01600"><p>We will remind the Deputy if we are here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01700"><p>In the meantime, we wish the Deputy the best of luck.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J01800"><p>We could even be challenging the Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Humphreys, on it.  He could be Minister for Social Protection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.145" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.

SECTION 8</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J02000"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p><blockquote>In page 8, line 3, to delete &ldquo;&euro;1,112&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;&euro;1,212&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>The amendment is required to correct a typographical error in the 2009 legislation, as published.  The Minister of the day was Ms Hanafin and the transcript of the D&aacute;il was checked.  The amount was &euro;1,202 and there is a typographical error in the Social Welfare and Pension Act (No. 2) 2009, which indicated the figure to be &euro;1,102.  I reassure the committee that at all stages the Department operated on the basis of the higher figure of &euro;1,202.  The purpose of the amendment is purely to correct that typographical error.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J02100"><p>Is there no back money?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J02200"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.149" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.150" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Section 8, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.151" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J02600"><p>Amendment No. 13 in the name of Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh has been ruled out of order as a potential charge on the Exchequer.  His proposal that the family income supplement should be increased could involve a charge on the Exchequer and, therefore, the amendment must be ruled out of order in accordance with Standing Order 1563.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.153" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 13 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.154" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Section 9 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.155" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Section 10 agreed to.

NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J03000"><p>Amendment No. 14 was already discussed with amendment No. 4.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J03100"><p>I move amendment No. 14:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Liability to maintain family</b><br /><br /><b>11. </b>The Principal Act is amended&mdash;(a) in section 2(7) (amended by section 15 of the Act of 2010)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in clause (I) of paragraph (a)(i), by the substitution of &ldquo;spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;wife&rdquo;,<br /><br />(ii) in clause (II) of paragraph (a)(i), by the substitution of &ldquo;former spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;former wife&rdquo;,<br /><br />(iii) in paragraph (a)(ii), by the substitution of &ldquo;other parent of that qualified child&rdquo; for &ldquo;mother&rdquo;,<br /><br />(iv) in clause (I) of paragraph (b)(i), by the substitution of &ldquo;spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;husband&rdquo;,<br /><br />(v) in clause (II) of paragraph (b)(i), by the substitution of &ldquo;former spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;former husband&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(vi) in paragraph (b)(ii), by the substitution of &ldquo;other parent of that qualified child&rdquo; for &ldquo;father&rdquo;,</blockquote>(b) in section 344(1) (amended by section 24 of the Act of 2010)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) by the deletion of the definitions of &ldquo;husband&rdquo; and &ldquo;wife&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(ii) by the insertion of the following definition:<blockquote>&ldquo; &lsquo;spouse&rsquo; in relation to a person who has been married more than once, refers only to the last spouse of that person and for this purpose that last spouse shall be read as including the person to whom, but for the fact that the marriage has been dissolved, being a dissolution recognised as valid in the State, that person would be married.&rdquo;,</blockquote>and</blockquote>(c) in section 345 (amended by section 24 of the Act of 2010)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in paragraph (a)(i), by the substitution of &ldquo;spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;wife&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(ii) in paragraph (b)(i), by the substitution of &ldquo;spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;husband&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.158" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J03300"><p>The following amendments were all discussed together until I indicate otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J03400"><p>I move amendment No. 15:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Meaning of spouse and civil partner for certain purposes</b><br /><br /><b>12. </b>Section 3 (amended by section 16 of the Act of 2010) of the Principal Act is amended by the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (10):<blockquote>&ldquo;(10) For the purposes of sections 43, 56, 66, 76, 77A, 102, 112, 117, 122, 134, 141(2)(d), 146, 149(4), 150(3), 158, 161D, 181(4), 210(2), 211(3), 214(2), 216, 219(2), 250(2)(b), 297 and 298, Chapter 9 of Part 3 and Part 7A&mdash;<blockquote>(a) &lsquo;spouse&rsquo; means each person of a married couple who are living together, and<br /><br />(b) &lsquo;civil partner&rsquo; means each civil partner of a couple who are both parties to a civil partnership who are living together.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.161" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J03600"><p>I move amendment No. 16:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Meaning of widow and widower for purposes of widow&rsquo;s (non-contributory) pension, widower&rsquo;s (non-contributory) pension, etc.</b><br /><br /><b>13. </b>Section 162(2) (amended by section 19 of the Act of 2010) of the Principal Act is amended by the substitution of the following paragraph for paragraph (b):<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(b) a widow who has remarried or entered into a civil partnership shall not be regarded as the widow of her former spouse and a widower who has remarried or entered into a civil partnership shall not be regarded as the widower of his former spouse, and&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.163" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J03800"><p>I move amendment No. 17:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Meaning of widow and widower for purposes of one-parent family payment</b><br /><br /><b>14. </b>Section 172(2) (amended by section 20 of the Act of 2010) of the Principal Act is amended by the substitution of the following paragraph for paragraph (b):<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(b) a widow who has remarried or entered into a civil partnership shall not be regarded as the widow of her former spouse and a widower who has remarried or entered into a civil partnership shall not be regarded as the widower of his former spouse,&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.165" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J04000"><p>I move amendment No. 18:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Calculation of supplementary welfare allowance</b><br /><br /><b>15. </b>Section 196(2) (amended by section 19 of the Act of 2010) of the Principal Act is amended, in paragraph (a), by the substitution of the following subparagraph for subparagraph (i):<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(i) both spouses of a married couple,&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.167" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J04200"><p>I move amendment No. 19:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Absence from State or imprisonment</b><br /><br /><b>16. </b>Section 249 of the Principal Act is amended by the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (2) (amended by section 26 of the Act of 2010):<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(2) Except where regulations otherwise provide, where any benefit under Part 2 to which a person is entitled includes an increase in respect of a qualified adult, that increase shall not be payable for any period during which the qualified adult&mdash;<blockquote>(a) is absent from the State, or <br /><br />(b) is undergoing imprisonment or detention in legal custody.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.169" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J04400"><p>I move amendment No. 20:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Excepted employments and excepted self-employed contributors</b><br /><br /><b>17. </b>Schedule 1 to the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote><blockquote>(a) in Part 2, by the substitution, in paragraph 1 (amended by section 26 of the Act of 2010), of &ldquo;spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;husband, wife&rdquo;, and <br /><br />(b) in Part 3, by the substitution, in paragraph 1(ii) (amended by section 19 of the Social Welfare and Pensions Act 2014), of &ldquo;spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;husband, wife&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.171" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J04600"><p>I move amendment No. 21:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Elections under Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 relating to charging, collection and recovery of certain contributions</b><br /><br /><b>18. </b>(1) Section 23 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in subsection (5) (amended by section 5 of the Act of 2013)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in paragraph (a), by the substitution of &ldquo;by the spouse in respect of whom the election is made&rdquo; for &ldquo;by a wife&rdquo;,<br /><br />(ii) in paragraph (a), by the substitution of &ldquo;the other spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;her husband&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(iii) in paragraph (b), by the substitution of &ldquo;each spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;the husband or the wife&rdquo;,<br /><br />and</blockquote>(b) by the insertion of the following subsection after subsection (6):<br /><br />&ldquo;(7) In subsection (5), &lsquo;spouse&rsquo; means each person of a married couple who are living together.&rdquo;.</blockquote>(2) Section 30G (inserted by section 6 of the Act of 2013) is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in subsection (5)&mdash;<blockquote><blockquote>(i) in paragraph (a), by the substitution of &ldquo;by the spouse in respect of whom the election is made&rdquo; for &ldquo;by a wife&rdquo;,<br /><br />(ii) in paragraph (a), by the substitution of &ldquo;the other spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;her husband&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(iii) in paragraph (b), by the substitution of &ldquo;each spouse&rdquo; for &ldquo;the husband or wife&rdquo;,<br /><br />and</blockquote></blockquote>(b) by the insertion of the following subsection after subsection (7):<blockquote>&ldquo;(8) In subsection (5), &lsquo;spouse&rsquo; means each person of a married couple who are living together.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.173" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J04800"><p>Amendment No. 22 has not yet been discussed.  Does the Minister of State need to outline anything in regard to it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#J04900"><p>I move amendment No. 22:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Medical assessor &ndash; registered nurse</b><br /><br /><b>19. </b>Section 2 of the Principal Act is amended in subsection (1)&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in the definition of &ldquo;medical assessor&rdquo; (inserted by section 3 of the Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2015)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in paragraph (a), by the deletion of &ldquo;or&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(ii) by the insertion of the following paragraph after paragraph (a):<blockquote>&ldquo;(aa) an officer of the Minister who is a registered nurse, or&rdquo;,</blockquote>and</blockquote>(b) by the insertion of the following definition:<br /><br />&ldquo; &lsquo;registered nurse&rsquo; has the same meaning as it has in the Nurses and Midwives Act 2011;&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>The intention behind this amendment is to add to the departmental adviser's capacity by means of the employment of suitably qualified nurses and to amend the definition of &quot;medical assessor&quot; in the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 to provide for that change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00100"><p>I am not sure whether I am opposing or agreeing with this.  I find it odd.  We had a discussion here about trying to get doctors as medical assessors and there was no comment last year about having nurses.  The vast majority of nurses I know do not have the diagnostic capability and the groups representing GPs or consultants have been very reluctant to allow nurses the extra power to go beyond certain tasks, even though they are well capable of doing it.  I am just concerned that we will end up creating a row between the two professional bodies.  It is not very clear what exactly the role of the nurse will be.  Most of the medical assessors are assessing documentation that is sent in to say whether a person qualifies or does not qualify for payments.  I presume that is what it is if they are assessing for the Departments.  That suggests they have diagnostic skill.  If not, if it is just that a nurse will go through the documentation or be present when a person who is making a medical application presents to make sure they do not take ill, that is acceptable.  Could the Minister of State elaborate on how he sees this working?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00200"><p>We had a very long debate last year on this.  We have gone to the market and are constantly trying to recruit.  The Department is determined and committed to keeping the number of medical assessors at 25, but we are finding it increasingly difficult to fill those positions.  When there is a panel and we go to the panel to offer the position, it is not taken up.  There is a problem.  From last year we went out seeking agencies and we have not yet been able to fill the number of medical assessor posts we would like to have.  It is envisaged as a desk-bound assessment, so the assessor would not have clients coming in and would not be doing medical assessments on them.  That would still be the responsibility of a doctor.  I am sure the Deputy remembers, from last year, that the Department's deciding officer is the person who makes the determination on that.  It is envisaged that these would be occupational nurses, who would be suitably qualified and would act as a triage, similar to what happens in our emergency departments.  I hope that reassures the Deputy.  It is an effort to give a better and a quicker service to our clients, who are applying for their various entitlements.  It is an effort to improve the scheme and to allow flexibility within the Department by using suitably qualified people to give their opinion to the deciding officer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00300"><p>Deputy Ryan wants to say something.  There will be about five minutes and then we will have to suspend for about 25 minutes, to be safe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00400"><p>Give me a few minutes before I have to go into the House to see what I am going in for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00500"><p>Yes.  We will keep going until then, to get as much done as we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his explanation of the need.  Is he confident that nurses would have the competence to fulfil this role?  Within the medical assessor structure is there a senior medical assessor and would there be some level of supervision over this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00700"><p>In all cases, full training is given.  It is not about that.  It is an effort to give a better service.  While we have successfully reduced the time from application to payment, and the Department and officials must be thanked for this, this is necessary to ensure that backlog never occurs again when there are particular times of pressure.  The nurses would be used in the Department in an evidence-based medical protocol under the direct supervision of the chief medical officer and the deputy chief medical officer.  This is a real effort by the Department to respond to demands, because there is an increasing number of claims coming in.  We want to make sure they are dealt with in a speedy and efficient manner and to ensure that the time between a person applying and the person getting the benefit is kept to a minimum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00800"><p>To respond, obviously we want-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K00900"><p>I will just check something first.  The Topical Issue, I understand, is Topical Issue No. 2.  It will just extend it to 40 minutes if we stop early, so we will give it another 15 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01000"><p>If it is okay with the Chair, we can see the screen.  Once Topical Issue No. 1 starts, we will know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01100"><p>Yes, perhaps when we see it we will go back to the Minister for the second time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01200"><p>Dealing with backlogs and speed is important, but it is also important that the proper decisions are made.  We could decide that we are going to speed it up, but it might not be the right thing to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01300"><p>The intention is that it is dealt with in an efficient manner, but I reassure Deputy Ryan that in the first instance proper training will always be given and there will be proper supervision.  In all cases in this Department, there is a constant review of how things operate.  This will be a benefit.  The focus is on directly recruiting nurses with experience in the field of occupational health, or who are in possession of an occupational health qualification.  Many of the referrals are in that area.  No disrespect to doctors on that, but in some cases nurses working in that sector would be far more experienced than a GP in a particular service.  They will be recruited directly to the Department.  We are not operating through agencies, so they will be employees of the Department of Social Protection, with the proper supervision, training and supports required and with the ongoing review of case files, where there is a continuity of decisions.  In all cases, it is not the occupational nurse who will make the decision, it is the deciding officer, taking it from the opinion of the assessor, whether they are a medical doctor or an occupational nurse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01400"><p>On the face of this, there could be an application for a payment with a certificate from a doctor or GP that could be rejected by a nurse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01500"><p>The nurse would not reject it.  The deciding officer makes the decision where the occupational nurse or medical assessor, as it is at the moment, gives an opinion to the deciding officer.  Not on all occasions-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01600"><p>It would be on the direction of the nurse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01700"><p>-----is the medical assessor's opinion accepted.  In some cases, it is overruled by the officer in the customer's benefit.  In all cases the medical assessor's recommendation to pay is accepted, but where there is a refusal to recommend it, the deciding officer is overruled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01800"><p>I have yet to come across that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#K01900"><p>There is quite a lot in this.  It was sprung on us.  I have not had a chance to talk to the representatives of the nursing organisation.  It is a step up.  Most occupational nurses are well capable.  It is the same argument in terms of midwives in hospital - they are not given the responsibility they deserve.  The Minister of State is right; most occupational nurses would be well capable of making decisions based on the documentation in front of them.  The problem is that I cannot see doctors being too happy about this.  They have been very protective about their role in the past, although not necessarily on this issue.  This might break it and it might be welcome in that way, but they have been very protective of their space, and the fact they are the ones making diagnoses.</p><p>The Minister of State is saying the deciding officer makes a judgment based on a medical diagnosis, which comes before a moral opinion, whereas nurses usually do not present medical opinions but rather they present it to a doctor who then makes the decision.  Often nurses spot things much more quickly than the doctor and, in that respect, this might work better.  The problem up to now is that the medical assessors seem to have been the people making the bad decisions.  If one notes the level of appeals overturned, many are in the medical area.  We must make sure that whatever new system comes in, we do not end up with more appeals that could be made on grounds such as only a nurse looked at an applicant's file and that the applicant wants a doctor look at it.  I am not saying that would be the case but some people will try to find a reason for the appeal to stand up.  I would not stand over that but that is the level at which we are.</p><p> In the past, I have encouraged people with whom I have dealt to get a consultant's letter because the consultant knows better than the GP.  The occupational nurse would probably know better than the GP but that is not to say the person involved would not kick up.  Has what is being proposed been broached with the Minister for Health?  Is the Department of Health happy with what is being proposed because it has implications in terms of what it has been trying to encourage, namely, to allow nurses to take on a greater role and to encourage doctors to allow pharmacies to take on a greater role?  That change has been very slow but this change is a major jump.</p><p> If appointed, a nurse will be taking on the role of a medical assessor.  Will nurses be paid the same amount as that set aside in the past for a medical assessor in the Department, if they are doing the same work or have to write up the same type of documentation as medical assessors, or will they be taken on at the rate of pay for an occupational nurse in the health service?  If it is at the higher rate, it would be welcomed by nurses and a flood of applications would be received but if is it at the lower rate, we might end up in the same position.  Having regard to the level of work and the level of stress medical assessors seems to be under, we might end up in a year's time with none applying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00200"><p>I appreciate what the Minister of State said about trying to recruit extra people to relieve the backlog and make the system more efficient but this is a fairly radical step.  I share some of the sentiments expressed by Deputies Ryan, &Oacute; Snodaigh and others.  The Minister of State said the deciding officer makes the ultimate decision but in the real world, the deciding officer almost invariably goes on the opinion of the medical assessor.  I have dealt with a number of cases where people who were obviously medically quite unfit and in very bad shape were turned down for invalidity pension, disability allowance or some other benefit based on the medical assessment.  I could not understand the decision or what the medical assessor was thinking.  One of the questions I have been regularly asked over the years is whether the people who make the decision are medically qualified.  I have said they are medically qualified, are employees of the Department of Social Protection and are doctors.  Now I will have to explain that the person who turned them down could have been a nurse.</p> <p>  As Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh said, there are definite problems here, judging by the number of successful appeals, where the initial medical assessment goes against the applicant and it is overturned on appeal.  The number is pretty scary.  The percentage of successful appeals in regard to medically based entitlements where the initial refusal was because the medical assessment was not sufficient is quite scary.  There should not be that many successful appeals in a properly functioning system.  Therefore, what is being proposed is quite a radical step.  I would be interested to know what consultations have taken place.  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh raises a very interesting question about the rate of payment, which I think will have a huge impact in how the system will operate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00300"><p>The Topical Issue Debate is taking place in the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00400"><p>There is another eight minutes before the next Topical Issue is taken.  The debate was late starting, so Deputy Catherine Byrne can speak.  We could dispose of this amendment before the Minister of State leaves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1029" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00500"><p>I have only one question on this amendment and I have listened to Deputies &Oacute; Snodaigh, O'Dea and others.  Who will make the final decision in a case?  The Minister of State said that this will speed up the process.  I agree with that because people have been left waiting too long.  In the past, we said that nurses did not get the recognition they deserved when dealing with the people who were making decisions, whether in an accident and emergency department or even in a surgery.  Thank God, that is changing.  The fear people would have is that a nurse, who has been brought up to speed and has read the file, would make a recommendation to the appeals officer, or the deciding officer, who then makes the decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00600"><p>We have covered a lot of ground.  Does the Minister of State want to respond as quickly as possible?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00700"><p>The Department of Public Expenditure and Reform will set the rate in regard to the salaries.  On the issue of appeals, I have discussed this matter with Deputy O'Dea on numerous occasions.  One of the reasons for the level of success in regard to appeals is that we allow additional information at every step of the way.  In other jurisdictions, that is not allowed; they only allow an appeal to be based on the information that was provided in the first instance.  If the Deputy wants us to go down that route, and I would fight him tooth and nail.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00800"><p>I never suggested that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L00900"><p>It would be totally wrong and that would be a great way to massage the numbers.  However, I am not into doing that.</p> <p>  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh raised a legitimate point, which was not a reflection on nurses.  Nurses are more than capable of doing this.  They operate in every area.  There have been preliminary discussions and during the suspension, I might be able to check this with the HSE but I am quite confident that the occupational nurses in that area are more than capable.  The deciding officer makes the final decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#L01000"><p>We will hold off on agreeing to the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.205" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.50 p.m. and resumed at 3.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#O00200"><p>We will resume in public session.  Did the Minister of State want to add anything further to the discussion on amendment No. 22?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#O00300"><p>No, other than the fact that it is anticipated there will be a core team of between five and ten nurses who will be employed by the Department to conduct triage and desk assessments and provide opinions for guidance to the Department's deciding officer to help determine entitlements in respect of various high-volume schemes.  There is not a backlog within the Department but we always have to plan and be prepared.</p><p>Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh asked about nurses and consultation.  The Department's chief medical officer met with the Office of the Chief Nursing Officer in the Department of Health.  There has been some discussion on this issue.</p><p> It may be my age group in many ways but the nurse looks at the nursing profession in a different manner.  The profession has changed so radically over the past decades in terms of training and experience.  It is a very high standard profession with a lot of hands-on experience.  I am not degrading general practitioners, but in many cases they would not have that.  I think nurses will be a real addition to the Department and will make it much more effective.  I welcome Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's comments on this.  It is actually quite a progressive move.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00200"><p>I was not trying to say it was not progressive.  I thank the Minister of State.  He is quite right that nurses' roles have changed although their everyday work may not have changed enough.  I was trying to make sure that if we go down this road, there will not be a hiccup.  There would be nothing worse than having a number of nurses lined up in a month or two to take up the position - for which I think they are eminently qualified as they have the hands-on experience - and then having a hiccup.  I want to ensure the nurses will play their full role.</p> <p>  I asked about remuneration because the text states "medical assessor".  I presume that role has been benchmarked at some stage.  If not, will a different layer be created on the basis that the nurses might not be seen as full medical assessors, keeping them on a lower rate?  Hopefully that can be clarified quite quickly as they should be on the full rate if they are doing the full job.  I hope they will be able to do that.</p> <p>  I remember for the domiciliary care allowance that there was a set of ailments that qualified and another set that required greater investigation within the Department.  There were two lists.  Thankfully, that is gone.  It was not always a medical assessor who made those judgments.  That is an easy enough role, but the role the nurses would have would be more intensive.  They would have a greater understanding of some of the ailments that come up and some of the restrictions, particularly if they are occupational therapists.  Some of the medical assessors in the past did not seem to get to grips with all of those issues.  I have seen people refused disability allowance when one look at them or at the original documentation would suggest they should have received it immediately.  At least some of the nurses will have some practice.</p> <p>  Is there a minimum level of practice or do they just have to be qualified?  Even with doctors, qualification is often not enough.  Maybe we should look at that in the future and require them to have some work experience before becoming medical assessors.  It is such an important role.  In past years it has caused quite a headache.  The assessments are made and sent on to the deciding officers, who invariably take what the medical assessor sends them because they are not qualified to make any judgment on it.  Then that decision is overturned.</p> <p>  Sometimes people do not have all the documentation supplied.  In the event that it is clear the documentation is not complete, a phone call to request this or that letter before making the final decision would save the Department a lot more money than some of the other schemes.  People can address that, which is what the review was to do.  Maybe the nurses with their hands-on experience would be able to have that approach as well.  If it is clear to them there is a problem, rather than making a decision they might encourage the Department to seek other documentation to back up what seems like an incomplete file.</p> <p>  I am not opposed to the section.  I am raising concerns that it was sprung on us and was not fully thought out.  If it is as I said, it might work and might help address the problem we have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00300"><p>Is it the case that the Department is considering nurses having a rule in adjudicating on some of the illnesses or medical issues that somebody might have?  Is that what we are discussing?  I imagine the Department gave a lot of thought to an initiative like that.  We could easily do nurses a disservice by assuming they might not be up to whatever task the Department envisages for them.  I am not quite sure I am happy with Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's line of argument.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00400"><p>In fairness to Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh, I do not think that is what he was saying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00500"><p>I do not understand, then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00600"><p>I have said all along that I think they are well capable of doing the work.  They have not been allowed do it because of demarcation within the medical professions.  It is the same with pharmacists.  This might be one of the steps forward.  I was just making sure that we do not have a clash in the future between the IMO and the Department.  If the IMO is happy with it, then work away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00700"><p>I can imagine the Department has looked into all the possibilities, difficulties and conflicts that might or might not arise and that it will avoid the situation Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh has described.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#P00800"><p>As I have just said, the chief medical officer has met with the Office of the Chief Nursing Officer in the Department of Health.  I thank Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh for the constructive manner in which he has given his opinions on this issue.  This is a movement towards a more holistic assessment of people, which is very important.  It is about putting a good, efficient service in place for our clients.  Suitable, qualified nurses certainly have a key role in this.</p> <p>  It must be made very clear that the medical assessor or qualified nurse in this role does not diagnose.  He or she does an assessment and gives an opinion but is not involved in the diagnostic element of it.  What comes to the assessors is the documentation, whether it is from a general practitioner, consultant, other medical practitioner or a counsellor.  It is an assessment on which they give an opinion.  The deciding officer makes the determination.  That has not changed.</p> <p>  Relevant experience, and I often think of occupational nurses, is what they will bring to the Department along with the life experience they have.  They will bring a whole new dimension to dealing with these cases.  It will be very much a holistic approach.  It is a progressive way.  I also take Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's point that when we bring in something new we have to make sure we put the supports, structures and mechanisms in place to make sure it will work as envisioned.  That is something the Department of Social Protection is very good at; it constantly reviews, checks and looks to make sure the job is being done exactly as it says on the tin.  I commend the Department in that regard.  When we came into office there was a backlog and an application was taking up to 26 weeks.</p><p>The times relating to those decisions are now down to 11 and 14 weeks.  I take Deputy Ryan's point that we must ensure that the determinations being made are correct.  We must ensure that we do not just speed up the process for the sake of doing so and see to it that good decisions are made within what I would regard as a realistic timeframe.  We have got there very quickly and we must ensure that this momentum is maintained.  Last year we had a long discussion on the use of agencies.  When we went to the market seeking qualified doctors, we found that there was a shortage.  In such circumstances, flexibility is required.  In fairness to everybody here, the debate has been very constructive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00200"><p>The amendment would simply broaden the base of opinion the Department would have at its disposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00300"><p>Yes.  I thank all of the members of the committee for their constructive engagement on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.219" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00500"><p>I move amendment No. 23:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Budgeting in relation to social welfare payments &ndash; amendment</b><br /><br /><b>20. </b>Section 290 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote><blockquote>(a) in subsection (1), by the insertion of &ldquo;, subject to subsection (3A),&rdquo; after &ldquo;paid&rdquo;,<br /><br />(b) in subsection (3), by the insertion of the following paragraph after paragraph (bc) (inserted by section 19 of the Social Welfare and Pensions Act 2012):<br /><br />&ldquo;(bd) a credit union within the meaning of the Credit Union Act 1997,&rdquo;,<blockquote>and</blockquote>(c) by the insertion of the following subsections after subsection (3):<blockquote>&ldquo;(3A) For the purposes of subsection (1), a payment to a credit union referred to in subsection (3)(bd) may be made&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in respect of a scheme that&mdash;<blockquote>(i) is approved by the Minister, and<br /><br />(ii) relates to a class or classes of borrowings from a credit union as may be prescribed,<br /><br />and</blockquote>(b) where the beneficiary concerned is a member of the credit union to which the payment is made under this section.</blockquote>(3B) Without prejudice to subsections (1) or (2), for the purposes of subsection (3A), the Minister may, in regulations made under this section, prescribe&mdash;<blockquote>(a) a class or classes of borrowings by a beneficiary from a credit union in respect of which payments under this section are to be made,<br /><br />(b) the maximum amount of such borrowings which shall not exceed &euro;2,000,<br /><br />(c) the interest rate charged in respect of such borrowings, the maximum amount of which shall not exceed 1 per cent for each month, and<br /><br />(d) the duration of the period for repayment, by the beneficiary concerned, of the borrowings.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote> <p>This amendment refers to micro credit, the availability of which has been welcomed in the House.  I am interested in hearing any contributions that Deputies wish to make on the subject. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00600"><p>A change was made to what became the Social Welfare Act 2012 which excluded credit unions from the household budgeting package.  I shall outline its effect on Travellers, in particular, who availed of the facility to pay for mobile homes through An Post using the Lough payment scheme, which relates to the Lough Credit Union.  I have argued with a number of Ministers about this matter and plus MABS and others have argued for the scheme's retention.  The anomaly was an inadvertent exclusion but once it was excluded, we had to ensure that it worked.  The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection introduced a pilot scheme last year, through the credit unions and MABS, to ensure the scheme worked.  I have been informed that the pilot scheme which dealt with micro budgeting and small loans worked quite well.  I hope such a scheme will continue into the future.  My amendment refers to the credit union.  I hope my proposal will benefit people who avail of the credit union movement, in particular those who have no other source of funding for major outlays such as upgrading a mobile home or making home improvements.  I want to ensure that people can have moneys for such outlays taken out of their payments with the agreement of the recipient and the credit union.  The credit union movement does not allow people to overextend their finances.  My amendment seeks to help people manage their payments.  MABS was set up to help people manage what little money that they have and ensure they pay their ESB bills, etc., which is why the household budgetary services was created.  Unfortunately, the 2012 Act excluded the credit union movement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00700"><p>We have received representations from the credit union movement specifically proposing such a change.  Naturally, I welcome the amendment.  We made approaches to the Minister about the matter and welcome this change.  Regulations are needed in order to bring the provision into effect.  When does the Minister of State envisage the regulations will be introduced?  Incidentally, section 290 of the principal Act also envisaged the making of regulations.  When were the regulations referred to in that section in place?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00800"><p>First, I shall reply to Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh.  To be truthful and honest, when the Deputy raised this matter on Second Stage, I was unaware of the Lough payment scheme and misunderstood him.  While the personal microfinance scheme may offer an alternative to those who remain in the Lough payment scheme, where their local credit unions are participating in the pilot, it may not provide a solution to all loans operated under that scheme.  The Department is prepared to allow the Lough payment scheme arrangements to continue on an administration basis until the remaining clients, who have transitioned to alternative methods, have discharged their current liabilities.  While the micro scheme may offer an alternative to that, its not particularly designed for the Lough payment scheme.</p> <p>  We hope to introduce regulations in respect of this matter as soon as possible.  I intend to have the pilot scheme operational by the end of this month in time for Christmas.  I thank the Citizens Information Board, the Money Advice and Budgeting Service, the Social Finance Foundation and the Society of St. Vincent de Paul for their assistance in designing the scheme.  I hope to roll out the pilot scheme by the end of the month to 30 credit unions in the first instance.  It will make an enormous difference to people who are paying up to 200% in interest.  The pilot scheme will operate well, especially as it works with the credit union movement.  I have met representatives of the credit union movement on numerous occasions and they are anxious to get the pilot scheme up and running.  Lessons will be learned from the pilot relating to the household budgeting scheme.</p> <p>  Regulations have been made in respect of the household budgeting scheme and are live at present but we need new regulations for microfinance.  I hope that the many people who avail of the services of the Money Advice and Budgeting Service will avail of the pilot scheme.  It is a game-changer and I hope it will allow people to move away, in the long-term, from paying extortionate interest rates and being enticed by individuals who knock on their doors offering roll-over loans, etc.  The initiative has received a good response.  It has been spearheaded by the Citizens Information Board, which has provided assistance and back-up.  The initiative has been universally welcomed.  As we said when we discussed nurses, the proof will be in the detail and that is why I am anxious that the pilot scheme be rolled out.  Let us learn any lessons from the pilot scheme and provide a proper microfinance system to people who have no access to borrowing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q00900"><p>When does the Minister of State intend to roll out the pilot scheme?  Did he say it would be rolled out at the end of the month?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q01000"><p>Yes, once the relevant regulations are in place.  That is the target date.  We need this amendment in order to use the household budgeting scheme and then introduce a regulation.  Our target is to keep pressing forward with the initiative, which has many moving parts.  Originally, I thought the initiative would be far simpler but, unfortunately, this is what happens in many situations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#Q01100"><p>I had hoped the scheme would cover the Lough scheme payments but it seems more limited.  Therefore, I again appeal to the Minister of State to include such payments because they are in the same vein.  I welcome the initiative but it is not as extensive as I had hoped.  The Lough payment scheme came about following agreement among a number of credit unions and it seemed to work well.  I met a number of Travellers who have benefited from the scheme.  They told me they never had a problem making repayments because they were facilitated in this regard by something similar to a direct debit.  As a result, their repayments were guaranteed.  Most of them previously had difficulties accessing funds other than by means of taking them from their savings.</p><p>They were unable to save sufficient money to buy a new mobile home or otherwise.  It was usually for a mobile home that they needed a loan.  They did not have a proper credit rating.  In some cases, they were transient because they were living in a mobile home, which meant the financial institutions would not accept their addresses even though the Department accepted them as they were in receipt of social welfare payments.  MABS and the credit unions worked with them.  As far as I know, in all the time it was operating - I think it was up to ten years, and unofficially in some cases - all of the debts were cleared.  They did not have to rely on the fact that the credit unions in these instances were the guarantors of the loan.  </p><p> The Department will be in existence long after us.  Will it examine the documentation produced at the time by the Northside Family Resource Centre and the National Traveller MABS group, which outlined the case?  It would be useful not only for Travellers in that more and more families are ending up homeless and without an address and they will face similar problems in the future as they do not have a permanent address.  Without a permanent address, they will find it difficult to access funding, whether for a car, a mobile home or something like that.  At least in this way, they would have some control because the money comes out of their payment and there is already a rule that money cannot be taken out which would leave people in absolute poverty.  The Department can also control that so people do not sign up to something they cannot afford.  Given the housing crisis, we should look at this as an urgent proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00200"><p>I thank Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh, who is quite correct in many ways.  Approximately 370 clients have transferred to alternative payment schemes.  Approximately 130 clients are still availing of the Lough scheme, as an administrated scheme.  The Deputy made some very good points in regard to the Traveller community and I would be happy to look at this again at some stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.229" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00400"><p>Amendment No. 24, in the name of Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh, has been ruled out of order as it involves a charge on the Exchequer.  The amendment seeks to provide that in recovering overpayments, the Department of Social Protection would ensure that a claimant's income would not fall below the relevant supplementary welfare allowance rate for the claimant or his or her family.  The amendment could have the effect of reducing the amount of money the Department could recover and thereby be a charge on the Exchequer.  It has been ruled out of order in accordance with Standing Order 156(3).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00500"><p>It is not a charge because the effect of the amendment is to reduce the amount, although it still has to be paid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00600"><p>It is a loss in income.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.233" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 24 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00700"><p>Amendment No. 25, in the name of Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh, has been ruled of out order in accordance with Standing Order 156(3).  It seeks to require the Minister to introduce statute of limitations to govern the recovery of historical repayments.  Overpayment amounts are recouped to the Social Insurance Fund.  If they were not recouped, this would be a charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.235" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 25 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00800"><p>I move amendment No. 26:</p><blockquote><b>26. </b>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Recouping Social Welfare payments from employer in wrongful dismissal cases</b><br /><br /><b>11. </b>Any employer who has had a finding made against them of unfair dismissal under the Unfair Dismissals Acts 1977 to 2007, shall reimburse the State the cost of the unfairly dismissed former employee&rsquo;s social welfare payments for the period of time between the date of the former employee&rsquo;s dismissal and the date on which the finding is made<br /><br />against the employer under the aforementioned Acts.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>This is something I put forward previously, although I do not know if the Minister of State has heard the argument for it.  This would be to the benefit of the State.  People who take cases to the Employment Appeals Tribunal must wait quite a long time before they are heard.  In the intervening period, some end up in receipt of a social welfare payment.  This amendment provides a mechanism to allow the Employment Appeals Tribunal to recoup the cost to the State of the social welfare payments from the employer in the event of the former employee winning a case.  Should an employer be found to have dismissed an employee unfairly, why should the State foot the Bill?  I cannot give the figures on the number of cases or the amount involved but in recent times, people were laid off without the rules of due process being complied with.  In some respects, this is a money making scheme for the Department because it would enable the Department to recoup what it has been forced to spend, whether on supplementary allowances or otherwise.  In the past, Ministers have said they will consider this proposal and that is the reason I keep tabling this amendment but they have never come back with a proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R00900"><p>I support the amendment, which is a very sensible.  As we are talking about money making schemes for the Department, will the Minister of State clarify a further point?  If a person on social welfare is claiming for an adult dependant and that dependent receives a prison sentence, what is the position of the person claiming the payment?  Does the adult dependant payment cease for the period of imprisonment of the dependent adult?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01000"><p>Is Deputy O'Dea suggesting that the person should continue to receive a payment in respect of the adult dependant?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01100"><p>No.  I am seeking clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01200"><p>I am sorry that nobody has come back to Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh on his proposal because we discussed it when we were looking at the amendments this morning.  In the first instance, this relates to legislation which should be dealt with by the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  However, there is merit in this amendment because the Department has done something similar in respect of accidents.  I do not propose to accept the Deputy's amendment but I will ask my officials to write to the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation asking him to consider it and for his views on the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01300"><p>I thank the Minister.  I will withdraw my amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.242" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01500"><p>Amendment No.  27, in the name of Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh, has been ruled out of order because it imposes a potential charge on the Exchequer as it proposes to increase payments.  Amendment No. 28, in the name of Deputy O'Dea, has been ruled of out order.  It proposes to delete section 4 of the Social Welfare and Pensions Act 2012 which provides for the application of the one-parent family payment for children depending on their age and the deletion of this section would have effect of restoring the one-parent family payment to its previous level, so it would be a charge on the Exchequer.  Amendment No. 29, in the name of Deputy O'Dea, proposes that the fuel allowance would be available for 32 weeks of the year, which would be an additional cost to the Exchequer and, therefore, has been ruled of order.  Amendment No. 30, in the name of Deputy O'Dea, proposes to increase the amount of profit per day which can be earned without having the day discounted as a day of employment and, therefore, not allowing the assistance to be claimed.  This would increase the number of days on which people can access particular benefits or assistance and it would be a charge on the Exchequer and, therefore, has been ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.244" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 27 to 30, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01650"><p>Amendments Nos. 31 to 33, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#R01700"><p>I move amendment No. 31:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;11. </b>The Minister shall, within 4 weeks of the passing of this Act, prepare and lay a report before the Houses of the Oireachtas, reviewing all expenditure reductions or the ceasing of payments in relation to the household benefits package, including the gas allowance, electricity allowance, telephone allowance since 2011, and setting out the options for restoring those payments to their previous levels.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I wish to withdraw amendment No. 31 and do not propose to move amendments Nos. 32 and 33, inclusive, as I wish to reconsider them.  I will resubmit them for Report Stage.</p><p>May I make a point on amendment No. 30?</p><p>I realise I am not entitled to discuss it because it represents a charge on the Exchequer.  However, it has been strongly represented to me that the regulation in this case is somewhat outdated.  Perhaps the Minister of State would review that.  We can discuss it privately sometime.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.248" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.249" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 32 and 33 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S00500"><p>I move amendment No. 34:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<div>&ldquo;PART 3<br /><br />PENSIONS OMBUDSMAN</div><b>Definition</b><br /><br /><b>21. </b>In this Part &ldquo;Principal Act&rdquo; means the Pensions Act 1990.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.251" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S00700"><p>I move amendment No. 35:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 126 of Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>22. </b>Section 126 of the Principal Act is amended, in subsection (1), by the insertion of the following definitions:<blockquote>&ldquo; &lsquo;Act of 1942&rsquo; means the Central Bank Act 1942;<br /><br />&lsquo;Act of 2004&rsquo; means the Central Bank and Financial Services Authority of Ireland Act 2004;<br /><br />&lsquo;Financial Services Ombudsman&rsquo; means the Financial Services Ombudsman referred to in section 57BJ of the Act of 1942 (inserted by section 16 of the Act of 2004);&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.253" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S00900"><p>I move amendment No. 36:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 128 of Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>23. </b>Section 128 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;(a) by the insertion of the following subsections after subsection (1):<blockquote>&ldquo;(1A) Without prejudice to subsection (1), the Minister may, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance, appoint a person who also holds the office of Financial Services Ombudsman to hold the office of the Pensions Ombudsman.<br /><br />(1B) An appointment referred to in subsection (1A) shall be made for a period that does not exceed the remaining period of appointment of the person concerned as Financial Services Ombudsman.&rdquo;,</blockquote>and<br /><br />(b) by the insertion of the following subsection after subsection (2):<blockquote>&ldquo;(3) In subsection (1B), &lsquo;remaining period&rsquo; means, in relation to an appointment of a person, the period commencing on the appointment of the person under this section and ending on the expiry of the period of the appointment of that person as Financial Services Ombudsman under section 57BJ of the Act of 1942.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.255" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S01100"><p>I move amendment No. 37:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 129 of Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>24. </b>Section 129 of the Principal Act is amended by the insertion of the following subsection after subsection (6):<blockquote>&ldquo;(7) Subsection (6) shall not apply to a person who holds the office of Financial Services Ombudsman, where that person is also appointed to be the Pensions Ombudsman pursuant to section 128(1A).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.257" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S01300"><p>I move amendment No. 38:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 130 of Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>25. </b>Section 130 of the Principal Act is amended by the insertion of the following subsection after subsection (2):<blockquote>&ldquo;(2A) Notwithstanding subsections (1) and (2), in a case where the person who holds the office of Financial Services Ombudsman is also appointed, pursuant to section 128(1A), to hold the office of Pensions Ombudsman&mdash;<blockquote>(a) subsection (1) shall not have effect in relation to remuneration, and<br /><br />(b) subsection (2) shall not have effect in relation to superannuation benefits.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.259" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S01500"><p>Amendments Nos. 39 and 40 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S01600"><p>I move amendment No. 39:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;11. </b>The Pensions Act 1990 is amended by inserting a new section 48A as follows:<blockquote>&ldquo;<b>48A. </b>A solvent firm shall not be allowed to close a defined benefit pension scheme except where the scheme has reached a minimum 90 per cent funding standard.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>We have had previous discussions about this topic, or at least we have had them with the senior Minister.  At the moment, in the case of a defined benefit pension scheme in operation in this country, the position is that the employer, regardless of how solvent, well-off or wealthy it is, can close down the scheme.  The employer is entitled, without any restriction whatsoever, to close it down to the detriment of the people who have been paying into it genuinely, sometimes for many years, with a legitimate expectation of a certain level of pension entitlement.</p><p>As I understand it, the position in the nearest jurisdiction, the United Kingdom, is that an employer is not legally entitled to close down such a scheme unless it brings it up to a 90% funding level.  The employer cannot close it down unless it is 90% funded so long as the employer is solvent.</p><p>Amendment No. 40 relates to the scenario whereby, because a scheme is in difficulty, the trustees make a decision to restrict entitlement under the scheme.  Again, it has been strongly represented to me that in many cases there are one or two categories of people who are sometimes unhappy with the decision taken by the trustees and they have no input.  In particular, I have deferred pensioners in mind.  They seem to have no input.  They have to take what they get.</p><p>I am suggesting there should be an independent appeal mechanism to which any group of pensioners adversely affected by the decision of the trustees could seek redress.  Everyone could have confidence in and appeal to such a mechanism on the basis that their rights are being severely restricted.  If an appeal system was in place, it might well lead to a rejigging of what has been done by the trustees.  I can think of cases where such changes would be applied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S01700"><p>I support the amendments.  The 90% figure has been suggested by the OECD in cases where there are healthy employers or those with positive net revenue.  This is to ensure employers are not chancing their arms, as they have done in the past, to avoid future liability or what they perceive as future liability.  The view of many employers is that a defined benefit scheme is more onerous than a defined contribution scheme.</p> <p>  We made the argument three years ago or more in respect of some of the major schemes under threat.  Legislation was produced which had a different scheme depending on who the beneficiaries were and whether a scheme was under threat or being wound down.  At the time there were more than 200 defined benefit schemes.  I understand there has been a substantial reduction in the number since then.  We are trying to ensure in the remaining cases that at the least the right decision is being made.  The idea is that a profitable company, whether it is profitable here or abroad or part of a group of companies, makes a suitable contribution and that the workers, pensioners and deferred pensioners are protected and can access what they have paid into the schemes.</p> <p>  The proposals in these two amendments are reasonable.  We have made the arguments before.  At the time, they were not accepted.  However, I hope things have settled down to the point where they would be accepted as reasonable and within the spirit of what our pension system should be doing to protect those who have, in many cases, paid into a scheme.  This would ensure those people would not be as much of a burden on the State pension regime.  In some cases the schemes are the only source of pension for these people, but if they do not get their full entitlement, they will become a burden on the State.  In some ways, this is a protection for ourselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#S01800"><p>As Deputy O'Dea has said, these arguments have been thrashed out with the T&aacute;naiste on many occasions by himself and Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh.  In many ways, I am giving information that the T&aacute;naiste has conveyed to them on several occasions.</p> <p>  Defined benefit schemes in Ireland are set up and maintained by employers on a voluntary basis.  There has never been a statutory obligation on employers under Irish law to contribute to pension schemes.</p> <p>  The Deputies referred to the wind-up of schemes.  The decision to wind up a defined benefit pension scheme does not rest with the sponsoring employer.  It is a matter for the trustees of the pension scheme.  The Deputies referred to that in their contributions.</p> <p>  I will go through the positives and negatives again if Deputies so wish.  However, I am not prepared to accept the amendments at this stage.  Although we are experiencing an improvement in our economic performance, the imposition of a significant additional cost on employers at this point may have a counter-productive impact with regard to the feasibility of the businesses and the jobs of those employed, given that many employers would lack the capacity to absorb the extra costs and the proposed changes could trigger the closure of schemes.</p> <p>  Given the uncertainty in respect of the overall impact and the potential for unintended consequences, legislative or otherwise, in applying debt on employers it is not proposed to make changes of this nature.  The regime is considered as a package of measures that the Minister for Social Protection has introduced in recent years.  The idea is to take an approach that can nurse and support schemes to move gradually to a more sustainable funding position.  The Pensions Authority is working with and supporting schemes to achieve a more sustainable funding position.</p> <p>  The funding standard is the key instrument in monitoring the health of a pension scheme.  The authority is paying particular attention to those schemes with weak funding positions.  The standard was in abeyance from the end of 2008 until it was restored in June 2012.  The reintroduction of the funding standard was to provide a clear view of the funding position of schemes.  It will facilitate the restoration of scheme funding levels.  In advance of the reintroduction of the funding standards the Minister introduced legislation to require pension schemes to obtain additional funding in the form of risk reserve to protect scheme members against further volatility in the financial market.</p> <p>  The objective in the short term is to support weaker schemes and enable them to get to a more sustainable funding position.  In the medium term, the objective is to support all schemes to meet the requirements of the funding standard.</p><p>If arguments and disagreements cannot be resolved regarding the trustees or some other matter, they can resort to the courts.  There are court proceedings over some schemes.  I was in a defined benefit pension scheme because, unusually in this House, I have worked most of my life in the private sector.  For private sector employees, it is always a concern.  There would be unintentional consequences, however, if we accepted these proposals.  They would have to be carefully studied before we go down that road.  It is not my intention to accept these amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00200"><p>The Minister referred to unintended consequences.  The only intended consequence of my amendments is to protect employees, who like the Minister himself, have been making bona fide payments into a pension scheme with a legitimate expectation that they will get a certain amount out after the sacrifices they have made over the years to pay in.  The moneys could have been used for other purposes, obviously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00300"><p>As the Deputy probably knows, in some defined benefit schemes, one does not make a contribution as it is included in one's package.  That was the norm in many of the defined benefit schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00400"><p>I understand that.  Again, the Department has made the point that it is the trustees who decide on closing down a defined benefit scheme, not the sponsor.  In the real world, however, they do so at the behest of the employer or the company.</p> <p>  I am not suggesting we should have a rule whereby the employer has to come up to 90% of funding if that is going to cause job losses, force the company to close down or restrict its activities.  There is no statutory obligation on employers to provide defined benefit pension schemes.  Nevertheless, when they do set them up, certain consequences follow.  Some years ago in the UK, a rule was introduced that a solvent employer, one who could well afford it, had to come up with 90% of the pension fund before they could close it down.  That was eventually accepted in the UK.  It has not caused, to my knowledge, any major industrial outfall, job losses or collapses because it is confined to those who can well afford to have the schemes at 90% paid up if they want to close them down.</p> <p>  I will not press the amendments but I am putting the Minister of State on notice that I will resubmit them for Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00500"><p>I accept the Deputy&rsquo;s good intentions and that he is not trying to undermine the viability of businesses.  However, while there has been an improvement in the economy, we have to be careful that there are not unintentional consequences by accepting proposals such as this.  That is why I would be cautious on this matter.  The last thing we want to do is put companies in a more difficult position by increasing their liability for pension schemes which, in turn, could result in job losses.</p> <p>  The pensions area is the next big challenge for the State.  We need to move slowly on it to ensure we get it correct because it will have an impact on the economy for many decades.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00600"><p>A category of pensioners, such as deferred pensioners, could be adversely affected by a decision of the trustees to change the terms of a scheme.  However, they have no input into that decision which seems grossly unfair.  The Minister of State said that if they are unhappy, they can take a case to the courts.  There is an old saying, "The courts are open to everybody and so is the Ritz Hotel".  Going to court in this country - I could go on about the legal profession of which I am a member - is ruinously expensive.</p> <p>  My proposal is an independent appeals mechanism which will not cost an arm or a leg or substantially further deplete a fund.  Will the Minister confirm if people have a right in a situation like this to appeal to the Pensions Authority?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00700"><p>On the question of the trustees and deferred pensioners, earlier this year the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection approved measures to facilitate engagement between the trustees of pensions schemes and groups representing the interests of pensioners and deferred scheme members by signing the Occupational Pension Schemes (Sections 50 and 50B) (Amendment) Regulations 2015 and the approved Pensions Authority guidelines to facilitate this change.  I hope this might be helpful to the Deputy for Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00800"><p>I accept that and thank the Minister of State.</p> <p>  Again, on the appeals system, if somebody is dissatisfied, even after engagement with the trustees, do they have to go to court?  Is there a facility to allow an appeal to the Pensions Authority?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T00900"><p>That is the ultimate sanction.  I will come back later with the precise details for the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.273" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1059" speakername="Willie O'Dea" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T01100"><p>I move amendment No. 40:</p><blockquote>In page 9, after line 22, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;11. </b>The Pensions Act 1990 is amended by inserting a new section 48A as follows:<blockquote>&ldquo;<b>48A. </b>An appeals mechanism for pension scheme members shall be put in place where trustees have decided upon reduced benefits for members, and such appeals mechanism shall ensure that any category of such pension scheme members have not been unfairly treated in any restructuring arrangement.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.275" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.276" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Schedules 1 and 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.277" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>TITLE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T01500"><p>I move amendment No. 41:</p><blockquote>In page 3, line 5, after &ldquo;Acts;&rdquo; to insert the following:&ldquo;to amend and extend the Pensions Act 1990 to provide for the appointment, as Pensions Ombudsman, of the person who also holds the Office of Financial Services Ombudsman;&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.279" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.280" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Title, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T01800"><p>I thank the Chairman for facilitating the interruption earlier to allow me take a Topical Issue matter in the D&aacute;il.  I also thank the staff from the Department of Social Protection and the committee staff who have helped with the smooth running of today&rsquo;s meeting.  Above all, I thank the members who have helped and engaged in a constructive manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.282" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.283" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T02000">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED22015111100002#T02100"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Sub-Committee on Social Protection has completed its consideration of the Social Welfare Bill 2015 and has made amendments thereto.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.285" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The select sub-committee adjourned at 4.10 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.286" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" url="">Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht: Select Sub-Committee on the Environment, Community and Local Government</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.287" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 19:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Paudie Coffey (Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government), Deputy Maureen O'Sullivan,* Deputy Joe Costello,* Deputy Brian Stanley. Deputy Robert Dowds, Deputy Tony McLoughlin,</p><p>* In the absence of Deputies Michael McCarthy and Catherine Murphy, respectively.</p><p>DEPUTY NOEL COONAN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.288" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C00100">Dublin Docklands Development Authority (Dissolution) Bill 2015: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C00200"><p>As we have a quorum of three Teachta&iacute; D&aacute;la, we will commence the meeting.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  Apologies have been received from the Chairman of the select sub-committee, Deputy Michael McCarthy.  I remind members to turn off their mobile phones as they can interfere with the sound system, make it difficult for the parliamentary reporters to report the meeting and adversely affect television coverage and web streaming.  I remind members that this meeting will be conducted in public session.  The meeting has been convened for the purpose of the consideration by the select sub-committee of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority (Dissolution) Bill 2015.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  This Bill was referred by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann to the Select Sub-Committee on the Environment, Community and Local Government on 8 October 2015.  The aim of the Bill is to dissolve the Dublin Docklands Development Authority, to provide for the transfer of certain rights and functions to Dublin City Council as a consequence of the dissolution, to establish the docklands consultative forum, to provide for planning and development matters in the Dublin docklands area and to provide for related matters.  The Bill contains five Parts and 44 sections.  There are 22 amendments proposed.</p> <p>  I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government with special responsibility for housing, planning and co-ordination of the Construction 2020 strategy, Deputy Paudie Coffey, and his officials to this evening's meeting.  I thank the officials for their attendance and remind them that they should not speak at this meeting, as only the Minister of State should speak.  It is proposed to group the following amendments for the purposes of debate: Nos. 1a, 2 to 4, inclusive, and 4a; Nos. 6 to 12, inclusive; and Nos. 13 to 19, inclusive.  Amendments Nos. 5 and 20 have been ruled out of order.  All other amendments that are not grouped will be discussed individually.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.290" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.291" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C00500"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 7, to delete lines 14 and 15 and substitute the following:&quot;(3) Every regulation made by the Minister under this Act shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made and, if a resolution annulling the regulation is passed by either such House within the next 21 days on which that House sits after the regulation is laid before it, the regulation shall be annulled accordingly, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.&quot;.</blockquote> <p>This technical amendment, which proposes to replace section 3(3) of the Bill, expands on the original wording, which required the Minister to lay every regulation before the Houses of the Oireachtas &quot;as soon as may be after it is made&quot;.  This amendment seeks to elaborate on this requirement by allowing for the annulment of any such regulations if they are voted down in either House by special resolution during the following 21 sitting days of the House after they are laid.  While this is an unlikely scenario in most circumstances, nonetheless it is prudent to make provision for such an eventuality.  I am proposing the amendment on that basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.293" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.294" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.295" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Sections 4 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.296" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01000"><p>As amendments Nos. 1a, 2 to 4, inclusive, and 4a are related, they may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1011" speakername="Robert Dowds" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01100"><p>I move amendment No. 1a:</p><blockquote>In page 8, between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:&quot;(3) An agreed statutory instrument, following consultation and negotiation with the existing boards be enacted in order to clarify the future structures and roles of the Docklands Housing Trust and the Docklands Community Trust.&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01200"><p>Is amendment No. 2, in my name, being taken now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01300"><p>We are discussing all the amendments together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01500"><p>We have moved on to amendments Nos. 1a, 2 to 4, inclusive, and 4a.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01600"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1011" speakername="Robert Dowds" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01700"><p>When are we going to discuss those amendments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01800"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C01900"><p>Amendment No. 1 has been agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C02000"><p>We are discussing the next group of amendments, including Deputy Stanley's amendment No. 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C02100"><p>We have done amendment No. 1.  I suppose amendment No. 2, in my name, is self-explanatory because it proposes that "following the dissolution of the Authority and after all its liabilities have been met and subject to there being a surplus remaining the Council shall establish a central fund to be used for social gain for the benefit of the local community to be administered in conjunction with the Docklands Community Trust".  I want to amend the Bill in this way to ensure any benefit arising from a surplus goes to the local community and to local businesses.  This will ensure they benefit to the maximum degree and the area benefits to the maximum degree.  We need to ensure the money is targeted specifically into those communities where there are many issues to be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#C02200"><p>I would like to speak in support of amendment No. 3, which proposes that "future master plans shall be developed for the area in its entirety".  The initial master plan recognised the need for the hinterland to be included.  This bloc was also recognised by Dublin City Council in the city development plan.  However, it now appears that anything outside the strategic development zone will be excluded.  That will rule out certain traditional dockland communities, many of which are on the north side but some of which are on the south side of the river.  This is having an effect on statistics.  One statistic showed that 80% of the residents in the built dockland area, if I can call it that, have third level education.  I do not believe that is indicative of the wider docklands community.  A similar point can be made with regard to property ownership.  Many people in the new areas own several apartments for renting.  It is a transient population as well.  The Government makes decisions on the basis of statistics.  The point I am making is that unless the hinterland of the docklands is included, the statistics will overwhelm the reality of the case to be made on behalf of the people who live in that hinterland.  There are different types of communities in the wider docklands area.  I am from one of the communities in question and I have family members in one of the other communities.  People in gated communities are not engaging for various reasons, perhaps because they are single people or couples that have not started families.  I suggest that these gated areas are very much out of sync with the overall dockland community.  I wonder whether the hinterland is being excluded because it would be an obstacle to foreign direct investment if it were included.  I do not see the rationale for excluding some of the communities that comprise the docklands.</p> <p>  Some of these amendments seek to deal with a point that has been made with regard to local employment.  I do not think it is too much to ask.  We are talking about areas of very high unemployment.  Deputy Costello and I are members of the Grangegorman Development Agency, which imposes a local employment clause.</p><p>When we come to the meeting each of the contractors gives us a percentage for how many are employed from the local population.  This is done through the local employment service, LES, centres.  This is very important in getting people into employment in areas where employment is not readily available.  There is a lot of work being done by youth projects which support young lads in doing things such as taking the manual handling course.  We would like to see an employment clause inserted to encourage employers to do this.  We are not asking anyone to take on somebody who is not qualified to do a job, but where there are local people who are qualified, there should be positive discrimination.</p><p> There is no mention anywhere of a community gain.  Under the old master plan of the DDDA, there was mention of a community gain which included a social regeneration programme involving intervention in the school, with classes in music and drama.  Training was involved and there were opportunities for educational advancement.  There was a senior citizens forum and other specific services were provided from the community fund.  Dockland conferences were held every year.  Communities would very much like to see such things as part of the new plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#D00200"><p>I echo some of the points made by both Deputies on amendments Nos. 1 to 4<i>a</i>which include our own.  I presume all of the liabilities will be taken on by the local authority when the Dublin Docklands Development Authority is wound up.  Let us hope there will not be much in the way of liabilities and that the authority will have a surplus in order that, when it is dissolved and the functions are transferred to Dublin City Council, a sizeable fund will also be transferred and that this will be a community gain.  This money should go to the docklands community trust to continue the good work being done.  There was always a community dividend which generated some good activities in local communities, particularly for the elderly.  It is to be hoped this will continue as an integral part of the new entity that will operate under Dublin City Council.</p><p>We are looking for 10% growth in both social and affordable housing.  In the master plan of the old dispensation, under the Dublin Docklands Development Authority, there was provision for a figure of 20%, but this commitment was never delivered on.  Only 52 units of accommodation were provided from 1997, despite the fact that 300 units were supposed to have been provided on the North Wall.  Even with a figure of 10%, we will not reach the amount which was supposed to have been provided by now.  We should up the ratio, but I hope we have cast iron guarantees in the new legislation that a figure of 10% will be achieved and that this will be overseen strictly to ensure it is.  </p><p>A 20% local labour clause would be very desirable.  As Deputy Maureen O'Sullivan said, this was part of the Grangegorman dispensation and, while it is not included in the legislation, it is included in the strategic development zone, SDZ.  There is goodwill from all quarters for this to happen in the development in the docklands.  Will the Minister use his good offices to ensure the provision is replicated in the docklands development?  That was the principle articulated in the master plan, but it was not delivered on.  Workers from outside were parachuted into the area under the pretence that they actually dwelt in the area and local people did not get the jobs inherent in the master plan for the old SDZ.  We cannot allow that to happen again because it will mean that, while we will have economic regeneration, we will not have social regeneration.  </p><p>These are very important areas and there is not much sense in continuing the current situation where the least affluent part of the country lies, cheek by jowl, with the most affluent part.  There is a lot of anti-social behaviour and there are drugs problems and difficulties with employment, apprenticeships and so on.  We need strong guarantees that, this time around, the massive development and investment that is to take place in the SDZ will deliver the goods.  We are representatives of that area and have seen what has and has not happened over an extended period of many decades when local communities lost out.  That cannot happen this time around, which is why these motions are extremely important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1011" speakername="Robert Dowds" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#D00300"><p>I will speak to amendments Nos. 1<i>a</i>and 4<i>a</i>in my name.  I support what the previous speaker said and thank the Minister of State, Deputy Paudie Coffey, for the significant conversation he has had with me and Deputy Joe Costello.  It is very important that the docklands be a vibrant area.  We need to get back to what the Victorians, of all people, believed, that it was important for people to live close to where they worked.  That is an important element of the provision of social housing.  We would like to see affordable housing, but I understand there is a problem in that regard.  We would also like to see a 20% local employment rate, or even higher, because the more people can live close to their places of work the better.  As members know, it is very difficult to move around the greater Dublin area; it took several hours for some Deputies to get to this building this morning.  I hope the spirit of the amendments will be taken on board.  I will be interested to hear the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#D00400"><p>The amendments cover many wide-ranging issues relating to the Dublin Docklands Development Authority (Dissolution) Bill.  I have a detailed and substantial answer which I need to read to address the concerns the Deputies have raised.  I ask them to bear with me as it is long and detailed, but it is important to read it to provide the necessary clarification.</p><p>I do not propose to accept the amendments which I will discuss together as they touch on similar themes.  Proposed amendment No. 1<i>a</i>suggests clarification of the future structures and roles of the docklands housing trust and the docklands community trust.  The docklands community housing trust owns 72 social housing units which it manages for the use of the residents within the docklands area.  The trust will continue to operate as before with the assistance and collaboration of the housing and docklands units within Dublin City Council.  The trust has contributed greatly, in its current guise, to meeting the social housing needs of residents of the docklands since its inception.  During the years the docklands community trust has managed funds allocated to it by the authority to the betterment of residents of the docklands.  The trust benefits the docklands community in a number of ways such as by providing assistance for residents in pursuing educational opportunities.  Both trusts have fulfilled their functions and roles admirably during the years.</p><p>The trusts mentioned were not established under the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997 and are legal entities in their own right.  As such, they are outside the scope of the Bill.  Article 10 of the memorandum and articles of association of the trust provides that they can be altered with the written approval of the authority.</p><p>In circumstances where the authority ceases to exist, it is replaced by its successor, which in this case is Dublin City Council.  The authority is currently engaging with the boards of the trusts on the governance requirements post-dissolution.  Therefore, it is not deemed possible to accept this amendment.</p><p> On amendment No. 2, the DDDA has over the years contributed to a community fund, administered by the Docklands Community Trust, to the benefit of the local community in conjunction with the Docklands Community Council.  That fund has now accumulated assets of &euro;1.3 million which uses the interest earned to assist and enhance the lives of local docklands residents, primarily through providing grants for local school leavers to pursue third level educational courses.</p><p> In seeking to dissolve the authority and transfer responsibilities to Dublin City Council, the Government was anxious that no additional financial burden would be placed on the taxpayer.  By means of a prudent transition plan, devised by the authority and the city council&rsquo;s docklands unit, an orderly wind-down of the authority has been ongoing.  This wind-down has sought to generate sufficient funds from the sale of the authority&rsquo;s residual assets to discharge all its liabilities at dissolution.  Given the ongoing nature of some aspects of the authority&rsquo;s business, the final financial picture will not become fully apparent until all liabilities are finalised and discharged, when the dissolution comes into effect.</p><p> During the Second Stage debate, a commitment was given to the House that the authority would make a substantial contribution to the community on its dissolution.  This commitment remains in place and the level of contribution will be decided in light of the financial circumstance of the authority on dissolution.  However, I can assure Deputies that it will be substantial and will enable the Docklands Community Trust and Dublin City Council's docklands unit to continue to support local community and educational initiatives.  That is to be welcomed.  For these reasons, I do not propose to accept amendment No. 2.</p><p> I am also opposing amendment No. 4 for the following reasons, and I propose to respond to each element (a) to (c) of amendment No. 4 in turn.  In respect of part (a), concerning the social housing element, it is already required, as part of the granting of planning permission for residential development within the SDZ area, that the social housing requirement of each development shall be provided in line with current national housing policy.  In this regard, current national housing policy requires the provision of 10% social housing, as introduced by the Urban Regeneration and Housing Act 2015 earlier this year.</p><p> An independent review of Part V of the 2000 Planning and Development Act regarding social and affordable housing was carried out prior to the initiation of the Urban Regeneration and Housing Bill.  This review, which included a public consultation process, identified that the provision of social housing through Part V should be retained.  The review also recommended that the overall requirement should be up to 10% of units in residential developments.  This requirement copperfastens the original objective of Part V in legislation, namely, the delivery of social housing, combined with integrated and sustainable mixed-tenure communities across the country.</p><p> The reduction in the requirement from 20% to 10%, as introduced by the Urban Regeneration and Housing Act 2015, should be considered together with other amendments introduced by the same Act which have reduced the alternatives to the delivery of units within a Part V agreement.  For example, the options of payment of cash in lieu of units or the transfer of sites or parts of sites have been removed and, instead, the remaining options are focused on the delivery of completed units.  In addition, under these new Part V provisions, it is the intention that all local authorities, including Dublin City Council, in their Part V negotiations, will seek for developers to fulfil their Part V obligations entirely by social housing.</p><p> Affordable housing provision shall not be agreed to by planning authorities until further notice.  That is something which both the Minister, Deputy Kelly, and I will keep under review.  We note that it is a very important tier of housing which should be made available to citizens.  We will be making further announcements on it in the future.  The effect will be that Part V agreements will in future deliver more social housing units than were realised before when the 20% social and affordable requirement was in place.  For the reasons set out above, I am opposing the first element, part (a) of amendment No. 4.</p><p> With regard to part (b) of amendment No. 4, concerning local employment, there are many objectives within the North Lotts and Grand Canal Dock SDZ that already address this issue.  For example, objective ER11 of the SDZ planning scheme 2014 requires Dublin City Council to liaise with agencies and organisations to maximise employment and training opportunities for docklands residents.  This process has already commenced, with Dublin City Council&rsquo;s docklands unit working with developers and the local employment services in the area to maximise new employment opportunities, both in construction and also with new employers in the area.  The rate of employment through the local employment services will be monitored and reported to the Docklands Community Council and its successor within the city council, the docklands consultative forum.</p><p> In addition, objective ER10 requires Dublin City Council to facilitate and harness the employment-generating opportunities of the support services sector as well as enterprise activity with a range of key skilled, semi-skilled, unskilled and volunteer workers of all ages, as part of the overall economic regeneration for the wider docklands area.  Further to that, objective ER12 requires the city council to facilitate agencies and organisations, in particular those engaged in employment and training initiatives in the docklands, to work together in a co-ordinated manner in order to maximise employment, volunteer and training opportunities for residents of all ages in the docklands area.</p><p> Objective CD10 requires Dublin City Council to promote a docklands local employment steering group with relevant stakeholders to facilitate an employment strategy promoting enhanced local employment access with a specific regard for younger and older people.  Objective CD12 requires the city council to provide commercial facilities, such as local supermarkets, restaurants, caf&eacute;s and leisure facilities, that provide opportunities for local employment and locations for the community to interact, meet and socialise, so as to assist community development.  Having regard to the comprehensive supports already provided for in the SDZ planning scheme for local training and employment, the implementation of which will be monitored and reported to the docklands consultative forum, I am opposing element (b) of amendment No. 4.</p><p> Finally, in response to the third element, part (c) of amendment No. 4, concerning a contribution scheme for community gain, Deputies should be aware that chapter 4.3 of the SDZ planning scheme addresses community development and community gain, wherein it is acknowledged, at section 4.3.1, that the regeneration of the docklands is a project about people, not just physical and economic regeneration.  With specific reference to community infrastructure and gain, the SDZ planning scheme confirms at section 4.3.4.2 that, as infrastructure is developed and regeneration advances to tackle the remaining brownfield sites, it will be a core requirement that opportunities for community infrastructure and gain are maximised through the design of buildings, the public realm that is provided and land uses that are proposed.</p><p> Dublin City Council has confirmed to my Department that its current development levies scheme requires all new developments to pay &euro;34.50 per square metre for residential development and around &euro;28 per square metre of commercial development to the city council.  Of these amounts, &euro;4.60 and &euro;3.75 respectively are dedicated and earmarked to funding community facilities and amenities.  Dublin City Council&rsquo;s development levies scheme is currently being revised with the final version to be adopted by the council next month and, according to the council, the percentage dedicated to community uses is proposed to increase from 14.6% to 17.16% next year.</p><p> The docklands SDZ area is subject to the same levies as the rest of the city.  What is perhaps more relevant here is that the benefits of the city council&rsquo;s development levies will apply to all areas of the docklands, not just inside the SDZ area of the North Lotts and Grand Canal quarter but across the more established community facilities in the wider docklands area.  Investment in upgrading community facilities from levies across the docklands will benefit new and upgraded community facilities and will serve both existing communities within docklands and new developments in the SDZ.  For the reasons set out above, I am opposing the third and final element (c) of amendment No. 4.</p><p> I am also opposing amendment No. 4a as, upon dissolution, there will no longer be a need for a master plan for the docklands area, with the key policies and objectives captured in the city development plan.</p><p>The role and function of a master plan under the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act are inextricably linked with the operational functions of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority, including, for example, the designation of areas where section 25 schemes would be appropriate.  When the DDDA is dissolved, there will be no statutory basis or need for a master plan.  </p><p> As a like for like replacement, the Dublin city development plan, as adopted by Dublin City Council, will be the planning policy document for the wider docklands area, in addition to the SDZ planning scheme 2014 which applies to the specified North Lotts and Grand Canal docks area.  In this regard, Deputies might note that the Dublin city development plan, 2016 to 2022, is being prepared by the city council and the draft version of the plan is on public display.  The draft development plan contains numerous policies and objectives relating to the social and economic regeneration of the Dublin docklands areas.  For example, policy SC8 proposes to recognise the distinctive character of the docklands regeneration area and work with the relevant authorities to increase connectivity with the city centre.  Similarly, section 15.1.1.6 of the draft plan states the docklands will be a strategic development and regeneration area and provide for the continued physical and social regeneration of this part of the city, consolidating the area as a vibrant economic, cultural and amenity quarter of the city, while also nurturing sustainable neighbourhoods and communities.  Section 15.1.1.7 of the draft plan, relating to the docklands areas' social and community development, provides numerous guiding principles relating to housing and employment, education and social engagement, economic performance and business promotion, the development of a maritime strategy, marketing, environment, movement and transport, land use, urban design and flood risk and the implementation of the various objectives and policies that are associated and which will apply to the future development of the docklands.</p><p> On the basis that the key objectives and measures previously covered by the master plan are now planned to be incorporated into the city development plan or are covered already by the SDZ planning scheme, there is no need for, or value in, having a separate master plan.  I, therefore, oppose amendment No. 3.</p><p> I have given a long and detailed response, but it addresses the concerns associated with the amendments.  There is a clear commitment that many of these concerns will be addressed in the new arrangements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#F00200"><p>I am disappointed that amendment No. 2 is not being accepted.  The Deputies from Dublin have outlined how the communities in question lost out owing to the fact that what was promised in earlier developments in the area was not delivered.  I will press amendment No. 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.317" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#F00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive response.  Regarding the reference to social housing, the changes that have taken place under the 2015 Act appear to tie down the 10% requirement in a manner it was not previously when it was lost under various guises.  That the Minister of State has indicated his openness to an affordable measure is promising.</p> <p>  Regarding the reference to 20% local employment clause, this must be strengthened to some degree.  It is operational in the Grangegorman development plan and there are regular reports.  Deputy Maureen O'Sullivan and I receive a monthly report on how the 20% local employment requirement is being met in order that we know where and in which company the employment is being provided.  While it might not be included in the existing legislation under which the Grangegorman Development Agency was established, it is included in the SDZ and likewise in the current plan.  We must ensure there is a structure in place to report in a manner whereby we can monitor it.  Obviously, the consultative forum is dealt with later in the Bill, but we must have something similar to what is in place for the Grangegorman development in order that we can be assured that what happened previously, when the companies that were employed and the developers simply bypassed the Dublin Docklands Development Authority and went on about their business, will not happen again and that there will be constant checks.  What can the Minister of State do to reassure us that there will be an adequate structure in place to deliver on the figure of 20% which all of the players agree should be in place?  If it is not a figure of 20% for direct labour, training places and apprenticeships should be built into it.</p> <p>  I take the point about there being a community gain, which I welcome.  With regard to the master plan, the docklands area was the first to have a master plan.  The idea was that owing to their nature the area would be developed with a master plan in order that there would be coherent development.  This should not be ruled out for the future, even though most of the elements appear to have been retained within the city council draft development plan, but we have yet to see whether that will be delivered in total.</p> <p>  I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive clarification.  Perhaps he might reassure me on the 20% local employment requirement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#F00400"><p>It was a comprehensive answer which provided much food for thought for community groups.  They can look at it and consider how to move forward.  </p> <p>  At a time when there is such a dire housing need, it is disappointing that there is a figure of just 10% for social housing rather than 20%.  Is it possible to ensure more family-friendly units will be built?  It is more lucrative for developers to build two-bedroom units, but we encounter families who need accommodation with three and four bedroom.</p> <p>  The Minister of State says there will be a substantial community gain, yet he does not wish to use the words "community gain" as suggested in the amendment.  That is surprising.  Is it playing with words?  I do not know, but it was good to hear what he had to say about what would be available to communities.</p> <p>  Regarding the SDZ, the Minister of State said he would be looking at all of the dockland communities in this area, yet he will not recognise that they should be part of what we are discussing.  </p> <p>  Deputy Joe Costello spoke about local employment.  We know that people living in the area felt very let down on the employment of young people from the area when the massive development was taking place in the past.  The few local people who were given the opportunity to move into employment, be it in financial services or otherwise, are still working there and doing very well.  There is a group of 18 to 21 year olds who cannot avail of the community employment scheme, but they would be ideal candidates for employment in this area, as well as training and apprenticeships.  The Minister of State does not wish to include it in the Bill, but is there some way of bringing it about in order that the community can be assured that this time it will not be left behind and that it will not be a case of "them and us"?</p> <p>  We have had meetings about the plan with Dublin City Council.  There are many positive items in the plan, but we would like all of it to be positive for local communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.319" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#F00500"><p>I thank the Deputies for the positive interaction we are having.  They are right to engage strongly because there is an opportunity to get this right.  I agree that we must learn from what happened in the past when there was potential but it was not delivered on for various reasons.</p><p>As for the Part V provisions on social housing, commitments might have been given, but they were either not delivered on or were delivered on almost like an afterthought, which is unacceptable.  There is now an opportunity to get this right.  The Urban Regeneration and Housing Act 2015 passed by the Oireachtas last July, on which there was good engagement at this committee, contains provisions to ensure housing units and homes will be delivered as part of the planning process.  A number of provisions are included in that legislation that protect the interests Deputy Joe Costello is quite rightly outlining.  First, through this Act, the Government has removed the cash-in-lieu provision which essentially gave developers the power to buy their way out of their social housing obligations.  I am told that if that cash-in-lieu provision had never been included from the outset, we would have approximately 10,000 more social housing units than is the case today, which is an interesting statistic.  While it is sad to a degree that a huge opportunity was lost, I am glad to state that in the aforementioned recently enacted legislation I have acted to remove the cash-in- lieu provision and indicated that units must be delivered.</p><p> On top of this, rather than having social housing being delivered as an afterthought or a lesser priority, as part of the planning process builders and developers or the proposers of projects will now be required to engage with the local authority and its housing section to agree on the type of housing to be provided.  This addresses the concerns of Deputy Maureen O'Sullivan who is correct, in that if there is a need for family units, that need must be addressed or if there is a need for single units, that need must be addressed.  The local authority is best placed to understand this because it is the housing authority.  There is an opportunity for the local authority for the first time in that in combining the housing and planning sections supply will be matched with demand.  Powers have been given to local authorities in the planning process before commencement to strengthen their negotiating hand.  This is a highly positive step forward which the Government will monitor closely to see how effectively it is working.  While it expects it to work, if it needs to be tweaked or strengthened in any way, I would be prepared to consider this.  However, the new system should be allowed to bed in and there is no doubt but that it will deliver more social housing units than has been the case heretofore.</p><p> In response to the good points made about employment opportunities for local workforces, I am not someone who believes in reinventing the wheel.  We must learn from past experiences and two Deputies present, namely, Deputies Joe Costello and Maureen O'Sullivan, have spoken about their experience of the Grangegorman strategic development zone, SDZ.  The Government should consider emulating the model operating in Grangegorman which, from what I hear, appears to be relatively successful.  It should ascertain how that experience can be emulated with the docklands authority and how some of its successful elements pertaining to local employment opportunities can be transferred into the new arrangements within Dublin City Council.  This is a possibility that should be considered and I certainly would be open to doing so.  That said, I do not believe there is a place in primary legislation for setting a 20% local employment requirement because, constitutionally or legally, it would be extremely hard to comply with it.  Nevertheless, my officials will take up the suggestion and ascertain how the positive experience in Grangegorman can be emulated in the Dublin docklands.</p><p> As for the consultative forum, I again take on board the Deputies' concerns.  It is important to have a level of transparency and oversight to ensure delivery.  I believe Deputy Joe Costello is concerned to ensure there will be adequate delivery on the social dividend and social provision side.  I am prepared to consider an amendment on Report Stage to ascertain how that transparency can be strengthened.  Perhaps there might be an obligation to submit the forum's annual report to the Minister who, in turn, would lay it before both Houses of the Oireachtas.  That could ensure a level of transparency and scrutiny by Oireachtas Members.  As the Vice Chairman is aware, when such a report was laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas, it would quite open to this committee, if its members wished to do so, to have it brought before it.  Moreover, it could invite to appear before it the officials and those responsible for report, as well as the Dublin docklands unit within Dublin City Council, as I can see no reason these officials could not be invited before the committee to scrutinise their work and progress in delivery.  That is an improvement I am willing to consider to take on board the concerns the Deputies have raised.  I believe I have addressed most of the concerns raised, but to be fair, the official response I gave from the scripted version was detailed, comprehensive and addressed the main concerns.  </p><p> With regard to amendment No. 2, I believe Deputy Brian Stanley indicated his intention to press the amendment.  I wish to try to address the issue to some degree for him, if possible.  He proposes that, following the dissolution of the authority and after all its liabilities have been met and subject to there being a surplus remaining, the council establish a central fund to be used for social gain for the benefit of the local community.  I believe I have already answered this suggestion to a degree.  While the wind-down is taking place - as all members are aware, there are ongoing liabilities - I cannot put a prescriptive figure on it.  However, I reiterate the point already made on Second Stage that it is expected there will be a substantial dividend.  The Government has stated quite clearly that it will go to the trust for the benefit of many of the projects and engagements from which people have benefited in the Dublin docklands area.  I cannot give a stronger commitment than that, except to state it has been given and that by using the mechanisms about which members of spoken, through the forum and the Dublin docklands unit, this dividend can be delivered successfully in order that it will reach those who require to benefit from it most and assist them in the most efficient way possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.321" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p><p>Section 7 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.322" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>SECTION 8</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.323" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#G00400"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 8, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:&ldquo;(4) Notwithstanding the generality of the foregoing, following the dissolution of the Authority and after all its liabilities have been met and subject to there being a surplus remaining the Council shall establish a central fund to be used for social gain for the benefit of the local community to be administered in conjunction with the Docklands Community Trust.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.324" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p><p>Section 8 agreed to.</p><p>Sections 9 to 15, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.325" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>SECTION 16</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.326" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#G00700"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:&ldquo;(5) Future master plans shall be developed for the area in its entirety and approved by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government in recognition of the importance of the Docklands area.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.327" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.328" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#G00900"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:&ldquo;(5) Future applications under Docklands Strategic Development Zone (SDZ) shall&mdash;<blockquote>(a) include a condition to provide for 20 per cent social housing,<br /><br />(b) include a condition to provide for local employment, and<br /><br />(c) include a condition to provide for a contribution scheme for community gain within the Docklands area.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.329" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.330" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 4a not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.331" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Section 16 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.332" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#G01300"><p>Amendment No. 5 has been ruled out of order because it involves a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.333" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 5 not moved.</p><p>Section 17 agreed to.</p><p>Sections 18 to 22, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.334" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>SECTION 23</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.335" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H00200"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 to 12, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.336" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H00300"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p><blockquote>In page 14, line 9, after &ldquo;time;&rdquo; to insert the following:&ldquo;and(iv) the developer can demonstrate previous compliance with fire safety regulations and can satisfy the Council that any outstanding issues in respect of fire safety or other planning regulations will be rectified;&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>The amendment is self explanatory.  It states that the developer must demonstrate previous compliance with fire safety regulations and can satisfy the council, in this case, Dublin City Council, that any outstanding issues in respect of fire safety or other planning regulations will be rectified.  We tabled the amendment because we believe it is important.  We saw what happened in the case of Longboat Quay, Priory Hall and other developments around the State.  It is important, in particular in the context of inner city multi-unit development complexes, that the previous record of developers is taken into consideration and that we cross all the t's and dot all the i's and ensure developers are compliant because we have had many difficulties dating back to the Celtic tiger years and we all agree that moving forward we do not wish to see a repeat of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.337" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H00400"><p>I call the Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, as his amendment No. 7 is related.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.338" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H00500"><p>First, in regard to amendment No. 6, we oppose the amendment.  I understand the concerns the Deputy has raised but they are not appropriate in legislation that is specifically about winding down an authority because clear and enforceable fire safety requirements are already set out appropriately in primary legislation, including in the Building Control Acts, the Fire Services Acts, the Planning and Development Acts and the Multi-Unit Developments Act.  Restatement of statutory obligations that already apply generally under existing law in new legislation prepared for a specific and limited purpose, such as this Bill, is unnecessary and serves no additional purpose.  In fact, depending on drafting and interpretation issues, a restatement may also inadvertently weaken the application and enforceability of existing requirements.</p> <p>  Furthermore, there are perhaps unforeseen and possibly unintended but potentially critical consequences arising from the proposed amendment.  For example, the inclusion of the wording "or other planning regulations" in the amendment would appear to have the effect of limiting the provision to planning-related fire safety requirements, such as road access for fire brigades and proximity to water mains hydrants, and, therefore, as a consequence, non-planning related issues, but more likely fire safety breaches, such as the construction not being in accordance with the fire safety certificates, defective fire compartmentalisation in buildings, fire stopping around building services, inadequate fire detection systems in building units and inadequate emergency access and evacuation provisions in buildings units, which we all agree are very important, would unfortunately be excluded if we were to accept the amendment.  For those reasons, I do not accept amendment No. 6.</p> <p>  Amendments Nos. 7 to 12 are Government amendments.  These six amendments are technical in nature and their collective purpose is to amend planning enforcement provisions in Part 8 of the Planning and Development Act 2000, so that they unambiguously apply to developments in respect of which a section 25 certificate has been issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority, or a section 12 certificate by the Custom House Docks Development Authority.  The amendments have been put forward following extensive engagement between officials in my Department and the Attorney General&rsquo;s office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.339" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H00600"><p>The Minister of State is of the view that the amendment we tabled could weaken existing legislation but I do not believe that is the case.  The intention of the amendment is very clear.  I will press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.340" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.341" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Section 23 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.342" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Sections 24 to 30, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.343" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.344" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H01100"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 14 and 15, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 154 of Act of 2000</b><br /><br /><b>31. </b>Section 154(5)(a) of the Act of 2000 is amended with effect from the dissolution day&mdash;(a) in subparagraph (i) by the deletion of &ldquo;or&rdquo; after &ldquo;as appropriate,&rdquo;,<br /><br />(b) in subparagraph (ii) by the insertion of &ldquo;or&rdquo; after &ldquo;is subject&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(c) by the insertion of the following subparagraph after subparagraph (ii)&mdash;<blockquote>&ldquo;(iii) in respect of a development in respect of which a certificate has been issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997 or by the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986, require that the development will proceed in conformity with the planning scheme made under those Acts in respect of which the development was certified to be consistent and any conditions to which the certificate is subject,&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.345" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.346" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Section 31 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.347" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.348" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H01500"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 157 of Act of 2000</b><br /><br /><b>32. </b>Section 157(4)(a) of the Act of 2000 is amended with effect from the dissolution day&mdash;(a) in subparagraph (i), by the substitution of &ldquo;development,&rdquo; for &ldquo;development;&rdquo;,<br /><br />(b) in subparagraph (ii), by the substitution of &ldquo;section 42,&rdquo; for &ldquo;section 42.&rdquo;, and<br /><br />(c) by the insertion of the following subparagraph after subparagraph (ii)&mdash;<blockquote>&ldquo;(iii) in respect of a development in respect of which a certificate has been issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997 or by the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986, after seven years beginning on the date the certificate ceases to have effect in accordance with <i>Part 4 </i>of the <i>Dublin Docklands Development Authority (Dissolution) Act 2015</i>.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.349" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.350" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H01700"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 160 of Act of 2000</b><br /><br /><b>33. </b>Section 160 of the Act of 2000 is amended with effect from the dissolution day&mdash;(a) by the substitution of the following paragraph for paragraph (c) of subsection (1):<br /><br />&ldquo;(c) that any development is carried out in conformity with&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in the case of a permission granted under this Act, the permission pertaining to that development or any condition to which the permission is subject, or<br /><br />(ii) in the case of a certificate issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997 or by the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986, the planning scheme made under those Acts to which the certificate relates and any conditions to which the certificate is subject.&rdquo;,<br /><br />and</blockquote>(b) in paragraph (a) of subsection (6)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in subparagraph (i), by the deletion of &ldquo;or&rdquo; after &ldquo;commencement of the development,&rdquo;,<br /><br />(ii) in subparagraph (ii), by the substitution of &ldquo;section 42, or&rdquo; for &ldquo;section 42.&rdquo;,<br /><br />and<br /><br />(iii) by the insertion of the following subparagraph after subparagraph (ii):<blockquote>&ldquo;(iii) in respect of a development in respect of which a certificate has been issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997 or by the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986, after the expiration of a period of 7 years beginning on the date the certificate ceases to have effect in accordance with <i>Part 4 </i>of the <i>Dublin Docklands Development Authority (Dissolution) Act 2015</i>.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.351" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.352" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H01900"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 162 of Act of 2000</b><br /><br /><b>34. </b>Section 162 of the Act of 2000 is amended with effect from the dissolution day by the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (1):&ldquo;(1) In any proceedings for an offence under this Act, the onus of proving the existence of&mdash;<blockquote>(a) any permission granted under Part III,<br /><br />(b) any certificate issued by the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986,<br /><br />or<br /><br />(c) any certificate issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997, shall be on the defendant.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.353" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.354" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H02100"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 163 of Act of 2000</b><br /><br /><b>35. </b>Section 163 of the Act of 2000 is amended with effect from the dissolution day by the substitution of &ldquo;(disregarding development for which there is in fact permission under Part III or in respect of which a certificate has been issued by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997 or by the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986)&rdquo; for &ldquo;(disregarding development for which there is in fact permission under Part III)&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.355" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.356" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H02300"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p><blockquote>In page 17, between lines 25 and 26, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of Act of 2000 &ndash; planning authority</b><br /><br /><b>36. </b>The Act of 2000 is amended with effect from the dissolution day by the insertion of the following section after section 164:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Development in Dublin Docklands Area </b><br /><br /><b>164A.</b>For the avoidance of doubt, Dublin City Council is the planning authority in respect of a development in respect of which a certificate has been issued by&mdash;(a) the Dublin Docklands Development Authority under section 25(7)(a)(ii) of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority Act 1997,<br /><br />or<br /><br />(b) the Custom House Docks Development Authority under section 12(6)(b) of the Urban Renewal Act 1986.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.357" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.358" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Section 32 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.359" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>SECTION 33</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.360" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H02700"><p>Amendments Nos. 13 to 19, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.361" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H02800"><p>I move amendment No. 13:</p><blockquote>In page 17, line 35, to delete &ldquo;may&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>The proposed amendment is a small one but it is very important.  The intention is that the forum shall consider and advise the council and the strategic policy committees of the council on the formulation, development, monitoring and review of the council's policy regarding the performance of its functions.  The word &quot;may&quot; is vague and from past experience, we know that anything that is vague tends to be ignored.</p><p>The same is true of amendment No. 14 on page 18.  The intention is to insert after the word &quot;employment&quot;, &quot;including community and social employment&quot;.  That is important because local community employment and social employment are very important to this area and I ask that the suggested wording would be inserted.</p><p>In amendment No. 15, we suggest replacing the word &quot;may&quot; with &quot;shall&quot; on line 10, page 18.  Again, we propose that the forum shall consider and advise the council and the strategic policy committees on a range of matters.</p><p>With amendment No. 16, we propose to delete lines 19 to 21 and replace them with the following: &quot;(3) The Council and the strategic policy committees of the Council shall consider the advice provided by the Forum in relation to the matters set out in <i>subsections (1) </i>and <i>(2)</i>.&quot;  I move the amendments in the spirit of trying to ensure the Bill is as straightforward and definitive as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.362" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#H02900"><p>The Docklands Consultative Forum is dealt with in Part 5.  The same structure is being replicated here as existed in the Dublin Docklands Development Authority.</p><p>I was a member of that authority for a number of years along with many other councillors.  A similar structure for the appointment of local authority, community, business members and so on is being provided for in this legislation.  The first problem with it is that it is a forum.  It is a place where people come together and talk, it is not a place where people make decisions.  Deputy Stanley's amendment suggests replacing the word "may" with the word "shall" because section 33(1) simply states the forum "may consider and advise" the council.  Surely the forum "should" consider and advise the council.  It is not much of a consultative forum if it does not do that and if it has a tentative rather than a specific mandate to do so.  I am not sure the wording is adequate.  I would like the provision to be strengthened and perhaps the Minister of State might deal with that in his response.</p><p> The legislation refers to five organisations which, in the opinion of the Minister, are representative of the community, five organisations which are representative of economic activity in the area, five public authorities and so on.  One of the amendments names various geographical areas in the community.  They are set out in the amendment and include City Quay, East Wall, Irishtown, North Wall, Pearse Street, Ringsend and Sheriff Street-Seville Place.  The communities want to have these areas represented on a geographical basis so that we do not end up with non-geographical representation.  They want even geographical representation.  The legislation provides for "not less than 5 organisations" but they are all organisations and how are these organisations going to put forward members?  Will there be a plebiscite?  How will nominations take place prior to the Minister making the formal appointment?  Will the Minister of State clarify that issue?</p><p> I am glad the Minister of State said he was interested in strengthening the forum in terms of reporting powers and giving it a level of oversight.  There is a danger that it will just be a talking shop.  It may well end up like the previous one.  Many people in a representative capacity came together but were not able to effect anything.  Everything happened outside their remit.  I would like the body's powers to be strengthened.  In addition, it should have an oversight role to allow it to ensure that objectives and targets are met.  The regeneration of the docklands was a fantastic idea in theory.  Principles were laid down and there was a master plan.  We had everything except the delivery.  It did not deliver social and economic regeneration in equal measure as it was supposed to do.</p><p> We need to ensure that not just economic regeneration is delivered on this particular occasion.  We are talking about thousands of jobs.  Some 23,000 jobs are meant to be created as a result of this.  There will be enormous development in terms of office blocks and residential developments and huge opportunities for training and employment.  There will be enormous opportunity to get this right for the docklands.  That is the nub of the matter.  We need to get it right on this occasion.  The docklands consultative forum could be the key to doing it, if we can get it right, but it needs to be more than a consultative forum.  It must have an oversight role so that it can ensure targets are met, social regeneration is not forgotten about, social housing is provided, employment targets are met and all the rest of it.  It would report to the Minister and this committee.  It would also be possible to bring in the Dublin City council development unit.  That sort of bite is needed.  I would welcome an amendment by the Minister which would tighten up this section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.364" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#J00200"><p>The amendment in Deputy Catherine Murphy's name refers to section 34 and mentions specific areas.  However, I think a number of amendments are being discussed together.  First, I acknowledge the docklands communities and the members thereof who served in the area, including the previous chief executives, Mr. Peter Coyne and Mr. Paul Maloney, who did amazing work representing their communities.  Many of them were here when this committee launched its report.  There was a strong and positive air around the committee's report that day but it seems that many of the recommendations of the committee are not being taken on board in this legislation.</p> <p>  I mentioned specific areas earlier.  They are the historical docklands communities.  I have read the section on the forum in the legislation which is a long section.  It concerns representatives of people engaged in activities the area rather than people who are and have been living there all of their lives and have a particular contribution to make.  There could be people on the forum from organisations which are engaged in the docklands but these individuals might only have been with the organisations in question for a year or two.  They may have no real sense of what it is to live in the docklands community.  As stated by Deputy Costello, social regeneration is important.  This is a lot of anxiety within the docklands communities.  Having put so much into the master plan, people fear their voices will now be lost.  Will the Minister of State examine the issue to ensure those voices are not lost?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.365" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#J00300"><p>I thank the Deputies for their contributions.  I know they are well meaning and the contributions are made in the interests of trying to ensure we get this right.</p> <p>  Before getting into the detail of the proposed amendments, it is important to note, and I agree, that unique consultative arrangements were put in place in 1997 when the DDDA was set up.  These have been referred to by the Deputies.  The input from interested parties in the docklands was previously channelled by the docklands council to the authority.  The advice and feedback from that council, which included representatives from community groups and business interests, as well as Government Departments and semi-State bodies, was invaluable in formulating policy and strategies in the past.  However, in dissolving the authority and transferring its functions to Dublin City Council, I was equally anxious to ensure that the voices of residents, businesses and other parties with an interest in the area are heard.  Accordingly, the legislation provides for a docklands consultative forum to provide an appropriate assembly for this specific and valuable purpose.  In devising the composition, role and functions of the new forum, the consensus of the outgoing docklands council, the board of the authority and the city council was sought.  The definition, composition, role and functions of the forum are detailed in Part 5 of the Bill and the related Schedule.  It should be noted - I note concerns of Deputy Maureen O'Sullivan in this regard - that four elected councillors who are accountable democratically to the communities living in the docklands are on the forum.  </p> <p>  I do not intend to accept amendments 13 and 15.  It is adequate for the forum to have the option to advise the council and its strategic policy committees rather than compelling it to do so.  The section as currently drafted does not preclude the forum from considering and advising the council on relevant issues but it does provide the flexibility for the forum to consider and advise on all or some of the issues as priorities arise, depending on their importance at any given time.  If the forum was required to address all issues, as the amendment suggests, it could place an undue burden on the work of the forum.  We must recognise that the members of the forum will be volunteers.</p><p>In the case of the proposed amendment No. 14, I do not consider the amendment necessary as the term &ldquo;employment&rdquo; listed in the current draft of the Bill encompasses all types of employment.  Therefore, I do not intend to accept it.  Indeed, being too explicit as to the forms of employment may in fact diminish other non-listed types of employment, which could cause problems down the road.</p><p> Similar to the reasons I have given in regard to amendments Nos. 13 and 15, I do not propose to accept amendment No. 16.  The consultative forum already has the power to consider and advise the council on matters set out in subsections (1) and (2) of section 33.  The intent of subsection (3) of section 33 is to allow the democratically elected council to request the forum to consider any issue under subsections (1) and (20) and, if so, the forum shall so consider the issue.  The provision of an instruction to the elected council is outside the scope of this Bill.</p><p> I do not intend to accept amendment No. 17.  I believe that it is important that the forum represent the full spectrum of stakeholders in the docklands, as did its predecessor, the docklands council, and this is adequately addressed in the Bill.  The composition of the forum is detailed in section 34 of the Bill, which provides a mechanism that allows nominations from a number of interested stakeholders in the docklands area, including community, educational, business, and political stakeholders and from public authorities who have an interest in the area.  </p><p> I do not intend to accept amendment No. 18 as the method of identifying and appointing an independent chair to the forum, as the provision set out in subsection (2) of section 34 of the Bill is sufficient and appropriate.  The position of chairperson is important for the effective operation and administration of the forum and it is crucial that an independent chair, who is not aligned to any of the nominating groups, is appointed.</p><p> Finally, I do not intend to accept the proposal contained in amendment No. 19.  As previously stated, the composition of the forum, as well as its role and functions, were devised in consultation with the outgoing docklands council, the authority and Dublin City Council.  The composition of the forum is set out in some detail in section 34 of the Bill, which provides a mechanism that allows nominations from a number of interested stakeholders in the docklands area.  This composition ensures that all interests are adequately represented on the forum.  In the circumstances, I am of the opinion that the composition of the docklands forum as detailed is well balanced, reasonable and reflects the complementary interests of the docklands community.</p><p> Some Deputies mentioned reporting and oversight.  I have already mentioned that the reports will be sent to the Minister and laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  This in turn provides an opportunity for the relevant Oireachtas committee to scrutinise the report or to call the relevant officials before it if the committee wishes to debate some of the issues in the report.  This provides for transparency, oversight and scrutiny.  I am prepared to reconsider the title of the consultative forum and its terms of reference to consider whether we can strengthen oversight.  However, I must make clear that decision-making will remain with the elected council of Dublin City Council which, as members will agree, is the democratically accountable body.  However, I am prepared to consider the oversight role of the consultative forum as its focus is to progress the interests and objectives of the docklands area.</p><p> I have outlined my reasons for opposing the amendments, but I am prepared to work with Deputies to ensure we have a system that will work and that will improve on those we have already seen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.367" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#K00200"><p>I want to respond in regard to amendment No. 17.  The insertion of the phrase "nominated by the local community, educational and business groups" does not weaken or dilute the Bill in any way, rather strengthens that section.  In regard to amendment No. 18, the issue of chairperson is important.  It is important for any group or organisation that they can select their chairperson.  In this case, we need to trust the local development groups.  I understand the Minister of State has said these have an advisory role, but that he is considering strengthening that role although it must be balanced with the statutory functions of the council and the fact it is a democratic forum.  It is positive that the Minister of State is willing to look at the issue.  It is important that an organisation or forum can select one of its members as chairperson.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.368" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#K00300"><p>Did I understand the Minister of State correctly that the outgoing council did not make its views known on the community aspect?  He said the outgoing council did not make any particular recommendation.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.369" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#K00400"><p>I will clarify that.  In regard to amendment No. 19, I said that as previously stated, the composition of the forum, as well as its role and functions, were devised in consultation with the outgoing docklands council, the authority and Dublin City Council.  Therefore, there was consultation in regard to it.  Also, in devising the composition, role and functions of the new forum, the consensus of the outgoing docklands council, the board of the authority and of Dublin City Council was sought.  The definition, composition, role and functions of the forum are detailed in Part V  of the Bill.  Therefore, there was engagement with the outgoing council, authority and city council.  I hope this clarifies the situation for the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.370" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#K00500"><p>Thank you.  It is disappointing that the outgoing council did not come across as being more cognisant of the role of the community members and did not stress that in the consultation.</p> <p>  Section 34 is very vague and we could end up with a forum that is not particularly representative of dockland communities, including the educational and community groups proposed in Deputy Stanley's amendment.   The vagueness of the section leaves me feeling that communities may get lost in the process unless this section is strengthened.</p> <p> Four members of the forum will be selected from elected members to Dublin City Council.  The docklands involve two different electoral areas, the north inner city and the south inner city, but there is nothing specific in the legislation to ensure that all four of these members will not come from one side of the Liffey.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.371" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#K00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the clarification on the strengthening of the role of the docklands consultative forum and to reviewing its title.  Hopefully it will not just be given an advisory and consultative role, but will also have oversight of it.  This is important to ensure targets are reached.</p> <p>  I agree with Deputy O'Sullivan that there is a lack of clarity in regard to the representatives of the local community organisations on the forum and whether they will necessarily be people who are living in the community.  Many people represent the community in different guises, but do not live in the community.  It would be good to see the areas represented by people living in them, because they are defined areas, such as North Wall, Ringsend, East Wall and so on.  The provisions should ensure there is a proper distribution of representation.  There is nothing in the legislation regarding a balanced distribution of representation for the people in the docklands area or regarding how the organisations may choose who will be on the forum or whether it will be an outsider or someone from within the community. </p> <p>  Another element missing from the Bill is a reference to any organisations representing heritage or culture in the area.  The docklands area has enormous heritage.  The Minister of State is from Waterford and is aware of its heritage.  We regard Dublin as a Viking city, perhaps even before Waterford was a Viking city.</p><p>We could argue about that one.  There is much industrial heritage, as well as maritime heritage and everything else with the confluence of the water at the canal, river and sea.  It would be useful to add a set of people to represent the heritage and culture of the area, considering the work being done at present by the docklands preservation society on the maritime history of the docklands.  Dublin Port has many artefacts as well.  We should look at developing that heritage in a proactive fashion so it would be desirable to have people as representatives on the particular forum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.373" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L00200"><p>I have outlined in detail my opinion on the amendments.  As the Bill is currently constructed, it provides for 21 members on the consultative forum and we must be careful not to dilute that.  I am not saying that would happen but by expanding it, the committee could become more unwieldy, as any committee might.  We need to be conscious of that.  In the 21 members, it is important to reflect the views of residents in the community.  I have already stated that four elected members of Dublin City Council will be nominated to the consultative forum by the council.  The elected members of any local authority have a democratic mandate to represent communities in those areas and we should not lose sight of that.  They are always accountable to the citizens of that area in the best way possible.  I am happy that the councillors nominated to the forum, whoever they may be, will do their job in advocating and representing those communities.</p> <p>  On top of this, five members are engaged in community development in the docklands.  I do not know any of these people but they are nominated by organisations because they work at the coal face, understand the needs of the area and work in a proactive way to improve the docklands.  In their own right, they bring valuable experience from those communities, daily life and working experience.  There are also five members engaged in the promotion of carrying out economic activity in the docklands, as it is also important to get a good balance in terms of commercial and economic activity.  The semi-State bodies or public authorities provide infrastructure and it is important they are represented, and there is also an educational representative.</p> <p>  The consultative forum is already well constructed and represented.  I have already agreed to have another look at how we might strengthen the oversight element - we are considering how it could report to Oireachtas in the interests of scrutiny and transparency - but I am happy that the forum is sufficient as it is currently constructed.</p> <p>  Deputy Costello raises a very important point related to heritage and culture and I have much interest in that.  The area has a rich social and industrial history.  The Deputy is correct in that much of the history is attached to Waterford, in my constituency, which is Ireland's oldest city and a Viking settlement.  It has much history shared with the Dublin docklands.  Dublin is the capital and economic driver of the country, which means there was much activity in the past involving dockers and the various associated social and industrial history.  That should not be lost in the regeneration of the area.  I am very conscious that there is a rich culture and tradition and although it is there now, how long more will it survive in living memory, with people capturing and retelling stories of the great industries located there and the lives sustained by that?</p> <p>  I am aware that a heritage audit is under way and there is much local engagement, as Deputies know.  I hope it can be finalised sooner rather than later and I expect it will make recommendations on how that heritage, culture and rich identity can be preserved as much as possible.  We should also be able to retell this rich history through the likes of design or interpretive and heritage initiatives.  I am very supportive of that idea and officials in Dublin City Council should be as well; I am sure they will be very supportive.  I look forward to seeing that heritage audit finalised and the consultative forum will take heritage as a very important aspect of its work.  It is open for the members to do so and the with the representatives on the forum, there will be adequate opportunity for all of those concerns to be engaged with on behalf of citizens and interested parties.</p> <p>  I will not accept the amendments as currently proposed for those reasons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.374" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L00300"><p>I make a final plea as communities are made up of the people who live in those communities and not just the people who work for the community or have a business there etc.  The forum is weakened by the way in which there is no emphasis on the people who live in the community being on the forum to speak for their communities, as they have always done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.375" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L00400"><p>I have made my statements on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.376" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.377" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 14 and 15 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.378" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L00700"><p>I move amendment No. 16:</p><blockquote>In page 18, to delete lines 19 to 21 and substitute the following:&quot;(3) The Council and the strategic policy committees of the Council shall consider the advice provided by the Forum in relation to the matters set out in <i>subsections (1) </i>and <i>(2)</i>.&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.379" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.

Section 33 agreed to.

SECTION 34</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.380" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L00900"><p>I move amendment No. 17:</p><blockquote>In page 18, line 23, after &quot;members&quot; to insert &quot;nominated by local community, educational and business groups&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.381" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.382" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L01100"><p>I move amendment No. 18:</p><blockquote>In page 18, lines 24 and 25, to delete &quot;The Minister, following consultation with the Council, shall appoint a person nominated by the Chief Executive&quot; and substitute &quot;The Forum shall select one of its members&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.383" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.384" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1005" speakername="Maureen O'Sullivan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L01300"><p>I move amendment No. 19:</p><blockquote>In page 20, between lines 27 and 28, to insert the following:&quot;(13) The Minister shall ensure following consultation that at least 7 community members be nominated from the geographic area of the Docklands i.e. City Quay, East Wall, Irishtown, North Wall, Pearse Street, Ringsend and Sheriff Street/Seville Place and the above areas' associated hinterlands.&quot;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.385" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.386" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L01500"><p>Amendment No. 20 has been ruled out of order because of a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.387" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 20 not moved.</p><p>Section 34 agreed to.</p><p>Sections 35 to 44, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.388" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Schedule agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.389" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>TITLE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.390" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Title be the Title to the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.391" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L01700"><p>Does the Minister of State have any final comments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.392" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#L01800"><p>I will be brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.393" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>I thank the Leas Chathaoirleach and the clerk to the committee for facilitating the Committee Stage of this very important Bill.  I thank the Deputies for their engagement in outlining their genuine concerns on Committee Stage.  I look forward to coming back on Report Stage where we can further debate the issues and I am sure there will be further amendments.</p><p>I take the opportunity to offer my personal condolences to the Cathaoirleach, Deputy McCarthy, who sadly lost his father recently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.394" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#M00200"><p>I would like to be associated with the expression of condolences to Deputy McCarthy and his family.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.395" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#M00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the comprehensive way in which he responded to all the amendments.  He is agreeable to coming back to see how we can tighten up on some aspects of the legislation on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.396" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#M00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, and his officials, Mr. Walsh, Mr. Dunne and Mr. Logan, for attending this evening's session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.397" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.398" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.399" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#M00500">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.400" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="19:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12015111100002#M00600"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p><blockquote>The Select Sub-Committee on the Environment, Community and Local Government has completed its consideration of the Dublin Docklands Development Authority (Dissolution) Bill 2015 and has made amendments thereto.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-11-11a.401" nospeaker="true" time="19:00:00" ><p>The select sub-committee adjourned at 8.52 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>