<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Áine Collins, Senator David Cullinane, Deputy Michael Conaghan, Senator Feargal Quinn. Deputy Seán Kyne, Deputy Anthony Lawlor,</p><p>DEPUTY JOHN LYONS IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from the Chairman and Deputy Calleary.  The joint committee will enter into private session to deal with housekeeping matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 1.40 p.m. and resumed in public session at 1.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700003#B00200">Access to Finance for SMEs: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700003#B00300"><p>The first session this afternoon is a meeting with Ms Regina Breheny, director general of the Irish Venture Capital Association, to discuss access to finance for the SME sector.  I welcome Ms Regina Breheny, Mr. Mark Horgan, chair of the association, and Mr. John Flynn, vice chair.<br />I advise the witnesses that, by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.</p> <p>Witnesses are further directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p> I invite Ms Breheny to make her opening statement, after which I will take questions from members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.11" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Regina Breheny" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700004#C00200"><p>My colleagues and I welcome the opportunity to meet with the committee today.  The Irish Venture Capital Association, IVCA, is the representative organisation for venture capital, VC, firms in Ireland.  These VC firms have specialist domain knowledge and invest primarily in fast-growing, high-tech companies operating in the information and communications technology, ICT, and life sciences, chiefly medical technology, sectors.  The companies are developing deep technologies, addressing global markets and creating thousands of high-calibre jobs.<br />Venture capital refers to the provision of equity capital to fund the start-up, growth and expansion of innovative small to medium-sized enterprises which are high-risk and high-potential but are unable to access credit markets because their underlying assets are typically based on intellectual property.  Venture capital firms bridge that five to ten-year funding gap between the small amounts of money raised from friends and family and the funding from bank debt that comes at a much later stage.  While banks do not lend to these companies, they support them by investing in venture capital funds, particularly at the seed and start-up stage.<br />A particular feature of the VC model is that funds are precluded from taking on debt.  Instead, they usually invest equity in return for a minority shareholding.  Leverage is not an issue and, therefore, venture capital activity does not pose any systemic risk.  Venture capital teams usually have a technology background - scientists, engineers, researchers and so on - or a business background with deep industry experience.  A core skill is the ability to identify novel technologies that have the potential to generate high commercial returns at an early stage.  Normally, the interests of the VC fund and entrepreneurs are aligned, with both having a common interest in building a business and exiting it through an initial public offering, IPO, or trade sale over time.<br />The VC fund is normally structured as a limited partnership with a fixed ten-year life.  Capital is provided by long-term private and public investment funds, such as pension funds, life insurance companies, endowment funds, foundations, sovereign wealth funds and state bodies.  VC fund managers also invest alongside other investors.  The capital is only drawn down as the fund makes its investments; VC funds do not hold cash.  The investment period for the fund is generally five years, after which the focus is on managing and making follow-on investments in an existing portfolio.  After an initial investment is made in a portfolio company, additional capital is reserved to fund further development but is only drawn down from investors as it is required.  Investments are sold through an IPO or trade sale, the cash is returned to the investors and the fund is closed.  In effect, the fund is self-liquidating.  After the five-year investment period, the VC firm raises capital for a new fund.  VC companies in this State are regulated by the Central Bank of Ireland under the alternative investment fund manager, AIFM, directive.<br /><b></b>The venture capital industry in Ireland is performing very well.  While the level of VC investment activity worldwide has been adversely affected by the credit crunch, with no growth and significant volatility in recent years, there was strong investment in Ireland throughout the recession.  In 2013 alone, &euro;285 million was raised by Irish SMEs.  The focus of venture capital activity is on investment in high-tech, early-stage companies in the ICT and the med tech sectors.  More than 350 of these companies have been supported by Irish VCs in the past ten years and, consequently, Ireland is recognised as a major force in technology development.<br />In the past decade, &euro;1 billion in capital has been imported by Irish VCs through syndication with United States and European-based venture funds.  On average, every one euro invested by an Irish VC is matched by one euro from an international VC.  Irish VCs add significant value to portfolio companies by syndicating with tier one international VC funds and corporate investors, introducing international business partners, customers and acquirers, recruiting senior management, introducing corporate governance, and endorsing the business and management team to the sector in which it operates.  Since 1997, the number of VC funds operating in Ireland has more than doubled and their average size has increased from &euro;20 million to &euro;75 million.  In addition, in response to increasing demand from SMEs, the market is now segmented, with both seed and start-up and early and-or expansion-stage funds present.  Irish VCs have invested in a wide range of deal types from research and development commercialisation to start-up and early-stage technology companies and companies requiring later-stage growth equity and development capital.  Many of the VC firms are entering their fourth investment cycle and have specialist domain knowledge in the sectors in which they invest.<br />The venture ecosystem in Ireland is well developed, with spin-outs coming from publicly funded research centres.  With the emergence of incubation centres and accelerator programmes, these start-up companies are now better prepared in terms of investor readiness than ever before.  Almost all of the leading American ICT and pharma, med tech and biotechnology companies have located their European headquarters in Ireland.  These enterprises draw talent and are breeding grounds for the entrepreneurs of tomorrow.  Most exits in Ireland are through trade sales, mainly to the multinationals, thus further expanding the presence of the multinational industry in Ireland.  On a note of caution in this regard, Ireland's tax regime has lost significant competitiveness compared with the United Kingdom.  There is a misalignment between the Government's tax policy in regard to entrepreneurship and the key objectives in the Action Plan for Jobs 2014.  The IVCA is lobbying the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and the Department of Finance to redress this disadvantage.<br />Returns are poised for a major recovery, because the quantity and quality of the pipeline of investment opportunities has increased greatly.  The commercial acumen, international experience and focus of SME management teams is impressive and relevant to what is required for success in world markets.  Early-stage valuations are stable after dropping significantly with the onset of the global financial crisis, while exit valuations are growing.  Companies are focused on addressing global markets and are scaling faster and building value earlier.  Tier one multinational companies have billions of dollars reserved for acquiring technology companies.  In addition, mergers and acquisitions activity is strong, leading to attractive exit opportunities for VC investors.<br />Investment by the State has been key to the success of Irish VC funds in raising capital from the private sector.  Since 1997, the Irish venture capital industry has been developed and nurtured by the Government through investment of &euro;348 million via the Enterprise Ireland seed and venture capital programme over three investment rounds.  VC firms have leveraged this commitment by raising additional private sector investment both for the fund itself and subsequently through syndicated deals for the individual companies.  As a result, nearly &euro;4 billion has been raised by Irish SMEs in this period.  The State's commitment has been leveraged upwards by a factor of ten.  In fact, payroll taxes of approximately &euro;600 million paid by VC-backed companies over the period 2003 to 2012 have made the programme self-financing from tax revenues alone.<br />International studies indicate that venture capital stimulates growth, innovation, research and development, new business and entrepreneurialism.  In Ireland, VC funding as a percentage of GDP trebled from 0.06% in 2003 to 0.18% in 2012.  This is the second highest level in Europe after Finland.  Throughout this period, the number of new innovative companies raising seed capital increased fourfold.  Irish technology companies have spawned a significant number of new companies and created a new generation of serial entrepreneurs who are now dominant in the early-stage sectors.  Three technology companies alone have spawned a further 146 companies.<br />Irish venture capitalists have driven growth in sectors such as software semiconductors, clean tech and med tech.</p> <p>Many of the multinationals operating in these sectors have located here and, consequently, Irish VCs have developed specialist sectoral clusters of innovative activities, including medical devices, telecommunications, laser optics, electronic switching devices, business software and gaming.</p><p> The IVCA commissioned the Centre for Entrepreneurial Studies in UCD to conduct an in-depth study of the economic impact of venture capital on the Irish economy and data have been gathered on venture-backed companies over the past decade to 2012.  The analysis shows that venture-backed companies create more high calibre jobs.  Employment is up 11% per annum since 2003.  In the past ten years, these companies created 16,400 high calibre jobs.  It is estimated that these companies support up to three additional indirect downstream jobs.  Hence the true number of direct and indirect jobs generated as a result of venture capital investment in innovative SMEs is approximately 66,000.  An additional survey indicated that since 2005, companies originally backed by venture capital and subsequently sold to multinationals went on to increase employment by another 38%.  </p><p> These venture backed companies are export-led.  Exports increased by 12% per annum since 2003 and in the high-tech sector, exports represented 80% of revenues.  These companies grow faster and their revenues are up 17% per annum since 2003.  They are knowledge based and graduates represent 75% of the workforce.  The research and development spend by venture-backed companies represents 30% of all Irish SMEs share of total spend on BERD.</p><p> Growing Ireland&rsquo;s indigenous export orientated SME sector is becoming a national imperative as these companies provide 50% of the jobs in the economy and generate 10% of exports.  A strong and well-financed venture capital industry is vital to this growth.  The IVCA estimates that over the next five years - 2014 to 2019 - up to 40 start-up companies will be supported every year by the seed funds and start-up funds and 110 existing early stage companies will receive additional expansion capital from the mainstream venture capital funds.  Within ten years, these companies could provide up to 21,000 new direct jobs and, based upon a 3:1 multiple, 63,000 additional indirect jobs.  They could pay up to &euro;300 million per annum in direct payroll taxes, and over ten years that could exceed &euro;2 billion.  They could export in excess of &euro;1 billion per year and spend up to &euro;300 million per annum on research and development.</p><p> The investment activity associated with the venture capital funds supported by the last seed and venture capital programme, 2007 to 2012, peaked during 2010 and available funds for new investment has now begun to decline.  Investment activity by the seed funds will also see a decline by the end of 2014.  Consequently, the number of new investments has started to fall off, bringing about a funding gap for indigenous companies.  The IVCA estimates that the capital required over the next five years to fund the growth and expansion of innovative Irish SMEs is &euro;1.65 billion.  In response to this, the venture capital industry is in the process of raising new funds to fill this gap.</p><p> The economic characteristics of venture-backed companies as outlined above have encouraged and influenced policy-makers to recognise the importance of venture capital activity and, consequently, innovation and venture capital are at the centre of Ireland&rsquo;s economic policy.  The evidence for this is funding initiatives from Enterprise Ireland at the seed stage and in the growth capital space; the establishment of a later stage expansion fund by the National Pensions Reserve Fund; and the commitment by Enterprise Ireland of up to &euro;175 million as a cornerstone investor to venture capital funds under the new seed and venture capital scheme 2013 to 2018.  Some &euro;99.5 million of this has been committed to early stage expansion funds.  The IVCA believes that the balance of &euro;75.5 million should be committed to regenerate the seed and start-up funds to finance entrepreneurship and to maintain a pipeline of high calibre start-ups.  </p><p> Irish venture capital funds are currently marketing the Irish opportunity and plan to raise funds from international investors, including the European Investment Fund, international corporate investors and foundations, fund of funds and private investors.  In recent weeks, the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund unveiled its plans to invest a &euro;6.8 billion fund in Ireland and indicated that venture capital has a central role to play in growing the Irish economy.  However, funds invested by ISIF must be matched by commitments from the private sector but support from the private sector in Ireland is limited.  This is because there is a distinct absence in Ireland of certain classes of institutional investors that have historically supported US VCs, such as private equity funds of funds, university endowments, foundations and family offices.  Most life insurance companies operating in here are foreign-owned and are managed from abroad, with little influence on decisions to invest in the Irish venture capital asset class.  There is a limited pool of Irish pension funds of sufficient scale and with the management resources that have been willing to invest in Irish venture capital.  They are largely semi-State or public sector defined benefit schemes.  Many of these defined benefit funds are in deficit and have been actively seeking to reduce their risk profile.  </p><p> The pension industry manages the largest pool of private capital in Ireland.  Notwithstanding strong recent returns from Irish venture capital funds, Irish pension funds are not investing.  This is because there are regulatory constraints on equity investments in general for pension funds and, in particular, there are regulatory constraints on liquidity issues within defined contribution schemes.  Many defined benefit schemes are closing or are converting to defined contribution schemes.  There is negative sentiment arising from the pensions levy.</p><p> This is inhibiting the development of the Irish venture capital industry and, with it, Ireland&rsquo;s high-tech SMEs.  If pension funds cannot be persuaded to invest in Ireland, it will also greatly impede the ability of the ISIF to invest in Ireland, as it will be unable to access the required matching private sector funding.  Initiatives to free up private sector capital should be considered and could include discussions with the pensions industry around the levy and an alternative could be to set up a national pooled mechanism funded by a 1% investment by all private and public pension funds which have received tax relief on contributions.  This could create a &euro;700 million to &euro;800 million fund to invest alongside the ISIF; and a Government or an EU initiative to underwrite a liquidity mechanism which allows defined contribution schemes to invest in selected Irish focused investments like venture capital.  </p><p> I hope these remarks have given some understanding of how the venture capital industry operates, in particular, in regard to its impact on funding innovative SMEs.  I thank members for their attention and my colleagues and I look forward to their questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700005#D00200"><p>I thank Ms Breheny.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700005#D00300"><p>I thank Ms Breheny for that explanation.  The Irish Venture Capital Association has undertaken a very exciting project.  Some of those figures are way beyond anything most of us would have known about.  My main query is competition from abroad.  Ms Breheny mentioned that the British are involved in tax competition.  I remember some years ago a tax was introduced in Ireland which did not apply in Britain.  We fought a very hard battle and managed to convince the Government that it made no sense in a marketplace where there was international competition to have a tax here which did not apply elsewhere because capital would automatically shift.  Will Ms Breheny touch on the effect of our tax regime on somebody coming to invest in Ireland or on somebody already in Ireland and on the choice of whether to go north of the Border, to Britain and somewhere else?  What are the tax implications?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Flynn" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700005#D00400"><p>If one looks at a very high level, the competition in early stage companies is about the resources and skills we can attract into the companies.  We are dealing with a fairly mobile workforce, so it breaks down into the two key categories of income tax and capital gains tax.  If one takes the two major economies which would be leaders and competitors of ours - the US and the UK - in both income tax and capital gains tax, we would be inferior.</p> <p>The two major economies that compete with us are the United States and the United Kingdom.  Our income tax and capital gains tax rates are less attractive than theirs.</p><p> Our 52% rate of income tax compares with 47% in the UK and 40% in the US.  Attracting talent into companies becomes an issue in respect of livelihood.  If we take a cut in salary, our net take home pay is lower but we can compensate for that with additional options in companies to help employees and founders own a piece of the company.</p><p> Capital gains tax in Ireland is 33%, but in the UK there is tapered relief for entrepreneurs at 10%.  Our rate is a major disincentive when we compete against employees in the UK and against people who want to invest in companies where there is less dilution of their ownership because employees can make more out of smaller stakes in their companies.  In the US, capital gains tax is approximately 23%.  Many of the share option schemes are subjected to income tax in Ireland.  We are lobbying to tackle those two tax features to attract the best people into the start-ups which is the key component of building a successful enterprise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00200"><p>Is the Irish Venture Capital Association being listened to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.18" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Flynn" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00300"><p>Yes.  There is significant progress.  It is a race to get things implemented because this is a live issue.  Therefore it needs to be tackled in a very short time span.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Horgan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00400"><p>Within Ireland there is competition between the various asset classes.  The Government gives a capital gains tax holiday to property investors.  If they buy properties now and hold them for seven years they do not pay capital gains tax on the profits.  That does not exist from an entrepreneur&rsquo;s point of view and in promoting entrepreneurship.  People who have the choice between investing in a property or in a business choose the property investment because the tax environment is far more attractive.  If a person invests in a business and sells it after five or six years, having possibly created 100 jobs, the profit on the proceeds will be taxed at 33%.  The Government's economic policy as set out in Action Plan for Jobs 2014 is misaligned with its tax policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00500"><p>We have to work on that if we are going to encourage more investment in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00600"><p>I welcome the panel here today.  At the outset the witnesses said they provide equity to companies unable to access credit markets.  Why are they unable to access credit?  Is it to do with risk or the scale of what they are looking for?</p><p>  Is the uncompetitive tax regime the main challenge?  What other challenges are there for venture capitalists who provide funding?  They have said investment activity will decline because of the seed funds and available funding.  They have mentioned initiatives that should be taken up, including discussions with the pensions industry and EU initiatives to provide liquidity as a backstop.  Have they pursued these with the Department of Finance or Government or are they just hopes?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.22" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Horgan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00700"><p>Typically, many of the innovative technology-based SMEs that operate around the world and in Ireland do not use debt as a way to fund their business.  They would use equity.  The most important point for Ireland is to make as much equity available as possible to these SMEs because that is their lifeblood.  Debt becomes an important funding factor for these companies at a much later stage.  That is critical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.23" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Flynn" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00800"><p>The anti-competitive tax regime is one challenge.  The two main challenges we face are the tax issues we have outlined and the availability of private sector financing from the pension fund industry.  That is a key issue that we need to get over to match money from the public sector markets.</p><p>  The pension fund industry is undergoing change and is under pressure because most defined benefit schemes are being moved to defined contribution schemes.  As a result, the investment managers in these schemes have less autonomy to make investment decisions and within the defined contribution scheme there is also a requirement to have liquidity so that people who own these pensions can sell in and out.  One of the drawbacks of our asset class is that it does not provide for a very liquid movement.  Hence we recommend putting some support systems in place to improve people&rsquo;s ability to sell in and out of a pooled resource.  That would enable defined contribution schemes, which are the larger market pension schemes, to consider investments in this asset class.</p><p>  Mr. Horgan referred to the debt feature.  The key asset of companies at this stage in their life cycle is intellectual property, their people, their idea and approach to the market, which are predominantly financed by equity funding rather than debt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E00900"><p>They are developing companies that are starting off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Flynn" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E01000"><p>Absolutely.  They are at a very early stage.  It would be unfair to say the banks have not participated.  The pillar banks in Ireland have participated in funding the equity funds and have relationships with the venture capital managers in the market.  As the companies grow and develop, opportunities open up for invoice discounting and working capital before they move into mainstream debt products.  There are some moves afoot, with the backing of the European Investment Bank and certain pillar banks in Ireland, to be able to provide an underwritten product for those types of markets.  The situation is improving but it is largely focused on equity products and the venture product is the most appropriate one for companies at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E01100"><p>How does this segment of economic activity here compare with other countries?  In broad, general terms, are there similar patterns?  Can we learn from the experience in other countries?  Are we perhaps ahead of them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Regina Breheny" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E01200"><p>We are well ahead of countries in Europe, particularly in respect of the amount of venture capital in the economy and in the number of new companies being supported and brought on.  There are difficulties around the world in funding venture capital from the private sector.  We are probably a bit behind the Americans because we have fewer institutional investors to choose from.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.28" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Flynn" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700006#E01300"><p>There are a couple of statistics that would shed light on that.  There has been a significant increase in investment activity as a percentage of gross domestic product, GDP.  We are second in Europe on that scale.</p> <p>Other initiatives have been taken by certain agencies, including, most notably, Enterprise Ireland, and also IDA Ireland, the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund and the venture capital community over the past period.  That has propelled Ireland to a very good platform at the moment for an expansive opportunity in a competitive sense.  This includes the seed investment programmes brought to bear again through the pillar banks investing and Enterprise Ireland's activities in terms of leadership programmes.  There has been a quadrupling from 16 to 64 seed investments per annum, which is a significant improvement, and we have also had quite a lot of investment into what we would term "pre-pipeline" development, with approximately 18 or so incubators and accelerators which help very early stage companies come together with mentor programmes.  That would compare well with any other geography.  There tends to be clusters of different venture and early stage activity, and Dublin is one of the hotter clusters within a European context.  It is second to main clusters in the US, which are on the west coast at Silicon Valley.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.30" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Horgan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00200"><p>We are preparing a submission to Enterprise Ireland as part of its call for submissions this week.  It is important that the remaining &euro;75 million from the allocated &euro;175 for the seed and venture capital fund should be given for seed and start-up funds.  If it is not, we could lose the momentum from the work done over the past number of years with those funds.  The &euro;75 million should now be allocated by the Government to seed and start-up funds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00300"><p>Is the witness suggesting it may go elsewhere?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.32" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Horgan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00400"><p>Not at all.  There is an ongoing public consultation and as part of our submission, we will make this point.  People at the coal face like ourselves know that the improvement in the pipeline and quality of early stage companies coming through - as compared to when I started 15 years ago - is significant.  If we want to continue the momentum, we must ensure the &euro;75 million is allocated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00500"><p>I thank the witnesses and I have attended a number of previous briefings for companies.  I am delighted at the fact that for most small and medium enterprises, SMEs, the problem is now working capital rather than investment capital.  The banks are being allowed to make decisions and they can micro-manage that issue better than the witnesses.  What is the average stake taken by venture capitalists, either in start-up companies or those seeking capital to expand?  What is the percentage rate of failure?  I am worried that there may be cherry-picking of companies which have gone through the process already.  I hate to see figures that 90% of companies get capital succeed - I would be much happier if it were 50% - as people learn from failure more than success.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.34" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Horgan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00600"><p>The average stake is between approximately 15% and 30%.  It is typically a minority stake that is taken by a venture capitalist in a privately held company.  The rate can differ but the 15% to 30% rate is normal.  The percentage rate of failure depends on the stage of development at a particular company.  At seed stage and with start-ups, the percentage of failure is quite high, given the risk involved.  At the other end of the spectrum, companies funded on various rounds at the growth equity stage - series B and C and more mature investments - the ratio of failure is quite low.  Typically, those companies are either sold, with investment returns made for the investors and entrepreneurs, or they continue as a lifestyle company, where they may not make a major exit but they continue to operate and employ people.  It depends on the stage of development for a company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00700"><p>Are there any final comments before we wrap up this part of the session?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00800"><p>Tell me something about the Irish Venture Capital Association.  What is it and how did it start?  How is it funded?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Regina Breheny" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F00900"><p>It has been going for approximately 27 years and was started by a small number of venture capitalists operating in Dublin at the time.  They included Smurfit, Paribas Bank, AIB and a number of others.  Members now comprise the venture capitalist funds operating in Ireland and there are approximately 15 of those.  We also have an associate membership category, with the service providers being solicitors and accountants who supply the infrastructure around the venture capital contracts and business.  We are totally funded by membership subscriptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01000"><p>Does it employ many people?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Regina Breheny" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01100"><p>We employ two people.  I operate as the director general and we have an administrator as well.  The venture capitalists may have up to 100 people in Ireland among their staff in various firms.  It is not a high population industry at the venture capital level but it is when we speak about the companies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. John Flynn" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01200"><p>We have a fairly active committee and members of the venture capital community participate in membership of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.41" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Horgan" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01300"><p>We are working on a submission to the Government that takes in taxes affecting entrepreneurship.  We are also preparing a submission for the Government on the remaining &euro;75 million of seed and venture capital which I spoke of earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01400"><p>The figures are quite high.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.43" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Regina Breheny" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01500"><p>We have a virtual office and do not pay for accommodation as such.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01600"><p>You are well ahead of most companies with that.  I thank Ms Breheny, Mr. Flynn and Mr. Horgan for engaging with the committee today as part of our report on access to finance for small and medium enterprises.  We appreciate them taking the time to come here today.  The significant points made at the end, in particular, will be noted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.45" nospeaker="true" time="15:05:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.25 p.m. and resumed at 2.27 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700007#F01800"><p>The second session will be a discussion with representatives of Forf&aacute;s regarding access to finance for SMEs.   They are Mr. Martin Shanahan, chief executive; Mr. Adrian Devitt, manager for economic analysis, competitiveness, infrastructure and tax and finance policy; and Ms Maria Ginnity, manager for enterprise policy and evaluations.  These are a couple of very long titles and there is much responsibility for people in those areas.  I welcome the witnesses.<br />As they know from listening in the Visitors Gallery, I must read out some formalities before getting into the session.  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if a witness is directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in regard to a particular matter and continues to do so, the witness is entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of his evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p> <p>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that members should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I invite Mr. Shanahan to make his presentation to the committee and thank him for coming before us today.  We will have questions afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.48" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700008#G00200"><p>I thank the Chairman and committee members for inviting us to discuss access to finance for small and medium enterprises.  The Chairman introduced my colleagues and the areas for which they are responsible.  Their titles are evidence of productivity in Forf&aacute;s where people cover many areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700008#G00300"><p>They are very busy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700008#G00400"><p>A detailed briefing paper on my presentation has been circulated to committee members, which I hope will be of assistance to the committee in preparing its report on the matter.  With the Chairman's permission I intend to take it as read and draw out some of the key messages from the paper for the purposes of my introductory remarks.<br />Most members are aware of the role of Forf&aacute;s.  It is the national policy advisory board on enterprise, trade, science, technology and innovation.  We work closely with our sister agencies, IDA Ireland, Enterprise Ireland and Science Foundation Ireland, and undertake evidence-based research and analysis to advise the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Invitation and the Government on a range of policy areas connected to enterprise.  Forf&aacute;s, together with the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, also developed the Governments Action Plan for Jobs and is responsible for implementing some of the actions therein.<br />With regard to the interest of the committee in access to finance for SMEs, in the past two years Forf&aacute;s has published two reports of direct relevance.  <i>The Irish Enterprise Funding Environment</i>was published in April 2012 and <i>A Review of the Equity Investment Landscape in Ireland</i>was published in January last year.  Both reports have been circulated to members with my briefing note.<br />The paper I have circulated clearly shows a number of issues including the importance of SMEs to the Irish economy.  SMEs dominate our economy.  They account for 99.8% of active enterprises in Ireland and employ seven out of every ten people employed.  Young, small and medium-sized enterprises in particular contribute more to employment creation and are therefore extremely important in the context of achieving the targets set out in the Action Plan for Jobs.  It is not easy to disentangle the impact of the supply and demand effects on access to finance and there is a range of issues on both sides.  On the supply side the availability of credit has declined as has the number of banks.  The cost of credit has increased and those banks which remain are concentrating on growing profitability.  The banks have reduced resources, particularly with regard to the number of staff and staff with the skills required to assess new lending opportunities.  Some of these resources have been diverted to deal with non-performing loans.<br />Access to finance is broader than just access to banking finance and the committee has already heard today about equity investment through venture capital.  There are also other products which are not as well developed in Ireland with regard to equity investment.<br />On the demand side, issues for some SMEs relate to poor cash flow and low profitability based on a continued weakness in consumer demand, particularly for those reliant on the domestic economy.  Over-indebtedness is an issue in some cases.  Credit institutions which are risk averse to certain types of businesses or certain sectors are also an issue and there is a lack of wherewithal in some SMEs to develop a business plan or make a business case.<br />Businesses in Ireland have traditionally been over-reliant on bank debt financing, and other models of financing have not received as much attention.  Even before the financial crisis emerged a number of long-standing issues were evident in the market for funding in Ireland.  Innovative exporting small and medium-sized enterprises traditionally had trouble in accessing external credit finance.  The reasons may be that newer technology and business models might not neatly fit into existing lending criteria of financial institutions, a lack of collateral or a lack of track record.<br />With regard to current performance, based on the ECB's most recent survey published in April we can see the financial performance of Irish SMEs is starting to show signs of improvement when compared to recent years and other European countries.  In aggregate terms turnover is growing and indebtedness is falling, although in net terms SMEs are not yet reporting increased profits.  It is important to acknowledge many SMEs have had a very difficult number of years.  Many have suffered from flat consumer demand in Ireland, challenging export markets and some managers are struggling with significant debt overhang.  The ECB data also suggests that while a high share of Irish SMEs regard access to finance as a pressing issue, demand for bank funding is relatively weak.  Demand is also more focused on short-term finance, for example overdrafts for working capital, rather than on longer-term capital for productive investment.  Of those Irish SMEs which apply for bank funding, 38% reported they had received the full amount for which they had applied as opposed to 66% of euro area SMEs.  The ECB survey finds a relatively high share of SMEs in Ireland, 19%, still face significant financing difficulties versus an EU average of 12%.<br />Examining the Irish data highlights that over the course of the past six months credit advanced to the enterprise sector has declined at an annual average rate of 5.1% to the end of January 2014.  The decline in credit advanced to SMEs was most evident in certain sectors, with hotels, restaurants, business and administrative services and the manufacturing sector having the greatest decline.  Irish data also confirms the demand for credit remains relatively weak.  The latest data also indicates a higher percentage of businesses believe banks are open for business and bank refusal rates for loans are falling.<br />The cost of finance continues to be an issue for Irish enterprises.  Cost competitiveness may weaken further as the banks need to rebuild profitability and competition has reduced.  While demand may be weak the extent to which the financial system can provide adequate funding for firms once aggregate demand recovers and the economy grows may be a challenge.  Research highlights that credit constraints affect between 4% and 11% of small and medium-sized enterprises.<br />As I stated earlier, while banking finance is important it is just one source.  Since 2008 we have seen strong growth in the use of share and other equity and the use of accounts receivable.  The initiatives on bank lending are now being complemented by greater focus on non-bank sources of finance to increase funding options and ensure SMEs have necessary equity to get bank credit.<br />I draw members attention to figure No. 2 on page 7 of the presentation circulated to them which demonstrates the supports available at various stages of development of business.  The committee has already heard a presentation today on some of these elements.  Different types of finance support different types of enterprises at different stages of development.<br />The State has put in place a number of new schemes and initiatives in recent years to address specific issues, such as the credit guarantee scheme introduced in October 2012 and the microfinance loan fund which was also introduced in 2012.  Enterprise Ireland has committed &euro;99.5 million to a new &euro;175 million seed and venture capital scheme which was launched in May last year.  The remit of the Credit Review Office was extended in budget 2014 to increase the threshold by which small and medium enterprises can appeal a refusal from &euro;500,000 to &euro;3 million.<br />The Action Plan for Jobs 2014 sets out a range of additional actions for implementation before the end of the year.  These include collating more detailed data from the banks on lending, particularly new lending; increasing participation in Government-sponsored access to finance initiatives for SMEs, including enhancing the credit guarantee scheme and the micro-enterprise loan fund; raising the level of awareness among SMEs and entrepreneurs on the full suite of Government supports available; and developing new sources of finance for SMEs including European sources.</p> <p>Given the depth of the financial crisis and its legacy impacts on the enterprise sector, the banks and the broader economy, it can be expected that it will be some time before debt levels and funding flows return to what might be regarded as normal levels.  As I noted earlier, it should also be remembers that during the good times small innovative export-oriented businesses had difficulties in accessing the appropriate funding.  </p><p> From the perspective of Forf&aacute;s, some of the key challenges that face Ireland in this regard includes the continuing need to ensure that the efficacy of measures put in place to improve credit flows through recapitalisation, deleveraging and restructuring of the banks can be assessed and further action taken if required.  In this regard, there is a need to continue to monitor bank lending carefully at a detailed level.  This is particularly important as the economy returns to growth and demand for funding increases.</p><p> The State needs to continue to work to ensure that the banking system is aligned with the strategic economic growth targets of the economy.  In this regard, a move towards a banking system with a deeper understanding of innovative sectors is required such as software, telecoms, digital content, medtech and life sciences.  Also, a proactive overseas banking network is required in the medium term.</p><p> More immediately there needs to be a focus on supporting internationally trading businesses in terms of both the provision of credit and banking facilities and products.  The scaling back of the domestic bank sector and the withdrawal of many foreign banks highlights issues over the levels of competition in the banking sector as the business banking market has become more highly concentrated.  A particular challenge exists for SMEs who rely on the banks that are withdrawing from Ireland. </p><p> The programme for Government contained a commitment to establish a strategic investment bank.  Since I submitted my presentation last week the Government has announced the establishment of the strategic banking corporation of Ireland.  The corporation will make &euro;500 million in credit available to SMEs.  It will be important that this mechanism and other mechanisms put in place address the challenges that I have outlined here.  </p><p> Encouraging equity investment represents a mechanism to help some over-indebted but viable businesses to rebalance their balance sheets.  Equity begins from the earliest stage of the business life cycle with friends, family and founders investing at the pre-seed stage to business angels, and venture capitalists investing in the seed and start-up phase right up to the latter stages, through mechanisms such as trade sales and initial public offerings.  Members will already have heard quite a bit about this matter so I will not go into it again in detail.</p><p> The Department of Finance is carrying out a review of the employment and investment incentive scheme and seed capital scheme.  The aim is to ensure it delivers on its potential to support the funding needs of growing enterprises so the outcome of the review will be important.  The State can also support other forms of funding and recently the committee heard from peer-to-peer lenders and businesses that it has supported.  There is strong potential for the State to provide a supportive environment for alternative sources of finance such as these.</p><p> I thank the Chairman and the committee for inviting Forf&aacute;s here today.  My colleagues and I are happy to take any questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700009#H00200"><p>I thank the chief executive.  I forgot to mention and extend a welcome to two members of Forf&aacute;s seated in the Visitors Gallery.  My notes tell me that they are Mr. Andrew Colgan and Ms Aideen Fitzgerald.  I call Senator Quinn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700009#H00300"><p>I want Mr. Shanahan to outline the role of the strategic investment bank.  What does Forf&aacute;s hope will happen?  I am interested to learn more about the figure mentioned by him earlier.  He said that 19% of SME applications in Ireland have been turned down but the percentage is only 12% in the rest of Europe.  Will the discrepancy be solved by the strategic investment bank?  How does Forf&aacute;s see the bank working?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.54" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700009#H00400"><p>There has been a high level announcement but obviously there is a lot more detail to come.  Based on what has been announced to date the fund will provide longer term loans at a lower cost via the existing banking structure, as I understand it, to SMEs.  It is positive measure if it leads to SMEs being able to access lower cost debt for longer durations than they are currently able to access.  The exact details of how it will operate remain to be seen.</p><p>  I wish to clarify that the 19% figure from the ECB survey that I quoted does not just relate to businesses that have been refused a loan.  It incorporates businesses that did not get the loan that they wanted at the cost that they wanted.  Perhaps they were offered loan facilities but not at a rate that they were willing to accept or not for the full amount which they applied for them in the first instance.  </p><p>  It is clear from the ECB survey that the credit environment in Ireland appears to be improving.  However, we are still some way off what one might regard as a normal environment if one take the averages experienced across the rest of Europe as normal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700009#H00500"><p>I wish to comment on the point made about the strategic investment bank and my issue with it is based on a couple of aspects.  We have discussed access to finance with other witnesses and there are banks that have not been lending to the extent that we would have liked them to do so.  Now a fund has been given directly to these high street banks to lend more money but they have not been lending at the levels that we wanted them to reach in the first place.</p><p>  Given what Mr. Shanahan has said in his report, pillar banks need to have a deeper understanding of the new innovative sectors in order for businesses to be sure of success and have loans granted.  The chief executive probably cannot give me the answer to the following questions.  Is it not a mistake to allow high street banks to access and deliver the fund considering they will not give out some of the money?  That is our opinion, which is supported by what we have heard from other witnesses.  Will that be the scheme's downfall?  Will people have to admit in a few months' time that this was a mistake?  Is it not a mistake to give more money to banks that are not doing what we asked them to do already and to the extent that we would like? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700009#H00600"><p>It is very difficult to predict what the outcome will be in the absence of details on how the strategic banking corporation will work.  Therefore, I do not intend to make a premptive comment.</p><p>  Let me respond to the point made by the Vice Chairman.  At the moment one of the issues is that we do not know enough about what the banks are doing in terms of lending, to whom they are lending and in what types of lending in which they are engaged.  We do not know if it is roll-over lending, which is important for existing businesses.  We do not know if it is new lending or what sectors they are not lending to.  We do not have the full picture.</p><p>  It is important to have a detailed understanding of the lending that is taking place, particularly by the banks that the State supports, because the prescription may be different depending on what the picture presents.  For instance, if innovative companies in new sectors are not able to access this funding then making more funding available may not be the answer.  It may be educating those involved in the lending process within those banks.  It may be increasing the level of understanding of both the sectors and cash-flow lending, particularly where there is not a significant amount of collateral available against the credit being sought.  A detailed understanding of what type of lending is taking place is important.  Actions to tackle the matter are contained in this year's action plan but I do not think that we understand the situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700009#H00700"><p>Is the chief executive saying there are enough processes in place to find out how banks are lending?</p> <p>Is he saying that those in place will need more in order to have a full picture of how banks are lending and will lend into the future?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.59" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00200"><p>I may ask my colleague, Mr. Adrian Devitt, to respond.  Certainly, the plan this year was that we would get to a greater level of granularity on exactly what lending is taking place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.60" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Devitt" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00300"><p>It is part of the 2014 plan.  As to whether the existing banks use the funding from the strategic investment bank, I think there will be requirements to ensure the funding is additional, so it simply cannot replace other funds.  Also there will be requirements to ensure that businesses get the value of the lower cost of the credit.  The banks cannot take that margin.  There will be a strong focus on additionality and making sure the funds are passed through.  There is also a goal that if this entity can offer long-term credit at lower costs that one can go to the market and to external banks or, perhaps, more niche credit providers, and ask them to Ireland where there are funds available on which they can draw to serve the Irish market.  Hopefully, it reduces a barrier to entry and, perhaps, we may see new entrants coming in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00400"><p>I call Deputy Anthony Lawlor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00500"><p>I wish to raise a couple of points one of which the representatives touched on in their presentations, that is, the cost of funding which SMEs have raised with me.  Based on the figures presented, some 83% of people who make application for money get money but the problem is that the cost of it is becoming prohibitive.  In terms of the new banking entity, is that one of the conditions that will be raised by the representatives?  It was mentioned earlier that funding is being provided to banks.  Could that funding be provided at a lower rate than is being provided by themselves because SMEs are squeezed on all the margins?</p><p>  An objective of the Action Plan for Jobs is a portal for SMEs whereby SMEs, entrepreneurs or people seeking finance can click on something and see what is available.  We have been asking about this for the past two years but nothing has happened on it.  If it is lost in the Department of the Taoiseach somebody should pull it out because it is vital that it happens.  There are many products available for SMEs but they do not know where to go for them.  The one portal would help them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00600"><p>Sorry, Deputy, on the second point I am almost sure that portal is up and running.  I have accessed a new piece on my telephone but I will allow Mr. Martin Shanahan to speak about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00700"><p>It is something we have not been told about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00800"><p>I will answer the questions in reverse order.  First, the new portal on which SMEs can seek to find out what supports are available to them was launched the week before last, if I am not mistaken</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J00900"><p>It is was in the middle of other things.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01000"><p>I understand, Deputy.  I may ask my colleague, Ms Maria Ginnity, to comment on it and what it does.  As the Deputy rightly points out, the cost of finance in Ireland is higher than elsewhere.  Some 31% higher is the estimate for loans up to &euro;1 million and 27% higher for loans that exceed &euro;1 million.  To be fair, the Department of Finance is best placed to comment on what will happen around the strategic banking corporation but it is clear from what has already been announced that one of the intentions is to reduce the cost of finance to the ultimate recipient, that being the SME.  We have yet to see the detail of how that will work through the credit institutions that will act as intermediaries for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01100"><p>I call Ms Maria Ginnity to speak on portal.  We got nothing official on it.  Perhaps she would say how it is going to be promoted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01200"><p>That is my point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.70" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Maria Ginnity" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01300"><p>The establishment of the local enterprise offices, LEOs, will play an important role in enhancing the supports available to all small firms.  They will provide a first-stop-shop to signpost firms to direct supports both financial supports and advisory services.  Within each of the LEOs an SME online tool is available.  It is relatively simple to use.  It asks the company to answer eight questions which will be around the sector in which it is involved, its scale, its market orientations and will signpost it to either the direct agency or the supports that are more relevant to it.  It is very much a signposting tool but easy to use electronically.  There is that online tool in the first instance and, second, the LEO offices acting as the first port of call for all small entities is an important step in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01400"><p>What is the name of the portal?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01500"><p>It is<i>localenterprise.ie</i>and from there one goes to one local enterprise office.  The question I have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01600"><p>This is creating another layer of bureaucracy.  Can I, as an ordinary Joe Soap, click onto something where I can find out everything rather than having to go through a LEO?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.74" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01800"><p>May I have the details please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J01900"><p>It is <i>localenterprise.ie</i>.  I do not want to put it on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.77" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02000"><p>We will forward it to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02100"><p>I think it is in this paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.79" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02200"><p>If it is not, we will forward it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02300"><p>The question to Ms Maria Ginnity, for which she may not be directly responsible but on which she may be able to shed some light, is on a one-stop shop where people can access information that may be of help in supporting their business.  Any private industry that is trying to promote a new commodity has a decent advertising campaign.  Where are we at in respect of an advertising campaign of this new one-stop shop online portal?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.81" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02400"><p>The need for this is probably recognised.  I am not sure if I can answer exactly what the plan is today.  It is a point we have made a number of times and there is a commitment in the Action Plan for Jobs around promoting the supports available.  The State has significant supports for businesses at all stages of development and for all types of business but if people are not being aware of them that is not the best use of State resources.  The new initiative is broader than SMEs.  It is about all the different supports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02500"><p>Is this nothing more than a rehash?  Sometimes the problem is not a lack of ideas and responses.  Sometimes when there are new ideas or ways to promote or support, say, SMEs the budget line that is needed to promote any other commodity or concept does not follow.  We have heard from our meetings here, and it is important for Forf&aacute;s to hear this to advise the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation in case it does not listen to the committee, that there must be a budget line to promote these through an effective advertising campaign in order that the right people get to hear these things.  That must be part of any new strategy, whether it be the Department of Social Protection in terms of an initiative to support taking on new people for labour activation measures or, in this case, directly supporting SMEs.  Deputy Anthony Lawlor got it right when he said he did not know about it.  I barely knew about it, having come across it by accident.  I do not know what hope SMEs have as such but there must be a decent budget line that reflects the work being done to promote supports so that SMEs can access them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.83" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Devitt" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02600"><p>It is really an application rather than a website.  The goal is to encourage every relevant State body and private sector bodies, chambers, ISME and others to place this app on their website so it can be used from there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02700"><p>With all due respect I am app friendly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02800"><p>With all due respect, an advertising campaign with a person with an advertising background is needed to promote the issue, because that website does not work.  Depending on the chamber, its website may not be sufficiently updated.  We are talking about the way a product is promoted such as in a supermarket store where it becomes popular and well known.  Unless we are at the races-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700010#J02900"><p>Superquinn sausages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00100"><p>There we go - Superquinn sausages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00200"><p>I will not have to say any more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00300"><p>That is what is needed.  It seems to be a missing chink all the time in new initiatives that come out.  I am sorry to beat the band there as such.</p><p>  Does Deputy Conaghan have any comments before we wrap up?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00400"><p>I will not introduce another rant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00500"><p>Are there any final comments before we wrap up because we have another session after this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.92" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Shanahan" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00600"><p>I thank the committee for its time and interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00700"><p>I thank Mr. Shanahan, Ms Ginnity and Mr. Devitt and the other representatives from Forf&aacute;s.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00800"><p>I ask them to pass on the app to us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K00900"><p>I propose that the committee go into private session for a minute or so.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.96" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 3 p.m. and resumed in public session at 3.06 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.97" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K01100">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K01200"><p>We are now in public session.  Session three is a meeting with Mr. Paul Cullen, principal officer, from the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, to discuss COM (2014) 221.  It is a proposal for a decision of the European Parliament and of the Council on establishing a European platform to enhance co-operation in the prevention and deterrence of undeclared work.  Members will recall that, at our meeting on 13 May, it was agreed to scrutinise it further.<br />I welcome Mr. Cullen to the meeting.  In accordance with procedure, I am required to inform him of the following.  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  For the third time today, I remind members of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.  I could almost recite that without looking at it.<br />I call on Mr. Cullen to make his presentation to the committee.  There will be a short opportunity for any questions, if necessary afterwards, from members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.99" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Cullen" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700011#K01300"><p>We submitted information to the joint committee in the form of the standard Oireachtas scrutiny note in April and when we learned that the committee was intending to proceed to further scrutiny, we sent it a more detailed written submission.</p><p>  In that submission, we addressed five areas that we thought would be relevant to the subsidiarity check that the committee has embarked upon.  First, we addressed the issue of the legal basis chosen by the Commission and the question as to whether the EU is competent to act on the basis of Article 153 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.  We point out that the Government does not have any objection to the use of Article 153(2) as the legal basis for the establishment of this platform.  This legal basis is also viewed by the Council legal service and by a large majority of the member states to be an appropriate legal basis for this proposal.</p><p>  Second, we looked at whether the kind of action proposed is consistent with the principle of subsidiarity.  We would point out that the objective of the proposed platform is to facilitate, promote, encourage and support co-operation among the member states rather than the introduction of any specific binding agreements or harmonisation of laws.  We are satisfied that all operational aspects of the measures that might be taken to combat undeclared work would remain exclusively within the competence of the member states involved and we have noted that the committee's counterpart scrutiny committees within the legislatures of Sweden and Poland, which are not without their picky approach to these matters on occasions, have already concluded that the proposal does not infringe the principle of subsidiarity.</p> <p> Third, we considered whether the action proposed is proportionate to the objectives the draft decision seeks to achieve.  We are satisfied that the proposed platform does not go beyond the range of activities, all of which are undertaken by member states on a voluntary basis, set out in the instrument and that any measures adopted would exclude harmonisation of laws and regulations of member states.  Fourth, we considered whether the action proposed could adversely affect national competence in the fields of social protection and taxation, and we have concluded that the proposed instrument would not impinge on national competence in the fields of social security, taxation policy or operational practice in that regard.  Finally, we looked at the transnational dimension to tackling undeclared work.  We note that the emphasis the European Parliament and the International Labour Organization have placed on promoting enhanced co-operation at EU level, especially through transnational exchanges of information and mutual learning between enforcement authorities in a bid to fight undeclared work.</p><p> The Irish experience of multi-agency co-operation and data sharing between different state authorities and the mechanisms established for them to work together with other labour market actors has already attracted a high level of interest especially among eastern European member states, as did the fact that the co-operation here extends across the Border through a cross-Border operational forum.</p><p> Counteracting undeclared work can create a better level playing field for businesses and improve the quality of employment.  We consider that in the light of the complexity and the heterogeneity of informal or undeclared work and the diversity of circumstances within the member states that there can be simple solution to tackling this problem.  The traditional mechanisms and resources employed by the enforcement authorities are best suited to tackling, mainly, domestic aspects of undeclared work.  The international dimension of undeclared is, however, a reality.  As a consequence of the free movement of services and workers, the effects of non-compliance with national legislation can influence businesses, societies and governments beyond a single country's borders.</p><p> We welcome the development of common concepts, measurement tools and the promotion of joint comparative analysis.  We are concerned that the World Bank estimates used by the Commission, along with many other sources, in its impact assessment seriously overstates the problem in Ireland.  The results for Ireland from the Eurobarometer direct survey undertaken last year of the general population's personal experiences of undeclared work are useful as a counterbalance to some of the problematic indirect methods used by the World Bank in this instance to estimate the size of the black economy.  It is interesting to note from the survey last year that Irish respondents were half as likely as the EU average to say that they had undertaken undeclared paid work in the previous 12 months.  Ireland had one of the highest proportion of respondents, 47%, who thought that people who worked without declaring their income ran a fairly high risk of tax or social security institutions finding them out and issuing supplementary tax bills or fines.  In our view, action at EU level is justified in order to enhance co-operation between the responsible national authorities such as labour inspectorates, social security and tax authorities, in particular, enabling them to exchange information and best practices, analyse common problems and so on in the effort to deter undeclared work.</p><p> The Irish Government considers that a European platform on the lines proposed would be an appropriate vehicle for practical voluntarily agreed activities and shared studies undertaken on the basis of co-operation between the Commission and member states.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00200"><p>I thank Mr. Paul Cullen.  We had hear from Mr. Cullen that the particular COM does not involve any harmonisation and does not infringe on subsidiarity.  Are there any short questions for Mr. Cullen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00300"><p>One of the issues we heard about was cross-Border movement, in other words a person who is registered in the North and comes across the Border to work without declaring, or the other way round, people here going North.  Is that a particular problem?  From what Mr. Cullen has said it does not appear to be in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Cullen" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00400"><p>There have been instances.  It has tended to be more from the North to the South and in the context, heretofore, of public procurement as well.  Consequently, there has been a tightening in the context of the social procurement arrangements for the new school building programme and much closer vetting in that instance.  The problem, and it is shared between the Northern Ireland authorities and ourselves, is that the work undertaken might be undeclared and unregistered, either North or South, for tax purposes.  However, the existence of a memorandum of understanding between the authorities North and South, and a forum the social security authorities North and South have established, is already an exemplar for practice between other countries but in that instance the practical focus tends to be country to country in a bilateral arrangement rather than more broadly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00500"><p>That makes sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00600"><p>Can Mr. Cullen explain the reason for the move from it being voluntary to mandatory as a platform?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.106" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Cullen" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00700"><p>We have had an instance of this already in the past year where, springing from work initially undertaken during the Irish Presidency, a decision was made on establishing a network of public employment services.  In these instances there is a degree of ambiguity.  Everybody was in favour of being party to it but they did not like the idea that the claims being made for the legal base were such that a decision is binding on all member states.  The decision to establish the platform, therefore, is binding but what is done within it is not.  In this instance we distinguished between the nature of the platform which will embrace all 28 member states and the activities they then decide to do, whether it is to produce guidelines or undertake particular studies.  Only the willing will engage in those actions and in that sense the decision to establish the platform is mandatory.  The Commission is asking the Council to take the decision to establish the platform.  The Commission cannot wriggle out of it; it is mandatory.  All member states will be engaged.  What they do is then-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00800"><p>Is Mr. Cullen saying that although we support this, if Ireland decided not to attend the platform, it can voluntary not attend it but it must endorse it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.108" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Cullen" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L00900"><p>No.  To put it another way, we do not have to take any decision to attend because our attendance is assumed to be necessary and part of the mandatory decision.  We are in the club.  Whether we decide to organise a particular night out in that club is up to us.  The activity we do is voluntary; being there is mandatory.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L01000"><p>I understand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.110" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Cullen" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L01100"><p>In our view, from the point of view of addressing some of the problems and the nature of the problems, it would not be particularly attractive to us if our immediate neighbour was not part of this, therefore, to some extent we are quite relaxed about the idea that it is mandatory.  We are thoroughly in favour of it then being up to all the people to subscribe to any actions that are taken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2014052700012#L01200"><p>Any final questions?  I thank Paul Cullen and Dermot Sheridan for attending and providing us with the comprehensive briefing.</p><p>  Are members agreed that this concludes the scrutiny of COM (2014) 221?  Agreed.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.112" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 3.19 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 3 June 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.113" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.114" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Eric Byrne, Senator Kathryn Reilly. Deputy Bernard J. Durkan, Deputy Seán Kyne,</p><p>DEPUTY DOMINIC HANNIGAN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.116" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700002#A00200"><p>The purpose of this meeting is to discuss the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, with the Minister, Deputy Bruton.  As a number of apologies have been received today the joint committee has a reduced membership in attendance for this meeting.  I thank the Minister for his attendance.  I remind members, guests and witnesses to turn off their mobile telephones, which interfere with the broadcasting equipment.  I note someone's telephone is switched on because I can already hear some background disturbance.  Mine is switched off and I ask everyone to check.  It is not sufficient to leave them in silent mode as they need to be switched off.  I would appreciate it were everyone present to do that now.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.118" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700002#A00300">Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership: Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700002#A00400"><p>The item on the joint committee's agenda today is the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership and members are delighted to welcome to the meeting the Minister, Deputy Bruton.  Members will be aware that the European Commission, on behalf of the member states, is negotiating a trade and investment agreement with the United States of America.  The Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership agreement, known to everyone as TTIP, is designed to drive growth and create jobs in both jurisdictions by boosting economic activity by making it easier to buy or sell goods and services between the European Union and United States of America.  Negotiations on the agreement opened last July and the fifth round of talks concluded last week in the United States.  As I stated, members are joined by the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, who will brief members on the opportunities and challenges of TTIP for Irish citizens, European citizens and companies.  The Irish Government's position on TTIP also will be discussed this afternoon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700002#A00500"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for the invitation to say a few words on TTIP and hopefully to take questions from members to the best of my ability.  During Ireland's Presidency last June, an agreement was achieved at the European Council to start negotiations on a trade and investment agreement with the United States.  It was an historic agreement and clearly for Ireland, with its deep involvement with the United States over many years, seeing it to its conclusion was something in which we had a significant interest.  A recommendation and a mandate were given to the European Commissioner, Commissioner De Gucht, to commence negotiations.  The disposition was that we should seek to be ambitious in three broad areas.  The first was market access, which basically is about tariffs and obstacles that stand in the way.  The second concerned rules addressing shared global trade challenges and opportunities and the third was in respect of regulatory non-tariff barriers.</p><p>  Since the Council's decision, five negotiating rounds have taken place, the most recent one being last week in the United States.  As I stated, three areas are involved.  The area of market access concerns goods and services and public procurement.  The first tariff offers, that is, the immediate or phased elimination of import tariffs on an extensive list of goods, were exchanged earlier this year and I expect there will be further work on these offers.  They exclude food and agriculture, so it pertains to non-food goods.  As for services, I understand the United States tabled its first offer last week.</p> <p>The EU side is still working on its first offer but expects to have it ready soon.  I understand that in depth negotiations took place last week on procurement but we do not yet have the details from the Commission.</p><p> The second broad category comprises rules on trade facilitation relating to the customs systems between the EU and the US; rules on state-owned enterprises, which should operate along commercial lines - in other words, they should not be subsidised to enter into other markets; rules on raw materials and energy, in respect of which the EU is looking for access to US oil and gas exports, which are currently restricted; and rules on labour and environment, in respect of which there will be no weakening of standards or protections.  Coming to agreement in these areas will also serve to set standards for other free trade agreements with trading partners, reduce complexity for small companies and generally open markets in a more transparent manner.</p><p> The most difficult and complex, but perhaps the most important, aspect of the negotiations is on reducing regulatory burdens.  This will involve a multiplicity of sectoral legislation, particularly in areas like financial services, the environment, health and public safety.  While there are legitimate but unfounded concerns about lowering regulatory standards, the goal is to maintain high standards of public protection while finding a way to prevent them from representing unacceptable barriers to trade.  This would involve issues such as mutual recognition of the way in which one assesses a product.  The pharma sector is a good example, in respect of which we could avoid the necessity to run trials on the same product in the EU and the US in order to give it recognition.  Mutual recognition would open up possibilities in that regard.</p><p> Progress in respect of regulation through harmonisation, mutual recognition or convergence is the most important area because the results of studies show it will yield the biggest net gains.  The Commission's impact assessment suggests that between two thirds and four fifths of the gains from a future agreement will come from cutting red tape and having more co-ordination between regulators.  It is important to see this as a two part issue, involving both the process of how regulation is enacted and the sector specific solutions being negotiated.  How regulations are made needs to be more transparent, with regulators deepening their relationships in order to address emerging issues together.  In addition, real progress on issues like car safety standards and ending double inspections at pharmaceutical and medical device plants should reduce costs for both businesses and regulators.  Implementing agreed international finance rules in a compatible way is an example of how immediate and positive impacts can be achieved for EU and US economies as agreements are reached.  Bringing about regulatory convergence will help exporters and investors by reducing the cost of doing business across the Atlantic.  It will make it easier for companies to comply with US and EU laws at the same time.  Extending the scope of mutual recognition across many professional bodies, for example, would make it easier for professionals to source new job opportunities on both sides of the Atlantic.</p><p> It is important to note that while regulatory aspects are one of the main elements of the TTIP negotiations, nothing in the negotiations would prevent or undermine the rights of both sides to regulate and the level of regulatory protection on both sides, whether in respect of the environment, food or consumer safety.  The European Commission is acutely conscious of the need to engage widely with stakeholders in these negotiations and it is doing so in a number of ways, including stakeholder briefing sessions during and following each round of negotiations, a dedicated TTIP website, a specific public consultation on investment protection, which may be of interest to the committee, and the establishment of a special advisory group.  During last week's round in the US, the lead negotiators from the EU and the US held a stakeholder meeting involving a wide range of interest groups from business to consumers, and trade unions to environmental and health NGOs, as well as representatives of US states.  I understand that more than 75 stakeholder presentations were made during that meeting.  The next such stakeholder meeting is planned for 3 June and will take place in Brussels.  The TTIP website contains comprehensive information about the negotiations, including the EU's initial position papers published last year and the more recent EU sectoral proposals in the areas of chemicals, cosmetics, motor vehicles, pharmaceutical products and textiles and clothing.  These proposals set out ideas for enhancing the compatibility of existing rules and regulations on both sides and for working more closely together on setting them in the future.  In each sector the papers focus on ways to end the unnecessary duplication of product testing and plant inspections, to recognise each other's existing regulations, to bring them more closely together and to align the respective procedures for approving or registering new products.</p><p> The Commission has proposed a specific chapter in TTIP aimed at small and medium enterprises.  I understand there was some discussion of this during last week's round.  The Commission has produced a brochure which highlights the opportunities for SMEs from the agreement.  The brochure, which can be found from the TTIP website, includes several small company success stories.  I do not doubt that we could all add a few more examples of success stories of small businesses that are making inroads into the US market.  The idea behind the specific focus on SMEs is to create many more opportunities.  TTIP should create new opportunities for SMEs to do business not only in the area of goods, but also in services, including professional services.  Improving the coherence of rules and rule making, including standards, would have a multiplier effect for SMEs and create opportunities by opening up even niche areas of procurement.  Even in areas like customs procedures, SMEs can make large savings from small changes in regulations when considering exporting.</p><p> The advisory group set up by the Commission comprises representation from all stakeholders, including agriculture, business services, consumers, trade unions and NGOs.  The group has thus far met on two occasions and the topics covered to date include regulatory coherence, sectors, investment protection, investor-state dispute settlement and sustainable development.  The reports of these stakeholder meetings can also be found at the Commission's TTIP website.</p><p> The TTIP negotiations have been the subject of negative comments in some quarters.  One of the main issues giving rise to disquiet is investment protection provisions, particularly in respect of investor-state dispute settlements, ISDS.  In regard to the proposal that companies will have the right to seek redress from expropriation or discriminatory policies through international arbitration rather than the courts system, fears have been expressed that companies will use this mechanism to change the regulatory direction of public policy.  Last January, Commissioner De Gucht announced his decision to consult the public on the investment provisions of a future deal on TTIP.  That public consultation opened on 27 March and will run until 6 July.  As part of the consultation, the Commission published a proposed EU text for the investment part of the talks, which includes sections on investment protection and the ISDS.  All stakeholders will have the opportunity to respond to this consultation so that specific interests and concerns about investor protection and settlement of related disputes are well understood by the European Commission and can be used to better define the EU's approach to investor protection in the TTIP negotiations.</p><p> Assessments made by the Commission and other studies show that a comprehensive agreement could, over time, boost EU GDP by 0.5%.  Given the current low level of economic growth in the EU and Ireland, this agreement will provide a significant injection of economic activity and, consequently, new job opportunities.  Based on these assessments, if Ireland simply benefited in proportion to the size of our economy within the EU, a comprehensive trade and investment partnership could over time provide gains to Ireland in the order of &euro;800 million per annum in increased GDP and 4,000 new jobs.</p><p> Ireland has a close trading and investment relationship with the US and, in addition, many Irish exporters are part of European supply chains, whereby exports to the UK, Germany and elsewhere in the EU feed into Europe's exports to the US.  The TTIP is, therefore, a stimulus for longer term economic growth and jobs in Ireland.  Members should have received invitations to a conference in Dublin Castle on 20 June on the topic of TTIP opportunities for Ireland.</p> <p>The target audience of the conference is political and senior executive level across Departments, agencies, regulators and representative organisations.  The line-up of speakers for the morning includes the EU chief negotiator with the US, Copenhagen Economics, a consultancy firm engaged by my Department to carry out a study of the economic impacts on Ireland of such a trade agreement and a panel of respondents from industry and regulators.  I hope members will be able to attend.</p><p> The aim of the TTIP negotiations was that it should be concluded within 18 to 20 months from its beginning last July.  This is an ambitious timetable.  More recent public statements suggest it will be more likely towards the end of 2015.  The aim is also that the TTIP will be a living agreement to provide the necessary space for dealing with more difficult issues and the mechanisms for jointly addressing any new trade and investment-rated issues that may arise.</p><p> We have circulated a note to members and I am happy to take any questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700004#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  It seems that excellent progress has been made.  We are very keen that this agreement will generate additional jobs in our country.  I have two questions about jobs at European level and at local level.  Is there a risk that jobs in large car production companies in Germany and France might be in danger because of an increase in the number of American cars coming into European markets?  I have in mind the potential for flooding the market.  The American car industry was rescued by President Obama a few years ago to the tune of $50 billion - I am not sure of the exact amount - in terms of public subsidies.  Will safeguards be in place to ensure that there will be no flooding of the European market by American car producers as this would impact on German and French jobs with a knock-on effect on the European economy?</p><p>  My second question is about Irish jobs.  One of the criticisms and complaints during the most recent election campaign and which is voiced at constituency clinics is the concern that many Irish companies are losing out to European counterparts because of public procurement rules.  What safeguards will be in place to ensure that Irish companies are not put at a disadvantage in the domestic market if American companies come in?  What can be done with regard to public procurement rules to ensure that while competition remains in the Irish procurement market, that there is not an excessive input of American companies which will take jobs and contracts away from Irish companies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700004#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister for his attendance and I thank the Chairman for starting the debate.  We have heard something about the TTIP, transatlantic trade and investment partnership and it helps to study the briefing documentation.  I have done my best to analyse it.  If I was naive I would wonder why this project is not being fast-tracked because I am reading that it will be of great benefit to the country and to Europe.  It would be an excellent political slogan to be able to say to electors that the benefit for supporting it would be &euro;545 in disposable income for each family of four in the EU.  There are many other attractions presented to us.  These enthusiastic figures show income gains as a result of increased EU trade and an increase in European exports to the United States by 28%, the equivalent of an additional &euro;187 billion worth of exports to America.  These are very compelling statistics which seem to be based on the Centre for Economic Policy Research in London.  We are an independent entity within Europe.  Has the Minister's Department analysed those findings of the Centre for Economic Policy Research with a view to confirming the veracity or otherwise of the glowing statements about the benefits of signing the agreement?  We are told that the programme will protect the health, environment and consumer protection rights of Europeans and that these will not be diluted in any way by virtue of this agreement.</p><p>  The Irish Medicines Board has an American equivalent.  The pharmaceutical industry in this country must undergo stringent analysis and examination of the methodologies they use.  Companies located here who export to America are subject to intensive scrutiny to find flaws.  If the Irish Medicines Board wants to maintain our high standards and the TTIP is a project negotiated by the EU, what is our position as an independent nation within the 28 member states when it comes to the standards of other European countries?  It is argued that the Irish Medicines Board is one of the most stringent regulators in the field.  If our standards are very high compared with, for instance, Lithuania or Estonia or some other European country, what is the red line that the European Commission is adopting on standards?  Will Ireland as a nation state be required to lower its standards in order to find the average within Europe?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700004#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister for his presentation to the committee.  Why is the food industry excluded from this part of the discussions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700004#C00500"><p>On a point of clarification, it is not excluded, rather it has not been included in the first exchange of offers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700004#C00600"><p>The question continues as to why it had not been included in the first range of issues.  We have a particular interest in the food industry because Ireland is a net food exporter.  How can we be assured that further stages in the negotiations do not erode the position of food industry exports which are of significant importance to our economy?  I refer to previous experiences in transatlantic negotiations when, after the event, the food sector was used in a trade-off against other products from Europe, such as cars from Germany, Italy, France, Spain, at the cost of the food sector throughout Europe.  What countries are represented on the EU negotiating team?  The Minister has indicated that the team is comprised of EU officials at this stage.  Where do they come from?  They did not just pop out of the EU without having a background from a member country.  Could the team members be all from a single member state or from two countries?  Which might those countries be?  Could their nationality have any impact on the outcome of the discussions?</p><p>  The Minister made a number of references to the stakeholders.</p> <p>I presume these stakeholders are representative of industry on both sides of the Atlantic.  To what extent has it been ascertained what these stakeholders are representing?  Do they represent the national interest, the European interest or a combination of both?  I would like to know a little more about the breakdown in this regard.</p><p> In respect of market access, all of this is of course to no avail unless it is a two-way process, that is, market access must work in both directions in all sorts of situations.  To what extent have the negotiations thus far indicated that such market access will be honoured in the spirit as well as the letter?  When will we see the benefits therefrom?  My final point pertains to regulation.  Regulations are the famous apparatus people can use to undermine or prevent an agreement.  Regulations can make an agreement impossible to operate or can include or exclude some parts of the agreement already entered into, depending on what they are.  Is the Minister satisfied that the tangent of the negotiations to date indicates in a meaningful way a recognition of the need to ensure that member states throughout the European Union, without exception, will benefit from the negotiations and have equal access to the market?  Alternatively, do the negotiations indicate whether one or more influential states within the Union are likely to be the greater beneficiaries?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700005#D00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and his officials and apologise for missing the beginning of the presentation while at another committee meeting.  I have a couple of issues, the first of which is to ask why now, whether this the right time or has this initiative been in train for a number of years?  Other speakers have touched on the issue of food, which is of huge importance to Ireland.  I have raised the issue of standards at either this committee or the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation - I am unsure which - and a reassurance was given that there would be no lessening of standards in any discussions on GM food, hormone-treated beef and bovine somatotropin-injected cows producing milk in the United States.  While I am sure this is the case, the Minister might comment on this subject.</p><p>  As Deputy Eric Byrne has noted, this appears on paper to have huge potential.  The European Commission's economic analysis suggests that the benefits for the European Union and the US would not be at the expense of the rest of the world but estimates the increase in GDP in the rest of the world would be almost &euro;100 billion.  How is it envisaged that this will happen?  If the European Union is exporting more to the United States, presumably other countries would be exporting less to it.  Similarly, if the United States is exporting more to the European Union, there therefore would be less room for other countries to export here.  From where does this &euro;100 billion come?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700005#D00300"><p>I thank the Deputy and invite the Minister to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700005#D00400"><p>Quite a number of questions have been asked.  In respect of the car industry, it is probably an area in which Europe is looking to opportunities in the United States market rather than losing out.  It is an area in which it is stated that we have an offensive interest and in which there are opportunities.  However, guarantees have been built into the Japanese or Korean agreements, for example, to prevent the flooding of product as raised by the Chairman.  In general, protections and safeguards are built into sensitive sectors such as the automobile sector and this has been a feature of the existing trade agreements.<br />On the public procurement rules, it is an issue that will be quite difficult in the United States, which I suppose is why it is not in the first round, because the United States has different procurement rules in different states within the federation.  Consequently, local rules apply and this is an area in which we obviously are seeking to get mutual reduction in barriers in order that US companies could trade in Europe and <i>vice versa</i>.  A fully open tender system is in operation within the European Union and consequently, one cannot discriminate.  Above a certain standard, there must be an open, published tender and one cannot apply discriminatory rules to favour one side or another although, as members are aware, one can have social clauses that might unemployed people, apprentices or whatever.  It is unlikely that such a level of openness will be reached in a negotiation of this nature.  However, one would be hoping to bring down barriers in order to enable people to have opportunities in this regard.  I refer in particular to Irish companies that have won interesting software applications in public procurement contracts within the European Union and elsewhere and one would hope similar benefits could be achieved by seeing a reduction in barriers in the US.  There would be some cases in which there would be a &quot;buy American only&quot; policy or whatever and clearly, it is in our interests to bring down barriers on both sides.  On that issue of the state versus the federation, it arose in the Canadian agreement and was an issue that took longer to unravel, that is, to get all the provinces within Canada to sign up to a set of common rules.<br />Deputy Eric Byrne raised the issue of how does one measure the benefits.  Obviously, economic models are used and while one always can criticise the assumptions that are made, these models consider the level of trade barriers and evaluate tariffs.  In the case of tariffs, they are not very high and I believe they are at a maximum of approximately 3%.  However, non-trade barriers can be very high and can be up to 20% in some sectors.  The models evaluate how big are the barriers, examine how trade flows could change as a result of that and then ascertain what are the benefits.  As the Deputy noted, assessments have been carried out at EU-wide level but as I stated in my remarks, this is why the Government has commissioned some work to drill down to the Irish situation to conduct an evaluation of the impact in Ireland.  In general, the Government envisages bigger gains comparatively for Ireland because we have fairly strong trading relationships with the United States and there would be opportunities for Ireland on foot of a reduction in barriers.  We have the familiarity of trading in the United States, a common language and a lot of already-built common trading relationships.  Therefore, one would hope to see better opportunities coming for Ireland.<br />The approach being taken by the European Union to public policy standards is to have no diminution of existing public policy standards.  This is not an issue of the European Union seeking to negotiate away any public protection that it has put in place but is to maintain standards.  I must revert to the joint committee on the extent to which Irish standards differ from European Union standards.  In general, EU recognition is what a medical device or pharmaceutical company seeks to achieve because it can then trade throughout the European Union.  Obviously, we seek to protect both sets of standards.  The United States will seek to protect whatever is its public policy in the same way as we in the European Union will seek to protect ours.  It may be easier to see this point in respect of the food sector, where the European Union has total bans on hormones and a fixed policy on GM that it does not intend to change in any way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700005#D00500"><p>May I ask a brief question in this regard?  I cited the Irish Medicines Board but what is the point of having an Irish Medicines Board, for example, if the European Union norm of standards is the established norm?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700005#D00600"><p>To allow a product to be approved to a standard, one needs a body to vet that this standard is being achieved.  However, I will revert to the Deputy on whether there are cases in which Ireland has different standards from the European Union.  In general, however, if an organisation comes to Ireland to produce a medical device, it will seek to get approval in Ireland but will want that approval to carry to the other 27 member states.  It will not wish to have approval just in Ireland and to be unable to go any further with the product.  While what regulators do is to approve to a standard, the hope is that if both the European Union and the US have certain expectations of a product and have a certain way of measuring the extent to which those expectations are being met, we will accept each other's measurements of where the product is on the spectrum.</p> <p>It is not that we would seek to reduce the cut-off point but that we would not require a measurement that has already been done through, say, clinical trials, to be repeated at significant cost.  It would also mean that regulators would have similar vetting procedures over time.  Having similar procedures in place allows for more opportunity for mutual recognition and reduced costs.  There is no intention to dilute public policy in this regard.</p><p> The reason food is not included in these negotiations is because it is one of the most contentious areas.  It was very contentious in the negotiations of the EU-Canadian partnership but agreement was reached in the end with greater access for European dairy products to the Canadian market and Canadian beef products to European markets.  This will be a hotly contested area and the stakeholders include those in primary production.</p><p> The European Commissioner for Trade, Karel De Gucht, will conduct the negotiations along with his directorate-general and the Directorate-General for Agriculture and Rural Development.  Their staff are drawn from across the European Union, not from one nationality - the trade Commissioner is Belgian - and they report weekly to the trade policy committee which is made up of officials from member states.  Mr. Gerard Monks is our representative on that committee.  The negotiators work on a mandate from the Council and report back to it.  Under European treaties, it is the Commission which negotiates trade agreements, not member states.  Every country, accordingly, ensures its interests are represented in negotiations.  When we negotiated the mandate, the specific issue around the recognition of cultural exceptions and diversity, a point which one would want to protect in any trade negotiations, was raised which caused disagreement across member states and had to be brokered.</p><p> The general European view is that we struggle for growth in the Union while up to 90% of future growth in the world economy will be outside of it.  Accordingly, we need trade agreements with growth economies such as the US, Japan, Korea, India and so forth.  Long-term European economic growth will be boosted if we can negotiate trade agreements.  Overall, it is reckoned that an additional 2% of gross domestic product could be obtained from such agreements with potential partners.</p><p> They have to be two-way agreements with mutual gains on both sides or else states will not sign up to them.  They are about bringing down barriers on both sides to ensure equal benefit to both.  There is a complaints mechanism if signatories feel the rules are not being applied.</p><p> Deputy Kyne asked why now.  It is the growth issue and the need for Europe to rebuild its economy.  Many European internal economies are going through fiscal correction and are not dynamic growth markets.  Clearly, there is an interest in the EU to getting better access to trading in other parts of the world where there is greater growth.</p><p> There will be no change in European policy on GM, genetically modified food, while the complete ban on hormone-treated beef and other meat will remain.</p><p> Progress in world trade negotiations on multilateral trade agreements has been virtually non-existent for the past decade.  In the Indonesian round last year, there were some modest changes.  That is why there have been more of these bilateral trade agreements.  If Europe starts to negotiate bilateral agreements, will it have an adverse effect on other trading partners, third countries?  Research showed it did not and that there were more growth opportunities than a displacement effect for third countries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700006#E00200"><p>When will the impact study of TTIP, transatlantic trade and investment partnership, on Ireland be completed and released?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700006#E00300"><p>It is expected in September but we will give some outlines in June.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700006#E00400"><p>Will that deadline be extended, bearing in mind the agreement will not be concluded before the end of next year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700006#E00500"><p>No, this study is more about giving a framework so that we know the areas of greatest potential gain for Ireland and, accordingly, we can ensure our negotiators concentrate on these.  This will not be a static study but one to give us ammunition so as to be active in the negotiation process.  For example, Ireland has large pharmaceutical and medical devices manufacturing sectors.  One would expect significant benefits for Irish-based companies if we can bring down some of the costs of mutual recognition.  This is the sort of information we would quantify and give us ammunition in discussions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700006#E00600"><p>One of the possible barriers to freeing up trade is what is referred to in some countries as red tape.  I call it bureaucracy.  For example, it has been a growth industry in this country, as well as in the EU and the US for some years.  A one-page document some years ago has been fattened up to 25 pages as members all know from dealing with local authorities and government institutions.  To what extent will bureaucracy be multiplied and used as a barrier in impeding progress in freeing up trade between the EU and the US?  On which side of the Atlantic is the greatest threat from this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700006#E00700"><p>The area of greatest potential benefit in the long term is if we move towards having more mutual recognition.  Tariffs are in and around 3% of costs, give or take.  Some non-trade barriers are in around 20% of costs.  While one cannot put a percentage on regulatory and red tape costs, if one gets mutual recognition for the setting of standards, over time the costs will come down.</p> <p>When jam used to come in 13 oz jars in one country and 12 oz jars in another country, to export jam to Europe one needed a different jar for each country, which killed trade opportunities.  When everybody agrees it is safe to eat jam from a 12 oz jar, for example, one opens up trade.  Many long-term benefits come from setting rules, and they exist in all areas, including customs, intellectual property protection, public procurement terms, environment, safety and sanitary issues.  They are very much apparent in financial services, which is probably a sensitive area because it includes wider prudential issues.  One does not seek to dilute any such safeguards of public policy objectives but to set them such that it is easy for people from other countries to comply and without red tape barriers that make it difficult.  That is why people on both sides have spoken about this being a dynamic agreement.  One does not just sign up and forget about it.  Rather, over time the regulatory systems would tend to converge in a way that makes it easy rather than difficult to trade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700007#F00200"><p>Can we learn anything from previous experiences in this area?  In a similar agreement years ago, some of the benefits gained at European level for Irish producers were eroded in the subsequent World Trade Organization, WTO, talks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700007#F00300"><p>Eroded in what way?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700007#F00400"><p>Trading one product or entity against another and conceding benefits in one area to facilitate the opposing negotiators and give them access to a certain product has undermined the benefits gained, particularly in the agriculture sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700007#F00500"><p>The EU negotiator will seek to represent all 27 member states and will not go to these agreements seeking hand trips.  People on both sides are going in good faith and see this as an opportunity for growth.  While there are sensitive sectors on both sides that they will defend to the best of their abilities - it comes down to negotiation - I do not see it as setting up a series of potential land mines further down the road.  Although neither side is going into these negotiations seeking to impede trade over time, they have real sensitivities they are seeking to protect which will be openly addressed in the agreement.  In the Canadian agreement there were very intense negotiations about the quantity of certain goods that would be allowed in.  Some things will be easy, for example, tariffs are not a major issue and people are generally sympathetic to dropping them to zero.  Some of the regulatory areas will be more tricky and that is why the negotiations will not be straightforward.  For example, Japan has traditionally had major non-trade barriers, and that agreement has been one of the most difficult in terms of identifying the sort of changes necessary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014052700007#F00600"><p>I thank the Minister for his attendance, presentation and answers to our questions.  We wish him well in his endeavours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-05-27a.147" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 2.55 p.m. and adjourned at 3.10 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Thursday, 5 June 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>