<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Committee on Budgetary Oversight</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 16:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett, Deputy Martin Heydon, Deputy Thomas P. Broughan, Deputy Michael McGrath, Deputy Joan Burton, Deputy Jonathan O'Brien, Deputy Dara Calleary, Deputy Eamon Ryan.</p><p>DEPUTY COLM BROPHY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#A00100">Business of Select Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#A00200"><p>We are in public session.  Apologies have been received from Deputy John Lahart.  Before we begin, I welcome all members to the meeting.  I am delighted to have been selected as the new chairperson for this committee.  I look forward to continuing to work with all members on a cross-party basis.  I will also take the moment to acknowledge my predecessor, Deputy Josepha Madigan, on behalf of the committee and to wish her well in her new ministerial role.  I particularly acknowledge my constituency colleague, Deputy John Lahart, who does excellent work as Vice Chairman of this committee and has chaired a number of its meetings since he became Vice Chairman.</p> <p>  The committee will meet with the Revenue Commissioners today to discuss the revaluation of the local property tax and commercial stamp duty.  As the Department of Finance officials will not be here today, I propose that we also discuss these items in greater detail with them on 16 January.  I also note that we have invited the Minister for Finance to meet with the committee in a separate session on that date to discuss the rainy day fund.  I now propose to go into private session briefly to deal with some committee business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.6" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 4.09 p.m. and resumed in public session at 5.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.7" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#B00050">Revaluation of Local Property Tax and Commercial Stamp Duty: Revenue Commissioners</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#B00100"><p>Before I begin, I remind members and witnesses to turn off their mobile telephones.  Interference from mobile telephones affects sound quality and transmission at the meeting.  I welcome Mr. Keith Walsh, the chief revenue economist at the corporate affairs division of the Revenue Commissioners.  He is accompanied by Ms Jean Kennedy, the head of capital taxes and personal tax division, and Ms Fionnuala Ryan, assistant principal at the statistics and economics branch and corporate affairs division.  I thank our witnesses for making themselves available to the committee.  We do appreciate their attendance.</p><p>Today we are discussing the local property tax re-evaluation and commercial stamp duty.  I understand that the officials in the Department of Finance are not available to attend our meeting today.  It is the normal practice that they do.  We will, however, have an opportunity to meet with the officials to discuss these matters in further detail on 16 January.  The purpose of this meeting with officials from the Revenue Commissioners is to discuss the concerns the committee flagged last September around the revaluation of the local property tax, LPT, and the potential sudden increases in LPT arising from the revaluation process.  We will also discuss the commercial stamp duty measures introduced in budget 2018.</p><p>I will now refer to privilege before we hear the opening statements of the witnesses.  I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  </p><p>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.9" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Dr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#B00200"><p>We welcome the opportunity to meet with the committee today and to provide whatever assistance we can around the matters covered in its letter of invitation.</p> <p>  I understand from the invitation letter that the committee wishes specifically to discuss a review of local property tax, the budgetary implications of the current process of revaluation and a review of costings around taxation matters, for example in relation to excise duties for tobacco and stamp duty.  I will discuss both of these issues in my presentation.  We will be happy to address any questions the committee might have on these topics.  While we will provide whatever assistance we can, the committee will appreciate that Revenue is constrained by law, specifically by section 8(5)(i)(a) of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 from discussing the tax affairs of any taxpayer on confidentiality grounds.  This includes any information that might lead to the identification of a taxpayer. </p> <p>  I am sure the committee will appreciate Revenue's role in costings and budgetary matters.  As the tax administration of the State, Revenue collects taxes and duties, and through this we have access to, and are able to provide statistical information and analysis of, tax returns and tax receipts.  While it is our role to provide facts and advice to inform the policy-making process, it would be inappropriate for us to make any comment on policy matters.  </p> <p>  As the committee will be aware, at the introduction of local property tax in 2013, property owners were asked to self-assess the valuation band on their property on 1 May 2013.  The original intention was for this valuation to hold for the purposes of LPT until the end of 2016.  At the time of the first valuation in 2013, Revenue provided extensive valuation guidance to property owners, including an interactive tool on our website and estimates generated with the returns that were sent out to owners.  We ran media and communication campaigns to ensure that property owners were aware of their obligations to assist in meeting these.  In 2015, the Minister for Finance published a review of local property tax implementation by Dr. John Thornhill, which was informed by a public consultation exercise.  Revenue and Department of Finance officials provided information and secretarial support to Dr. Thornhill's review. </p> <p>  Dr. Thornhill notes the successful response of the Office of the Revenue Commissioners and its staff to the challenge of setting up the new assessment and collection arrangements for this tax.  It should be noted also that compliance with LPT is high, at 97% or 98% for each year of operation so far.</p><p>Our most recent statistics for LPT at the end of October 2017 indicate the compliance rate for 2017 is also around 97%.  <br/><br/>The valuation period was extended from 31 October 2016 on foot of the Finance (Local Property Tax) (Amendment) Act 2015.  The current valuation period is now 1 May 2013 to 31 October 2019.  At the end of the current valuation period, under the current legislation, owners will be expected to value their properties on 1 November 2019 and this will form the basis for the subsequent valuation period.  Revenue intends to run a compliance communications campaign to assist property owners to value their properties and file their returns in the run up to this valuation date.  <br/><br/>In the context of the possible budgetary implication of LPT revaluation, it may be of interest to the committee to note that as part of the Thornhill review, the Department of Finance undertook an analysis of the implications of property price increases for LPT liabilities.  At the time of the review in 2015, property prices had risen by 26% nationally and 41% in Dublin since May 2013.  This analysis indicates that based on property prices at that time in 2015, 48% of properties would have remained in their original valuation band and thus not generated any increase in liability; 35% of properties would have moved by one band and thus generated an increased annual liability of &euro;90; and the remaining 17% of properties would have moved by two or more bands.  While more indepth analysis will be required to update this work, it is important to note that this indicates that property price increases do not necessarily translate into liability increases in many cases because of the valuation banding system in LPT.  The Thornhill review made a number of recommendations, some of which have been implemented since.  Any further policy decisions on LPT remain a matter for the Department and the Minister.<br/><br/>I will now turn to costings on taxation matters.  An important part of Revenue's role is the provision of high quality advice and support to the Department of Finance and, through the Department, to the Government and the Oireachtas in the development of tax policy.  To assist with this objective, Revenue decided from 2014 to move all of our published statistics derived from tax receipts and returns to a new and dedicated section of our website <i>revenue.ie</i>.  This has significantly enhanced the service we provide to policy makers in a number of ways.  Statistics published online, of which we now have over 100 datasets, are published in accessible and machine readable formats.  As well as making it easier for researchers to query and join our data, our approach means we are at the forefront of the Government's open data initiative.  By publishing statistics on our website, we ensure consistency by making the same information available to all.  This also enables us to become more effective in the use of our resources.  By diverting simpler queries to our website and published material, we also have more time to address more complex or specific queries.  I have provided a table that gives more detail on the tables we publish and also on the fact that we answer significant numbers of parliamentary questions.  Around one third of those are answered by reference to published material. <br/><br/>With statistics published, they are open to comment or critique.  This makes us more accountable and assists in identifying errors, if any.  In addition, through 2017, we engaged with the Central Statistics Office to achieve the official statistics accreditation which is a type of quality mark to indicate our statistical processes meet a series of quality standards and principles.  In December 2017, the CSO confirmed that Revenue's audited official statistics, which is nearly 50 datasets, can be published under the official statistics quality mark.  Revenue is the first Government Department or office outside of the CSO to achieve this standard.  Our statistics are also more timely.  Whereas previously we published material once a year, we now do so on a regular basis as updated data become available.  We have also dedicated statistical releases, for example monthly reports on the help-to-buy scheme, quarterly reports on LPT and annual profiles of the farming sector.  All of these statistics complement our more in-depth research papers on particular topics of interest.  Perhaps our most significant resource published is our ready reckoner.  The ready reckoner shows the estimated Exchequer impact of changing rates, thresholds, bands and more for nearly all of the main taxes.  The ready reckoner is updated pre-budget and post-budget based on the most recently available data from tax returns and receipts and so presents our best assessment of current conditions and the impacts of potential changes.  <br/><br/>For most taxes, costings presented in the ready reckoner assume no behavioural change and for the majority of cases, this is a reasonable approach unless very significant policy changes are being sought, for example, big increases in rates.  An exception to this relates to tobacco products' tax.  Revenue's estimated impact of receipts from changes in excise duty on cigarette packets uses the elasticity measure to partially reflect the responsiveness or change of behaviour of smokers following duty and price changes.  As research shows that smoker behaviour can be quite variable, a range of estimates is used to reflect this.  Variations in tax receipts from tobacco in recent years suggest the use of the range is appropriate but also that the higher end of the range is likely the most suitable to use when undertaking costings.  <br/><br/>The committee's invitation notes costings of stamp duty as an interest and these provide a useful case study to outline the method we use to generate costings estimates.  To produce costings for a stamp duty change we use data for recent years to estimate the taxable base.  This is done on a prudent or conservative basis.  In particular, for stamp duty on non-residential property, in estimating the pre-budget 2018 base, the assessment included factoring out a series of very significant transactions in prior years that we deemed to be once-off and thus not likely to reoccur.  Had we not done that, the estimated yield would have been higher.  In addition, revisions to macroeconomic growth forecasts post-budget suggest a slightly higher potential yield than we would have indicated before the budget.<br/><br/>We have noted that commentary regarding the basis for the stamp duty increase in budget 2018 has not been supported by estimates in market transaction volumes.  However, based on revenue returns and actual tax paid with regard to non-residential stamp duty, the considerations in the market are around &euro;9 billion or so over the past three years even when once-off factors are excluded.  In summary, Revenue is publishing increasing amounts of information on tax statistics, tax receipts and costings of tax policy options.  We do this because we believe it is a key part of our role to bring what facts we can based on tax returns and other data to the tax policy making process.  We will answer any questions raised by the committee, subject to the constraints I mentioned in my opening comments.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#C00200"><p>I thank Mr. Walsh.  I propose that we discuss the local property tax revaluation first.  When that item is concluded we will move on to commercial stamp duty.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  Following the discussion, there might be requests for more specific information in advance of our next meeting with the officials of the Department of Finance in early January.  I will now call on members in the order in which they indicated.  Deputy Calleary was first.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1335" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#C00300"><p>I welcome the delegation and thank them for their ongoing work.  What level of engagement has the Revenue Commissioners had with the Department of Finance on LPT since 2015?  Was engagement parked subsequent to the Government decision not to proceed with the revaluation?</p> <p>  Mr. Walsh said that very few 2015 valuations would be affected by increases.  We are in 2017 now and we have new figures today showing that in Dublin prices have increased 80% since 2008.  How would the figures Mr. Walsh has be affected by that?  What would the average increase in LPT be for homes in the Dublin area that are being affected most particularly by property tax?  What would the increase in the overall yield of LPT be based on current bands and based on the 2017 valuation?  Will Mr. Walsh clarify a couple of specific situations?  Are new houses built since 2013-2014 when the tax was introduced still excluded from LPT?  What is the position there?  Houses that have been diagnosed with pyrite continue to be excluded from LPT.  There has unfortunately been an expansion of houses that have been found to be affected by pyrite or mica.  What is the process for those house owners to get the exclusion that is available in some parts of the country and not in others?  Is there not unfairness in that?</p> <p>  This question is connected to LPT.  As a result of Revenue's success in LPT, it has been recommended as the agent to collect the TV licence fee.  Was there any consultation with Revenue on its capacity to do that in advance of the report being published by the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment last week?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.13" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#C00400"><p>I will try to address the first couple of questions and Ms Jean Kennedy might comment on the new houses and the pyrite.  In terms of engagement with the Department of Finance, the most comprehensive engagement was as part of the Thornhill review which ran for a fair chunk of the early part of 2015.  Aside from that, we have fairly regular engagement on topics.  When parliamentary questions are asked we respond to them jointly.  Beyond queries coming in and that sort of thing, we have not had any significant engagement since the Thornhill report.</p> <p>  In terms of the yield and the estimates, the Deputy is absolutely right that property prices have moved on a lot since the 2015 analysis done for the Thornhill report.  We have not updated the analysis since then.</p><p>The reason I was highlighting this in my opening statement was to make the point that, just because there is an increase in property prices, this does not necessarily translate one-to-one into an increase in local property tax receipts because of the valuation banding system.  A property can increase in value but stay within its valuation banding system.  If a property worth &euro;125,000 increased to &euro;140,000, it would stay within the same local property tax, LPT, valuation banding.  The Thornhill report indicated that, even though property prices have gone up by 26%, nearly half of all properties would not change valuation band, based on that analysis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1335" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00200"><p>Price rises of 26% would have a relatively small impact.  What level of increase would flip that and result in the majority moving into a different band?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.16" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00300"><p>We have not undertaken that analysis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.17" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jean Kennedy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00400"><p>Houses not in existence on 1 May 2013 are still outside the LPT net, as are houses which were always outside the scope of LPT.  As the legislation is currently drafted, they will not be brought into LPT until there is a new valuation date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1335" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00500"><p>How many houses are in that situation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.19" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jean Kennedy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00600"><p>We do not know.  We would be aware of some data coming through our electronic stamping system.  However, we have not kept detailed records of that.  If we have to update the register because there is another valuation date, we will do so at that stage.  We do not know how many new houses have come on-stream at this stage.</p> <p>  Specific criteria are needed to establish the existence of pyrite and to provide evidence that a house is actually affected by pyrite.  Some increased flexibility was introduced in this regard following the Thornhill report in 2015.  We moved away a little bit from the insistence on having an actual certificate from an engineer and a laboratory analysis of the affected materials.  There could still be houses that might have a low degree of pyrite and it might seem as if there is pyrite damage.  However, they do not meet the level of damage required for the exemption.</p> <p>  There is currently no statutory basis for any exemption because of mica.  It has not been examined so far.</p> <p>  As for Revenue taking on the television licence work, I am not aware that there has been any detailed consultation with Revenue on that.  However, I do not know whether there has been at a higher level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00700"><p>The estimates of what a revaluation might look like are based on a review in 2015.  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.21" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00800"><p>It was analysis done by the Department of Finance in 2015 that fed into the Thornhill review which was also undertaken in 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D00900"><p>This week the Central Statistics Office, CSO, estimated property prices in Dublin have increased since 2013, the year of the original valuation, by 86%.  The Thornhill review is based on a rise in property prices of 26% nationally and 41% in Dublin.  The CSO, however, stated the increase is actually 86%, more than double the valuation on which Thornhill operated.  If the latter increase is the case, it would be fair to say that the overwhelming majority of people will see a significant increase in their property tax.  Given the current spectacular rises in property prices in Dublin, many householders might be jumping nearly three valuation bands.  Is that a fair comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.23" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01000"><p>The Thornhill analysis was carried out in 2015 and, as the Deputy said, property prices have increased continuously since then.  One would expect LPT liabilities would have increased over that period too.  The main point is not to assume that a property price increase leads to an increase in valuations because of the banding system.  It is important to bear in mind that a fair proportion of the properties in the first valuation period in 2013 fell into the first valuation band of &euro;0 to &euro;100,000.  That valuation band is wider than the other valuation bands which go up in intervals of &euro;50,000.  Properties in that band would be less impacted.</p> <p>  Aside from that, the points the Deputy is making are valid.  It was the Department of Finance which undertook this analysis.  As far as I am aware, it has not updated the analysis since then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01100"><p>Even as it stands, based on 2015 prices which in Dublin were less than half what they are now, 52% of households saw a jump of either one band or two.  It would be safe to say that, if the CSO figures are correct, property prices have jumped to the extent that the overwhelming majority - we already had a majority in 2015 - will jump at least one band, if not two and, potentially, three.  Is that fair to say?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01200"><p>That is reasonable but I do not have any specific figures to confirm it or not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01300"><p>Is the Department of Finance suggesting that Revenue should update its estimates of the potential impact of property tax increases based on current property valuations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.27" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01400"><p>Not at the present.  Under the current legislation, if nothing else changes, the next valuation change will be one of 1 November 2019.  It is still two years away.  We would not have started any detailed planning in advance of that as yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01500"><p>How long would working out projections and estimates take?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01600"><p>It is difficult to say in advance.  For the next valuation period, I would imagine we would have to do similar work that we did last time such as sending out large volumes of returns and building the IT systems to capture information to provide evaluation guidance.  Our IT resources, for example, are planned a year in advance.  We would have to start planning it for the end of next year.  It is difficult to be more specific than that, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01700"><p>What proportion of payments are deferred?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01800"><p>There are 48,000 exemptions in effect for this year and 62,000 deferrals in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D01900"><p>Does an exemption mean the householder is not required to pay at all?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.33" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02100"><p>Is the number of deferrals fairly steady since the tax came in or is it increasing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02200"><p>The number of deferrals has increased a little bit.  I do not have the exact figures but it would have been around 40,000 or 50,000 originally.  It has increased to 62,000 over the past two years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02300"><p>Is the number of deferrals increasing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02400"><p>Slightly, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02500"><p>Are most of those deferrals anything to do with an inability to pay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02600"><p>Over 95% are in the deferral category for being below the income threshold.  If a person's income is under a certain threshold, they can apply for a deferral.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#D02700"><p>Up to 95,000 deferrals-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.41" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00100"><p>It is 62,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00200"><p>Rather, it is 62,000 and that figure is rising.  Their incomes are too low for them to be able to pay that tax.  How much, on average, do they owe?  What is the cumulative figure of what they might owe?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.43" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00300"><p>I do not believe we have a figure for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00400"><p>There are no figures on how much they might owe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00500"><p>We do not have that figure to hand but we could get it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00600"><p>It would be useful to get a breakdown of how much could be owed both in totality and aggregate and what the average figures in terms of liability might be.</p> <p>  Has any analysis been done or would it be possible to do an analysis when Revenue is estimating a revaluation of the impact that might have, how much the increases in the tax would be, how many people would move from one band to another and so on to cross-check that against people's income?  Revenue has figures on people's income.  Such analysis would help inform us of the benefit, or otherwise, of a tax such as this one.  Is it disproportionate in its impact and to what extent is it hitting people on different incomes?  </p> <p>  As an opponent of the local property tax, I believe it is regressive and will hit those with lower incomes hard and disproportionately but regardless of that being my view, it might be useful in any estimates or revaluation process to examine the impact on different income levels of a certain level of property price increase and revaluation based on those property price levels.  Is that possible?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00700"><p>Yes.  I would point out, and the Deputy is probably aware of this, that the local property tax is based on the value of the home and the deferral is based on the income of the individual, so the link is limited.  We could have a look at where home owners and property owners under the local property tax fall within the distribution to see if they are more at the top end or whether they are spread out across income deciles or something like that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1238" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00800"><p>I suggest to the Chairman that such a proposal would be a good idea.  Regardless of what one might think of the local property tax, that would be useful information for us to have and we could recommend that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E00900"><p>There is agreement on that.  I call Deputy Jonathan O'Brien.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01000"><p>Most of the questions I had have already been asked but I have a brief one related to the revaluation process.  Mr. Walsh commented that Revenue would probably start preparing that process at the end of next year.  Could he give members some detail of the timescale which would be needed by the Revenue Commissioners to carry out that revaluation process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01100"><p>It is difficult to be specific but, as I said, we would probably need to start planning for it in 2018 and the actual implementation would occur in 2019.  If we look back to the experience of 2013, the valuation date was 1 May.  In 2013, we started sending out returns in February or March of that year.  The returns went out two or three months in advance and perhaps something similar could happen in 2019, which would give people time to value their property and get their returns back to us before the end of the year.  We would need to have them back before the end of the year in order that payroll systems and matters like that could be updated if people are choosing to pay in that manner.  It is not something we put a huge amount of time into planning out or scheduling in great detail, but on the assumption that it would happen in roughly the same way or if the tax is still structured as it is in 2019, we would expect to start planning for it in 2018 and then scheduling returns, IT systems, bills and everything else within 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01200"><p>Following on from Deputy Boyd Barrett's point on a significant increase arising for many people as a result of that process, does Mr. Walsh believe that would have an impact on compliance rates?  Were a home owner to have a large increase in his or her local property tax demand within the space of three months, would that form part of Revenue's forecasts in terms of how such increases could affect compliance rates?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01300"><p>For these types of forecasts and estimates not only for the local property tax but for other taxes, we would assume the compliance rates stay roughly the same or as they are at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01400"><p>How likely is that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.55" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01500"><p>With the local property tax, we were very careful to provide as much assistance to home owners as we could in advance.  We provided valuation guidance and whatever assistance we could to help them file their returns.  People could file returns online or on paper.  We made it as easy as possible for people to pay.  There were seven or eight different payment methods and there is the deferral option as well.  One can pay over the course of the year through direct debits or whatever.  Again, we will be trying to make it as easy as possible for people to pay.  The experience from the local property tax so far suggests that even though people may not like the tax, they are willing to pay it.  The compliance rates have been consistently high throughout the whole process.  We have a compliance programme that we run every year that follows up on people who do not pay or who do not file their returns.  We would be fairly confident that the compliance rates would be maintained.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01600"><p>Revenue would have a mandatory deduction at source as part of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.57" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01700"><p>For the small minority who do not file their returns, mandatory deduction at source is one of the compliance options.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01800"><p>I call Deputy Burton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#E01900"><p>First, regarding the yield from the tax and potential reviews of the local property tax, has Revenue modelled what the different approaches might be?  In particular, if Revenue wanted to maintain the yield from the tax as being broadly in line with increases in the consumer price index, has it examined how it would achieve that by maintaining valuations but lowering the rates, which is the way it is approached in a number of countries?  For householders, the idea that on foot of increasing house prices they would face, as indicated by some newspapers, potentially very large increases in the tax, would be very unfair and counterproductive in terms of our understanding of the tax being devoted to funding local services.  Has Revenue carried out any evaluation given current levels of property values and what kind of rate would be appropriate to yield increases or decreases that were broadly in line with the consumer price index?</p> <p>  Second, I refer to older people and those who may be in nursing homes or some form of care where they are maintaining their residence in the hope they will return to it but where in practice that hope may turn out not to be realistic.  Many people - the individuals concerned and often family members - are unclear as to what their options are in that situation.  Has Revenue prepared an easy guide in that respect?  I refer in particular to people who may be moving into nursing home care or hospital care over a long period.  In the context of the current housing crisis, constant references have been made to houses that are vacant because a person has gone into hospital or a nursing home in the expectation of returning home.  During that time, however, the house ends up being vacant over a protracted period.  We are constantly told that for many families where a fair deal agreement is involved it causes problems regarding property tax.  Has that issue been brought to Mr. Walsh's attention?</p> <p>  A third issue that is important relates to areas such as big cities and towns in which significant amount of property tax are being paid because of higher property tax and higher valuations.  Does Mr. Walsh have details of the equalisation and what that costs councils in, for example, Cork, Dublin and Galway, where not all of the property taxes paid in those areas go to fund the councils in those areas?</p><p>Such a council may have services, such as homelessness services, which it finds it difficult to fund because a significant amount of property tax generated in that council area is being awarded to other areas and because such counties are not getting the boost they need from general taxation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.61" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00200"><p>I will respond to the Deputy's first and third question and Ms Kennedy will respond to the question on nursing homes.  On evaluation of the other options mentioned, we have not undertaken that type of analysis.  The first Thornhill interdepartmental group was responsible for the design of the local property tax.  In this regard, Revenue supported the supervision of information and analysis as requested and we did the same in respect of the Thornhill review in 2015.  Beyond that, we have not undertaken any more detailed analysis as yet.  It is probably a matter for the Department of Finance and the Minister but Revenue has not been asked to undertake any further analysis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00300"><p>Does Revenue need to be asked to do that by the Minister?  I think it would be an interesting exercise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.63" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00400"><p>The role of Revenue is to administer the local property taxes as set out in legislation.  We are more than happy to examine options for change.  We feed a lot of information into tax strategy group papers and so on in the run-up to the budget but we do not necessarily have the time and the resources to examine all the options for all of the different taxes.  We work closely with the Department of Finance and we try to prioritise its requests for research or analysis.</p> <p>  On the question regarding equalisation, I do not have a huge amount of information on this issue because, again, it is a little beyond Revenue's role.  We collect the tax and we hand it over to the Exchequer or to the local government fund.  We do have a little  information on the local adjustment factor, which is somewhat related to equalisation.  As the Deputy is probably aware, the local adjustment factor allows local authorities to vary the local property tax rate up or down by 15% of the standard rate.  For example, 11 local authorities have availed of the opportunity to vary the rate for 2018.  In our estimation, this covers approximately 0.9 million properties and will probably lead to a slight increase in the amount collected in local property tax for next year.  Approximately 20 local authorities have decided to not change their rate.  Three local authorities have increased their rate by 10%.  Limerick City and County Council has increased its rate by 7.5% and two other councils have increased it by 5%.  Waterford City and County Council has increased its rate by 2.5%.  The four Dublin local authorities have decreased their rates by either 10% or 15%.  Across the spread of those 11 increases, we expect a marginal increase in the receipts collected. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00500"><p>Mr. Walsh might send that information to the committee in tabular form, if available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.65" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.66" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jean Kennedy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00700"><p>On the nursing homes question, there is an exemption for a house that has been vacated because the person has gone into a nursing home or is being cared for in the home of a relative but the nature of the person's infirmity has to be certified by a doctor.  Also, the person must have been out of the house for 12 months or a doctor must certify that there is no possibility that the person will return to live in the house.  Another condition is that the house must remain vacant while the person is being cared for elsewhere.  There is information on that exemption on our website but I am not sure if it is specifically tailored towards older people.  There may be scope for us to review what other Departments or bodies publish in regard to facilities for older people that we could supplement.</p> <p>  I am not sure what the interaction between the fair deal and the nursing home would be.  In regard to market value, the local property tax market value is fixed as of 1 May 2013.  Market value under the fair deal scheme would have to be determined at the point at which the person applied for the fair deal scheme.  I cannot think of any other possible interaction or conflict between them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1253" speakername="Joan Burton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00800"><p>Many of the articles being written about housing refer to large volumes of houses lying empty that could be let to the local authorities for long or short periods or let into the general rental market to help ease the housing shortage.  However, as there is a great deal of confusion around the rules people are standing back from doing that.  Has the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government contacted Revenue about this issue?  As I said, there is a stream of empty houses, certainly in my constituency, that are not occupied.  Does Revenue have round-table meetings with other players, particularly the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, local authorities and the Health Service Executive, on the 62,000 exempted properties and what proportion of them could be made available to rent because people in practice no longer live in them?  Perhaps if the fair deal-style problem could be ironed out, a proportion of these houses could be made available to rent.  The Taoiseach regularly speaks of a whole-of-Government approach.  I put it to the witnesses that cross-departmental engagement on how some of these properties could be made available would be appropriate.  This would help to alleviate the current shortage of properties to rent.  There does not seem to be any comprehensive source from which to identify these properties.  I am sure the witnesses are aware that many people are accidental house minders because of situations that have developed with parents and so on who, if the rules were clarified, might be prepared to make these houses available.  While they might lose the local property tax exemption, assuming they are in receipt of rent that would not be a problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.68" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jean Kennedy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F00900"><p>There is a statutory rule that requires the property to be vacant.  Our records indicate that 7,500 exemptions have been claimed in respect of homes that have been vacated.  We generally do not have any direct interaction with the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government.  Our interaction tends to be with the Department of Finance.  Unless there is a change in policy decision and the statutory rule we have to continue to operate the exemption based on existing legislation.  We can provide statistics to anybody who wants to examine policy in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1294" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#F01000"><p>I am conscious that the witnesses were not involved in discussions on the possibility of the broadcasting charge being collected by Revenue but are they aware of any restriction to such a charge being collected by Revenue rather than An Post?  During consideration of this issue by the Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and the Environment, of which I am a member, reference was made to this not being possible because this fee is a charge rather than a tax.  Are there any restrictions on Revenue collecting this charge if that is what the Minister directs?</p> <p>  As a Dublin Deputy I am concerned about the statistics which indicate that 29% of all households in the State account for 38% of local property tax receipts.  Given that price increases in Dublin are significantly higher than elsewhere it could well be the case that 50% of the tax will come from Dublin households.  There is in equity issue here because typically a lot of those properties would be small and different in character to houses elsewhere in the country.  Have the Revenue Commissioners undertaken any work on the alternative property tax collection mechanism, which would be based on site value?  I recall I heard a Minister say that this option is being reviewed.</p><p> Has the work on title and the land ownership register that I know was started a number of years ago been completed, so that we have full understanding of who owns what property, which would facilitate the introduction of a site value tax?  Have any of the officials here done any background work on that as an alternative mechanism?  That is an alternative to a situation where Dublin prices would continue to rise and property tax would be very heavily skewed towards the capital, in a way that certainly would have equity issues.  In particular, someone in a very small, cramped apartment might pay a multiple of the amount paid by someone in a very large property, with very large costs to the State in providing social and other services.  There is an equity issue if we just continue with the current system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jean Kennedy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#G00200"><p>In regard to the broadcasting charge, I am not aware of any statutory reason that Revenue would not be able to collect it.  Obviously what happens there and how it might be charged are policy issues.  Whether the charge should be linked to existing properties that are on our local property tax, LPT, register, or based on people's ownership of televisions will be a policy decision for the Minister for Finance.  If that is going to happen, I am sure there will be discussions with Revenue in the future.</p> <p>  On the site value issue, the original Thornhill inter-departmental group, which was set up in 2012 to consider the introduction of property tax considered both the house value base and the site value base.  The group came down on balance in favour of a market value basis.  It was seen to be more efficient, but against the criteria of simplicity and transparency, and possibly equity, it did not measure up so well.  However, I am not aware of any work having been done in that area in the meantime.  Certainly Revenue has not been involved in looking at any different criteria.  Again, the basis of the charge would be a policy decision, and that would not be a decision for Revenue.  Moreover, I am not aware of any work being carried out in connection with the Land Registry to arrive at a situation where one could have a site value tax.  I do not know if the Department of Finance has looked at this either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#G00300"><p>No other member is offering at this point, so I am going to draw our consideration of the local property tax to a conclusion.  I propose that we move onto commercial stamp duty.  Is anybody offering on that area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1237" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#G00400"><p>I have a few questions about projections of stamp duty in general.  Does Revenue believe that there is sufficient consultation with and by the Department of Finance in advance of this measure being introduced?  I will start with the preparation of the budget each year.  Is it normal practice for officials from Revenue to compile data and projections for the Department of Finance on any revenue-raising measures?  Does Revenue provide the Department of Finance with any data or projections on commercial stamp duty to inform the preparation of the budget and if not, why not?</p> <p>  Is it the case that Department of Finance officials accompany officials from the Revenue Commissioners to meetings with Oireachtas committees so that policy matters can be covered?  The practice should be followed in meetings with the Committee on Budgetary Oversight as well, but that is an issue for another day.</p> <p>  To repeat my first question, is it normal practice for officials from Revenue to compile data and projections for the Department for any revenue-raising measures?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.74" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#G00500"><p>The answer is "Yes".  As I mentioned in my opening remarks, in the last few years we have published more and more information.  Probably most significantly, we publish a ready reckoner and we update it in the run-up to the budget.  That ready reckoner shows a series of tax policy options, including the impact of increasing or decreasing universal social charge, USC, rates, and the impact of changing value added tax, VAT, rates.  It is pretty much those sorts of changes to rates, bands and thresholds for all of the major taxes.  We publish that on our website and it is available to everyone, including the Department of Finance.  Aside from that, we interact with the Department.  Sometimes in the run-up to the budget Department officials will simply look at the ready reckoner and will use the figures there.  Sometimes they will want clarifications or figures that are not exactly covered by the ready reckoner or they might want something to be refined or confirmed.  It is a little difficult to give a general answer, but we certainly have ongoing interactions with the Department of Finance on budgetary matters.  That starts well before the summer, before the tax strategy group papers, and continues all the way through the budget process into the Finance Bill.</p> <p>  I will now address the commercial stamp duty or non-residential property stamp duty change in the budget.  The increase provided for in the budget, from 2% to 6%, was shown in our ready reckoner.  The figure projected there, a &euro;376 million increase, was taken by the Department of Finance and accounted for in the budget.</p> <p>  I will explain where that figure comes from.  When we are trying to project stamp duty, there are three phases to our work.  First, we look back at the most recent year for which we have complete data, in this case it is 2016.  We look at 2016 to try to get an idea of the general taxable base during that year.  We try to factor out once-off revenues, because if they are once-off in nature they are not a good indicator for receipts in future years.  In 2016 in particular, we factored out a number of very significant once-off payments that inflated the tax base.   If we had not factored them out, we would have had a higher estimate for commercial stamp duty.</p> <p>  Looking at 2016 data is the first phase.  Then we look at 2017 data.  We try to see if the trends that we expected from 2016 have continued, and if there are changes we should be aware of.  Lastly, we look at the growth prospects based on the Department of Finance forecasts for 2018.  Based on that assessment of data from 2016, trends since then in 2017 and expectations for 2018, we formed a view that the taxable base for non-residential property for stamp duty purposes was around &euro;9 billion in the last several years.  The consistent or stable tax base is about that, and we think that will reoccur next year.  That is essentially the basis for the costing of the increase from 2% to 6%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1237" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#G00600"><p>I would also like to ask about the changes on Report Stage concerning consanguinity arrangements for land.  Does Revenue have a valuation of the impact those changes could have?  Also, given that this is a transactional tax, have the Revenue Commissioners any concerns about dependence on volatile tax revenues to fund permanent expenditure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.76" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#G00700"><p>There would always be some concern, but the process I mentioned, whereby we tried to factor out the once-off payments during 2016, is our template in trying to adjust for that.  Our forecasts are based on an assumption of no behavioural change.  We look at what we think was raised in 2016 once the outliers and once-offs are excluded, what is happening in 2017 and what we think will happen in 2018.  Based on that, we make an assumption or we draw a conclusion on what we think will happen next year.  We are fairly confident that when once-offs are excluded, the activity levels for the last two or three years are actually quite stable where stamp duty is concerned.  I have seen some commentary from industry groups or groups within the market suggesting that the figures are too high.  That said, the figures and estimates that some of industry groups have produced look too low to me, considering the actual tax receipts that we collect and what they imply about a commercial base.  Based on the tax receipts that we collect, that is, the actual money coming in, we are fairly confident that there has been a broadly stable base of around &euro;8 billion or &euro;9 billion in consideration values for non-residential property in the last couple of years.  We do not have any reason to assume that will not continue, certainly for the next couple of years.  I have not seen any convincing forecasts suggesting that level of activity will suddenly drop off.  It may change over the longer term, but we are fairly confident that it is representative of recent years' trends.</p><p>It may change over a longer term, but we are confident that it is representative of the trend in recent years.  The forecast is based on an assumption that there will be no behavioural change and that exemptions or reliefs will remain unchanged.</p><p> The Deputy mentioned consanguinity relief.  We costed that measure and estimate that if it was applied at the new 60% rate and the age rule was removed, it would cost approximately &euro;9 million per annum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1237" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00200"><p>That presumes there would be the same level of activity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.79" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00300"><p>Yes, based on the assumption that there would be no behavioural change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1237" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00400"><p>The argument is that it would not be tax forgone in that the activity probably would not happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00500"><p>I wish to raise a number of issues, on some of which Mr. Walsh touched in his replies to Deputy Martin Heydon.  The first relates to the commentary since the budget on how accurate and reliable is the figure presented in the budget.  Mr. Walsh has outlined the process Revenue went through to arrive at the figure, taking out one-off large-scale sales.  I would appreciate a little more detail on the process involved.</p> <p>  The Revenue Commissioners provide data for the Department of Finance in the preparation of budgets.  Was this part of that process or did the Government seek the information specifically from Revenue?  If so, how late in the day did that happen?</p> <p>  Does Mr. Walsh have concerns that we are potentially moving to a position where we are relying on future expenditure being based on transaction taxes which could go up or down?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1335" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00600"><p>On the same issue, the commentary was not just confined to commercial or property interests.  The IFAC is cautious about it.  Again it suggested the policy decision was based on activity in 2016 and early 2017.  The concern is not confined only to people who may have a horse in the race.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.83" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00700"><p>I will also try to address that comment.  I will go through Deputy Jonathan O'Brien's questions in reverse order.  His final question was related to concerns about basing the tax system on transaction-based measures.  It is not for Revenue to comment on that issue; it is more a matter of policy for the Minister or the Department of Finance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00800"><p>Unfortunately, departmental officials are not present.  It would normally be the case that they would be present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H00900"><p>I appreciate that, but it is not for us to comment on the issue.</p> <p>  On whether there were contacts between us and the Department of Finance about this measure in the run-up to the budget, as I mentioned to Deputy Martin Heydon, it is one of the measures included in our published ready reckoner.  It was published some time in September, perhaps a month or so before the budget was announced.  As far as I can recall, there was no contact between us and the Department on the rate increase.  There was some contact either just before or just after the announcement of the budget on the cost of continuing the exemptions or extending some of them such as consanguinity relief, but as regards the rate increase, the Department just used the information in the published ready reckoner.  It varies a little, depending on the different measures being proposed.  It is not unusual for the Department to simply take the published figure and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01000"><p>Did the ready reckoner exclude once-off transactions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01100"><p>Absolutely.  The Deputy's first question was about the process involved.  When we were trying to figure out costings for budget 2018, we looked back over a three-year period.  Therefore, we looked at 2016 as the most recent complete year and tried to factor out once-off transactions.  In 2016 there were some significant transactions that when we reviewed them we deemed to be once-off.  I cannot say much about them for reasons of confidentiality because there were not that many.  However, this is a manual process where we examine the largest transactions to identify whether they are likely to recur or whether they are once-off or outliers of some kind.  The value of non-residential property transactions in 2016 was more than &euro;12 billion, but when we factored out what we thought were once-off transactions, the figure reduced to approximately &euro;9 million.  There were no major once-off transactions in 2014 and 2015.  The value of non-residential property transactions in both of those years was &euro;8 billion or &euro;9 billion.  One never knows what will happen in the future, but that is why I have some confidence that if we look at the three-year period 2014 to 2016, there is a steady rate of transactions when once-off transactions are excluded valued at &euro;8 billion or &euro;9 billion.  That is on what the ready reckoner costing for the increase from 2% to 6% was based.</p> <p>  On Deputy Dara Calleary's comment, I was not trying to ignore the IFAC.  I am open to correction, but it is my understanding the council did not have detailed information and that it may have quoted industry sources in its report.  Without singling out any of them, the industry is slightly underestimating the value of transactions in recent years because when I compare the estimates the industry is putting out with what we are taking in in tax payments and hard cash, our figures are consistently higher over a three-year period.  For the first three quarters of 2017 the value of transactions was approximately &euro;6.5 billion.  If that trend continues in the fourth quarter, the yield will reach &euro;8 billion or &euro;9 billion.  We have three and a half or three and three quarter years of transactions in the market with a value of &euro;8 billion or &euro;9 billion, which suggests a certain level of consistency on which we can rely at least in the short term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01200"><p>Will Mr. Walsh clarify that to the best of his knowledge the Department did not come back to Revenue seeking clarifications or to have a conversation about this measure before it was introduced?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.89" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01300"><p>Not in terms of the costing.  There might have been interactions on the exemptions or discussions on the the Finance Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01400"><p>Mr. Walsh may not be aware of this, but I have just been handed a note.  Facebook has announced that it is moving to a local selling structure in countries where it has offices.  It means that the company's advertising revenue will no longer go through its headquarters in Dublin.  Can Mr. Walsh comment on this?  I will not put him on the spot by asking him how it will affect corporation tax forecasts.  However, from a revenue-raising point of view, what impact is it likely to have?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01500"><p>That is an unfair question to land on anybody at this point.  Mr. Walsh does not have necessarily have to comment on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01600"><p>It is something on which Mr. Walsh can come back to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01700"><p>I have no doubt that there will be plenty of follow-up on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1280" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01800"><p>Unless Mr. Walsh wants to answer the question now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.95" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H01900"><p>The Chairman has responded well.  We cannot discuss individual cases because of taxpayer confidentiality.  As a general comment, there was a significant increase in corporation tax receipts in 2015 and 2016.  At the end of November this year, receipts were of the order of &euro;380 million or &euro;390 million, or 5%, ahead of target.  Over the course of this month we will see the final figure for the year.  Aside from that general comment, I cannot talk about individual cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1310" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#H02000"><p>Departmental officials will appear before the committee on 16 January 2018.  I forgot to ask one question about the local property tax before we concluded our discussion on it.  With regard to the movement of the local authority mean up or down, Revenue indicated earlier this year that there could be an increase because 11 local authorities had raised the rates.</p><p>How does that compare to the number of local authorities which actually raised the rates of LPT in previous years?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.98" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#J00200"><p>Twenty local authorities have stated they are not going to make any change next year, while 11 have stated they will either increase or decrease the rates.  Among the 11, the four local authorities in Dublin will be maintaining the lower rate and staying below the standard rate, while the other seven will be increasing their rates by various amounts up to 10%.  On average, we think there could be a marginal increase of perhaps &euro;2 million or &euro;3 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1243" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#J00300"><p>How many local authorities increased the rates in previous years?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Keith Walsh" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#J00400"><p>I do not have the figure for the number of local authorities which increased the rates.  Last year eight varied the rates for 2017, while 11 had varied the rates for 2016.  A total of 14 had varied the rates for 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1243" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/CBO2017121200002#J00500"><p>I thank the delegates for attending.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.102" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 5.20 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 16 January 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.103" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.104" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 16:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Niall Collins, Senator Aidan Davitt, Deputy Tom Neville, Senator Kevin Humphreys, Senator James Reilly.</p><p>DEPUTY MARY BUTLER IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.105" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Deputy Maurice Quinlivan and Senator Paul Gavan.  I propose that we go into private session to deal with some housekeeping matters.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.107" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 4.05 p.m. and resumed in public session at 4.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.108" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#C00100">Cost of Doing Business in Ireland: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#C00200"><p>I remind members, visitors and those in the Visitors Gallery to ensure their mobile phones are switched off completely or left in flight mode for the duration of the meeting as they interfere with the recording and broadcasting equipment, even when left in silent mode.</p><p>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.<br/><br/>Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/><br/>I welcome our guests, Mr. Tom Parlon, director general of the Construction Industry Federation; Ms Jeanette Mair, policy executive; Mr. Martin Stapleton, chairman of the IFA national farm business committee; Mr. Damian McDonald, director general of the IFA; Mr. Adrian Cummins, chief executive of the Restaurants Association of Ireland; and Mr. Liam Edwards, president of the Restaurants Association of Ireland.  They are all very welcome and I thank them for taking the time to come to the meeting to discuss the cost of doing business.  This is the committee's fourth meeting on the topic and we plan to hold one more meeting in the new year.<br/><br/>I remind our guests their presentations should be no more than five minutes.  Members have received the presentations.  I ask Mr. Parlon to make his presentation to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.111" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#D00200"><p>I thank the committee for the opportunity to highlight some of the issues which the Construction Industry Federation sees affecting costs within the industry.  At the outset I will give a picture of the industry which might not normally be appreciated.  In our industry, 97% of entities are very small players employing fewer than ten people.  The committee will see the big sites and big players but the bulk of the industry is small.  Small players have extra challenges in dealing with different issues.  The industry is in a pretty good place at the moment having come through a torrid time when it deteriorated to almost one quarter of its size with massive job losses, massive companies going out of business and so on.  The industry is growing now.  Generally when the economy is doing well the construction industry does well.  CSO figures suggest that for the past 30 months, we have employed an extra 1,000 people per month.  We have not heard the Minister or a Minister of State saying it is wonderful.  The industry has been taking people largely off the live register, including many foreign people.  Many people who were forced to leave the industry are coming back to take up good jobs again.  It is a very competitive industry and is very labour intensive.  Traditionally, it was very simple to look at the costs of building.  One employed labour and bought the materials and put them to work as efficiently as possible.  It was very straightforward.</p> <p>  I will go quickly through the tendering costs.  Practically all the work done, whether in the private or public sector, is put out to tender.  Very often the cost of tendering for projects is disproportionate to the probability of winning.  There might be a pre-qualification tender and six or eight people might pre-qualify who have to employ a fairly substantial team of surveyors, engineers, designers and so on.  Particularly if it is a design build, they have to go into a lot of detail in terms of coming up with the plans and so on.  There is only one winner, which has to be factored into the cost.  We have been negotiating with Government for more effective and fairer public works contracts.  We are making some progress there but there is still a lot of work to do.</p> <p>  Building and material costs are a big factor.  We had a decade of declining and flat building costs.  The wholesale price index recently showed that in the year up to December 2017 costs increased by 3.2%.  The most notable increase was glass, which went up by 21%.  Sand and gravel prices increased by 8.9%.  Stone prices increased by 7.8% and structural seal prices increased by 6%.  Timber pipe fittings also increased in price.  One of the biggest costs is insulation, which is a big factor in new quality builds now.  There has been big inflation in costs.  </p> <p>  Planning and development costs are another major issue.  Regulation has increased substantially in that area.  The whole process is extremely slow and expensive.  Lead-in times can be slowed down massively and that all adds to cost.  We have had some fairly positive amendments to planning legislation, including the fast-tracking of applications for developments with more than 100 housing units.  We have LIHAF and extension to planning permission in some cases.  It is still a major cost and can cause a big slow down.</p> <p>  The costs of building a house is a very big issue at the moment.  It can be divided between the cost of providing the house and building the house.  The Society of Chartered Surveyors Ireland recently did an in-depth survey of the cost of providing a house.  The hard construction costs are just 45% of the total costs.  Development finance, the cost of land, the design and taxation elements, levies, VAT and all of that are very big costs.  While I am saying there is inflation on the building side, it is still a small part of the overall cost.  We met with the IDA yesterday.  A big concern is the lack of quality apartments in Dublin particularly for the big workforce of foreign workers we have here.  The Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, is reviewing the proposals with regard to apartment building and he is looking at parking provision.  Previously one was obliged to put in very expensive underground parking.  With regard to lifting the height caps, we have very restricted height caps in the city centre.  With regard to build-to-rent policies, the dual aspect requirement is an issue.  One cannot build an apartment unless it looks out east and west or north and south.  There is also the issue of units per lift core.  That is practical stuff that we hopefully will get a positive view on.</p> <p>  Finance is a big cost and a big constraint on the industry.  Can the Chairman see the clock?  She is looking over my head.  Do I have time left?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#D00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.113" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#D00400"><p>Finance is a major cost.  When the industry got into trouble ten years ago, the problem was the ease of getting finance.  Now it is a different story altogether.  We did a survey recently and despite the chronic under-supply of houses, 63% of our builders mentioned their difficulty in securing finance.  Senior debt is maxed at 60%.  No matter how good one's standing with the bank is, it will only give a maximum of 60% for a project.  Very often our members, after coming through ten hard years, do not have the balance sheet to fund much so they depend on mezzanine finance which is generally in double digit figures.  It can be up to 15% or 16%.  When that rate is blended it can be 8% or 9%.  It is a substantial cost.  The Government recognised this in the last budget and has talked about setting up home building finance Ireland, which will have a fund of &euro;750 million.  The details are being developed at the moment and we are in consultation on that.  If it came on a hare's back it would not come quickly enough because the industry needs access to that finance.</p> <p>  Labour is a big factor.  Generally across the board labour accounts for about 40% of the total cost of any project.  In October a sectoral employment order was written into law by the Minister of State, Deputy Pat Breen.  It provides a set standard rate for the different grades of skilled people across the country, which is good, and it means everyone has a level playing field.  It provides for a 10% increase in the rates as well, which is a very substantial increase that the industry has to live with.  It is adding to the costs.  There is also a scarcity of workers now.  Our unemployment rate has dropped substantially.  The number of potentially skilled people within the ranks of the unemployed is scarce.  There is a lot of competition for skilled people.  That is adding to inflation.  </p> <p>  Energy and transport costs are a factor.  Unfortunately, the bulk of construction work is happening within the M50 and the greater Dublin area.  Anyone who travels to and from the country, which I and many of the people around me do, will know there is a massive clogging of the roads with traffic.  Much of that is made up of construction workers with their vans and tools and their gear coming to work in Dublin.  That adds substantially to the cost.  Many of our firms have to provide vans for people because they commute long distances.  Unfortunately the option of living in Dublin is not a viable one.  That is probably another major player.</p> <p>  Construction and demolition waste is the next cost.  The new children's hospital is under construction.</p><p>The first part of this construction project involves the digging of a massive basement several storeys deep to accommodate services, plant and car parking.  All the material taken out will have to be disposed of.  There is a strict and highly regulated waste policy in place, and rightly so, because it is important for the environment.  The bulk of demolition waste has to travel up to 100 km outside the city for disposal.  One can imagine the cost of that, as well as travelling through congested traffic.  We are negotiating with the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, and the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment to reduce costs in this regard.</p><p> We all have to live with taxation.  However, the issue of VAT on residential housing is a thorny subject which we have raised with the Department of Finance for quite some time.  There is no VAT in Northern Ireland or the UK on housing.  However, in the Republic, there is a 13.5% VAT rate on houses, which adds &euro;40,000 to a typical &euro;300,000 starter home in Dublin.  Some of my colleagues beside me today negotiated a reduced VAT rate when the industry was in difficulty in the past and it appears to have worked extremely well.  A reduction of even &euro;10,000, 4.5% of the rate, would make a house much cheaper for a first-time buyer.</p><p> Our biggest concern is the cost of building residential apartment blocks.  We are currently building well in excess of 100 acres of office space.  This activity signifies 45,000 new construction jobs but we are not building homes for them.  We need to accelerate the building of apartment blocks.  One can secure viable finance to build an office block, a hotel or student accommodation but not for residential development.  The Taoiseach made a commitment at our annual conference this year that he would set up a construction sectorial group, which would embrace several different Departments and be chaired by his Department, to look into problems with costs which are making certain developments unviable.  The sooner that sectorial group is established the better.</p><p> It is not a tale of woe.  The industry is doing well.  However, we appreciate there is a void in the turnout of residential housing.  It is the viability of those and high costs associated with that which is the problem.  We will continue to underline those issues and see if we can make any policy changes in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#E00200"><p>I call Mr. Adrian Cummins of the Restaurants Association of Ireland to make his opening statement.  The last time he was before the committee, he was concerned about VAT rates.  He must be smiling today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.116" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#E00300"><p>I thank the committee for the invitation to present to it today.</p> <p>  The Restaurants Association of Ireland represents 2,700 restaurants, coffee shops, gastro pubs and hotel restaurants.  It would be remiss of me not to thank all Deputies and Senators for their continuous support for the 9% VAT rate for food and tourism attractions.  The Restaurants Association of Ireland has long advocated that the 9% VAT rate for food and tourism is the correct one when benchmarked against our European Union colleagues.  Since 2011, we have created over 50,000 jobs in our sector.  Many of these jobs are in rural communities where tourism is very often the only employer.</p> <p>  Today's discussion is around the cost of doing business.  It is widely known, with many reports outlining it, that Ireland is the costliest place in the European Union to open a business.  Over the past several years, insurance premiums for businesses and the public have rocketed.  In 2017, the average annual insurance premium for the restaurant sector rose by 45%.  This is unsustainable for any business, let alone our sector.  The problem lies squarely at the door of the insurance companies and the legal profession.  We would welcome a full and absolute investigation into the outrageous insurance premium increases over the past two years and why payouts to claimants have increased by 400% in the past five years.  The Personal Injuries Assessment Board has been totally bypassed by the legal profession to maximise profit for its industry to the detriment of small businesses and the general consumer looking for insurance.  The time for action to deal with this issue is now.  Otherwise, our sector will be forced to source insurance from outside the jurisdiction for our industry.</p> <p>  Before a business opens its doors, local authority rates will be the first charge for that business.  Over one third of all local authority budgets come from commercial rates to the tune of just over &euro;1.5 billion per annum.  Small businesses, restaurants, coffee shops and pubs which serve food complain to our organisation that their commercial rates are not good value for money.  For a restaurant, the calculation of rates does not take into account the ability to pay, the size of the premises, profitability, numbers employed or location.  However, other licensed premises such as hotels and public houses are valued by reference to the trading data of their property.  When a small business receives its commercial rates bill for a year, why does the bill not show where exactly its commercial rates are spent?  Why is the payroll cost excluded from the percentage of the commercial rate given to a business?  This should be investigated by the committee.  Local authorities should be instructed to split out the payroll cost and it benchmarked between local authorities.</p> <p>  Water charges are another cost to small business which most consumers do not understand.  Harmonisation of water charges for all businesses must be a matter or priority.  Why do two counties, side by side, have the highest and lowest commercial water charges?  It does not make sense.</p> <p>  Business improvement district levies were brought in through primary legislation in 2006.  The levy is generally a 5% top-up on commercial rates, double taxation at its best.  The measure is in use in D&uacute;n Laoghaire, Dundalk, Sligo, Sandyford and Dublin city centre but the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation is advocating its roll-out across the country.  Business improvement districts are run by private companies and are outside the remits of the freedom of information legislation and the Standards in Public Office.  For example, in Dublin city centre, &euro;29 million was raised from this tax on businesses.  We would like the committee to investigate this levy.</p> <p>  Another bugbear of our industry is the famous sunshine tax, otherwise known as outdoor seating charges.  Outdoor seating charges are seen by businesses as a tax on their business.  There is no benchmark or uniformity of charging with regards to this tax with some local authorities maximising it for profit.  For example, for every &euro;1 spent by Dublin City Council administering the charge, &euro;4 is being raised from businesses.  This makes no sense to a small business and is another example of double taxation.</p> <p>  The fats, oils and grease trap charge for restaurants is an environmental charge with an average annual cost of &euro;1,000 per business.  It is another example of double taxation.  Any restaurant will have a minimum of 28 different licences, regulations or regulatory regimes with which it must legally comply.  We were advised in 2012 that work would be conducted by the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation to streamline inspections for all businesses, utilising technology and reducing paperwork and form filling.  For example, an environmental health officer could arrive in a restaurant in the morning to carry out a food safety audit.  However, he or she would not be allowed conduct an audit of fats, oils and grease trap standards, even though he or she would be fully qualified to do so.  That is two inspections, two regimes and two fees for that individual business.</p> <p>  Excise duty, specifically around wine, is the highest in Europe.</p><p>An increase in excise duty would be a retrograde step to the competitiveness of our sector.  Other forms of taxation for restaurants around copyright, music performance and motion picture licensing are a major concern.  We have three different organisations in Ireland collecting copyright fees from small businesses across the country in respect of three different types of copyright and these businesses must also have a standard television licence.</p><p> On the shortage of skilled labour in our sector, since 2012, the Restaurants Association of Ireland has been highlighting the shortage of chefs in this country.  I will explain the reason for the shortage of not only chefs but all skilled labour in the hospitality industry.  Each year, our colleges and institutes of technology qualify, on average, 1,800 chefs.  As per the 2015 expert skills report for hospitality conducted by the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation, we require 5,000 chefs per year to have a functioning hospitality industry.  The problem is that we do not have one organisation with sole responsibility for hospitality and tourism training policy in Ireland.  This problem arose with the dismantling of CERT, which was the State agency for hospitality training and management in 2003.  We are asking the committee for its support for the re-establishment of CERT or a small secretariat with responsibility for hospitality training policy and development in Ireland.  Until we have leadership, we have nothing and, unfortunately, decisions are being made by State organisations to spend taxpayers' money in a way that will not benefit our sector.  The tourism and hospitality industry is seeking this leadership as a matter of urgency.  If one compares the tourism and hospitality industry to the agricultural industry this is akin to the dismantling of Teagasc as the training authority for farmers.  Ireland is either serious about tourism and hospitality, or its not.  Unfortunately, the State agency for tourism development in Ireland, Failte Ireland, closed training centres around the country from 2010 to 2013 and it has no interest in re-entering the chef training space.</p><p> I thank the committee for listening to our concerns and we welcome any questions from members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#F00200"><p>I thank Mr. Cummins for his presentation and I invite Mr. Stapleton to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#F00300"><p>I thank the committee for this opportunity to outline the views of the IFA on the cost of doing business in Ireland.  I am chairman of the IFA national farm business committee.  I am joined today by Mr. Damian McDonald, IFA director general.  Mr. Joe Healy, president of the IFA, sends his apologies for not being here today but he had to go to Argentina for the Mercosur discussions.  I acknowledge the presence of our colleagues from the Restaurant Association of Ireland and the Construction Industry Federation, particularly our former president, Mr. Tom Parlon.<br/><br/>IFA is the representative organisation for over 70,000 members throughout the country and is the recognised voice of Irish farmers in Europe and internationally.  The association promotes the ongoing development and competitiveness of Irish agriculture and the food industry which is making an important contribution to Ireland's economic recovery.  Farming and the agrifood sector is Ireland's largest indigenous productive sector, exporting food and drink worth over &euro;11 billion in 2016 and providing employment to over 300,000 people directly and indirectly.  It has been a key driver in Ireland's economic recovery and it is the backbone of economic activity across the rural economy.  A strong agriculture sector is critical to the achievement of a more balanced economic recovery in this country.<br/><br/>Agriculture provides employment and generates earnings across the country not just at farm level but in the thousands of regionally based jobs dependent on and linked to the sector.  Many of these jobs are located outside of the main urban centres.  For those of us who live and work in rural Ireland, it is a really good place to live and work.  However, there are many challenges facing farmers, in particular the challenges of Brexit and CAP post 2020.  Consolidation of farm holdings and increasing the scale of farms are necessary to operate efficient and competitive businesses.  It is, therefore, important that this would be taken into consideration in the new review of agri-taxation measures due to commence in early 2018.  The IFA has identified key areas where barriers exist for farming enterprises to doing business.  First, access to credit at a competitive rate is critically important to support farm investment and improve efficiency.  There is an ongoing market failure within the Irish banking system which is placing Irish farmers at a competitive disadvantage to their EU counterparts.  The lack of competition between the financial institutions and the legacy of historical banking losses is resulting in higher interest rates being charged on new lending.  The high demand in 2017 for the agri cashflow loan scheme demonstrated the need for competitively priced working capital on Irish farms.  The funding of &euro;25 million in budget 2018 for a low-interest loan package for farmers provides some recognition of the market and income difficulties facing farming enterprises in 2017.  This fund needs to be rolled out as soon as possible.  The high costs of registering a legal charge is resulting in a barrier for customers to move between banking institutions, further contributing to a lack competition between the banks.  Another area of concern to farmers is the new Central Bank requirements around the valuation of farm land<b></b>that is being used to secure funds.  IFA understands that such valuations may have to be reviewed every two to three years, and that valuations must be obtained from a list of auctioneers selected by the bank.  This has the potential to add significant unnecessary cost to the finance being borrowed.<br/><br/><b></b>Second,<b></b>Ireland faces significant challenges in delivering on 2020 EU renewable energy and climate obligations, which may result in fines over &euro;400 million being imposed on Ireland.  Farm businesses are considerable users of energy.  In recent months, IFA has developed a clear strategy to displace fossil fuel use in the agriculture sector with energies from renewable sources.  In a recent submission to Government, the IFA called for 20% of the public service obligation, PSO, levy paid by all consumers, which is equivalent to &euro;100 million, to be ringfenced to support the development of farm scale, roof-mounted and farmer led community energy projects.  The current strategy of exclusively using this levy to support the construction of thousands of large-scale wind turbines across our natural landscape is no longer acceptable to rural communities.  It has also resulted in the transfer of millions of euros paid by Irish citizens to enrich multi-national energy companies.  The IFA's proposal to ringfence 20% of the PSO levy would contribute to energy savings for the sector by displacing fossil fuels and will, in turn, assist in addressing climate and renewable obligations.  Over time, the competition this would create among service providers must deliver further energy cost-savings for Irish businesses. <br/><br/><b></b>Third, a shortage in labour supply has emerged in the last number of years in the agriculture sector due to a number of factors, including the fall in unemployment in Ireland, which is leading to a labour supply shortage, particularly for lower paid employment.  This is particularly relevant for the horticulture sector.  There is an increased demand for skilled farm workers, particularly in the dairy sector, arising from the expansion in milk supply and the dairy herd since the abolition of milk quota in 2015.  A recent Teagasc survey indicates that there is potential for 6,000 extra jobs to be generated on dairy farms in the next few years.  The improvements in the economies of newer member states has reduced the supply of workers who have traditionally filled jobs in the horticulture sector since EU accession over a decade ago.  There is an increasing demand for skilled farm workers in the pigmeat and poultry sectors arising from increased output and increased scale in these operations.  The shortage of labour supply at farm level is restricting the ability of the sector to achieve its growth targets over the next decade.  We urgently need a scheme to facilitate the issuing of work permits to non-EU workers in the agriculture sector.  The IFA has raised this serious issue with the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation and the Department is currently reviewing the criteria for non-EU work permits.<br/><br/><b></b>On the earned income tax credit, the failure of the Government to increase the earned income tax credit to match the PAYE credit to the level committed to in the programme for Government maintains the inequity in the income tax system between employees and the self-employed, including farmers.  The &euro;200 increase in the earned income tax credit does not go far enough.  The Government has chosen to continue the discrimination between employees and self-employed in the income tax system for yet another year.  It is simply not right that a farmer earning &euro;16,500 will be paying &euro;500 a year more in income tax than a person in employment.</p><p>It is simply not right that a farmer earning &euro;16,500 will pay &euro;500 a year more in income tax than a person in employment.  The Government has reneged on a clear commitment in the programme for Government that the PAYE and earned income tax credits will reach parity, at &euro;1,650, by 2018.</p><p> I refer to incentivising apprenticeships in rural SMEs.  A skills shortage is emerging due to the lack of availability of trade-based vocational training programmes.  The IFA recognises the commitment in the programme for Government to double the number of apprenticeships by 2020, with a significant increase in the number of traineeship places and the development of a mechanism to recognise a person&rsquo;s practical work experience and expertise to qualify him or her to take on an apprentice.  The IFA has proposed to the Government that SOLAS and the Apprenticeship Council should target a specific number of apprenticeship places and provide the supports required for small business employers who take on apprentices in an approved programme.</p><p> With regard to the rural fibre broadband network, while some progress has been made, the Government needs to swiftly conclude the tendering process for the new rural broadband scheme.  It must ensure every home, school, farm and business in rural Ireland will have access to high-speed fibre broadband, no matter where they are located.</p><p> The vast majority of rural businesses are micro-enterprises, employing ten or fewer people.  These businesses struggle with administrative costs and regulations which often act as a disincentive to increasing the number of employees.  The IFA has a number of recommendations to make to address these issues.  The Leader programme has an important role to play in supporting enterprise development and job creation in rural Ireland.  However, the current programme is proving to be inappropriate for administering and progressing the approval of project funding.  The Government needs to undertake a review of the application process for Leader funding, with the target of simplifying the process for applicants and significantly reducing the turnaround time between project proposal and approval.  In addition, a review needs to be undertaken of the new local community development companies, LCDC, structures at local authority level to determine what their impact has been to date.</p><p> The Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, as Ireland&rsquo;s independent energy and water services regulator, has important economic and customer protection responsibilities.  The timelag in reducing retail energy prices when wholesale prices are declining is a significant source of concern for farmers.  We call on the committee to consider granting legislative powers to the CRU to intervene in energy pricing policy where it is clear that wholesale price savings are not being passed on businesses and domestic consumers.</p><p> Insurance and transport are two sectors that need to be monitored to maintain competitiveness.  I hope what I have outlined demonstrates some of the key areas where farmers find difficulty and meet barriers in their day-to-day farming activities which prevents them from doing business in the most efficient way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#G00200"><p>I thank all three delegations for their submissions.  The common denominator is the skills shortage and the lack of skilled labour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1221" speakername="Niall Collins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#G00300"><p>I thank the delegations for their presentations, two of which referred to work permits.  I am contacted from time to time by representatives of the transport industry who experience difficulties in recruiting drivers.  I have never been contacted by someone in the agriculture and construction sectors.  What is the experience of the organisations in dealing with the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation?  What refusal rate are they experiencing?</p> <p>  Water charges are linked with the issue of commercial rates which has been mentioned by other groups that have appeared before the joint committee.  Local authorities vary the rates hugely, which impacts on farming, as well as business.  The delegates have said they are seeking uniformity, which makes sense.  Are they looking for the pricing model to be transferred to the new utility regulator?  In doing so, they need to be mindful that their members will experience a lift in the areas of the local authorities that charge less if the rates are averaged out.</p> <p>  The upcoming legislation to amend the Planning and Development (Strategic Infrastructure) Act 2006 has been flagged by a number of groups, including at last week's meeting.  It came up in the context of the proposed data centre in Athenry.  We have kicked around the concept of data centres.  Wind energy was also mentioned.  What else would the CIF recommend that should be considered in the proposed legislation?</p> <p>  What interactions have the organisations had with the Department on the apprenticeship scheme?  The shortage of chefs is an ongoing issue, but I am particularly interested in shortages in the agriculture sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.123" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#G00400"><p>With regard to the granting of work permits in the construction sector, the whole of Europe is a massive resource.  No matter where one goes in Ireland, there are people from every corner of Europe working in the construction sector.  We do not see it as an issue.  We have got back approximately half of the professional and skilled workers we lost and we are still encouraging others to come back.  The big issue in the construction sector is taking advantage of new technology and faster ways of engaging in off-site production and so on.  The amount of labouring work done on a site is much lower than it ever was.</p> <p>  With regard to water services, the issue for the construction industry is securing a water supply connection.  There is quite a delay in that regard.  When our house builders sit down to engage in internal discussions with the IHBA, they are more agitated by the difficulty in securing connections with the ESB or Irish Water than by other issues because it is a nightmare.  For an individual unit, it costs &euro;5,000 up front to have a water supply connected.  That is a direct cost which is passed on to the first-time buyer.  An ESB connection costs much less as customers will continue to pay on a monthly basis though their electricity bill.</p> <p>  We know from our recent discussions with IDA Ireland and our big players who deal directly with FDI and other infrastructural projects that the planning process is horrendous.  I am annoyed most by the respect afforded to vexatious objectors who live 100 miles away from a proposed project and choose to throw their oar in.  When the proposed amendment to Planning and Development (Strategic Infrastructure) Act 2006 is examined, that factor has to be taken into account.  Clearly, people who have genuine objections and concerns about a future development have a right to express them.</p> <p>  Earlier this week I attended the launch in Grangegorman of the new apprenticeship scheme by the Minister for Education and Skills.  The bulk of the apprenticeships are not in the construction sector.  We still have a good pipeline of fitters, plumbers and electricians coming through, but the number with wet skills such as block laying and plastering is scarce.  The intensive house building that will have to happen in the next few years will be a struggle.  It will be difficult because we are competing for workers with farming and the hotel and catering industries.  I have read commentary that workers are leaving these sectors to work in the construction industry because our pay rates are substantially higher, but that is putting pressure on the industry because we are subject to a sectoral employment order.  We used to have a registered employment agreement to set pay rates, but now we have a sectoral employment order.  The Minister made a commitment to direct 20% of school leavers to apprenticeships in the next few years.</p><p>It is a major challenge to get those school leavers into apprenticeships because the system has been designed to encourage them to move towards third level colleges.  Third level colleges have a vested interest in attracting them because they are their bread and butter.  However, that has led to many square pegs being put in round holes.  If someone wants to enter an apprenticeship, he or she must first find an employer and go through his or her local SOLAS office and so on.  Many changes could be made to make apprenticeships more attractive.  A challenge for our industry and others is encouraging people to enter it.  It is very positive for young people coming out of school and so on that they have choices.  Our challenge is to sell the construction industry as one which offers a good long-term career to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.125" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#H00200"><p>I will start by addressing the issue of work permits.  We have made a submission on work permits to the Department every six months since 2010 during the window of opportunity and each has been refused because the Department does not want to deal with the issue of work permits for our sector.  Some 210 were received in the sector in 2016, but the road haulage industry, a far smaller sector, received 350.  New Zealand which is of a similar size to Ireland has a functioning work permit system involving a two-year permit.  It targets specific countries to attract skilled labour in a similar manner to how many nurses in the health care sector in Ireland come from the Philippines.  The same could be done in our sector if we followed a similar system to that in place in New Zealand, involving a quota system for 1,000 people in the hospitality industry which would be cut off for two years.  The country is approaching full employment and our industry is crying out for staff.  There are the same issues across Europe in terms of the need for skilled labour.<br/><br/>Our industry will benefit from the commis chef programme, one of the new apprenticeship programmes.  It is to be welcomed that it was picked as one of the new programmes and that it was recognised that it should be developed.  That is the only good thing about it.  There is a very poor take-up and very poor marketing of apprenticeships outside the construction industry in Ireland and a proper marketing programme must be developed in that regard.  In terms of how it is structured, organisations such as F&Aacute;S and its replacement, SOLAS, do not have expertise in certain sectors.  They were heavily involved in the trades and construction industry, but the hospitality sector is very new to them.  A sufficient level of expertise was and is not present in these organisations.Education and training boards are not hospitality trainers<i>per se</i>.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland which previously had responsibility for hospitality training has ceased to provide it, even though the legislation states it must do so.  It is not doing what it is supposed to be doing.<br/><br/>I take Deputy Niall Collins' point on the harmonisation of water charges.  We have met Irish Water on the issue which is going or has gone to the regulator.  However, we should look at the lowest common denominator, ensure there are efficiencies and best value for the customer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.126" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#H00300"><p>Like our colleagues in the hospitality industry, we have been seeking permits to bring in non-EU workers.  For the past ten to 15 years Irish farms have been given a supply of workers from eastern and south eastern European countries, but that supply is no longer sufficient to match demand.  Like my colleagues, we have hit a stone wall in the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation in getting permits to bring people in.  The downside is that it will limit the capacity of our industry to grow in accordance with the projections made.</p> <p>  On apprenticeships, we need a pathway for people to enter agriculture, to secure an apprenticeship to become trained managers and have an opportunity to go on and become farm business owners, which is different from the low-skilled workers we are hoping to bring in from outside Europe.  That can only be done through having a proper apprenticeship scheme in place.  An opportunity is needed to set it up whereby people would be incentivised and given the wherewithal to take on apprentices in order that they would be able to build a career in the farming sector and have an opportunity to fulfil their ambitions.</p> <p>  As regards water charges, it is about harmonisation and making sure everybody gets fair play.  It is a source of particular frustration that those involved in community water schemes are still paying for water, which is not fair.  I do not know how long Deputies and Senators will allow that to continue, but it is unfair that although water charges have been rescinded for everyone else, those involved in community water schemes still have to pay.  Most of those involved in large-scale farm businesses use their own well water, which involves a significant cost in pumping and supply, but it is more competitive than having to pay for community water schemes.  Those whose farms are fragmented often have to pay for the connection of two, three or four water meters.  If one is connected to the supply line, one should only have to pay for one connection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1221" speakername="Niall Collins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#H00400"><p>On a point of clarification, what other items of significant infrastructure would the delegates like to see under the Strategic Infrastructure Act?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.128" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#H00500"><p>Motorways are key.  The Government has promised that a motorway will be constructed between Cork and Limerick and given a commitment to provide funding for its design and planning.  That is a factor.</p> <p>  As regards big infrastructure plans, the country's reputation has been damaged by the Athenry issue and other big players may now think twice about deciding to spend &euro;1 billion or $1 billion here.  All of the big foreign direct investment infrastructure should be included.</p> <p>  We are being told that the fast-tracking of developments of more than 100 housing units will halve planning time, but that will involve a reduction from two and a half years to a little over a year, which is still far too slow and will put pressure on An Bord Plean&aacute;la and its resources.  Local authorities will continue to have a role.  Whatever about efficiencies, resources must be committed to ensure success.  A proper pre-planning meeting on any issue, be it for a &euro;1 billion data centre or a private house, ensures one gets to know the parameters and what one should do, which is a wonderful help.  People very often have to wait between three and six months for a pre-planning meeting, which I assume is a resource issue.  Many practical things could be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#H00600"><p>I noted that in the presentation made by Restaurants Ireland it was stated its members might have to look outside the country for insurance cover.  The cost of insurance has been repeatedly raised as an issue before the committee and it is, with rates, one of the two biggest issues.  Has Restaurants Ireland done any work in that regard or on associated problems?</p> <p>  Although it falls slightly outside the remit of Restaurants Ireland, an issue raised previously before the committee which will feed into the number of visitors to towns and cites is that of the cost of hotel rooms.  The number of visitors from the United Kingdom fell last year for the first time, which is quite shocking.  That may be related to fluctuations in the strength of sterling and so on, but I am curious as to at what point Mr. Cummins or Mr. Edwards think the cost of hotel rooms will harm the city and the tourism industry.</p> <p>  Mr. Parlon made a very good point about the shortage of apartments in cities.  The American Chamber of Commerce made a similar point about people not being able to find apartments for their staff to enable them to expand their businesses and the impact it was having.  Although Mr. Parlon has mentioned a few issues already, what does he think it will take to move the bigger construction firms on from building offices?  As he alluded to, all of the cranes on the skyline are being used to build offices.  What will the biggest factor be?</p><p>We talked about the planning process.  The big developers involved in construction have calculated what they are able to get out of their investment and evidently it all comes down to business.  What do the witnesses believe would help to push development in the direction of building apartments and to help those big job providers in Ireland?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Liam Edwards" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#J00200"><p>Regarding the Senator's question on the rising cost of hotel prices, I would say the position is different for restaurants.  Reference was made to the issue of supply and demand for hotel accommodation in Dublin city where there is not enough supply and too much demand.  However, the opposite is the case in much of rural Ireland.  There is a fear among restaurants owners about increasing prices for consumers.  Many restaurant owners have been soaking up their overheads to stay competitive and in business, and their profit margins have been decreasing.  There is a fear among them, if they increase their prices, about whether consumers will still frequent them. We are monitoring the competition all the time.  At this stage, I believe the consumer will see an increase in prices.  We cannot do anything about that.  We have to stay in business and maintain employment.  It will not be anything of the order of the increase in hotel prices but there will be a creep up in prices because we have to stay in business.  That is affecting rural Ireland.</p> <p>  We have seen the immediate effect of Brexit in the off season.  Many small towns in rural Ireland have lost business from short trip visitors from the United Kingdom.  That has been lost.  The peak season was very good in Ireland.  The number of American visitors was exceptional.  We did not feel the effect of Brexit in the peak season, but in the off season we felt it straight away.  I live in Kinsale, and if one was to go into the town tonight, one would find that 70% of the restaurants would be closed.  We do not have the volume.  It is cheaper to close one's doors in the off season than to remain open.  It is worrying for those operating in the industry in rural Ireland in the off season.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.132" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#J00300"><p>I will reply to the Senator's question on insurance costs.  Every day of the week our association would get a telephone call about the rising cost of insurance.  We are actively looking at going outside the jurisdiction to source block insurance for our sector.  The vast majority of our membership has not had a claim in the past five years, and those who have not had a claim have seen an increase in their premia of 40% on average.  It simply does not make sense.  They have got a 40% increase in their premia in 2017 and they are wondering what the increase will be in 2018.  They have said that enough is enough and that they need to work together to get 2,500 businesses to come together in this respect.  A vast majority of others are also in support of the idea of looking outside the jurisdiction for insurance cover.  If they can get cheaper insurance that covers them, they will go for it.  That is what they are currently examining.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#J00400"><p>I also asked about the construction industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.134" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jeanette Mair" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#J00500"><p>The Senator asked about apartment developments.  There are a number of issues, which Mr. Parlon outlined, around some of the reasons the viability of apartment developments, particularly in the Dublin area, is fairly limited such as the building height, the number of lift cores per floor and issues around dual aspect.  It is to be hoped the working group of the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, will examine that and come up with solutions to amend the 2015 guidelines for apartments.  On the other hand, there is the investment side.  With the change in the types of tenure among apartment dwellers within the city and across most urban centres in Europe and the world, an increasing focus on urbanisation and the requirement for a change of tenure, we are moving to a build-to-rent model.</p> <p>  Current providers of housing within the urban centres are largely focused on housing units, three-bedroomed developments and so on.  Even where large developments of apartments are taking place, they are often being built by larger companies, and even where they are able to pre-sell some units, it is being done on a phased basis.  One of the problems about getting the finance in place to undertake the significant site infrastructure works that are needed to begin to develop an apartment building of significance, say, within the city area, is that there are site restriction issues, accessibility, and all the site infrastructure works that have to take place.  Developers have to put together a model which their lenders will support.  Lenders which are currently in that space come from international sources largely and some international firms are operating in this area.</p> <p>  As Mr. Parlon mentioned, we have received large investment in commercial office space, the hotel sector and student accommodation.  Unfortunately, there has not been the same appetite to invest in the residential sector, although it is changing.  There is also the matter of the viability of being able to build units that a developer will know will be rented or possibly sold.  Unfortunately, it is very difficult to pre-sell apartments.  Even within housing developments, very liquid builders are only getting the finance to build ten or 20 houses at a time.  They must have contracts signed and agreements in place before they will be given the next amount of development finance to proceed with the remainder of the phase in a development.  That is the current environment, but obviously market demands will probably dictate that.  We will slowly see a maturing sector within the construction industry moving into that space in time.  It is to be hoped the amendment of the standards, if that is to happen by the end of the year as promised by the Minister and the Department, will go some way to aiding the build prospects and the viability of entering into that, which is quite a high-risk investment in the first place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#J00700"><p>I thank all the witnesses for their presentations.  We were especially keen to have them appear before the committee on this issue, especially the Irish Farmers Association, IFA, because often people do not accept it is a major part of Irish business, but this committee fully acknowledges that it is and we are pleased that its representatives have come along to this meeting.</p> <p>  I apologise as I will have to leave to go to the Seanad in a few minutes and I will therefore quickly ask my questions.  One of the recurring themes has been finance and access to it.  All three presentations alluded to that.  We have discussed previously the need for examining the opportunity to bring a third and different type of bank into this country.  I am sure the witnesses have heard of a Sparkasse, and its representatives are coming over to talk to us next year.  I would like the witnesses to comment on that.  Would they welcome a third force that would be of the old-style banking, and while this group is a not-for-profit one, it will lend anything from &euro;5,000 to &euro;50 million.  They will come and walk one's land and visit one's business to understand one's model.  It has a very much a personal approach and is run through offices in a region.  There is talk of perhaps the credit unions collaborating with it, but we do not know if that will happen.  Would the witnesses welcome such a model and the capacity to access finance in a more face-to-face fashion?</p> <p>  The witnesses' issues around insurance costs are well made and everybody who has come to this committee has made the same point.  We had representatives of the insurance industry at our last meeting and we agreed that we will have them back for a more robust exchange.  I am particularly interested in what one of the representatives of the Restaurants Association Ireland said about going outside the country to look at other possibilities.  I would welcome that because that is what is needed to shake up the industry here.  Nobody can understand why the costs have gone up.  There are always rationale, reasons, legal costs etc., but nonetheless we heard of one small restaurant-food company in Galway whose insurance was &euro;10,000 ten years ago and it is now &euro;110,000 and little has changed.  We are all very much concerned about that.  As an aside, I would mention where the reverse occurred years ago when GPs in this country found it ridiculously expensive to be insured by English companies and we set up our own company.  While the restaurants association will possibly be doing the reverse, more competition is needed in the insurance sector.</p> <p>  How would the witnesses address the Irish Music Rights Organisation, IMRO issue in regard to that?  I would agree with comments made by people around greater transparency on how rates are spent.  I would not have an issue with that.</p> <p>  On the labour shortage, I would point to the number of people who had jobs in the agriculture industry that were created in 2011, 2012 and 2013 as the building sector was collapsing.  Many people who had been engaged in farming had gone into the building sector and then moved from it back to farming and now the building sector is struggling to attract people back.  Nobody has mentioned the minium wage but they have mentioned labour costs.  We will need to have wages competition to attract people into any element of labour, whether it be in the building sector or restaurant sector.</p><p>Work permits etc. are an issue that we have dealt with here under a different guise where there was ferocious abuse.  Will the witnesses comment on how they would protect people from that?  We have had plenty of stories here of people having passports taken from them and basically living a life of indenture.<br/><br/>I am interested in the apprenticeship issue.  I think we place far too much importance on going to university.  In these other trades, people make as much money or more money and have as good a life and they are just as critical to the well-being of our society as any university degree.  How would the IFA communicate to us or the powers that be in educational facilities its needs <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>where it sees a need for apprenticeships?  The same goes for the building trade and the restaurant industry.<br/><br/>I will comment on the issues with renewable energy.  It has always struck me that we have all these amazing agricultural buildings with roof space and we are not using it for solar energy and photovoltaics.  There are newer possibilities too.  We have asked the Minister for regulations because a number of local authorities have declined planning for farms for solar energy on the basis that there are no national guidelines.  My main question to the witnesses is about the finance issue and what their feelings would be if there were a third banking force.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00200"><p>I will take that.  We would welcome it.  Having grown up in a post office, I think that would have been a prime opportunity to have had a post office outlet as a point of contact for a third banking force.  It might be a missed opportunity.  It could possibly include credit unions too.  We have set up our own microfinance.  We have a &euro;30 million fund for peer-to-peer lending through grid finance.  It is a form of leasing for our industry.  If a restaurant wants to lease equipment, the payback is through credit card payments per day based on its levels of business.  If it takes in &euro;1,000 in a night, it will pay 10% of &euro;1,000 as opposed to having a flat fee across the year.</p> <p>  The national minimum wage will go up in January.  We have wage inflation.  The Low Pay Commission looks at it but I think this morning's report from the National Competitiveness Council has raised red flags about competitiveness, and wage costs are part and parcel of that.</p> <p>  On work permits and the abuse of work permits, we fully endorse that the laws should be adhered to and anyone found in breach of those should be prosecuted.  The Oireachtas could bring in what is called a trusted partner scheme for work permits.  That is where companies such as Google or other large tech companies are seen as trusted partners, whereas small microenterprises are not allowed into that because of scale.  It is easy for the Department to deal with one large organisation that has 1,000 people working in it as opposed to dealing with a small to medium-sized enterprise with ten people that is trying to find one staff member.  We need to look at that and roll it out.  When a company is seen as a trusted partner, it is allowed to get permits fast-tracked, but if it steps outside the scheme, its trusted partner award is taken off it so it may not be able to look for a work permit in the future.  I will defer to our president about the Irish Music Rights Organisation, IMRO, Phonographic Performance Ireland, PPI, and copyright.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.138" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Liam Edwards" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00300"><p>On IMRO, Mr. Cummins mentioned that we are paying fees for 28 different licences.  We are paying for three different licences for background music for restaurants.  We are also paying for a television licence.  It is just another hidden cost that the consumer does not see and it is just another burden on the restaurant.  The consumer may see it at some stage when the prices are increasing and wonder why.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00400"><p>Have the witnesses any suggestions to deal with the IMRO issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.140" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00500"><p>My suggestion is to have it all under one licence.  Why are there three organisations collecting?  Three administrative regimes collect three different licences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00600"><p>It is helpful for the committee to have a suggestion as to how it could be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.142" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00700"><p>On finance, our big campaign for the past year, which will be ongoing, is to make sure that competitive finance is available to farmers.  It is clear to us that rates are, on average, approximately 2% higher in Ireland than they are in north-western Europe and those are the people we compete with on the European market.  It is a significant charge.  There are different types of finance, as I am sure the committee knows, including finance for capital investment, for increasing the size and scale of a farm and purchasing land, and for working capital.  On the question of Sparkassen, we would welcome its participation in the Irish market to provide a new source of funds.  The most important part is that if Sparkassen is to come here, it will have to be competitive.  It will have to help drive down rates.  The funding model for Sparkassen may mean that it will not be available for long-term capital investment but it should certainly be a big help at the level we are talking about with working capital.  Traditionally and currently, banks' overdraft rates are between 7% and 9% and merchant credit is often charged at as high a rate as 1% a month, which is compounded to 13% to 13.5%.  Any time that we see an opportunity to increase competition in this market is a benefit not only for our sector but for all of our economy.  That has to be seen as being a good thing.</p> <p>  I agree with the Senator about renewable energy.  The time has come for investment at farm level to produce renewable energy in this country.  For far too long, we have let our contribution or investment into renewable energy be put into huge companies.  One can see that with wind farms.  It is also the case with solar panel development where solar farms at the moment are run by big businesses where farms have been leased long-term and solar panels have been installed.  It would be innovative for us to incentivise farmers to put solar panels on the roof and to get involved in community projects such as putting in anaerobic digestion which has the potential to reduce our carbon output significantly and so allow farmers to play their part in meeting our renewable targets.  I will defer to Mr. McDonald.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#K00800"><p>On the work permit issue, there were obviously bad experiences before in how work permits were operating and nobody wants to be associated or to have anything to do with that type of behaviour.  This is an issue we will have to grasp.  As some speakers have said, even if we were to roll it out on a fixed number basis for a start, there are models that could be looked at.  A seasonal horticultural workers scheme operated before where workers came in and were placed through a body, which was Macra na Feirme at the time, that was authorised by the Department to provide oversight to the scheme.  It brought in the workers and placed them on farms.  If there were issues, that organisation could intercede in those and make sure that if workers had any problems, they had options to come back into the system and be moved to another farm.  Problems arose where somebody was tied to a particular employer as a condition of getting his or her work permit.  That works in most cases, but unfortunately the bad cases get highlighted.</p> <p>  We are open to looking at innovative ideas to do this but it is a nettle that we have to grasp quickly because it is an increasing problem in our sector and in other sectors as well.  We had more positive engagement by the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation when we last met but we need to get on with it.  I know that farms face huge problems this spring, particularly dairy farms.  In our sector, cows have to be milked.  We are dealing with animals.  Some businesses can close down for the summer.  For example, a construction business might not build an extra unit.  In our case, however, we have cows, they will calve, milk will be produced and, even from a farm safety perspective, relief labour is a huge issue on farms now.  Something could be done pretty quickly with a bit of innovative thinking, and mechanisms to give additional safeguards are available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.144" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#L00100"><p>The lack of finance and its cost are major factors in the construction industry that are holding up the necessary residential building.  I have met Sparkassen and its model looks good.  I can understand that our Government has a vested interest in allowing the pillar banks to rebuild their balance sheets, but it should not be at the cost of a chronic undersupply of housing with all the social and other effects.  One of the latest reports of the Central Bank stated that Irish households have more than &euro;100 billion on deposit.  We feel we are a very indebted country, but there is &euro;8.2 billion more in deposits than there is in loans to households at the moment.  There is a wall of cash there.  The credit unions are awash with cash, or all of the good ones at any rate.  Unfortunately, a few have difficulties, but they are a minority.  A friend of mine works in a credit union in a very small country town which I was astonished to discover has more than &euro;30 million.  His job is to find someone who can take a loan.  The credit unions are very restricted in what they can do and they have to lodge their deposits in pillar banks which charge them for minding their cache of money.<br/><br/>The challenge for this committee and for all of us will be to find a way to release the money.  Representatives of foreign funds telephone me every other day asking how they can provide funding.  When I ask more, they are all looking for quite high interest rates.  However, there is a large amount of cash around and there is a need to use that cash for infrastructure.  I know that our Government is restricted by the fiscal rules in what it can borrow for our capital programme.  I think there will be some flexibility there.  There is a new vice president of the European Investment Bank and that bank is highly active in lending to our semi-State companies and is keen to invest money<b>, </b>but obviously the fiscal rules are restrictive.<br/><br/>This is a big challenge for us, right across the board.  Everybody could do with more working capital at cheaper rates.  The problem is that we are not able to get access to it at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#L00200"><p>I would like to comment on the issue of work permits.  One thing we have to ensure is that our long-term unemployed have an opportunity to get back into the workforce.  I compliment Mr. Parlon and his association on their engagement with the local employment service, LES, in focusing on upskilling and training people who have been out of the workforce for a long period.  A lot of that has been done in the inner city.  I must say, not everyone has been as good.  I have seen quite a few blank faces when I have tried to discuss access for the long-term unemployed and for older people, that is, those over 50 years of age.  There seems to be a resistance in those organisations to seeing those people as possible good employees.  However, I compliment Mr. Parlon on the work his organisation has done in partnership with the LES, and I encourage other organisations to copy some of its initiatives.</p> <p>  Where apartments are concerned, the issue is one of quality.  I am still dealing with the problems of the 2000s when so-called reputable developers left mayhem and destruction across this city with so-called quality-built apartments featuring cold bridging or downright dangerous construction.  I am still living with the problems, and so are the residents.  We cannot go back there.  I totally accept that finance is a factor and has to be dealt with.  In the construction industry, I am slightly nervous about finance.  We should start looking at equity uptake rather than opting for 90% and 100% borrowings as we did in the 1980s.  Sometimes we hear that sound very loudly.</p> <p>  I have a couple of questions about business improvement districts, BIDs.  Having worked on the business improvement districts, I would urge people to be careful with their language.  The ratepayers were given a full list of services provided by the local authority, down to the number of times a stop sign on a particular street would be cleaned.  The business improvement district scheme consisted of additional services on top of that.  That was my experience of BIDs.  That was the contract arrived at.  The additional levy was for additional services.  There may have been a problem during the recession, when the council could not provide the basics, but we need to return to that.  The extra payment in a business improvement district should provide additional services.  In Dublin city, that extensive consultation document is still there, so we should get the local authority to fulfil its side of the contract.</p> <p>  I must also ask about sunshine tax.  I live in the city centre.  Outdoor tables can be a blessing and also a disaster.  I like outdoor tables for reasons of passive policing and things like that.  It is all counted as additional services.  However, in the part of the city in which I live, a charge is normally applied for the renting of space in a public area.  I would not deem it a tax if a business is renting public space to put tables out.  I do not count that as a tax.  It is a business proposition.  The business is renting the space, for use as a commercial entity, from the citizens of the city through the local authority.  It is referred to as a sunshine tax, but I do not buy into language like that.  We have to be honest, precise and fair with each other.  The charge should reflect the possible business return on that table.  Accordingly, I would agree with Mr. Cummins on standardisation.  Outdoor seating has different economic returns in Kildare town and in Dublin, and that should be reflected in different charges.</p> <p>  I totally accept the point on water charges and their equalisation.  All organisations must be honest with their membership and with citizens and small businesses.  In many cases that will mean an increase in water charges for small businesses.  That is the reality.  Some of those will be the most vulnerable small businesses.</p> <p>  Mr. Parlon has advocated the 9% VAT rate for the construction industry for a long time.  I often listen to my colleagues, and the biggest argument is that if a 9% VAT rate is introduced as a temporary measure, the rate will never go back up again, as we saw in the hospitality sector.  I supported the 9% VAT rate in hospitality when it was introduced as a targeted measure, and I think it worked as such.  It now needs to be refined further.  Hundreds of millions of euro in tax has been forgone to assist the hospitality sector.  Some of that sector no longer needs that targeted intervention, yet some other areas do, such as rural Ireland.  With regard to the hospitality sector, I would be interested to know if there is a way of targeting that forgone tax to particular areas that are in trouble.  Some restaurants in the capital are doing extremely well, and their prices have not been controlled.  I have seen restaurants not too far from Mr. Parlon increase prices by 20% or 25%.  Mr. Parlon has probably paid the prices himself when visiting.</p> <p>  Something that costs hundreds of millions of euros in forgone taxes must be targeted properly.  I am not talking about a reduction in assistance to the industry.  However, in the hospitality sector, I would certainly like to see that forgone tax targeted to assist businesses that are still being challenged by Brexit and the performance of the American market, which has suffered.  If we consider how best to spend hundreds of millions of euros in forgone tax, I am not too sure that the 9% VAT rate is the proper way to assist the industry.  We need to target it much better, and speaking as a Senator that comes from Dublin, we must target it to assist industries outside of Dublin.</p> <p>  I remember being lobbied extremely hard on visas when I was a Minister of State.  Since I had access to the information, I enquired about the number of people with the required skill sets in a particular sector of the industry.  Those skill sets were available.  Suitable people were on the live register and their skill sets were still new.  As the recovery kicks in, we must ensure that those who lost their jobs at the beginning of the recession have an opportunity to get back into employment.  I will give Mr. Parlon credit where it is due.  The construction industry has stepped up in that area, but not all the industries have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00100"><p>In 2013 we engaged with the MOMENTUM initiative, a good project, which dealt with long-term unemployment.  At the time, it came out of the training centre in Finglas and we trained 100 chefs but the Department stopped funding it.  If we had got extra funding, we would have continued with the project.  I take the point about ensuring we have exhausted all efforts.</p> <p>  In Dublin city centre, &euro;500,000 is raised from businesses through the outside seating charges but it only costs &euro;100,000 to administer, meaning a &euro;400,000 profit is made by Dublin City Council.  We have asked the council to look at reducing the charges to ensure more businesses will create a caf&eacute;-style culture in the city centre, which we are being encouraged to do by the tourism authorities.  However, these charges are prohibitive in doing that.  A report was made recommending a reduction in outdoor seating charges but the council did not take it up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00200"><p>Does Mr. Cummins accept that it involves rental of public space?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.148" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00300"><p>I accept that.  However, there is a loophole whereby not having an outside chair means one can bypass the charge.  Certain businesses are using this loophole.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00400"><p>However, Mr. Cummins is not doing his industry any good by not calling it exactly what it is, namely a rental of a public space.  It is not a tax.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.150" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00500"><p>Our small business members see it as &euro;500,000 raised in revenue while it only costs &euro;100,000 to administer.  In turn, Dublin City Council makes &euro;400,000 profit from 150 businesses in the city centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00600"><p>It varies among local authorities.  Waterford County Council took a proactive approach by reducing the outdoor seating charge in Dungarvan by 75%.  I accept Dublin city is different with higher footfall involved.  However, it varies among local authorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00700"><p>The Chair is right but I am taking issue with the concept of renting the public space from the citizen.  In turn, the money goes back to the citizen through the local authority.  We need to be more careful with our language in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.154" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M00900"><p>Businesses are saying it is a tax, however.  If the local authority engages with us and follows what has been done in Dungarvan and other local authorities, we would have a better-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01000"><p>Mr. Cummins will have to accept there is pressure on the four Dublin councils about the inappropriate positioning of chairs and tables forcing pedestrians, pushchairs and wheelchairs onto the main road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.156" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01100"><p>I accept the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01200"><p>Mr. Cummins's point is that it is an added cost to doing business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.158" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01300"><p>The BID levy is a 5% top-up tax on businesses' rates.  Those for and against the levy all agree the 2006 legislation is not fit for purpose for 2017.  It falls outside the remits of the freedom of information legislation and the Standards in Public Office.  We need to have this levy reviewed to ensure it is fit for purpose for this day and age.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.159" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Liam Edwards" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01400"><p>I thank the committee for supporting the 9% VAT rate.  We feel it is essential.  Since the rate was reduced in 2011, everything else has gone up.  We have remained in business because of it.  I realise there is a three-tier economy in our industry.  Dublin city centre is going well but not so in the suburbs.  We all know of the effect of Brexit on the Border counties.  We need to represent all of our members, particularly those in rural areas which have not seen the recovery when it started four years ago.  The 9% rate is the benchmark of Europe.  It must remain and we will fight for it to remain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01500"><p>Could it be targeted better?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.161" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01600"><p>The 9% rate cannot be targeted at, say, a Border region.  It has to be across the entire country.  The European Union has dictated that to the Department of Finance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01700"><p>This issue was addressed when the hotel industry was before the committee.  At the hotel which I normally use when in Dublin, I was quoted &euro;279 for a room during the All-Ireland hurling final weekend, much higher than the usual weekend rate.  There are areas in which it will be important to retain the 9% rate.  However, the committee has heard there are some abuses of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.163" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01800"><p>The 9% VAT rate was brought in for newspapers, hairdressers, food, tourism attractions and accommodation.  Theoretically, one could look at different sectors.  Targeting it outside Dublin, however, is against EU rules.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M01900"><p>Mr. Cummins is misunderstanding my question.  I accept there are EU rules on VAT.  However, if one puts the value of the 9% rate in real terms it comes to hundreds of millions of euro.  If the rate were returned to 13.5%, it would yield between &euro;500 million and &euro;600 million. In turn, that could be spent in a more targeted manner in assisting growth in the tourism industry in rural areas.  For example, assistance required by Border counties to deal with Brexit issues or investment in the Wild Atlantic Way and Ireland's Ancient East could come from this tax take.  We have to be much smarter in how we spend our money to make the best hit.</p> <p>  There are hotels near where I live which are running at a 92% occupancy rate and management have to put on a night-time shift to turn rooms around.  However, that is not happening across the country.  The hotel in Dublin with 92% occupancy rates is benefiting from this foregone tax yield when hotels in west Cork or Clare may need targeted financial assistance to ensure they can stay open.  We may have to be more intelligent in how we spend a foregone tax of &euro;600 million.  One of the biggest arguments against the reduction of the VAT rate is that once it is introduced, it is hard to go back on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#M02000"><p>I welcome the delegations.</p> <p>  The Construction Industry Federation, CIF, referred to the lack of finance in the market resulting in pent-up demand.  The CIF referred to 60% of funding raised by builders.  What has the CIF done seeking the remaining 40% of funding from venture capitalists and investors?  We have seen investors from outside the State buying up existing property.  With pent-up demand for property, from a potential private investor's point of view, there is a market.</p> <p>  Is there a percentage point above 60% at which the market would tip?  Has there been any statistical analysis of this to present to financial institutions?</p><p>They are considering their commercial interests as well but that does not take away from the huge number of people on the housing list who need houses and the economic effects of the issue.</p><p> In terms of the Restaurants Association Ireland, RAI, and the recruitment of staff, has the shortage of staff forced any of its members to consider the employment models in operation?  There is a mixture of permanent, part-time and casual staff and flexibility arrangements in the sector.  When I worked in the hospitality industry my co-workers and I were on minimum wage.  Has there been any industry pressure on employers to consider productivity?  Productivity has increased in recent years with the improvement in the economy, which has created staff shortages.  The sector has hit a kind of ceiling but productivity has increased and I assume that, for some organisations, profits have also increased.  Companies are out of the situation they were in during 2011 and 2012, if they were lucky enough to survive those years.  Has that forced them to consider profit sharing, commission or such schemes that have worked in order to attract staff?</p><p> As regards the IFA, as a rural Deputy representing County Limerick and dairy farming being the backbone of my constituency, I am particularly interested to hear more about the skill shortages mentioned in dairy farming and whether there has been any thought on the specifics of apprenticeships that the IFA would like to be put in place.  Could that be pushed back onto Government to make that happen because in education there is an increasing consideration of apprenticeships, broadening apprenticeships and moving towards the German model, which provides a broad range of apprenticeships, and growing that part of the economy?  That was neglected in the past, both culturally and by Government.  From a dairy farming point of view, and as one who worked on a dairy farm in my younger years, what is the minimum requirement for a person to be employed on a dairy farm who does not necessarily wish to pursue it as a career?  Has any thought been put into putting training modules or courses in place that could be run through Teagasc or a similar organisation but would have Government backing, or any way to expand in that regard in order to incentivise staff to come in?  Eastern Europe was mentioned but there are probably other parts of the EU that may need to be targeted as well as outside the EU because I am all for underpinning the industry that kept the country going through the recession.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#N00200"><p>In response to Senator Humphreys, who raised the issue of the legacy of poor-quality work that is a difficulty for the industry and is still being dealt with, thankfully much has been done and the industry has moved on.  The new Building Control (Amendment) Regulations, BCAR, have been in place since 2014 and set a very strict statutory certification whereby every build, be it a single house, extension or any other scale of construction, must have an assigned certifier with insurance cover who must be a chartered surveyor, chartered engineer or an architect and must sign off on all aspects of the build.  We have moved on, as we clearly needed to do, and we are in a good place.  The industry, together with the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, has set up the construction industry register of Ireland, CIRI.  That means that in order to be a construction professional or involved in any element of the sector one must be registered and tick all the boxes with regard to one's experience, quality, insurance, tax compliance and so on, which will take the cowboys out of the industry, who, unfortunately, were among those involved in such poor-quality work, which was also due to the lack of implementation and scrutiny of the regulations at the time.</p> <p>  As regards the 9% rate, I understand exactly where finance comes from.  It annoys me that the calculation is done and it is said that if 4.5% VAT is taken from the industry whatever number of hundred million euro will have to be found.  However, that does not take into account that construction, in particular residential building, is a massive economic boost for the Exchequer.  Almost 40% of the cost of a house goes directly to the Exchequer and the extra cost, therefore, would be less than is represented.  As regards it being a temporary measure, I appreciate that has been a problem.  In fairness to my colleagues from the Restaurants Association of Ireland, they are holding on very strongly to the 9% rate.  It has been said on many occasions that a particular year would be the last year for the 9% rate but woe betide the Minister who follows through on that.  He or she would need to be fairly well galvanised or would not want to be going out for a meal around the country for a while.  That is a problem but we need to be innovative about how it will be done.  The issue about targeting is a difficulty because the EU lays down the rules and one either does or does not do it.  The Government is quite entitled to target the construction side for a 9% rate as it would qualify in the same manner as the hospitality sector.  However, we have to be innovative and find a way that we can do it temporarily or otherwise.  If there was a window of opportunity of two years, for example, we would make a major dent in the housing deficit.</p> <p>  As regards the point made by Deputy Neville on seeking finance from the private sector, the banks are senior debt and our bigger players are able to get into joint ventures.  Many houses are currently being turned out with the support of NAMA and others have many of the big international funds behind them but smaller players do not have that capacity.  As I stated, the bulk of our members around the country who are employing fewer than ten people do not have the capacity to link up with a big player and that is where the &euro;750 million the Government has now set aside or is about to set up will play into their hands.  The difficulty is that the banks which provide the 60% maximum have the deeds and the security on the project and the next player coming in does not have that comfort and, therefore, feels obliged to take a far higher cut in terms of an interest rate and so on and that is a difficulty.  The &euro;750 million house building finance envisages lending up to 80%.  There has been some speculation about interest rates in that regard but the Taoiseach said he expects it to be approximately 4%, which would be affordable for the industry and would give it a good boost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#N00300"><p>I have a question before I let Deputy Neville back in on this issue.  I was a member of the original committee dealing with housing and homelessness before the Government was formed and at that time it was difficult to ascertain the cost of building a house.  Mr. Parlon stated that 45% of the cost of building is the hard cost, 40% is tax related, including VAT and so on, and there are then 15% in associated costs such as land and so on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#N00400"><p>If one takes the example of a house sold for &euro;300,000 or &euro;320,000, the VAT is approximately &euro;40,000, the development levies to the local authority are approximately &euro;15,000, the Part V contribution, which goes to social housing, is approximately &euro;10,000, the connection to Irish Water is &euro;5,000 and if one takes a cost of &euro;50,000 per site in Dublin, one has reached &euro;110,000 or &euro;120,000 with just those costs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#N00500"><p>Mr. Parlon addressed the undersupply of housing and all members know there is a huge issue in the country in that regard.  He also discussed the fast-track planning that decreased a period of approximately two and a half years to perhaps just over a year.  Does he get a sense of the required urgency from the Department?  We get it from the Minister but does he get it from the Department?  This is probably going off the issue a little but I have waited all day to ask it.  Everybody is focused on the issue of housing at the moment because it is extremely cold and there are 8,500 homeless people in the country, most of whom will have a roof over their head tonight.  However, in terms of the cost of doing business, the committee heard earlier in the year from a colleague of mine who said that when he discussed possibly reducing the VAT rate he was laughed out of town.  Can Mr. Parlon give any guarantee that if there was a reduction in VAT it would be passed on to the purchaser and would not be dissipated in the building process?  There are a couple of questions there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.171" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#N00600"><p>We are now on our third Minister for housing who has promised to do a lot.  The big initial challenge is to get support for money to be put into the system.  We believe there are now funds there to provide social housing.  There is a very frustrating delay in the State organising local authorities or housing agencies to get those tenders out and I reiterate that I guarantee that members of the CIF, whether contractors or specialist house builders, are waiting to tender and will do so very competitively but it is painfully slow for those tenders to come out.  We need hundreds of developments of 50 to 100 units of apartments if we are going to get the required volume.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#N00700"><p>Are there people in Mr. Parlon's industry who will build affordable houses as opposed to social housing or other accommodation?  Affordable housing is what we are missing.</p><p>Does the CIF have people in the industry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.174" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00200"><p>The new building regulations set a standard and clearly that is adding to the cost.  A cheap house cannot be built at the moment.  They are all built to a standard, which brings its own cost.  However, the Government put a housing delivery unit in place as well and deployed some hard nosed, experienced civil servants to see where the stoppages are.  There is frustration.  I have made many contacts with the unit and I have received a good hearing.  I said, for example, that developments were being held up here, there or wherever but there is a high level of inaction and difficulty getting activity going within the public sector, despite the good push from the political side to put the funding in place and from the Department.  It seems to be difficult for the public sector to get some projects over the line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.175" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jeanette Mair" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00300"><p>I support what Mr. Parlon said.  There are multiple issues around housing delivery but, through the Rebuilding Ireland programme, the Department has done significant work to put better structures in place.  There are still issues at local planning authority level, which we have touched on, including delays at the pre-planning stage.  There are delays before developers even get to site.  The delay is not related to being on site when everything is ready and the houses can be built.  The LIHAF was a welcome Government initiative.  It was oversubscribed when more than &euro;200 million was allocated to it originally.  Budget 2018 allocated a further &euro;75 million to the fund, which was hugely welcomed by local authorities and the building sector which are working in partnership and employing civil engineering contractors and so on to open up the lands.  Planning permission for a housing development will not be granted until the wastewater treatment plant or access roads are in place.  The problem with housing delivery is that it takes time.  The resourcing from administration through to planners at local authority level should be a significant focus of the committee, as it is a significant focus of the Department.  There has been a ramping up of resources in respect of planning and building standards throughout the local government sector.  That is one of the major delay factors.  I acknowledge there is debate in the media and so on around the statistics we use and the ESB connections which give us our completion figures.  Completions are increasing and, more important, commencements increased to approximately 15,000 for the first ten months of this year, which is a 45% increase on 2016.  We are on course to deliver approximately 18,500 houses this year and that will increase, according to our forecast, to 22,500 next year.  We are incrementally increasing annual housing supply to the 25,000 homes the ESRI estimates that we need.  The national planning framework has clear guidelines relating to where housing projects and population increases will be located up to 2040.  We need in the region of 550,000 new homes.  What is not mentioned is the pent-up demand and the additional supply that will have to come on stream over the next five years, particularly around some urban centres.  Planning permissions have increased and supply will improve significantly but it will all not come on stream this year.  Supply will increase incrementally over the next few years and, hopefully, by 2021, we should be up at the level of house building we need to be at to maintain supply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00400"><p>I have a supplementary question relating to finance and the private sector.  Mr. Parlon mentioned that the bigger players can get finance from the private sector on top of the pillar banks but the smaller players are getting caught.  Has the CIF considered bundling the smaller builders together to increase buying power when they seek a commercial arrangement?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.177" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00500"><p>We have had a great deal of engagement with the banks but clearly the Government's proposed &euro;750 million fund is a small builder's fund and it is being introduced on the basis of that demand.  There are other political issues but the budget was announced a while ago.  We are engaging with the Department of Finance and we hope that the fund will materialise quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00600"><p>Does the CIF hope that fund will clear the bottleneck?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.179" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Tom Parlon" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00700"><p>It will provide the capacity to build 6,000 houses.  That would make a big dent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00800"><p>Has any consideration been given to builders amalgamating?  That would give the CIF buying power if 14 or 15 members came together.  Their hand would be much stronger than that of one person.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.181" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Jeanette Mair" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O00900"><p>There is complexity around due diligence, which the investment arm or equity company would have to undertake, because in that case the balance sheets, history, capacity and competence of multiple firms would have to be examined rather than those of one firm.  That is a question the investment community would have to answer.  The problem is equity funds are not interested in lending shy of &euro;5 million because they will not generate a return on their investment and it is not worth the paperwork that they would have to go through.  That is why they are only interested in the larger builders and so on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O01000"><p>Mr. Cummins referred to inspections by EHOs.  He said that one official might arrive in the morning to check something and another might arrive in the afternoon to check something else and, therefore, there is a lack of joined-up thinking.  Are there fees associated with those inspections?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.183" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Adrian Cummins" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O01100"><p>Not for food safety inspections by EHOs but there are fees for fats, oils and grease traps payable to the inspecting company that goes in.  Our argument is this could all be done by the State in one inspection.  As the president of the association outlined, we have to deal with 28 different licensing or regulatory bodies.  In 2012, we were promised that this would be studied to try to amalgamate the inspections into one inspection that might cover four different regulatory regimes, use of technology to reduce paperwork and form filling and some thinking outside the box that would ultimately reduce costs for a business.  However, there is a reason for the 28 licensing or regulatory bodies but why can they not be merged to ensure only one inspection?</p> <p>  With regard to Deputy Neville's question about employment models, productivity and profit share, my colleagues will speak about productivity and profit share.  The average number of staff in a small business in our sector is 15 full-time equivalents.  It is usually busy between Thursday night and Sunday afternoon, which is a short window to maximise profit at the end of the day.  Businesses tend towards casual labour at the weekend, usually students or those looking for part-time work.  Many of our businesses do not open on Monday or Tuesday because it is not worth their while opening.  Many also close on Sunday evenings.  The committee is examining the cost of doing business and we need to examine how we can reduce costs and give people more work.  According to our balance sheet, 36% of expenditure is on payroll and that is the average throughout the industry.  If payroll costs exceed 36%, one is entering the drop zone of a non-profitable business.  Our businesses are people businesses and customers will vote their feet.  They expect good service and they expect to meet good staff.  We are not into lean technology similar to a manufacturing plant.  We are different from other sectors.  It is about utilising people in our business but we have to make a profit at the end of the day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.184" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Liam Edwards" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#O01200"><p>The RAI's big gripe with EHOs is the inconsistencies in their reports.  The reports do not cost money directly but they result in indirect costs.  There is a great deal of inconsistency even within counties.  For example, many members have a couple of restaurants.</p><p>They may own restaurants that are two miles away from each other and they are told to do one thing in one restaurant and another thing in the other restaurant so there are big discrepancies.  That is the big gripe and costs occur.</p><p> I hope everyone in the room would agree that the standard and quality of food in the restaurant industry has improved dramatically in the past couple of years.  As an association, we feel it has.  It has improved despite a shortage of skilled staff.  In-house training has been huge in our industry.  A lot of chefs have taken on kitchen porters and trained them slowly to become commis chefs or second chefs.  Many become fully qualified chefs and some even have their own businesses.  The other success has been chef-owners who, because there was a shortage of skills, decided they would own their own restaurants.  That is what Mr. Cummins spoke about.  When restaurants close on Mondays and Tuesdays, it is because a lot of chef-owners make a life choice to close on a Monday and Tuesday and to give all their staff those days off so they are all refreshed coming back on Wednesday.  That is food productivity.  It is what restaurants are doing now.  That is why they are surviving and why there is a good standard of food around Ireland.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00200"><p>Would Mr. Stapleton like to contribute at this point?  I was going to ask about wind and solar energy but it has already been addressed.  Mr. Stapleton said there is a lack of skilled workers.  Is it specific to one type of farming such as the dairy industry or is it across all sectors?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.187" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00300"><p>Yes.  It ties in perfectly with Deputy Neville's question.  Dairy, horticulture, pigs and poultry are the sectors that have the opportunity to grow their businesses.  There is a different skill set required and a different level of skills shortages.  Deputy Neville asked about dairy farming and referred to it being the backbone or his constituency.  Up until 1 January 2015, there was a milk quota.  For 30 years there was no increase in demand and a good deal of potential built up in the system.  Over the past three years, we have seen that potential used up.  We have gone from capacity to a deficit of skilled workers.  It is not new.  The Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine has set up a working group under Tom Moran to see how the skills shortage can be rectified.  It put in place a pilot project which operated in Kilkenny.  The last I heard five people have been taken off the live register.  Its aim was to take people off the live register and train them to milk cows.  I am not sure if the people who are on the live register right now have the potential, skills or interest in taking up milking cows as a career.  As farmers, we are interested in taking on workers and building a career for them in our businesses but we have to take into account that we have significant challenges as employers.  Much of our work is seasonal.  In dairy farms, it is around calving and breeding time.  Where crops are growing, whether grain or horticulture crops, the big demand is around harvest time so it is seasonal.  It is the nature of farming.  By and large, it is a low-margin business, which means many of our employers struggle to match minimum wage requirements.  They have to try to match the employment they can offer with their ability to pay for it.  There is more work available to people than our businesses generate the capacity to pay for.  We have to manage and balance that.  The type of skills shortage we have is on two levels.  It occurs with the general operatives who do the basic work on a daily basis and within that there is relief work.  There are farmers who end up working 80 or 90 hours a week at busy times.  It is a challenge from a health and safety point of view.  It is also a challenge from an animal welfare point of view to make sure there is enough capacity to get those animals managed.  That is one side of it.  There is a shortage that is starting to impact on the potential of the business to achieve what it can for us as farmers and for the economy.</p> <p>  With regard to the issue of apprenticeships, there will be a shortage of future managers and business owners and we need to have a roadway for those people.  The first step is to create apprenticeships, to find a way of assessing farmers and to treat them as potential trainers for the future so that when new people go on to farms run with really good, efficient, modern technology, they will come out after one, two or three years with a certificate or qualification to show what they have done.  It will provide those people with a pathway to go on to become farm managers, assistant farm managers or business owners.  That is the way we can develop dairy farming to its maximum potential.  There is the potential for 6,000 jobs to be created in our business in the next five or six years.   </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00400"><p>On the skills shortage in farming, has there been a geographic mapping of where the skills shortages are and in what type of areas?  In social protection, the Intreo offices, as an employment agency, have done quite extensive research into the skills that people who attend those offices have.  I always worry when people talk about the first option being bringing in foreign workers who need work permits.  What level of engagement has there been with the Intreo services on this issue?  I listen to my rural colleagues who constantly say there is a challenge in respect of part-time employment and that the number of people in receipt of farm assist payments has increased.  Such people obviously already have skills because they are already part-time farmers.  I am anxious for there to be some joined-up thinking between the IFA and the Intreo offices.  Perhaps there already is.  Is there a level of engagement with the Intreo services of the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection to see if the skill base and workers are there but are not being tapped into?  That may already be happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.189" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00500"><p>I gave the example of the pilot project in Kilkenny.  We had hoped for a lot more than five people to get involved.  There certainly is the capacity on farms to try it but there is a mismatch because the people on the live register do not see farming as a future career.  It tends to be the case that people who go to work on farms come from rural areas and from the locality.</p> <p>  People who are eligible for farm assist payments tend to come from western counties and not the counties where the intensive commercialisation and expansion of the dairy industry has occurred.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00600"><p>There has been an expansion of farm assist beyond rural areas in the west.  Has there been engagement other than the pilot scheme?  We have to consider the unemployment figures in rural Ireland.  Mr. Stapleton is saying there are job opportunities.  There has to be a matching up of skills rather than the first option being to look for work permits for workers from outside the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.191" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00700"><p>That is why the pilot scheme was put in place.  Does it need to be expanded to other areas?  I am sceptical that it has the capacity to solve the problem we have.  Our door is open for people to come and learn the skills required to manage cows.  We would be delighted to see people coming in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00800"><p>Is the IFA engaging with the Intreo offices?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.193" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#P00900"><p>The answer to the Senator's question is that I do not know.  The pilot project was a major effort in an area where we thought there were opportunities to draw people in and the numbers that went through with it were not at the anticipated level.  Farmers are making huge efforts in villages and towns to try to get people to work on farms.  Working on a farm is a cultural issue.  It is not for everybody.  It is probably not practical, realistic or ideal in a lot of situations for a person who grows up and lives in a town all of his or her life to go out and work on a farm.  While a lot of the work might be seen as manual, one needs a fair degree of experience and skills.</p><p>It involves looking after animals.  People would say one can teach a person to milk cows but it is not that simple.  It is quite a technical operation.  If one makes a mistake milking cows, I will not go into the nitty gritty of it but it is a very specialised job.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00200"><p>Mr. McDonald's argument regarding work permits would be much stronger if he were to formally engage on a larger scale and show that people with the necessary skills are not available here and neither is their potential to employ such people here.  The association has to engage on this on a larger scale other than a pilot  project.  The same applies to the argument regarding the expansion of a work permit.  There have been nasty experiences regarding work permits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.196" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00300"><p>While undoubtedly there is certainly a demand for workers all year round, there is a seasonality factor.  There is a precedent both here and in the UK, where it has worked very well, for a seasonal workers scheme.  The frustration expressed by our members relates to the fact that we have had a very rapid expansion on the dairy side and farmers are trying very hard to get people to work on farms.  They cannot get people.  It is probably a bit unfair to say that the work permits solution is the first option because farmers have tried very hard to get people, but some response is required.  We would suggest having a more supervised type programme for people to come in and work on Irish farms would certainly be worth piloting.  We believe there are many people from countries outside the European Union who have a latent skill in agriculture who would have a great deal to contribute if they came to Ireland to work and they would also have the potential to get involved at managerial level on farms.  There is a great deal of frustration among farmers.  Someone else made the point that farmers are essentially sole traders.  They do not operate like a big company that has an advertising department and human resources department to seek to take on somebody.  This is a complex enough operation for a sole trader.  I believe we need to intervene if we are going to make it work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1328" speakername="Tom Neville" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00400"><p>I must concur with that comment.  Culturally, we have been moving towards an increasingly more urbanised environment during the past 20 to 30 years and it has been much harder to attract people into farming.  The sons of farmers who I would have gone to school with back in the day would have grabbed the opportunity to take over the family farm but they were given an education, choices and options to do different things.  Culturally, we have changed and we are grappling with all of that as well in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.198" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Martin Stapleton" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00500"><p>It is much easier for the farmers I know to bring in somebody who would speak their language to operate in their business so it is out of desperation that they want to bring in foreign workers.  I would regularly hear farmers who have taken on workers from eastern European countries speak about the difficulty they have not only in teaching them the business but in trying to teach them the language, but it is far better than not having anybody to do the work.  We would be delighted if we had Irish workers who were interested and wanted to pursue a career in agriculture and it is because we cannot get them that we are looking for foreign workers.  That also applies to European workers.  The supply of workers that traditionally came from Poland, Lithuania and from down as far as Romania has dried up in the past year or two.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.199" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00600"><p>We understand that in Poland they are bringing in many Ukrainians to do some of manual work and those people were traditionally a source of employment to probably all of our sectors here.  The dynamic is moving.  This is not only an Irish problem.  The improvements in the European economy are causing knock-on problems all over the place.  I cannot stress enough how big an issue this is for some dairy farmers because of the stress involved.  Cows must be milked twice a day and that is a huge tie.  Farmers not being able to get relief labour is an increasing point of concern that we pick up at all our meetings around the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00700"><p>I thank all the witnesses.  That concludes our discussion for today.  I thank all the witnesses for coming in and engaging with the committee.  The exchange was very informative.  We will invite the witnesses back when we produce our document, which I believe will happen at the start of February.  We will have the launch on Thursday of our document on the non-EEA crew in the Irish fishing fleet under the atypical workers scheme and I ask everybody to be here for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00800"><p>That was quite a mouthful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1220" speakername="Mary Butler" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JEJ2017121200002#Q00900"><p>The joint committee is now adjourned until January 2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2017-12-12a.203" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 6.35 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 16 January 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>