<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht: Select Sub-Committee on the Environment, Community and Local Government</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 10:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Paudie Coffey, Deputy Tony McLoughlin, Deputy Noel Coonan, Deputy Catherine Murphy, Deputy Dessie Ellis,* Deputy Jan O'Sullivan (Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government). Deputy Kevin Humphreys,</p><p>* In the absence of Deputy Brian Stanley.</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL McCARTHY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00100">Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2012: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00200"><p>Cuirfimid t&uacute;s leis an gcruinni&uacute;.  T&aacute; an cruinni&uacute; seo ar si&uacute;l chun breathn&uacute; ar an mBille um Thion&oacute;ntachta&iacute; C&oacute;naithe (Leas&uacute;) (Uimh. 2) 2012.  This meeting has been convened for the purpose of the consideration of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2012.  Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it agus a hoifigigh, Cian O Lion&aacute;in Uasal, principal officer; Ms Catherine Higgins, assistant principal officer; and Ms Paula O'Reilly, assistant principal officer, from the Department's housing regulation section.  I call on the Minister of State to make her opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00300"><p>I am very pleased to be here to take Committee Stage of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2012.  Any healthy society with a well run economy needs a balanced housing sector in order to address the needs of various types of household and their different needs.  Among the many reforms required is more equitable treatment of tenures.  The legislation before the select sub-committee is, therefore, another important step in the ongoing development of a strong, vibrant and well developed rented sector.  Before we proceed to discuss the amendments, I wish to briefly outline the key issues we will be discussing.</p><p>  The Residential Tenancies Act 2004 set out a framework of rights and responsibilities for landlords and tenants in the rented sector.  The application of that framework to all tenants and landlords, regardless of the form of rented housing involved, is an important principle for the Government.  The Bill will extend the framework to housing in the not-for-profit approved housing body sector and, thereafter, we will need to turn our attention to how best to legislatively provide for a similar extension to the local authority housing sector.  I have previously referred to this as an evolutionary, rather than a revolutionary, approach to housing rights and I am confident that there is broad support for this strategy.  Good and broad support for the Bill was voiced on Second Stage, for which I thank members.</p><p>  On Second Stage I committed to extending the remit of the 2004 Act to as much of the approved housing body sector as possible.  The impact of the amendments which have been tabled will lead to the entire sector coming under the 2004 Act, with the exception of those tenancies that would be exempt under its provisions.  The Government's Committee Stage amendments to the Bill, as published, include a number designed to provide for the tenancy registration fee and timeframe that will apply to the approved housing body sector.  Also included are further measures to assist the board in the performance of its functions, as well as amendments to clarify the scope of its legal powers in terms of enforcement.</p><p>  The issue of over-holding, that is, where a tenant remains <i>in situ</i> without paying any rent, is a significant problem for landlords and I am pleased to be able to introduce amendments in this area.  A core legal principle, one which bears restating, is that, no matter the circumstances, the correct rent must be paid.  In an environment where many landlords are struggling to pay mortgages on buy-to-let properties, the creation of a mechanism that will allow the PRTB to deal with over-holding in a much quicker fashion than is often the case should greatly help matters.  </p><p>  An issue of equal concern to tenants is that of illegal retention of their deposits by a minority of landlords.  I am absolutely determined to deliver on the commitment in the programme for Government to establish a deposit retention scheme to address this issue.  My Department is engaged with the Office of the Attorney General on this matter and I look forward to introducing the relevant amendments when the Bill goes before the Seanad.</p><p>  I will also introduce amendments in the Seanad to improve the mechanism by which anti-social behaviour is dealt with and, specifically, to make it easier for neighbours, residents' associations, etc., to take a case to the board on the grounds of such behaviour by tenants.  I was very close to having amendments finalised in this area for today's discussion, but I am confident that they will be ready very soon.  Without further ado and if it is acceptable, I would like to begin moving the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00400"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.9" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00600"><p>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00700"><p>I move amendment No. 1:<blockquote><br />In page 5, subsection (2), line 33, to delete &quot;<i>sections 10</i> and <i>43</i>&quot; and substitute &quot;<i>sections 10, 43</i> and <i>45</i>&quot;.</blockquote>These are technical drafting amendments to provide for the amendment of the collective citations for the Housing Acts and the Residential Tenancies Act.  They are a consequence of amendment No. 54 which amends the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1992 and which we will be discussing later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.12" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A00900"><p>I move amendment No. 2:<blockquote><br />In page 6, subsection (3), line 1, to delete &quot;<i>sections 10 </i>and <i>43</i>&quot; and substitute &quot;<i>sections 10</i>, <i>43 </i>and <i>45</i>&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.16" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A01400"><p>Amendments Nos. 3, 6 and 8 to 13, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000002#A01500"><p>I move amendment No. 3:<blockquote><br />In page 6, to delete lines 21 to 40 and substitute the following:&quot; &quot;(<i>c</i>) a dwelling that is let by or to a public authority,&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote>On foot of detailed discussions with the approved housing bodies sector during the initial drafting of the Bill, it was decided to exclude approved housing body tenants in receipt of care support services from the application of the Residential Tenancies Act.  This was done on the basis that the sector was of the view that these services could be more effectively delivered outside the confines of the Act.  However, in the light of further consultation with the Irish Council for Social Housing and the sector in general following publication of the Bill, I decided that the 2004 Act should be applied to all approved housing body tenants, unless they came under one of the exclusions already provided for in that legislation.  The amendments in this group provide for that policy change, which I signalled during the debate on Second Stage and which was supported by almost all Deputies who took part in that debate.  In essence, this is a rights-based issue and the amendments will lead to the same rights, obligations and legal protections being extended to as many tenants as possible.</p><p>  Amendment No. 3 provides for the inclusion of all approved housing body tenancies under the Residential Tenancies Act 2004 by completely removing the exemption in section 3(2)(<i>c</i>)(ii) of that Act.</p> <p>The effect of this amendment will be to extend the rights and protections provided by the 2004 Act to a greater number of approved housing body tenants.  This is a significant and far-reaching improvement and was raised by one of the members on Second Stage.</p><p> Amendments Nos. 6 and 13 are drafting amendments to clarify the wording used in the Bill, as published.  I commend these provisions to members and I am happy to discuss the details further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B00200"><p>To clarify, several of our amendments have been ruled out of order on the grounds of cost.  It is very frustrating, having taken the time to bring forward proposals, to have them ruled out in this way.  Where costs arise, there is always the possibility of making them up in other ways.</p><p>  In regard to the amendments, the Minister of State has indicated that she will consider a scheme to include local authorities at some future date.  Excluding local authorities from the rigorous rules applying to other housing bodies does not make sense.  However, I take on board the Minister of State's undertaking to review the matter in the future.  It would be a very important step.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 in the name of Deputy Brian Stanley have been ruled out of order because they involve a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B00600"><p>I move amendment No. 6:<blockquote><br />In page 7, to delete lines 6 to 8 and substitute the following:&quot;(<i>b</i>) for the avoidance of doubt, this Act does apply to that dwelling where that dwelling is the subject of a sub-tenancy arising from that sub-letting, including any such sub-tenancy created before the commencement of this subsection.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.26" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B00800"><p>Amendment No. 7 has been ruled out of order because it involves a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 7 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B01000"><p>I move amendment No. 8:<blockquote><br />In page 7, line 16, after &quot;2009,&quot; to insert &quot;and&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B01200"><p>I move amendment No. 9:<blockquote><br />In page 7, lines 19 to 22, to delete all words from and including &quot;and&quot; in line 19 down to and including &quot;and&quot; in line 22 and substitute the following:&quot;and&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.32" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B01400"><p>I move amendment No. 10:<blockquote><br />In page 7, line 28, after &quot;2009,&quot; to insert &quot;and&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.34" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B01600"><p>I move amendment No. 11:<blockquote><br />In page 7, lines 31 to 33, to delete all words from and including &quot;and&quot; in line 31 down to and including &quot;section 3(2)(<i>c</i>),&quot; in line 33.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B01800"><p>I move amendment No. 12:<blockquote><br />In page 7, line 45, to delete &quot;and&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.38" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B02000"><p>I move amendment No. 13:<blockquote><br />In page 8, line 2, to delete &quot;accordingly.&quot; and substitute the following:<blockquote>&quot;accordingly, and</blockquote>(<i>c</i>) notwithstanding that the dwelling is the subject of a sub-tenancy, the subtenancy shall be treated as a tenancy under this Act and references to a tenancy in this Act shall, in so far as they concern that dwelling, be construed accordingly.&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.40" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.41" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 3, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.42" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B02400"><p>Amendments Nos. 14 to 16, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B02500"><p>I move amendment No. 14:<blockquote><br />In page 9, line 4, to delete &quot;and&quot;.</blockquote>These amendments provide that sections 19 to 22, inclusive, and section 139 of the Residential Tenancies Act 2004 will not apply to approved housing body tenancies.  Approved housing bodies use the differential rent scheme applied by local authorities to determine the rent charged for their dwellings.  Under this system, the amount of rent to be paid by a tenant is based on the income of the household and the provisions in the 2004 Act, including section 19 which deals with market rent, conflict with the scheme.  As the differential rent scheme is more advantageous to approved housing body tenants than the provisions relating to rent in the 2004 Act, approved housing body tenancies are excluded from these sections.</p><p>  The amendments also provide for the exclusion of approved housing bodies from section 139 of the 2004 Act which provides that a landlord must update the details of his or her registration with the Private Residential Tenancies Board whenever the rent changes.  As the rent might change a number of times in a given year under the differential rent scheme, approved housing bodies are also exempt from this section owing to the potentially significant administrative burden it would impose.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.45" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B02700"><p>I move amendment No. 15:<blockquote><br />In page 9, to delete line 8 and substitute the following:&quot;a dwelling the subject of a tenancy referred to in section 3(4),&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.47" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B02900"><p>I move amendment No. 16:<blockquote><br />In page 9, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:&quot;(<i>e</i>) sections 19 to 22 shall not apply to a dwelling the subject of a tenancy referred to in section 3(4), and<br />(<i>f</i>) section 139 shall not apply in respect of a dwelling the subject of a tenancy referred to in section 3(4).&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.49" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03100"><p>Amendments Nos. 17, 18 and 22 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03200"><p>I move amendment No. 17:<blockquote><br />In page 9, subsection (2), line 13, to delete &quot;section 3B(1)(<i>b</i>)&quot; and substitute &quot;section 3B(<i>b</i>)&quot;.</blockquote>These are drafting amendments to correct errors in the numbering of the Bill, as published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.52" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03400"><p>I move amendment No. 18:<blockquote><br />In page 9, subsection (4), line 23, to delete &quot;section 3B(1)(<i>a</i>)&quot; and substitute &quot;section 3B(<i>a</i>)&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.54" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03600"><p>Amendments Nos. 19 to 21, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03700"><p>I move amendment No. 19:<blockquote><br />In page 9, subsection (5), line 26, to delete &quot;paragraph&quot; where it firstly occurs and substitute &quot;paragraphs&quot;.</blockquote>On foot of the amendments applying the 2004 Act to all relevant approved housing body tenancies, I am proposing to include a further ground of termination for Part 4 tenancies which will only apply to approved housing bodies.  This new ground for termination will allow approved bodies to terminate a Part 4 tenancy in circumstances where the dwelling is no longer suitable to the needs of the household because a member of that household requires care support services which are not available.</p><p>  The amendments are designed to allow approved housing bodies to terminate a tenancy in very limited circumstances where the care support services available are not sufficient to allow the tenant to continue to live in the dwelling.  For example, termination of a tenancy may be necessary where an elderly tenant is no longer able to live alone and needs to move to accommodation with on-site support, or where a tenant with special needs is required to move to accommodation with a higher level of care.  Amendment No. 21 provides for the definition of care support services to be included in the principal Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03800"><p>I accept the necessity of these provisions.  The key issue is the safeguards in terms of who will make the call on the termination of a tenancy and what engagement there will be with the individual concerned.  People will sometimes fight to stay in a particular property, even where it no longer meets their needs.  If a tenant is happy with the alternative accommodation offered, there is no problem.  My concern, however, is whether the mechanism whereby these decisions are made will be sufficiently robust to ensure that is the case.  Will the Minister of State indicate how she envisages this playing out in practice?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B03900"><p>We have to get the balance right in these proposals.  Our concern is that if this measure is not in place, approved housing bodies might be slow to take tenants who are likely at some point in the future - people usually sign up to a tenancy for four years or more - to progress to needing the type of care services that simply are not available.  We are anxious not to create a disincentive for housing bodies in taking on certain clients.  They must cater for everybody, particularly elderly persons and people with disabilities.  For this reason, we are including a mechanism for the termination of a tenancy where it is clearly not possible for a person to receive the supports he or she needs in the current dwelling.</p><p>  As I said, we are eager to ensure there is a balance.  A number of advocacy services will be available to tenants.  Threshold is probably the most obvious, given that it already advocates generally for people in rented accommodation of one type or another.  The organisation has represented people before the courts and, under these proposals, will be able to do the same with regard to the PRTB.  Likewise, the Third Age national advocacy programme is ideally placed to advocate for elderly people.  The national advocacy service for people with disabilities will take a similar role for the individuals it represents.  Where a person requires advocacy, there are several bodies with a great deal of experience in the area.</p><p>  I am very conscious that these provisions will have to be carefully monitored to ensure matters are handled in a sensitive manner.  We do not want a situation where approved housing bodies would be reluctant to take people whose condition may deteriorate.  We are striving to get the balance right in these amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000003#B04000"><p>Will the Minister of State comment on the position of large families?  I am dealing with a family of ten who are being accommodated in a hotel.  Their housing needs are not being met because the local authority cannot deal with them.</p> <p>This is a complicated case as there is a mother, a father and ten children.  If they secure private rented accommodation which is what is being sought because they are not deemed to be homeless, will that mean that with the measures the Minister of State is including they will be scrutinised more and that they will have to be considered in a proper fashion by the approved housing bodies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C00200"><p>No.  The intention is not to interfere in such a situation.  This measure only applies to approved housing bodies.  If the family were to move into private rented accommodation, this section would not apply in those circumstances.  The intention is that it will only apply in circumstances where a person is demonstrably not able to stay in the accommodation because the supports are not appropriate.  There are other mechanisms of the State available, including the fair deal scheme and health services, which provide care for people who need a greater level of care.  The idea is that there will be engagement before it reaches that point in order that a suitable alternative place can be found for the person concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C00300"><p>The Minister of State referred to advocacy groups, some of which I know well and I would be very happy if they were the advocacy groups in this respect, but will they have a specific function in being advocates?  The issue may not only be that the person concerned is wheelchair bound but often whether the person concerned can have soft supports, as it were, from his or her neighbours.  We all know how traumatic it is to move house away from all the things with which one has got comfortable.  An holistic approach is needed in terms of what the person sees as being in his or her best interests.  As long as there is a function for the advocacy groups in making sure an holistic approach is taken, I can see it working.  As the Minister of State will know, there is very little choice within the housing stock, whether it be small units in a supported living environment that are located downstairs as opposed to upstairs, or otherwise.  She has inherited a serious problem in that respect.  If people could be moved out of this sector, is there a possibility that they could be moved into units in the private rented sector in which they would cease to have the protections they have had?  It is the possible loss of such safeguards that concerns me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C00400"><p>In engaging with the approved housing bodies I intend to ensure the dialogue will continue.  As members will know, the approved housing bodies already have facilities for people in wheelchairs and people with considerable needs.  There is no intention to change this.  This measure will only apply in a situation where it is demonstrable that a person cannot manage anymore in the accommodation provided.  The primary advocates will probably be the person concerned in the first instance and his or her family, neighbours, etc., but there are these other bodies also and they can play a role, if necessary.</p><p>  I want to be clear in setting out that this is not something we expect to happen frequently.  It will arise only in those unusual cases in which the approved housing body finds itself in a situation where it simply cannot cater for the needs of a person whose needs have advanced considerably during the period of the tenancy with the body in question and where it is clearly in his or her interests to be placed where he or she will receive more appropriate care.  I expect that person will have engaged for a long time with the health service before that happens, for example, to ensure there is a place for him or her to go.  There is no intention that he or she will be placed in the private rented sector.  This measure will apply where the person goes to a place where he or she will have a greater level of care appropriate to his or her needs, not in any other circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.64" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C00600"><p>I move amendment No. 20:<blockquote><br />In page 9, line 38, to delete &ldquo;renewed.&rdquo;.&rdquo; and substitute the following:<blockquote>&ldquo;renewed.</blockquote>4B. In the case of a dwelling referred to in section 3(4), the dwelling is no longer suitable for the accommodation needs of the household referred to in that section, or any member of that household, because the requirements of that household, or any member of that household, for care support services, exceed the care support services that are available to that household or any member of that household.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C00800"><p>I move amendment No. 21:<blockquote><br />In page 9, lines 39 to 42, to delete subsection (6) and substitute the following:&quot;(6) Section 35 of the Principal Act is amended by inserting the following subsections after subsection (6):<br />&quot;(7) Paragraph 4 of the Table is subject to section 3B(<i>c</i>) (inserted by <i>section 4 </i>of the <i>Residential Tenancies (Amendment) Act 2013</i>). <br />(8) In paragraph 4B of the Table, &lsquo;care support services&rsquo; means&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) medical care,<br />(<i>b</i>) personal care services, the primary purpose of which is the provision of assistance to address a physical or mental requirement of the household concerned, or a member of that household, or<br />(<i>c</i>) a service, the provision of which is assisted by the Health Service Executive under section 39 of the Health Act 2004.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.69" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Section 4, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.70" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Sections 5 and 6 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C01300"><p>I move amendment No. 22:<blockquote><br />In page 10, line 21, to delete &quot;section 3B(1)(<i>d</i>)&quot; and substitute &quot;section 3B(<i>d</i>)&quot;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Section 7, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.75" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Sections 8 to 10, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.76" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C01700"><p>Amendment Nos. 23 to 25, inclusive are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000004#C01800"><p>I move amendment No. 23:<blockquote><br />In page 11, before section 11, but in Part 2, to insert the following new section:11.&mdash;(1) Section 134 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (2), by substituting &quot;Subject to subsection (2A), an application&quot; for &quot;An application&quot;,<br />(<i>b</i>) by inserting the following subsection after subsection (2):<blockquote>&quot;(2A) Where an application under this section is made in respect of a tenancy and the dwelling that is the subject of that tenancy is a dwelling referred to in section 3(4), an application under this section in respect of such tenancy shall be made&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) where the tenancy has commenced before the day on which section 3(4) comes into operation, within 12 months from the day on which section 3(4) comes into operation,<br />(<i>b</i>) where the tenancy commences within the period of 12 months from the day on which section 3(4) comes into operation&mdash;<blockquote>(i) within 12 months from the day on which section 3(4) comes into operation, or<br />(ii) within 1 month from the commencement of the tenancy, whichever is the later, or </blockquote>(<i>c</i>) where the tenancy commences on a day that falls 12 or more months from the day on which section 3(4) comes into operation, within 1 month from the commencement of the tenancy.&quot;,</blockquote></blockquote>(<i>c</i>) by substituting the following subsection for subsection (3):<br />&quot;(3) An application under this section shall&mdash;<blockquote><blockquote>(<i>a</i>) be in the prescribed form,<br />(<i>b</i>) subject to subsections (4) and (7), be accompanied by&mdash;<blockquote>(i) subject to subparagraph (ii), the fee referred to in section 137(1)(<i>b</i>)(ii), or<br />(ii) in the case of a tenancy referred to in subsection (2A), the fee specified in section 137A(1)(<i>a</i>) or as the case may be the fee prescribed under section 137A(1)(<i>b</i>),<br />and</blockquote>(<i>c</i>) where a fee referred to in subsection (8) is required to be paid under that subsection, be accompanied by that fee.&quot;,</blockquote></blockquote>(<i>d</i>) in subsection (4)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) by substituting &quot;requirements&quot; for &quot;requirement&quot;,<br />(ii) by substituting &quot;do&quot; for &quot;does&quot;, and<br />(iii) by substituting &quot;subsections (2)(<i>a</i>), (2)(<i>b</i>), (2A)(<i>a</i>) or (2A)(<i>b</i>)&quot; for &quot;subsection (2)(<i>a</i>) or (<i>b</i>)&quot;,</blockquote>(<i>e</i>) in subsection (5)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in paragraph (<i>a</i>), by inserting &quot;or where the applications are made pursuant to subsection (2A), the fee specified in section 137A(1)(<i>a</i>) or as the case may be the fee prescribed under section 137A(1)(<i>b</i>),&quot; after &quot;section 137,&quot;,<br />(ii) in paragraph (<i>a</i>), by substituting &quot;subsections (2)(<i>a</i>), (2)(<i>b</i>), (2A)(<i>a</i>) or (2A)(<i>b</i>)&quot; for &quot;subsection (2)(<i>a</i>) or (<i>b</i>)&quot;, and <br />(iii) by substituting the following paragraph for paragraph (<i>b</i>):<blockquote>&quot;(<i>b</i>) the applicant has paid&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in respect of several applications falling within section 137(3), the single fee referred to in section 137(2) and the dwellings to which those several applications related included the relevant dwelling, or<br />(ii) in respect of several applications falling within section 137A(3) the single fee referred to in section 137A(2) and the dwellings to which those several applications related included the relevant dwelling,&quot;, </blockquote></blockquote>and</blockquote>(<i>f</i>) by inserting the following subsections after subsection (6):<blockquote>&quot;(7) The requirement, in subsection (3), for an application to be accompanied by a fee shall not apply to an application to register a further Part 4 tenancy pursuant to section 135(1)(<i>c</i>) if the application to register a further Part 4 tenancy is made within the period specified&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (2)(<i>a</i>) or (2)(<i>b</i>), or <br />(<i>b</i>) in subsection (2A)(<i>a</i>) or (2A)(<i>b</i>).</blockquote>(8) Where an application under this section is not made in electronic form the applicant shall pay the prescribed fee.<br />(9) The fee prescribed for subsection (8) shall not exceed the reasonable costs of processing the application.&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>In summary, these amendments provide for the registration fees approved housing bodies will pay to register their tenancies with the PRTB and the timeframe within which these tenancies must be registered.  They also provide for some other miscellaneous amendments in relation to fees.</p><p>  Under the 2004 Act, a landlord must register a tenancy within one month of the commencement of the tenancy.  Amendment No. 23 provides for the timeframe within which approved housing bodies must register their tenancies as follows.  Where the tenancy was entered into before the commencement of the new provisions, it must be registered within 12 months from the commencement date.  Where the tenancy is entered into 12 months or more after the commencement of the new provisions, it must be registered within one month of the commencement of the tenancy.  This mirrors the current requirements for the private sector.  Where the tenancy commences within the first year after the commencement of the new provisions, it must be registered either within 12 months from the commencement of the new provision or within one month of the tenancy, whichever is the later.  </p><p>  This registration timeframe takes into account the significant numbers of existing tenancies held by approved housing bodies and the significant administrative burden of registering these tenancies.  Therefore, I have sought to give approved housing bodies as long a timeframe as possible within which to register, while having regard to the need to have finality in the process.  As such, all approved housing bodies have a full year to register their existing tenancies.  This can now be done quickly and easily on the PRTB's online system.  There is also an interim period provided for tenancies created in the first year after commencement.  After the first year of operation of the new system, all approved housing bodies' tenancies must be registered within one month, which mirrors the system in the private sector.</p><p>  Provision is also made in amendment No. 23 for the PRTB to charge an administration fee for processing a hard copy application form.  The amount of the fee must be prescribed by the Minister and must not exceed the reasonable cost of processing the application.  In addition, the amendment provides for the abolition of the registration fee for reregistering a tenancy after four years as long as the reregistration is done within the specified timeframes.  The removal of this fee will encourage stable long-term tenancies in the private sector.  This will also remove a significant financial burden from approved housing bodies as the approved housing bodies sector is predominantly made up of long-term secure tenancies.</p><p>  Amendments Nos. 24 and 25 provide for changes to the composite registration fee charged by the PRTB.  Section 137 of the 2004 Act provides for what is known as the composite registration fee or the multiple registration fee.  This allows a landlord to avail of a significant discount when registering at the same time multiple tenancies of dwellings in the same property.  This amendment limits the number of tenancies that can be registered using the composite fee to ten.</p><p>  Amendment No. 25 provides for the registration timeframe for approved housing bodies.  Where the tenancy is registered within the first year after the commencement of these provisions, the fee to be paid by approved housing bodies will be &euro;45 for a single tenancy and &euro;187.50 for multiple registrations.  This is equal to half of the registration fee currently paid by landlords in the private sector.  The amendments further provide that the fee after the first 12 months is to be prescribed by the Minister.   The intention is that approved housing bodies will pay the same fee as private landlords after the initial discount period.  That fee is currently &euro;90 per tenancy.  A similar power is also given in relation to prescribed fees for late registration, which I intend to be the same as the fees charged in the private sector. </p><p>  The amendments make provision for a graduated late fee.  The 2004 Act provides that if a landlord is late in registering a tenancy, he or she must pay double the registration fee.  The amendments provide for penalties for late registration on an ascending scale.</p> <p>The purpose of the amendment is to incentivise early registration but also to make the system fairer, as under the current provision, a landlord who pays the fee a year late is subject to the same penalty as a landlord who pays it a day late.  The late fee will be &euro;20 for each month the landlord is late in registering the tenancy.  I also intend to provide on Report Stage for a maximum total late fee that may be charged.  These amendments achieve a fair balance and I ask members to support them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D00200"><p>I agree with much of what has been said.  Regarding the fees, what penalty will be put in place if the approved housing bodies are not prepared to register properly?  The Minister of State has laid out a number of timeframes, but as a new system is being introduced, how feasible are some of them in allowing people an opportunity to register properly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D00300"><p>I am broadly supportive of what is being provided for, but I ask about the definition of approved housing bodies and whether voluntary housing associations will be included in that category?  Some of them are dysfunctional.  I can give the Minister of State an example of where tenants inappropriately ended up in court because the process had been mishandled.  I am sure she is aware of some of them and I could give her others, but I would be surprised if they had not been brought to her attention.  I presume voluntary housing associations are included as approved housing bodies.  Is there anything in this section that will bring them into line or is it likely that if there is a deficiency in that regard, it can be corrected on Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D00400"><p>In reply to Deputy Dessie Ellis, we have had extensive discussions with those involved in the sector while working on the Bill and they are aware of the timeframes proposed.  They may not love them, but they accept them, as well as the fees to be charged, on which there were detailed discussions with them.  We wanted them to be affordable.  That is the reason they can pay half the fee rather than paying the full fee.</p><p>  On the issue of late fees, it will be the same as for the private sector, that is, &euro;20 a month on an ascending scale.  As I said, on Report Stage I intend to put a cap on the figure.  The sector is very much aware of the content of this amendment and I hope it is accepting of it.  We have not received any indication that those involved in it are not accepting of it and we have had ongoing discussions with them.</p><p>  With regard to the definition, "approved housing body" means a body standing approved for the purposes of section 6 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1992.  We did a trawl of housing bodies, some of which have been deregistered, mainly because they are not active, but we are also working with them on a voluntary code which will take in governance issues and the concerns Deputy Dessie Ellis expressed.  Some of the issues of concern arise in Deputy Catherine Murphy's constituency and have been brought to my attention.  We will have a voluntary code.  Eventually, we will have a regulatory code because we must have what is happening in this sector fully transparent and above board.  It is not in the interests of any of those involved to have a few rogue operators among them.  I accept that there are issues outstanding in regard to a few of them, but we are actively working to ensure they will be properly regulated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D00500"><p>Some of them are not disposed to taking on board anything that is of a voluntary nature.  The tenants are not the problem; the people running the boards are the problem.  I have come across situations where houses could not be insured.  It would be a serious matter if we were to lose houses from the housing stock that could not be replaced because of this measure.  The softly, softly approach may not work in this case and I ask the Minister of State to give a commitment that if it does not, there is the prospect of tabling an amendment that will be framed in the interests of protecting tenants' rights and making sure the housing stock is protected.</p><p>  The point Deputy Dessie Ellis made on which the Minister of State replied is an issue.  This year, for example, a large housing association such as the Iveagh Trust had to pay property tax and it will now have to pay this fee.  Trying to function in an environment where one is operating a differential rent system and giving long-term security of tenure might be a challenge because of the extra obligations imposed.  An issue could arise from that point of view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D00600"><p>I hope to publish the voluntary code in a month's time.  When it is published, it will be a mechanism in terms of the bodies that are problematic.</p><p>  Regarding the burden on AHBs, we had extensive discussions with them and are satisfied that they will be able to take this on.  We have not received any indication that this will be a burden with which they will not be able to deal.  They want to be properly governed and within this system.  They want it to be clear that their operating systems are well governed and protect the rights of their tenants.  It is something of which they want to be part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D00900"><p>I move amendment No. 24:<blockquote><br />In page 11, before section 11, but in Part 2, to insert the following new section:12.&mdash;Section 137 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (1) by inserting &ldquo;and section 137A&rdquo; after &ldquo;subsections (2)and (6)&rdquo;,<br />(<i>b</i>) in subsection (2) by substituting &ldquo;section 134(3)(<i>b</i>)(i)&rdquo; for &ldquo;section 134(3)&rdquo;,<br />(<i>c</i>) in subsection (3) by substituting &ldquo;in respect of not more than 10 tenancies&rdquo;for &ldquo;in respect of tenancies&rdquo;,<br />(<i>d</i>) by substituting the following subsection for subsection (6):<blockquote>&ldquo;(6) If an application under section 134(2) is not made within the period specified in section 134(2)(<i>b</i>)(ii), the fee to accompany that application shall be&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) the total of the amount of&mdash;<blockquote>(i) the fee referred to in subsection (1)(<i>b</i>)(ii), and<br />(ii) an additional amount of &euro;20 for&mdash;<blockquote>(I) each month, or<br />(II) part of a month,</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>falling after the expiration of the period specified in section 134(2)(<i>b</i>)(ii),<br />or<blockquote>(<i>b</i>) the fee prescribed for the purposes of this paragraph.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.87" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D01100"><p>I move amendment No. 25:<blockquote><br />In page 11, before section 11, but in Part 2, to insert the following new section:13.&mdash;The Principal Act is amended by inserting the following section after section 137:<blockquote>137A.&mdash;(1) The fee to accompany an application under section 134(2A) shall be&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) if the application is made in the period of 12 months beginning on commencement of section 3(4), a fee of &euro;45, or<br />(<i>b</i>) if the application is made after the period referred to in paragraph (<i>a</i>), the prescribed fee.</blockquote>(2) The requirement under section 134(3)(<i>b</i>)(ii) for a fee specified in this section to accompany an application under section 134 shall be regarded as satisfied, as respects the applications referred to in subsection (3), if the applicant referred to in subsection (3) opts to pay the Board a single fee of the amount specified in subsection (4) in respect of those applications.<br />(3) The applications referred to in subsection (2) are applications made by the same person at the same time in respect of not more than 10 tenancies of dwellings comprised in the same property.<br />(4) The amount of the single fee referred to in subsection (2) is&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) if the applications concerned are made in the period of 12 months beginning on the commencement of section 3(4), &euro;187.50, or<br />(<i>b</i>) if the applications concerned are made after the period referred to in paragraph (<i>a</i>), the prescribed fee.</blockquote>(5) The option of paying the single fee referred to in subsection (2) is not available to the person referred to in subsection (3) if the applications concerned are not made within the period specified in paragraph (<i>a</i>) or (<i>b</i>) of section 134(2A).<br />(6) If an application under section 134(2A) is not made within the period specified in paragraph (<i>a</i>) or (<i>b</i>) of section 134(2A), the application shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee.<br />(7) The Minister shall, before making regulations prescribing fees under this section, section 134(8) and section 137(6)(<i>b</i>), consult with the Board in respect of the amount of the fees to be prescribed.<br />(8) When prescribing a fee, or fees, for the purposes of subsection (6), the Minister may prescribe different fees having regard to the different periods of time elapsing between the making of the application and the expiration of the period specified in paragraphs (<i>a</i>) and (<i>b</i>) of section 134(2A).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.89" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.90" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" ><p>Section 11 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.91" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" ><p>SECTION 12</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D01500"><p>Amendments Nos. 26 to 29, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D01600"><p>I move amendment No. 26:<blockquote><br />In page 12, to delete lines 8 to 16 and substitute the following:&ldquo; &ldquo;1A. The tenant has failed to comply with the obligation, in relation to the tenancy, to pay an amount of rent due (whether arising under section 16 (<i>a</i>) or otherwise) and&mdash;<br />(<i>a</i>) the landlord has, in accordance with section 67(3), notified the tenant in writing that&mdash;<blockquote>(i) an amount of rent due has not been paid, and<br />(ii) the landlord is entitled to terminate the tenancy if the failure to pay the rent is not remedied within 14 days from the date on which the notice is received,</blockquote>(<i>b</i>) 14 days have elapsed from the receipt of the notification given in accordance with section 67(3), and<br />(<i>c</i>) the tenant has not paid the amount of rent due.&rdquo;,&rdquo;.</blockquote>These amendments further clarify the amendment in section 11 which inserts a specific ground in the table to section 34 relating to termination of a tenancy for non-payment of rent.  Under the 2004 Act, when a landlord wishes to terminate a Part 4 tenancy for non-payment of rent, he or she must serve a notice informing the tenant of the breach of obligation and give him or her a reasonable time to remedy that breach.  However, he or she must also serve a 14 day warning letter under section 67 and, having served these two notices, can only then issue a notice of termination when the rent is not paid.  The amendment simplifies the termination process for non-payment of rent.  It provides that the landlord only needs to serve one 14 day warning letter to the tenant and that if the rent remains unpaid, he or she may then proceed to serve a notice of termination to terminate the tenancy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D01700"><p>My only concern about the 14 day warning notice, in terms of rent arrears, is that sometimes the welfare officer is late in giving the tenant the money required.  I have experience of this happening.  I am concerned that if there is a 14 day warning, the tenant will not have enough time to get the money required.  The normal notice period is 28 days to quit the tenancy.  Therefore, is a notice period of 14 days too short?  That is my main worry in giving enough scope in that regard.  My experience tells me otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000005#D01800"><p>To clarify, this does not affect the 28 day minimum notice termination period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E00100"><p>I understand that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E00200"><p>They get 14 days and then 28 days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E00300"><p>It would make a little more sense to allow a further period after the 28 days.  Sometimes people tend not to heed a warning.  In addition, the person must seek assistance from the welfare officer who may be slow in delivering the money.  The tenants must respond to the written notification of their obligations to pay the rent before they know they have been given the supplementary payment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E00400"><p>This measure is to clarify and simplify the system.  It is not to deny the tenants the rights they already have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.100" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E00600"><p>I move amendment No. 27:<blockquote><br />In page 12, between lines 16 and 17, to insert the following: &ldquo;(<i>d</i>) in paragraph 4(<i>b</i>)(ii) by inserting &ldquo;1A,&rdquo; after &ldquo;paragraph 1,&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.102" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E00800"><p>I move amendment No. 28:<blockquote><br />In page 12, paragraph (<i>d</i>), line 22, to delete &ldquo; &ldquo;available for re-letting&rdquo;.&rdquo; and substitute the following:&ldquo; &ldquo;available for re-letting&rdquo;,(<i>e</i>) in paragraph 5(<i>b</i>)(ii), by inserting &ldquo;1A,&rdquo; after &ldquo;paragraph 1,&rdquo;,<br />(<i>f</i>) in paragraph 6(<i>b</i>)(ii), by inserting &ldquo;1A,&rdquo; after &ldquo;paragraph 1,&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.104" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.105" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 12, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.106" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E01200"><p>I move amendment No. 29:<blockquote><br />In page 12, before section 13, to insert the following new section:<br />13.&mdash;Section 67 of the Principal Act is amended by substituting the following subsection for subsection (3):&ldquo;(3) The condition mentioned in subsection (2)(<i>b</i>)(ii) is that&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) the tenant has been notified in writing by the landlord that&mdash;<blockquote>(i) an amount of rent due has not been paid, and<br />(ii) the landlord is entitled to terminate the tenancy if the failure to pay the rent is not remedied within 14 days from the date on which the notice is received,<br />and</blockquote>(<i>b</i>) 14 days have elapsed from the receipt of that notice without the amount concerned having been paid to the landlord.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.108" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.109" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 13 agreed to.
NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E01500"><p>Amendment No. 30 is in the name of the Minister.  Amendments Nos. 30 to 33, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E01700"><p>I move amendment No. 30:<blockquote><br />In page 12, before section 14, to insert the following new section:14.&mdash;Section 82 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (5) by substituting &ldquo;subject to subsection (6), any costs referred to in subsection (7)&rdquo; for &ldquo;such costs and expenses&rdquo;, and<br />(<i>b</i>) by inserting the following subsections after subsection (5):<blockquote>&ldquo;(6) Any costs awarded under subsection (5) shall not exceed &euro;1,000.<br />(7) In subsection (5), costs incurred by the other party includes costs or expenses&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) relating to travelling and attendance at any place required for the adjudication or determination of the matter concerned, and<br />(<i>b</i>) relating to the preparation of his or her case,</blockquote></blockquote>and, for the avoidance of doubt, such preparation costs do not include legal costs referred to in section 5(3)(<i>a</i>).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote>Amendments Nos. 30 to 33, inclusive, are related.  They provide for limits to be placed on the awards of costs that may be made by the PRTB.  Section 115(3) of the 2004 Act provides that the amount, other than costs or expenses of whatsoever kind that an adjudicator or tribunal may direct to be paid, shall not exceed &euro;60,000 for arrears of rent and &euro;20,000 in damages.  While section 115(3) places a limit of &euro;20,000 in terms of the level of damages which can be awarded, there is no limit on the amount of expenses and costs that may be awarded.  This amendment provides for limits on all types of costs that can be awarded by the PRTB under the residential tenancies Act and is provided for on the basis of legal advice furnished to my Department.  </p><p>  The amendments place a limit of &euro;1,000 on the costs that can be awarded under sections 82, 115, and 119 of the Principal Act.  Amendment No. 55 which we will discuss later also provides for a limit of &euro;5,000 on the amount of legal costs that may be awarded on the same basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.112" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.113" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 14 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.114" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Sections 15 to 22, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.115" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>SECTION 23</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E02200"><p>I move amendment No. 31:<blockquote><br />In page 15, line 16, to delete &ldquo;subsection&rdquo; where it firstly occurs and substitute &ldquo;subsections&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.117" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E02400"><p>I move amendment No. 32:<blockquote><br />In page 15, line 21, to delete &ldquo;subsection (3)(<i>c</i>)(i).&rdquo;.&rdquo; and substitute the following:<br />&ldquo;subsection (3)(<i>c</i>)(i).(5) The amount of costs or expenses that may be awarded to a party shall not exceed &euro;1,000.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.119" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.120" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 23, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.121" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E02700"><p>Amendment No. 33 is in the name of the Minister.  Acceptance of this amendment involves the deletion of section 24 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E02900"><p>I move amendment No. 33:<blockquote><br />In page 15, before section 24, to insert the following new section:24.&mdash;Section 119 is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (1)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) in paragraph (i) by substituting &ldquo;subject to subsection (3), costs&rdquo; for<br />&ldquo;costs&rdquo;, and<br />(ii) by deleting paragraph (iii),<blockquote>and</blockquote></blockquote>(<i>b</i>) by inserting the following subsection after subsection (2):<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(3) The costs awarded under subsection (1)(i) shall not exceed<br />&euro;1,000.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.124" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.125" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 24 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.126" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 25 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.127" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E03500"><p>I move amendment No. 34:<blockquote><br />In page 15, before section 26, to insert the following new section:26.&mdash;Section 123 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (1), by substituting &ldquo;an agreement referred to in section 96(1)&rdquo; for &ldquo;an agreement mentioned in a mediator&rsquo;s report under section 95(4)&rdquo;, and<br />(<i>b</i>) in subsection (4), by deleting &ldquo;in relation to the point of law concerned&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.129" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.130" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 26 deleted.
NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E03800"><p>I move amendment No. 35:<blockquote><br />In page 15, before section 27, to insert the following new section:27.&mdash;Section 135 of the Principal Act is amended by substituting the following<br />subsection for subsection 5:<blockquote>&ldquo;(5) Where an application under section 134 is received by the Board and the application is&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) incomplete, or<br />(<i>b</i>) not accompanied by&mdash;<blockquote>(i) the fee referred to in section 134(3)(<i>b</i>)(i) or as the case may be section 134(3)(<i>b</i>)(ii), and<br />(ii) the fee referred to in section 134(3)(<i>c</i>) where that fee is required to be paid,</blockquote></blockquote>the Board shall notify the applicant of the omission concerned and specify a date by which the application is to be completed or the fee is, or the fees are, to be paid.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.132" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.133" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 27 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.134" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Sections 28 to 40, inclusive, agreed to.
NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E04200"><p>Amendment No. 36 is in the name of the Minister.  Acceptance of this amendment involves the deletion of section 41 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E04300"><p>I move amendment No. 36:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 41, to insert the following new section:41.&mdash;The expenses incurred by the Minister in the administration of this Part shall, to such extent as may be sanctioned by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, be paid out of monies provided by the Oireachtas.&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.137" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.138" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 41 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.139" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Section 42 agreed to.
NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E04700"><p>Amendment No. 37 is a new section.  Amendments Nos. 37 to 47, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000006#E04800"><p>I move amendment No. 37:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:<div>&ldquo;PART 5*<br />COMPLAINT RELATING TO FAILURE TO PAY RENT PAYABLE UNDER THE TENANCY PENDING <br />DETERMINATION OF DISPUTE</div>43.&mdash;Section 75 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (2) by inserting &ldquo;76A,&rdquo; after &ldquo;76(4),&rdquo;,<br />(<i>b</i>) in subsection (4)(<i>d</i>), by substituting &ldquo;landlord,&rdquo; for &ldquo;landlord, and&rdquo;, and<br />(<i>c</i>) in subsection (4) by inserting the following after paragraph (<i>d</i>):<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(<i>da</i>) in the case of a complaint mentioned in section 76A&mdash;<blockquote>(i) the landlord, and<br />(ii) the tenant and, in the case of a sub-tenancy, the sub-tenant,and&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>The substantive amendments provide for the introduction of a new procedure which will enable the PRTB to deal effectively with tenants who do not pay rent during the dispute process.  A dispute between a landlord and a tenant may be referred by either party to the PRTB for resolution under section 76 of the 2004 Act.</p><p>  Under section 86 of the Act, rent continues to be payable pending the determination of the dispute and a termination of the tenancy may not be affected during the course of the dispute.  However, the fact that a tenancy may not be terminated pending the determination of the dispute has led in practice to a small number of tenants withholding rent during the time their dispute is waiting to be dealt with by the PRTB.  The landlord cannot evict the tenant during the dispute process and as such may not be paid any rent for considerable periods.  This has led to hardship for some landlords who in many cases rely on rental payments to pay the mortgage on the dwelling.  The purpose of these amendments is to provide for a new procedure to deal with tenants who do not comply with their statutory obligation to pay rent, pending the determination of their dispute.  These amendments insert a new section 76A into the 2004 Act, which will provide that where there is a dispute before the board and the tenant does not pay the rent the landlord may bring a complaint before the PRTB.  On the hearing of this complaint the PRTB can order the tenant to pay any rent due.  The matter will then be adjourned for a period of no more than 14 days to allow the tenant to comply with this order.  Where the tenant does not comply, the PRTB will now have the power to terminate the tenancy for breach of the statutory duty to pay rent, irrespective of whether a notice of termination has been served.  </p><p>  The PRTB do not have this power under the 2004 Act, as such.  Even in cases in which a tenant has not paid rent for a number of months the PRTB do not have the power to terminate the tenancy unless the landlord has served a valid notice of termination.  Where the notice of termination is invalid, the landlord has to reserve the notice and wait out the notice period before getting possession of the dwelling.  If the tenant challenges the second notice, there is a further waiting period before the matter is finally resolved, with the landlord not receiving any rent during this time.  In some cases this can result in a tenant remaining <i>in situ</i> for over a year without paying rent.  While the PRTB endeavours to prioritise all cases where rent is not being paid, under the current law they have no power to terminate the tenancy regardless of the behaviour of the tenant.  These new provisions will allow the PRTB to deal effectively and quickly with tenants who do not comply with their statutory obligation to pay rent during the dispute process.</p> <p>Under this new procedure, a landlord may apply for relief only where a dispute has been referred-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000007#F00200"><p>Has the Minister of State much more left because there is a vote in the D&aacute;il?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000007#F00300"><p>Approximately another minute.  Does the Chairman want to wait?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000007#F00400"><p>I must suspend the committee and we will come back after the vote.  T&aacute; v&oacute;t&aacute;il ar si&uacute;l.  Mar sin, cuirfimid an cruinni&uacute; ar fionra&iacute; ar feadh c&uacute;pla n&oacute;im&eacute;ad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.146" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.20 a.m. and resumed at 11.40 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000008#G00100"><p>I interrupted the Minister of State, Deputy O'Sullivan, before the vote in the D&aacute;il.  She may finish her contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000008#G00200"><p>I will begin roughly where I left off.  I was making the point that where the tenant has not paid the rent, the PRTB has not the power to terminate the tenancy unless the landlord has served notice of termination.  Where the notice of termination is invalid, the landlord must re-serve the notice and wait out the notice period before getting possession of the dwelling.  If the tenant challenges the second notice, there is a further waiting period before the matter is finally resolved, with the landlord not receiving any rent during this time, in some cases, as I stated already, if the tenant remains <i>in situ</i>, for over a year.  While the PRTB endeavours to prioritise all cases where rent is not being paid under the current law, it has no power to terminate the tenancy regardless of the behaviour of the tenant.</p><p>  These new provisions will allow the PRTB to deal effectively and quickly with tenants who do not comply with their statutory obligation to pay rent during the dispute process.</p> <p>Under this new procedure, a landlord may apply for relief only where a dispute has been referred to the PRTB and the tenant has ceased to pay rent.  This application will be fast-tracked and deal only with the non-payment of rent issue.  The original dispute will be dealt with in the usual way at a later date.  The amendments provide that the PRTB must endeavour to ensure a complaint under this new procedure is dealt with as soon as is reasonably practicable and notice periods for disputes and appeals have been shortened to allow complaints under this procedure to be dealt with as quickly as possible, while still giving due notice to the parties involved.  However, the tenant will still be entitled to notice of the making of the application and, following this, will have a minimum of ten days notice of the hearing of the application.  The mediation provisions under the Bill will not apply to this procedure, as this would introduce a further step in the process and result in further delay.</p><p> I have also provided that the PRTB must provide six monthly reports for me on the progress of this new procedure for the first year of its operation.  Thereafter, reports on the procedure must be made in the PRTB's annual report which, as members know, is laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas every year.  I am sure we have all been in receipt of correspondence from constituents who are at their wits' end trying to pay a mortgage on a rental property where the tenant will not pay the rent.  I am confident this new procedure will give the PRTB the power and means to deal quickly and effectively with that small number of tenants who blatantly disregard their statutory obligation to pay rent during a dispute.  This may require some discussion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000009#H00200"><p>I welcome the amendment in general.  We all have experience of tenants who have not paid rent for various reasons.  Some may not be happy with the maintenance work carried out by the landlord and end up saying they will not pay rent until the matter is sorted out.  I hope that if the board is given more powers to intervene and perhaps move against a tenant, all of these issues will be taken into account.  This is a considerable problem.  Most people end up in disputes with their landlords over maintenance.  I assume this will be taken into account by the board.  It is sometimes very hard to get through to people when they are very upset by various issues affecting them.  If the PRTB is to have the ability to recommend that a tenant be put out, it will have been given a very big role and responsibility.  I hope every avenue is exhausted if this is to occur.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000009#H00300"><p>There is no doubt that where there are rights, there ought to be responsibilities also.  It is a question of finding a balance.  I do not dispute the principle of the amendment, but I have some concerns about the responsibility of the State.  As we know, there is a dual application process for rent assistance.  If somebody out of work discovers he or she must put himself or herself on an approved housing waiting list, he or she applies and the local authority has 12 weeks in which to deal with it.  There is sometimes correspondence between the various parties which results in a breaking of the 12 week deadline.  I certainly have experience of this in the cases of some constituents.  The next step for the applicant is to apply to a separate body.  This issue may well resolve itself in that there may eventually be one application process.  At present, there are two.  The difficulty is that the second application can take another 12 weeks to process.  The State has a responsibility in this regard.  Some arrears and non-payments arise because the State does not deal with the application for rent support in a timely way.  It is a complex system, as members know.  The issue I describe could lead to a problem.</p><p>  If a community welfare officer or the Department of Social Protection hears there is a dispute, rent assistance will be stopped.  If a tenant complains that accommodation is of poor quality or that a landlord is not dealing with a matter, rent assistance could be stopped at that point.  How would this be handled?  Threshold produced a report last year that showed that 61% of tenants were topping up the rent assistance payment.  The caps are way below market rents in their respective areas and people obviously face having to top up, mostly from social welfare payments, to try to ensure there is a roof over their heads.  Such circumstances can result in homelessness.  The State has a responsibility and it is undermining some tenancy rights by virtue of the fact that it is forcing tenants to negotiate reductions with landlords.  These are not real reductions.  What is occurring is that they are saying the landlord has agreed to a reduction, while, in reality, they are topping up.  Inevitably, they will end up with the community welfare officer trying to seek help with an electricity bill or another bill because their income simply does not match their outgoings.  I have concerns about these issues.  While I do not dispute that there is a need for the legislation, I am concerned about how the tenants in the position I have described will be catered for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000009#H00400"><p>As both Deputies implied and as I have been saying, we are trying to strike a balance between the rights and responsibilities of both the tenant and the landlord.  That is essentially the purpose of the amendment.</p><p>  To answer Deputy Dessie Ellis's question on a tenant who is not paying, where a landlord is not carrying out certain maintenance work, a tenant has a legitimate reason to go to the PRTB.  The amendment does not affect the hearing on the main issue of complaint.  The issue of the tenant having to pay the rent is being dealt with in the legislation.  Irrespective of the duration of the dispute, one should be paying one's rent until the matter is resolved.  That is the purpose of the provision.</p><p>  The general issues raised by Deputy Catherine Murphy are of concern to us all.  They have been raised many times in making reference to rent supplement, caps and the fact that people top up, although they should not or should not have to.</p><p>  The Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, is carrying out a review of rent caps.  This is not my area of responsibility.  The review will probably be published very soon.  One will be aware that we are planning to transfer the long-term rent supplement scheme to the local authorities through the housing assistance payment scheme.  This will address the issue of affordability.  There will be a much more satisfactory arrangement for the people concerned.  In effect, they will be paying differential rent on the basis of their income and will not face all of the poverty traps and issues that arise with regard to rent supplement.  There will still be rent supplement for those who need it urgently in the shorter term.  Anyone who is on a housing list for a reasonable length of time and whose needs are more long term will be transferred to the local authority system in the next year and a half approximately.  This is the time it will take to introduce the system gradually throughout the country.  This issue is somewhat separate from the one we are discussing, namely, the time it takes to get on the local authority housing list and receive rent supplement.  However, the matter certainly needs to be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000009#H00500"><p>The problem is that there is no provision for backdating.  That is how some rent arrears will arise and there is no solution.  The State is part of the problem in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000009#H00600"><p>Is the Deputy referring to backdating in people getting on the housing list?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000009#H00700"><p>One cannot apply for rent assistance until one gets on the waiting list, which may take three months.  One must then apply for rent assistance, but it can take up to three months to receive it.  It is only after this three month period that one qualifies for rent assistance.  Therefore, the tenant may not have been able to pay rent for a period of six months.  The State has a responsibility in this regard.</p> <p>What does one do in that kind of situation?  In general, tenants do not want to stop paying their rent because they know that if they are to continue renting, they will need a reference.  Sometimes, however, these situations arise.  It is all very well for us to talk about this in an academic sense, but in a practical sense a cohort of people will run into difficulty.  If a community welfare officer or the Department of Social Protection even gets a whiff that there is a dispute, they will stop giving rent assistance.  That happens, so these matters tie into this until we get to the point where the HAP system is in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J00200"><p>One way or another, a landlord is entitled to get his or her rent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J00400"><p>This amendment is about ensuring a landlord has the right to have the rent paid.  The issue the Deputy is raising is whether a tenant can afford to pay the rent for a variety of reasons, whether it is because they have not yet been approved on the housing list or whether a community welfare officer has not paid them rent supplement for one reason or another.  That is a valid point but I do not think it negates the point that a landlord is entitled to have rent paid while there is an ongoing dispute.  Other mechanisms may be necessary to ensure a tenant can afford to pay, but we should not persist in a situation where there is no mechanism for a landlord to have rent paid while a dispute is going on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.160" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J00700"><p>I move amendment No. 38:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:44.&mdash;Section 76 of the Principal Act is amended by inserting the following subsection after subsection (4):<blockquote>&ldquo;(5) The landlord may refer to the Board for resolution a complaint under section 76A that a tenant or, as the case may be, a sub-tenant has failed to comply with section 86(1)(<i>a</i>).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.162" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J01000"><p>I move amendment No. 39:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:45.&mdash;The Principal Act is amended by inserting the following section after section 76:<blockquote>76A.&mdash;(1) This section applies where a matter has been referred to the Board for resolution (the &lsquo;original dispute&rsquo;) and pending the determination of that dispute a tenant referred to in section 86(1)(<i>a</i>)(i), or a sub-tenant referred to in section 86(1)(<i>a</i>)(ii), has failed to comply with section 86(1)(<i>a</i>).<br />(2) A landlord may, on notice to the tenant, and the sub-tenant in the case of a sub-tenancy, refer to the Board for resolution a complaint that the tenant referred to in section 86(1)(<i>a</i>)(i), or a sub-tenant referred to in section 86(1)(<i>a</i>)(ii), has failed to comply with section 86(1)(<i>a</i>).<br />(3) A complaint under this section shall not be the subject of mediation under section 93.<br />(4) The Board shall as soon as practicable arrange for a complaint under subsection (2) to be the subject of an adjudication under section 97 by an adjudicator designated to hear and determine a complaint under this section.<br />(5) The adjudicator, or as the case may be the Tribunal on appeal, shall proceed to hear and determine, in accordance with this Part, the complaint that the tenant, or as the case may be the sub-tenant, has failed to comply with section 86(1)(<i>a</i>) and shall make all necessary findings and determinations for that purpose.<br />(6) Where an adjudicator on the hearing of a complaint under this section, or the Tribunal on appeal, is satisfied that there has been a failure to comply with section 86(1)(<i>a</i>) the adjudicator or Tribunal may&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) make a determination that there has been a failure to comply with section 86(1)(<i>a</i>),<br />(<i>b</i>) make a determination comprising a direction that the tenant or the sub-tenant shall pay to the landlord the amount of rent due and owing on or before a specified day which shall be not later than 14 days from the date on which the determination is made, and<br />(<i>c</i>) adjourn the matter for such period as is appropriate for the purpose of confirming that the amount of rent referred to in paragraph (<i>b</i>) has been paid by the specified date.</blockquote>(7) Where at the end of the period of adjournment referred to in subsection (6)(<i>c</i>), the tenant or sub-tenant fails to comply with the determination referred to in subsection (6)(<i>b</i>), the adjudicator or the Tribunal may&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) make a determination that there has been a failure to comply with the direction under subsection (6)(<i>b</i>), and<br />(<i>b</i>) notwithstanding section 86(1)(<i>c</i>), make a determination that the tenancy stands terminated and direct that the dwelling the subject of the tenancy be quitted by a specified date.</blockquote>(8) Where the dwelling the subject of the tenancy terminated under subsection (7) is one out of which a sub-tenancy has been created, a determination under subsection (7)(<i>b</i>) may include a determination that the sub-tenancy stands terminated and a direction that the dwelling concerned be quitted by a specified date.<br />(9) Subject to subsection (10), the original dispute may proceed to be determined in accordance with the provisions of this Act.<br />(10) Any relevant findings or determinations made in hearing or determination of a complaint under this section shall apply, as appropriate, to the original dispute.<br />(11) For the purposes of the determination of the original dispute, a copy of a determination made under this section shall be provided to&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) the adjudicator determining the original dispute, and<br />(<i>b</i>) in the case of an appeal against the determination of the original dispute, the Tribunal.</blockquote>(12) Section 119 shall not apply to the determination of a complaint under this section.<br />(13) An amount of rent directed to be paid under this section shall count in the calculation of an amount of rent for the purposes of section 115(3).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.164" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J01300"><p>I move amendment No. 40:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:46.&mdash;Section 86 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (2) by inserting the following paragraph after paragraph (<i>c</i>):<blockquote>&ldquo;(<i>ca</i>) in the case of paragraph (<i>c</i>) of that subsection, the tenancy has been terminated pursuant to a determination under section 76A,&rdquo;, and</blockquote>(<i>b</i>) by inserting the following subsection after subsection (3):<blockquote>&ldquo;(4) Where a tenant or a sub-tenant fails to comply with subsection (1)(<i>a</i>), the landlord may make a complaint under section 76A.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.166" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J01600"><p>I move amendment No. 41:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:47.&mdash;Section 94 of the Principal Act is amended by inserting the following paragraph after paragraph (<i>a</i>):<blockquote>&ldquo;(<i>aa</i>) mediation of the kind mentioned in that section in respect of complaints under section 76A,&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.168" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J01900"><p>I move amendment No. 42:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:48.&mdash;Section 97 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (1) by inserting &ldquo;76A,&rdquo; after &ldquo;under section&rdquo;,<br />(<i>b</i>) in subsection (2) by inserting &ldquo;76A,&rdquo; after &ldquo;under section&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.170" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J02200"><p>I move amendment No. 43:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:49.&mdash;Section 100 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (2) by substituting &ldquo;Subject to subsection (3), such an appeal&rdquo; for &ldquo;Such an appeal&rdquo;, and<br />(<i>b</i>) by inserting the following new subsection after subsection (2):<blockquote>&ldquo;(3) An appeal concerning the determination of a complaint referred to in section 76A shall be made within 10 days from the date the Board serves on the party the report and statement referred to in section 99(3).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.172" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J02500"><p>I move amendment No. 44:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:50.&mdash;Section 104 of the Principal Act is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) in subsection (5) by substituting &ldquo;Subject to subsection (5A), the duration of&rdquo; for &ldquo;The duration of&rdquo;, and<br />(<i>b</i>) by inserting the following subsection after subsection (5):<blockquote>&ldquo;(5A) The duration of the notice under subsection (3), where the hearing concerns the determination of a complaint referred to in section 76A, shall be 10 days.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.174" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J02800"><p>I move amendment No. 45:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:51.&mdash;Section 109 of the Principal Act is amended by inserting the following subsection after subsection (1):<blockquote>&ldquo;(1A) For the purpose of the hearing and determination of a complaint under section 76A, without prejudice to the generality of subsection (1), the Board shall endeavour to ensure that a complaint under section 76A is determined as soon as is reasonably practicable and for that purpose rules under this section shall&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) establish procedures to provide for the hearing and determination of such complaint as soon as is reasonably practicable after the complaint has been referred to the Board,<br />(<i>b</i>) designate, from the panel of adjudicators referred to in section 164(4), a number of adjudicators to hear and determine complaints under section 76A that is appropriate for those complaints to be heard and determined as soon as is reasonably practicable, and<br />(<i>c</i>) cause to be constituted, under section 102, a number of tribunals, to hear and determine complaints referred under section 76A or appeals under section 100 of determinations of those complaints, that is appropriate for those complaints and appeals to be heard and determined as soon as is reasonably practicable,</blockquote>and when designating an appropriate number of adjudicators or causing to be constituted an appropriate number of tribunals the Board shall have regard to the number of complaints under section 76A referred to it.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.176" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J03100"><p>I move amendment No. 46:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:52.&mdash;Section 124 of the Principal Act is amended by inserting the following new subsection after subsection (5):<blockquote>&ldquo;(5A) Where an application is made in respect of a determination order under section 76A(7) that requires the dwelling to be vacated, the court may, pending the hearing of the action, require the respondent to lodge in court or pay to the applicant, as it thinks appropriate, that amount of rent together with such amount as it specifies in respect of the dwelling&rsquo;s continued occupation by the respondent after the service of that notice.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.178" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J03400"><p>I move amendment No. 47:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:53.&mdash;The Principal Act is amended by inserting the following new section after section 180:<blockquote>180A.&mdash;(1) Without prejudice to section 180, the Board shall, not later than 6 months after the coming into operation of section 76A, make a report to the Minister in such form as the Minister may approve, on the performance of its functions under that subsection and in respect of the making and determining of complaints under section 76A and appeals against determinations of those complaints.<br />(2) The Board shall, not later than 6 months after the day on which the report under subsection (1) was made, make a further report to the Minister in respect of the same matters provided for in that subsection.<br />(3) Following the making of the report referred to in subsection (2), the Board shall include in its annual report under section 180 the matters provided for in subsection (1).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.180" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J03600"><p>Amendments Nos. 48 to 51, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.  They form a composite proposal and therefore a decision in respect of amendment No. 48 will also apply to amendments Nos. 49, 50 and 51.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J03700"><p>I move amendment No. 48:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:<div>&ldquo;PART 5*<br />DEPOSIT RETENTION SCHEME</div>43.&mdash;In this Part, &ldquo;deposit&rdquo; means any money intended to be held (by the landlord or otherwise) as security for&mdash;(<i>a</i>) the performance of any obligations of the tenant, or<br />(<i>b</i>) the discharge of any liability of the tenant,arising under or in connection with a tenancy.&rdquo;.</blockquote>One of the problems we found concerned how the deposit retention issue is handled.  The Minister of State has said that she will examine that issue, but we felt that the debate on this Bill would have been the appropriate time to examine it and bring forward such proposals.  We know that some 72% of complaints relate to deposit retention, which shows how big this matter is.  Because deposit retention is one of the main complaints, my colleagues and I felt that the matter should have been dealt with at this Stage of the Bill.</p><p>  The Minister of State's colleagues, Deputy Patrick Nulty and Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Lynch, have made similar suggestions to ours concerning deposit retention.  It is also a big issue for welfare officers, some of whom will give deposits while others will not.  Continuity and clear rules are required regarding deposits.  Every landlord will seek a deposit, so guidelines are needed in this respect.</p><p>  Those are the reasons my party has tabled these amendments.  I am seeking support for them from my colleagues on this committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J03800"><p>I agree with Deputy Ellis concerning the difficulties he has outlined.  If a person cannot get their deposit back and the community welfare officer will not grant a deposit, they can very easily end up homeless.  The average deposit is approximately &euro;1,000, but for somebody on social welfare payments that is a fortune.  There is no way they will be able to make that up if it is not refunded.</p><p>  We are trying to change the culture because there are 100,000 people on the housing waiting list.  Approximately 40% of rented properties are occupied by people in receipt of rent assistance.  That group of tenants is very exposed in this situation.  In attempting to create a balance of rights, I would have thought the deposit retention issue would have to have been a feature of this Bill.</p><p>  There is a desire that the process concerning the Private Residential Tenancies Board would move more quickly.  One of the issues that takes up most of the board's time is the return of deposits.  How can one streamline the system if that one item continues to absorb all the PRTB staff's time?  Will extra staff be put in to deal with it?  This has to worked out on a practical level, so it should be a feature of the Bill before us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J03900"><p>I fully appreciate the intention behind Deputy Ellis's amendment.  I wish to repeat what I said on Second Stage.  I intend to bring forward an amendment in this regard in the Seanad.  We were just not ready to do so here, as it has not been fully drafted.  It is a priority and a commitment in the programme for Government to establish a deposit protection scheme.  On foot of that commitment, I asked the PRTB to commission research on such a scheme.  The research contract was awarded to Indecon Economic Consultants.  I received the final report from Indecon in November 2012.  The report presents a comprehensive analysis of the range of options for delivery of the programme for Government's commitment.  I am currently engaging with the Office of the Attorney General on drafting proposals to establish a deposit protection scheme with a view to bringing proposals to Government shortly and introducing these provisions on Committee Stage in the Seanad.</p><p>  I fully appreciate and share the concerns of Deputy Ellis and Deputy Catherine Murphy, but the issues are quite complex and we must ensure we draft the amendment properly.  In giving a commitment that the matter will be brought forward in the Seanad, I would ask Deputy Ellis to withdraw the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000010#J04000"><p>Having tabled these amendments, I feel we should have debated whether they are sufficient to deal with the problem.  I do not think we are being afforded an opportunity to do so.  The Minister of State has said that she will look at this matter in the future, but I always worry when people say that because things tend to drag out for a long time.  I know the issue is complex, but the Government had enough time to examine our amendments and draw up something that would satisfy all of us.  There was enough time to do so in the period allowed.  I will press the amendments, therefore, because I feel they should have been responded to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000011#K00100"><p>We are dealing with amendments Nos. 48 to 51, inclusive.  Deputy Ellis has the choice.  It is entirely up to himself.  I merely want to explain this.  He can move and push the amendments to a vote, or he can move and withdraw which means he can return to them on Report Stage.  In any event, the decision is up to himself.  We are taking amendments Nos. 48 to 51, inclusive, and the resolution on amendment No. 48 will stand for amendments Nos. 49 to 51, inclusive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.187/1" nospeaker="true" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000011#K00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: T, 1; Nl, 6.</p>  <p></p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.187/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-05-30" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000011#K00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="1" noes="6" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" vote="aye">Dessie Ellis</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" vote="no">Noel Coonan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1033" vote="no">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/996" vote="no">Michael McCarthy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1082" vote="no">Tony McLoughlin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" vote="no">Jan O'Sullivan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.187/3" nospeaker="true" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000011#K00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.188" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 49 to 51, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L00500"><p>I move amendment No. 52:<blockquote><br />In page 19, before section 43, but in Part 4, to insert the following new section:&quot;47.&mdash;(1) The Department of Social Protection shall not make a payment of a supplement towards the amount of rent payable by a person in respect of his or her residence where the tenancy has not been registered in accordance with the provisions of Part 7 of the Principal Act.<br />(2) <i>Subsection (1)</i> does not prevent the payment by the Department of Social Protection&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) of such a supplement upon the creation of a tenancy, or<br />(<i>b</i>) of assistance in the form of a deposit prior to the registration of the tenancy.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote>I raise this issue because the deposit is important.  I want to push it.  While the Minister of State provided me with a commitment that it would be examined, plenty of time was given.  I will not say anymore other than that I am pressing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.190" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.191" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Section 43 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.192" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L00900"><p>Amendments Nos. 53 and 55 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L01000"><p>I move amendment No. 53:<blockquote><br />In page 19, after line 39, to insert the following new section:44.&mdash;(1) The Principal Act is amended in the manner specified in the Schedule*.<br />(2) The following provisions of the Principal Act are repealed:<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) section 115(2)(<i>i</i>);<br />(<i>b</i>) section 126;<br />(<i>c</i>) section 190(2)(<i>b</i>).&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote>The amendment provides for the repeal of three sections of the Residential Tenancies Act 2004 and the insertion of a new Schedule to the Act.  Section 115(2)(<i>l</i>) of the 2004 Act provides that the PRTB may direct a party to pay the costs or expenses of a PRTB adjudicator or tribunal to the PRTB in special circumstances.  Legal advice furnished to me has indicated that the provision should be repealed on the basis that the PRTB should not be a judge in its own case.  Similarly, the amendment provides for the repeal of section 126 of the 2004 Act which provides that non-compliance with a determination order is automatically a criminal offence.  The amendment is proposed on the advice of the Office of the Attorney General arising from the judgment of the High Court in McCann <i>v.</i> The Judge of Monaghan District Court &amp;amp; Ors.  The PRTB will continue to enforce its orders by means of the civil enforcement procedure in section 124.  On foot of further legal advice, I propose to provide for the repeal of section 190(2)(<i>b</i>) which provides that the Circuit Court may authorise a PRTB adjudicator or tribunal to award costs to a party in an application to the Circuit Court for injunctive relief under section 189.  I have been advised that it is not appropriate for the PRTB to make a direction in relation to the costs of a Circuit Court application.</p><p>  Amendment No. 55 proposes to insert a new Schedule to the Act.  The proposed new Schedule provides for three miscellaneous amendments.  The proposed amendment to section 5(4) of the 2004 Act provides that where the board awards legal costs, such costs shall not exceed &euro;5,000.  I mentioned this amendment earlier in the context of amendments Nos. 30 to 33, inclusive.  While legal costs may only be awarded by the PRTB in exceptional circumstances and with the permission of the board, there is currently no limit on the amount of any award.  On foot of legal advice received by my Department, the amendment is proposed to provide for a limit of &euro;5,000 on any award of costs made by the PRTB.  The second amendment provided for in the new Schedule is to section 6(1) of the 2004 Act.  This is a technical drafting amendment to clarify that the service provisions of the 2004 Act apply to all documents that must be served under the legislation.  The new Schedule provides for an amendment to section 88(1) of the 2004 Act to clarify for the avoidance of doubt that the PRTB may extend time for a party to appeal to the tribunal against a determination of an adjudicator.  I commend these somewhat complex amendments to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.195" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L01200"><p>I move amendment No. 54:<blockquote><br />In page 19, after line 39, to insert the following new section:45.&mdash;Section 6 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1992 is amended in subsection (2) by inserting the following paragraph after paragraph (<i>e</i>):<blockquote>&quot;(<i>ea</i>) by letting a house (including a house provided under Part V of the Planning and Development Act 2000) to another housing authority referred to in subsection (1)(<i>a</i>) or a body referred to in subsection (1)(<i>b</i>);&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote>Amendment No. 54 is a technical amendment to section 6(2) of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1992 to clarify that a housing authority may give assistance to an approved housing body under that section by letting a house to that approved housing body.  It is the advice of the Attorney General that we should insert this provision for certainty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.197" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.198" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>NEW SCHEDULE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L01550"><p>I move amendment No. 55:</p><p><div style="padding-left: 20px; margin-bottom: 10px">In page 19, after line 39, to insert the following new Schedule:</div></p><p><pcenterli1>SCHEDULE</pcenterli1></p><p><table><tr><th><div>Provision affected(1)</div></th><th><div>Amendment(2)</div></th></tr><tr><td><div>Section 5(4)</div></td><td>Insert &quot;and the amount of such costs shall not exceed &euro;5,000&quot; after &quot;of that subsection&quot;.</td></tr><tr><td><div>Section 6(1)</div></td><td>Insert &quot;or other document&quot; after &quot;notice&quot;.</td></tr><tr><td><div>Section 88(1)</div></td><td>Insert &quot;or an appeal under section 100 to the Tribunal against a determination of an adjudicator under section 97(4)(<i>a</i>)&quot; after &quot;for resolution&quot;.</td></tr></table></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.200" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.201" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.202" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.203" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L02000">Message to Dil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EN12013053000012#L02100"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:<blockquote><br />The Select Sub-Committee on the Environment, Community and Local Government has completed its consideration of the Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2012 and has made amendments thereto.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.205" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" ><p>The select sub-committee adjourned at 12.20 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 9 July 2013.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.206" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.207" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 11:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Eric Byrne, Senator Terry Leyden, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, Senator Kathryn Reilly. Deputy Timmy Dooley, Deputy Bernard J. Durkan,</p><p>DEPUTY DOMINIC HANNIGAN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.209" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000002#A00050">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000002#A00100"><p>I suggest we suspend the sitting for 15 minutes.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.211" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.35 a.m. and resumed at 11.50 a.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.212" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000003#B00100">EU Developments: Discussion with French National Assembly</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000003#B00200"><p>I remind members, guests and others to ensure that their telephones are switched off.  It is not sufficient to put them on silent, as they will interfere with the recording equipment.</p><p>  We have received apologies from Deputy Kyne.</p><p>  The first item on our agenda is an exchange of views with the European affairs committee of the French National Assembly.  I am delighted to welcome a delegation from the Assembly to our meeting in Dublin.</p> <p>The delegation is led by the committee chairperson, Ms Danielle Auroi, who is welcome, and she is accompanied by Mr. Michel Piron, who is also a member of the committee.  With both Deputies are the French Ambassador to Ireland, Ms Emmanuelle D'Achon.  Ms Annabelle Archien is the committee administrator, Ms Marianne Ziss is first secretary at the French Embassy in Dublin and Ms Alexandra Hambling will interpret proceedings today.  Members should bear in mind that we should wait for the translation when the guests are speaking.</p><p> The French delegation is on a short visit to Ireland at our invitation during the Irish Presidency.  A key priority of the committee is to engage with fellow parliamentarians to ensure we understand the joint challenges we face across Europe and within our respective countries.  We are looking forward to an exchange of views today with our French colleagues and we hope to impart an understanding of what our committee sees as the interests for Ireland during the Presidency.  I will outline where we are with our priorities when I get a chance to speak later today.</p><p> I understand the key themes the delegation would like to discuss today are the deepening of economic and monetary union and the implications on national parliaments, particularly in the context of budgetary integration.  We will all have something to say about that.  They also wish to speak about the strengthening of the economic and monetary union and where we are in agreeing the multi-annual financial framework.  They will also speak about energy transition and tackling climate change, which is a subject that has dropped from the political radar in the years since the economic crisis began.  I am sure there will be other areas we would also like to discuss.</p><p> I invite Ms Auroi to make her opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.215" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Danielle Auroi" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000004#C00200"><p>I will speak French as, unfortunately, my English is not good enough to speak to the committee in that language.  I thank the committee for the time it will spend with us and in view of the fact that there is a time limit, I will not detail our committee at the French National Assembly.  I will just say that Mr. Piron and I are members of the committee, and Mr. Piron is rapporteur for two important draft directives.</p><p>  Our committee and this committee spend much time showing the importance of European issues at national level.  We want to give ideas when it comes to Europe and we want to show our citizens how important is Europe.  It is important for us to meet the committee so that we can exchange ideas, and some of us have already met during the COSAC meeting and we will meet again in a month, towards the end of the EU Presidency.  Sharing ideas between parliamentarians is very different to parliamentarians simply listening to the Executive.</p><p>  There are three concerns I would like to share with the committee and which are important.  First, we are talking about deepening democracy and the participation of national parliaments in the context of budget integration.  Over the last month and a half since the events in Nicosia, it has been decided that during the European semester, there will be a legislative time, meaning that twice a year national parliaments and the European Parliament will have the opportunity to meet at the same time as the Commission is meeting to discuss budgetary matters, as per article 13 of the treaty.  France proposed this possibility and is very happy it has been adopted.</p><p>  I would like to have the committee's opinion on the first time this will happen in the autumn, under the Lithuanian Presidency.  I do not believe we have a date yet but it will be some time in the autumn.  I ask this question because I must present a report on the democratic deepening of the EU.  It is an easy topic, as the members can imagine, and it is interesting for all of us.  I would like the committee's opinion on the doubt that our citizens feel regarding the efficiency of Europe in making citizens happy.  Are Irish citizens more confident that the EU can do so than are their French counterparts?  One year before the European Parliament elections, there is a great fear in France and in other countries - I was in Poland last week - that nationalistic movements are increasing and there is more euro-scepticism and not enough "euro-conviction".  It is especially important as we are in the European year of citizenship.</p><p>  The second concern is the deepening of the economic and monetary union within the multi-annual financial framework.  We know we must have more ambition when it comes to the deepening of the economic and monetary union, even if we already know that the banking union is taking shape.</p> <p> I congratulate the Irish Presidency because it has managed to reach some conclusions.  We need the single supervisory mechanism as it is very important for European stability.  We will have the European stability mechanism which is as essential as a resolution mechanism.  It is very important to have a strong fight against tax fraud in all European countries.  I have seen some hesitation, even though Vienna has recently changed tack.  Tax harmonisation, I repeat, will only happen if we there is an efficient fight against tax fraud and evasion.  It is a challenge for the multiannual financial framework and it is essential that there is a social reference.  Ireland has shown good example with its plan to support young unemployed people.  Thankfully, we have received an envelope of &euro;6 billion, to that end, for accompanying measures.  Unfortunately, &euro;6 billion is not a lot for 27 member states.  It is important that national measures accompany European projects.  </p><p> With regard to the second point, I will share some of our concerns.  We believe that the budget is not ambitious enough.  The Commission proposed the budget but the Council reduced it and I think that the European Parliament is right to block it at present.  Dialogue must take place between the national parliaments and the European Parliament in order to strengthen the budget for the benefit of our citizens.  Under the Irish Presidency we will see, in a few weeks, if the European Parliament decides to block everything.  That would prove a serious difficulty compared with what happened last year.  The European Parliament does not want the same as a national assembly. Perhaps there will be a compromise.  To that end, there is a mid-term review clause that the budget can be blocked for seven years, especially as it is such a small budget.  </p><p> I shall now talk about a very sensitive topic for us, the EU's resources.  The EU budget depends on what every member state contributes which means money is taken direct from the pockets of our citizens.  The financial transaction tax has been approved by 11 member states so can go ahead.  Therefore, the EU budget will be taken direct from financial flows and not from the pockets of our citizens.</p><p> My third point is on energy transition.  We must fight against climate change and make it a European topic.  We must defend the idea and make it a new European period.  We started with the European community of coal and steel.  The second European period was the Common Agricultural Policy.  The third European period could be a European energy and environment policy.  We have a sponsor called Mr. Jacques Delors.  It is very useful to have him sponsor our proposal to have a carbon tax at EU borders.  An advantage of the carbon tax would be for the EU to have its own resources.  It would balance out the negative affects on the import market which is a hot topic at present.  The carbon tax has two further advantages.  It would encourage growth and employment.  We all know that a new source of employment is in green jobs such as in energy efficiency and renewable energies.  The jobs would have an important impact on employment, social aspects and the environment.</p><p> It is important for us to fight against climate change.  As members will know, today we were welcomed with beautiful sunshine but when we left Paris it was only 11&deg;C.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000005#D00200"><p>We know about bad weather.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.218" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Danielle Auroi" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000006#E00100"><p>What is most interesting is having a rich exchange.  We hope the Irish Presidency will manage to close an important file for Ireland and France.  I am talking about agriculture and CAP reform.  We have a common vision when it comes to husbandry and cattle and Ireland is in the same situation as France.  We want further greening of the CAP because it is unlikely that the Lithuanian Presidency will follow down that road.  We run the risk of Lithuania encouraging the large cereal plains in the north of Europe, which would not be good for citizens in the south, whether in Italy, Spain, France or even Austria and Germany.</p><p>  Perhaps the Irish Presidency might reopen some topics, even though the Commission has the lead.  I refer to the format and framework of the EU-US free trade agreement negotiations.  Members will certainly know that France has some reservations on some of these topics and will exercise its right of veto on the cultural exception, if necessary.  It would be useful in that context to take heed of the lessons we learned in the negotiations with Canada on its free trade agreement with the European Union.  It is blocked because the original mandate was too wide and not clear enough, especially on industrial issues.  There is no agreement between the European Union and Canada.  </p><p>  There are some agricultural methods in the United States which are not acceptable to EU citizens, for example, when it comes to animal feed, the labelling of meat products or what they do with animal carcasses.  </p><p>  I thank members.  We are here to answer their questions, to which we will listen carefully.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000006#E00200"><p>I thank Ms Auroi who has raised a number of issues.  I will update the delegates on the Presidency and talk about COSAC and what this committee is doing on some of the issues raised about the future of the European Union and banking and political union.  There were other issues such as Article 13, about which I can talk.  I will allow some of my colleagues to answer some of the questions and if they do not pick up on them, I will come back to them.  If no one picks up on the issue of the financial transaction tax, I will come back to it also.  The democratic deficit also concerns us.  The expert on climate change is not with us today, but we can all talk about that issue.</p><p>  I will start with the Presidency.  At this stage, we have just over one month left.  One of our key priorities was to restore stability to the European Union.  That involved trying to sort out the multi-annual financial framework.  We still have some way to go before reaching agreement with the European Parliament, but we think we are quite close and are hopeful we will reach agreement.  </p><p>  We thought it important to proceed and progress the issue of banking union.  We have managed to conclude the issues involved in regard to the single supervisory mechanism, thanks to the agreement of countries such as France.  We have moved in the area of banking union, but there are still issues in regard to resolution which will take more time to conclude. </p><p>  Another key priority for us was seeking economic growth and job creation.  Ms Auroi referred to the EU-US trade agreement.  As she will know, we have progressed that issue and have also looked at trade agreements with Japan and countries in the Far East.  </p><p>  We have managed to get agreement on an issue of key importance to us - youth unemployment.  The youth guarantee scheme agreed at the February Council is very worthwhile.  We are in complete agreement on the issue of finances.  The point was made that there was not enough to go around.  The initial agreement was that the scheme would be accessible to those countries such as Ireland and Spain which had a youth unemployment rate of more than 25%.  That level has come down to 20%, while, at the same time, the age limit has gone up from 25 to 30 years of age.  Therefore, many more people are in the pot, so to speak, but the money has not increased.  This is an issue for us and we believe the figure of &euro;6 billion is nowhere near enough.  Senator Kathryn Reilly might wish to speak about that matter because she will publish a report on behalf of the joint committee specifically on the youth guarantee.  However, in terms of the Presidency, we are happy that we have moved forward on the issue.  </p><p>  The other issue about which we are very keen is enlargement.  We were glad to see the agreement between Kosovo and Serbia last month.  That means that the progression of Serbia towards accession has improved.  We are hoping to open a chapter on Turkey before the end of next month.  What is the mood in France towards Turkish accession compared to three years ago when it was considered unlikely to be agreeable?  What are the delegate's views on the issue?</p> <p>Enlargement was one of our priorities and we think we will get to the stage, thanks to the agreement of other member states, where we will be able to open up a chapter with Turkey.  </p><p> In essence, our Presidency has been a lot of fun as well as a lot of hard work.  We have managed to move forward on a lot of issues that were on our agenda.  I should also have mentioned the CAP, which is very important for both France and Ireland.  Our Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine has been working very hard on that issue.  We are hoping to reach agreement on CAP reform before the end of our term.  </p><p> We have a programme put together for COSAC and one of the key areas is enlargement.  We will be talking about the Balkans, Iceland and Turkey.  We will also have a session on development aid, to which NGOs and a number of philanthropists have been invited to discuss what Europe needs to do in this area, as one of the biggest aid donors in the world.  Another session is planned to deal with the question of how to encourage more young people to engage with the EU.  We have invited three young speakers from the Roma, LGBT and disabled communities to tell us what they expect Europe to deliver to them as citizens.  We are looking forward to that session in particular.  We also have a session planned on the future of Europe, at which Mr. Jacques Delors has agreed to speak, as has Ms. Viviane Reding.  Mr. Delors, as our guests know, is a founding member of the Spinelli Group and a federalist.  Ms Reding will be talking about political union, no doubt.  Mr. Bill Cash from the UK Conservative Party will respond to the remarks of Mr. Delors and Ms Reding and we hope to have a very in-depth debate about political union and where member states see the future of Europe.  A discussion between Mr. Delors, Ms Reding and Mr. Cash should make for a very stimulating and interesting event, which will take place in four weeks.  </p><p> On the issue of the future of Europe, this committee is carrying out a study on the impact in Ireland of initiatives such as banking union, EMU and fiscal union, as well as the question of UK membership of the EU.  Our guests will be aware that the British Government has announced that it will hold a referendum on continued membership of the EU if re-elected.  If the UK chose to leave the union, that would have significant implications for us and we are examining what it might mean for us in the longer term.  </p><p> I hope I have answered the majority of the questions raised.  I have not dealt with the financial transactions tax issue because other committee members, such as Deputy Dooley, may want to deal with that, as well as the issue of climate change and Article 13.  Senator Reilly will probably pick up on the issue of the youth guarantee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000007#F00150"><p>I welcome our guests today.  I also welcome two colleagues from the French embassy who are very prominent visitors to Leinster House and very effective in representing their country.  </p><p>  I wish to address the issues of political and democratic legitimacy and monetary union.  Many of us feel that it is important to draw clear lines of delineation between the role of national parliaments and that of the European institutions.  That division is very clear in terms of policies on deficits, Government spending and taxation.  It is acceptable and beneficial for the European Union to require that Government borrowing stays within certain limits but I do not believe it is the role of the EU to determine how much any country raises through taxes or spends.  If one country wants to tax at 50% of its national income and spend at 53% of its national income, while another wants to tax at 30% and spend at 33%, that should be the decision of the national parliaments.  That is why we would have concerns about tax harmonisation.  It seems that everyone is in favour of harmonising tax measures that tax other people, apart from their own citizens.  Everybody is in favour of taxing multinational companies that are not based in their own country.  They are also in favour of taxing global capital that does not originate in their own country.  At the same time, everyone is against harmonising tax measures that affect their own people.  That is my concern about tax harmonisation.  France is adopting a stance on the audiovisual component of the free trade agreement which is in the French national interest, which is its right to do.  Similarly, Ireland has concerns about measures that would negatively affect our ability to move to recovery.  Only three years ago, our national deficit was almost 30% of our national income.  Next year, it will be at 4.5%.  Our country has made gigantic sacrifices to get to that point.  We will ensure that what we think is needed to allow our country to move forward is recognised and respected by other countries, just as France will do.  I say that in the context of a country that has regularly had referenda on European treaties and has always voted for their acceptance.  I include here our adoption of the fiscal compact in the middle of gigantic difficulties for all of our families.  </p><p>  I will conclude by thanking France for its support during a period of difficulty for Ireland.  I assure our guests of our continued support for European progress, as our Presidency has shown.  However, I must also emphasise that our country and its people have made huge sacrifices to deal with the challenges facing us.  We will continue to do all we can to ensure that our country moves towards recovery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000007#F00200"><p>I welcome our guests, with whom we have many common causes, particularly in the agricultural arena.  Ireland exports 90% of its produce, unlike our next door neighbour, which imports the great majority of its food produce.</p><p>  We are not federalists.  We do not believe in federalism but in close economic, social and political co-operation within the EU.  We are concerned about our next door neighbour's intention to hold a referendum on its membership of the EU, which could result in Britain leaving the union.  Some of us believe that could have devastating consequences for the European concept.</p> <p>The original founding fathers of the modern Europe had a vision and I strongly believe - we have discussed this at our meetings on many occasions - in the need for Europe to retain its original vision.  Departure from that vision can only mean going back to where Europe came from, and that is not a place to which we would want to go.</p><p> My colleague quite correctly referred to tax harmonisation.  We should look at the United States, in which there are variations in taxation depending on the individual states.  The same must apply to Europe.  There are different demands and requirements in different countries, but there should be a general thrust towards taking a common direction and making progress with an emphasis on economic and fiscal controls and growth.  Without that, the unanimity and cohesiveness that is required for the European project will diminish. </p><p> There is a danger of a two-tier Europe developing.  That is not in the interest of anybody in Europe.  It is not in the interests of the new member states, and it certainly is not in the interests of the existing member states.  People who profess their adherence to that concept are wrong.  They will be proven to be wrong.  </p><p> We do not have a particular problem with the financial transaction tax, provided everybody applies it.  Were it to apply right across the globe from Tokyo to the United States and right across Europe, particularly in the United Kingdom, which is reticent in that area, we would have no problem with it.  We recognise that sometimes those in the private sector can find ways and means of circumnavigating the system to their advantage.</p><p> I wish to refer to the recent discussions on tax fraud.  We want to state emphatically that the tax laws applied by Ireland are exactly as they profess.  Our corporation tax rate is 12.5% and this is strictly enforced.  All profits generated, whether through manufacturing or services, by foreign direct investment in this country are taxed at that rate.  The effective rate is deemed to be about 1.5% less.  I know that other European countries that profess to have a much higher corporation tax rate have in effect a much lower one.  This has generated discussion in the United Kingdom and the United States in recent weeks.  The discussion does not take account of the true facts.  The situation is within the control of the states themselves: should states wish to tax companies from their countries on the profits they generate in other countries, they can do that.  It is within the control of the United States or the United Kingdom to do so.  In this country we tax companies on the basis of the goods and services manufactured here.  Anything else they want to do after that is of no relevance in the Irish system of taxation.</p><p> We fully agree with the deepening of the economic and monetary union.  The establishment of a common currency has had devastating consequences for countries throughout Europe.  We thought the introduction of the euro throughout Europe meant the application of controls by the ECB in respect of borrowing and spending right across the eurozone states.  There was no proper control and no supervision, and as a result we incurred appalling debt.  My colleague has referred to measures taken by the previous and the current Governments.  These cruel measures were inflicted on our people.  In the past few days Ministers have repeated that taking such measures is not something they enjoy; however, they are having the beneficial effect of bringing our deficit down more rapidly than we thought, as my colleague has just said.  Initially, we were worried that the burden imposed on the people of this country would break their resolve to withstand the shock of what we must deal with.  We have achieved a considerable degree of success.  The trade figures announced this morning show that our level of success is much greater than we had anticipated.</p><p> The country was criticised heavily when the economic bubble burst originally.  We got a lot of unfair criticism in many quarters, which we did not deserve.  Of course we were wrong.  We hold up our hands and accept responsibility for wrongdoing.  We set about rectifying that, but it is important that everybody else across Europe recognises that they also have responsibilities.  If the powerful countries and the smaller countries work together we can recover the lost ground in a much more meaningful way than we might have thought just a few short years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000008#G00200"><p>There are a number of questions outstanding.  I will take contributions from a few more members and I hope that will have answered some of the issues.  Deputy Dooley might want to cover the financial transaction tax among the other issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000008#G00300"><p>I thank the delegates for attending.  I thank the ambassador, Ms Emmanuelle d'Achon, and her deputy, who maintain regular contact with the committee.  They are outstanding.  There is a good relationship between the Oireachtas and France.</p><p>  For a long time I have advocated a much closer relationship between Ireland and France and between Ireland and Germany.  We have been successful and have started to build a closer relationship at parliamentary level with Ms d'Achon and the German ambassador.  We often use the opportunity in the Houses of the Oireachtas to criticise what we perceive to be the misunderstanding of our economic and tax situation and we do so in the expectation that somehow people will be listening to what we say.  Of course, when one considers the detail, one appreciates that other countries have other things to deal with.  It is important to have more regular dialogue similar to this, and also through COSAC, which has been helpful.  If we have learned anything from the recent crisis, it is the importance of ensuring that the individual member states understand the conditions and concerns and the framework in which other parliamentarians have to work.</p><p>  That brings me to the point the Chairman wants me to address, the financial transaction tax.  I am a member of the main Opposition party but, notwithstanding that, I share the views of my colleague, Deputy Durkan.  We have a similar view that the introduction of a financial transaction tax can only be done on a worldwide basis.  The mobility of investment capital is such that we cannot expect it to reside within the borders of Europe or the EEA.  It would be foolhardy if a number of countries in Europe or indeed Europe generally were to proceed on that basis.  It must be done on a global basis.  The G20 is the forum in which to try to seek a level of consensus.  However, I support in principle the concept of a financial transaction tax, which does provide a considerable opportunity to generate significant revenues for the State.</p><p>  We have been critical in the past of positions taken by some politicians in France on their perception of Ireland's low corporate tax rate.  As my colleague has said, what you see is what you get, and the 12.5% rate of corporation tax is applied across the board.  There are very few opportunities, through the provision of tax credits, to reduce that further.  Studies and comparative analysis have been done across member states and by no measure does Ireland apply the lowest effective corporate tax rate.  That is a misapprehension that is worth exposing.</p><p>  I know the common consolidated tax base is an issue of particular concern for our delegation.  We as a State have indicated our willingness to participate in that discussion.</p> <p>This willingness should not be taken as an acceptance of a positive outcome from our perspective in supporting that principle.  I know this may be at variance with the French position on that matter.  We do not see it as helpful from our point of view.  </p><p> We attract considerable foreign direct investment, not only for tax reasons.  We are an English speaking nation, with a good base for providing onward capacity for American companies to target the European market.  We want to protect this investment. </p><p> To turn to the European project, considerable damage has been done to the notion of the Community method of dealing with issues and crises and building and developing for the future.  While I do not wish to be political or overly critical, the holding of bilateral meetings on a Sunday afternoon, week in and week out, during the term of President Sarkozy damaged, albeit not irreparably, the notion of a Community where it was important for smaller states to be treated as equal participants.  Unfortunately, the Franco-German discussion appeared to be the focus in resolving issues as they arose.  This sidelined the Commission and damaged its role.  We have work to do to re-establish the authority of the Commission, the composition of which ensures equality.  Its role is not only to keep the system pure.  It is important in retaining the engagement of citizens of all member states.  The delegates will be aware that Ireland has found it necessary to hold a second referendum on a number of occasions.  Many people outside Ireland who believe the country has benefited from its relationship with the European Union, as it has, asked why Irish citizens did not share their view.  Efforts to deal with the crisis at a bilateral level alienated citizens in many countries.  As parliamentarians, we have a role to play in addressing this issue.  We must do so in a collective way, with parliamentarians from other member states, to try to ensure the Community method is re-established.  Europe is predominately made up of smaller states which must believe they have access and influence and are part of a developing European Union.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00200"><p><i>Bienvenu</i>.  I welcome the delegation.  I propose to discuss the issue of youth unemployment and the youth guarantee before responding to our guests' question on doubts that citizens entertain about the European Union.  As the Chairman stated, I am producing a report on the youth guarantee on behalf of the joint committee.  The organisations that deal with young people and the most marginalised groups across Europe are concerned about the adequacy of the funding allocated for the youth employment initiative.  We are also concerned that the release of funding is being held up by the negotiations on the multi-annual financial framework.</p><p>  The roll-out of the youth guarantee at national level will be important.  A danger arises from the Council recommendation about gradual implementation because if member states are given too much scope to implement the guarantee, young people who are not in education, employment or training and are in most need of funding may not receive it when they need it.  Concerns have also arisen regarding the funding member states will contribute to the youth guarantee, especially member states which are in programmes or fiscal difficulty.  We must ensure this matter is prioritised because the costs to member states of youth unemployment in terms of GDP are very high and they will also face social and economic costs in the future. </p><p>  In terms of citizens' doubts about the European Union and the issue of the democratic deficit and legitimacy, the Eurobarometer polls taken last year are very telling as they show that the level of trust of citizens in European institutions is very low.  This lack of trust is also reflected in citizens' attitudes to national institutions.  The President of the European Parliament made an interesting comment when he described Europe as a Frankenstein monster and spoke about the need for greater parliamentary scrutiny.  I ask the delegates to comment on his remarks.</p><p>  A widely published article co-authored by the Minister for Social Protection, a senior French MEP and the chairman of the EU Employment and Social Affairs Committee has been published and addresses one of the reasons citizens do not trust European institutions.  It may explain the reasons there is so little trust in the European Union and people do not believe they have ownership of European institutions.  The authors wrote: ...the pressure to make far-reaching &ldquo;adjustments&rdquo; often means that there is limited time to discuss reforms with trade unions and employers&rsquo; organisations before they are introduced, undermining reforms&rsquo; sustainability and sometimes leading to social unrest.  Many citizens feel increasingly disconnected from national politics, and even more so from European decision-making, over which they feel they have little influence.</p><p>  This is a key reason for the dramatic decline in the popularity of European Union institutions.  In times of economic turbulence people do not believe they have ownership of the decisions being made and believe they are being rushed through.</p><p>  On the issue of further integration, the article continued: &quot;There is no solution to the crisis without reconstructing Europe&rsquo;s economic and monetary union, and without shifting the focus on to people&rsquo;s needs and potential&quot;.  The authors called for the convening of a Bretton Woods-type conference to put in place an economic and monetary arrangement for the coming decade&quot;.  They also questioned austerity which, they argued, could only bring Europe so far and stated a broader vision was needed.  If people believed they had ownership of the process and would not be consistently penalised by some of the European institutions and if a lasting arrangement or &quot;grand bargain&quot;, to use the words of the authors, were in place, there would be greater European solidarity and people would probably become more accepting of integration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00300"><p>A large number of important questions were asked, many of which have been answered.  I will start with traditional Irish pl&aacute;mas.  I am struck immediately by the gender composition of the delegation in comparison with the gender composition of the committee members present.  This is probably a result of President Hollande's decision to give equal representation to the genders.  This puts us at a disadvantage.</p><p>  It would be nice if the delegation could convey on my behalf, as a personal friend, and presumably on behalf of the Chairman and members, best wishes to <font color="#444444">H&eacute;l&egrave;ne Conway</font><font color="#444444">-</font><font color="#444444">Mouret</font><font color="#444444"> whom I have not seen since she became a member of the French Cabinet.</font></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00400"><p>There is nothing unusual about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00500"><p>I hope I am not overstepping my position in asking that my message be conveyed to her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00600"><p>Not at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00700"><p>We would love to hear how she interacts with the French overseas electorate, just as we are debating intensely our relationship with the Diaspora throughout the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00800"><p>I would like to be associated with the Deputy's comments about H&eacute;l&egrave;ne Conway-Mouret.  D&eacute;put&eacute; Axelle Lemaire also attends regular meetings and meets us on an informal basis to keep us posted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000009#H00900"><p>Our guests raised fascinating and interesting points.  Ireland has a great relationship with France, which it wishes to build and develop.  We also have a great relationship with our next door neighbour, England, which we also wish to develop.</p> <p>Just as France has a common interest with us, for example, in the agricultural field, we have a very important relationship with England which is now worrying us in the context of its position on Europe.  Just as we have friendships in many ways, we did not have that great a friendship with the French position of Sarkozy or with the Germans who attempted to sideline and attack us because we have our own national taxation code.  It has been mentioned here and it has been mentioned in America.  We believe our tax code is beyond criticism in so far as it is open to anyone who wishes to see it.  It is based on legislation and there are no special deals for anyone.  We have our interest because we are an island nation.  The witness mentioned the French potential veto of any EU-US trade relationship that is evolving quickly.  We see it as very important in so far as we would see Ireland as a bridge between Europe and the US for the transfer of goods and investment and <i>vice versa</i>.</p><p> We may have problems in agreeing some of these measures.  Obviously, our most recent disagreement was between our Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade on sanctions for Syria.  I understand where the witnesses are coming from, in that France is a very large arms producing nation and has decided, along with Britain, not to go along the European path.  While we will not be exporting arms, it is still a big disappointment for us as I understand 25 nations stood with us while France and Britain stood alone.</p><p> The witness mentioned that the European Parliament had not sanctioned the European budget and said she was not satisfied that it was sufficiently large.  We agree.  However, as one sees the evolution of the political climate in Europe, Mr. Cameron publicly applauded the reduction of the European budget as a victory for England.  There are friendships that come into conflict and others that do not.  We are not part of the Schengen area and, as a nation, we are ardently pro-European.  We test our electorate now and again.   Our Constitution obliges us to put very important and complex issues to the electorate and we are happy that on each occasion - maybe not the first time every time - we bring the people with us.</p><p> I am aware that Ms Danielle Auroi serves on the committee of foreign affairs in the French National Assembly.  I am fascinated by the French position on Turkey and the Armenian massacre given that we are speaking to Turkey with a view to enlargement of the European Union.  Does she think that is an important issue for France?  Given that she is from a colonial power and multicultural society, presumably a contributing factor being its former colonies, what is the French position on the wearing of the hijab and the burka?  Given that we are talking about Turkey being a predominantly Muslim country, are we facilitating an understanding among the Turkish electorate and politicians that they are welcome?  I understand that Sarkozy might not have recognised Turkey as being a European country.</p><p> I applaud the French decision to move rapidly into the Sahel area of Mali and I understand it has a great fear of jihadists.  An open debate will have to take place in Europe about the jihadists.  I congratulate the French on being bold enough to make that independent decision to move to inflict damage on the jihadists who were heading to Bamako.</p><p> We agree on many things and we disagree on some.  We agree with England on many things and we disagree on many.  We have a strong independent political philosophy when it comes to the United States.  We love the Americans but we have our own independent foreign policy.  I thank the witnesses for their praise of Ireland's Presidency.  As a collective, we are extremely proud of the hard work put in by our Prime Minister and Ministers.  We concluded the Common Fisheries Policy agreement last night.  We hope the budgetary position and other unfinished business will be resolved during our Presidency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.236" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Danielle Auroi" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000010#J00200"><p>We are going to answer all the questions with two voices.  Perhaps I will start with an issue that was mentioned several times, that is, EU enlargement.  In this period when citizens have many doubts <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> the European Union, it is even more difficult to ask this question.  I want to mention especially the example of the Lithuanian Presidency which, like other states, such as Poland and Germany, will wish to open discussions with other states that Europe may not have mentioned.  I will come back to Turkey later.  However I want to mention the Ukraine because the Lithuanian Presidency will want to have a strong partnership with the Ukraine.  It is very difficult for us as there is a lack of democracy and a lack of respect for human rights in that country, which means we are going to be very careful.</p><p>  I am going to speak about something that is, perhaps, simpler and it has been mentioned already.  Serbia has now won the right to start opening some chapters.  Over a month ago, I was in the Serbian capital with a German colleague from the Bundestag who was saying that Croatia had joined the European Union and that was sufficient, but we believe the Balkans are going to join the European Union.  It is very important for the stability of the whole region of the Balkans and for peace in that area.  Let us not forget that the two world wars started in the Balkans.</p> <p>Turkey asked a long time ago to join the EU.  The country has several qualities.  First, it is a large country and, therefore, we are changing scale completely.  If Turkey joins the EU it will mean 100 million people will join the EU.  That is difficult for us.  Second, Turkey plays an important role in the equilibrium and peace of that region.  It is a direct link between Europe and the Mediterranean area.  It is an area of stability and we should bear this in mind in view of what is happening in Syria and the Lebanon, which is currently having some difficulties as well.  Let us not forget that Turkey is an interface with Iran as well.</p><p> I offer one last point on Turkey.  Turkey has a working model which integrates Islam without going all the way to extremism.  Reference was made to the burka, but I know Turkey well and there are few burkas in Turkey.  I see more burkas in Parisian suburbs.  The fundamental question is that Turkey is an economic and social model that works and manages the risk of extremism within the Mediterranean area.</p><p> The committee members were nice enough to congratulate France on our intervention in the working of Mali to guarantee stability in Africa and the fight against Islamic extremists.  It is important to bear in mind that Turkey is keen to reinforce the partnership, perhaps more than the EU accession.  Turkey is keen to have a strong regular working method with the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000011#K00200"><p>I suggest we conclude, unless you wish to continue in public session.  I have been told lunch is ready.  We could continue the discussion over lunch.  Would that be acceptable?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.239" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Danielle Auroi" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000011#K00300"><p>Okay.  Thank you very much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2013053000011#K00400"><p>I will adjourn the meeting and we will head there now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.241" nospeaker="true" time="12:40:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 1.05 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.242" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.243" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 10:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Frank Feighan, Senator Jim D'Arcy, Deputy Martin Ferris, Senator Mary Moran, Deputy Peter Fitzpatrick, Senator Mary M. White. Deputy Michael P. Kitt, Deputy Aodhn  Rordin, Deputy Brendan Smith, Deputy Jack Wall,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Gerry Adams, Senator Terry Brennan and Mr. Pat Doherty, MP.</p><p>DEPUTY JOE McHUGH IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.245" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000002#A00200">Exploring Education and Overcoming Social Disconnection: Discussion with Minister for Education and Skills</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000002#A00300"><p>As we have a quorum we will commence in public session.  Apologies have been received from Deputies Regina Doherty, Se&aacute;n Crowe, and Joe O'Reilly.</p><p>  I remind members of the usual drill regarding mobile telephones.  I ask that they switch them off or put them on silent mode.</p><p>  We will have a discussion with the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, to explore education as a tool for empowerment and overcoming social disconnection.  In layman or laywoman terms, that means we will have a good conversation about education and how we can learn and share experiences in terms of tackling disadvantage.  The Minister will give account initially and then I will open up the discussion to the members.  </p><p>  The Minister is very welcome.  It is his first time to attend before this committee.  We appreciate him coming here and giving of his time.  We hope to have a good engaging conversation this morning.  His presence here today has garnered considerable interest in this discussion.  I appreciate the attendance of members from different organisations and individuals in the Visitors Gallery who have come here today.  </p><p>  I will throw out a statistic that would be in the back of everybody's mind, namely, that of all the students who go to university in the Republic, only 0.5% are from Northern Ireland.   That 0.5% statistic from 2008 has been a recurring one.  There are issues around mobility, mobility challenges and mobility opportunities into which we will hopefully delve today.</p><p>  I invite the Member to make his presentation and I will then open the discussion up to members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000002#A00400"><p>I thank Chairman and committee members.  I will speak to the paper I have prepared, which has been circulated, and go down through the headings rather than read it formally into the record, but I presume it can be taken as being read formally into the record.</p><p>  The first issue is literacy and numeracy.  In 2009, this State got a wake up call in regard to our presumption that we had one of the best education systems in the world.  It was a presumption that was based on an internal form of arrogance because we had nothing with which to compare it.  It was a case of if one says it often enough, one begins to believe it.  We dropped from fifth place to seventeenth place.  We had a similar but not as precipitous a drop in terms of mathematics.  The Department got word of it in August, did some research and when the results were published in October, it had started to create a response.  There was a change of government in March 2011.  A draft literacy and numeracy strategy was prepared and it was finalised and formally launched by me in June of that year.  It is appropriate to say to this committee that much of the reform and change in the system, and I can get details on this if people want it, was based on some of the experience in Northern Ireland.  The Northern Ireland Department of Education had started to reform the way in which it was teaching literacy and numeracy.  There is very close co-operation between the inspectorate in the North and in the South.  There is co-operation with Wales and Scotland as well because they have separate education systems under devolution.  We have now put in place a literacy and numeracy strategy on which we will probably get some results later this year because we are into the new cycle.  I would be happy to answer any questions on that.</p><p>  One of the changes we made in the context of the literacy and numeracy strategy is around initial teacher education, and this is confirmed in a document that will be published later today.  We have had 19 centres of teacher education for both primary and post-primary in the country.  We realised that there needed to be a change in the way teachers were educated.  The changes, which I can speak to in detail, are, in summary, that the 19 colleges - most of them privately owned  by the Catholic Church or the Church of Ireland which reflects the history, our system of primary education being 182 years old having been established in 1831 - are being reorganised into six clusters of education provision.  A primary school teacher will now study for four years rather than three years.  The fourth year will be focused very much on pedagogic skills, namely, learning how children learn.</p> <p>The post-primary secondary school teacher will now do a two year H.Dip course rather than the one year course, and again there is an emphasis on the way people learn, learning techniques and so on.  I can go into the detail on that.</p><p> I have already referred to PISA.  There are two other literacy testings - TIMSS and PIRLS - in which we have participated.  The results of the Progress in International Reading Literacy Study, known as PIRLS, and the Trends in International Mathematics and Science Study, TIMSS, are very positive from our primary school point of view.  Primary school students scored above average in literacy, mathematics and science.  In mathematics, Ireland was placed 17th out of 50 participating countries, and in science we were placed 22nd out of 50 participating countries.</p><p> The PIRLS report shows that in reading, Irish students were ranked tenth out of 45 participating countries.  Students in only five countries performed significantly better than Irish students.  They were Hong Kong, Finland, Singapore, the Russian Federation, and Northern Ireland.  As I said, we are learning from our colleagues in Northern Ireland the way they have been able to improve their performance, and there is very good co-operation between both systems at institutional and ministerial level between myself and John O'Dowd, and also at a personal level in terms of individuals on this island.</p><p> The second aspect I want to discuss is the change in our junior certificate.  The most significant development is our plan to reform the post-primary junior cycle for children from ages 12 and 13 to 15 and 16 in our secondary system.  The framework published in October 2012 sets out the principal statements of learning and key skills that will underpin the new junior cycle.  </p><p> We have concerns about the literacy and numeracy standards achieved by students.  Consequently, the key tenants of the literacy and numeracy strategy are integrated within and complement the framework.  The framework is designed to provide schools with flexibility rather than restrict them as they develop a junior cycle programme that reflects the educational and personal needs of their students.</p><p> In addition to its own range of literacy initiatives provided through the school system, the Department has had some involvement in the prevention and early intervention programme in Dublin through the work of the Department's inspectorate.  These projects, undertaken in Tallaght, Ballymun and Darndale, involve a range of pilot programmes to improve outcomes in areas such as literacy, speech and language, parenting, health and pro-social behaviour.  The projects, which are now concluding, are currently being evaluated by national and international experts.</p><p> In Tallaght west,<i></i>the emphasis was to ensure that the initiatives complemented existing education disadvantage initiatives.  In Youngballymun,<i></i>the Department participated in the Write Minded Implementation Team, which, in partnership with local schools and other key stakeholders, developed a local literacy strategy which focused on two strands: school-based literacy support to complement Delivering Equality of Opportunity in Schools, DEIS, and family and community-based literacy support.  Overall, the principal strength of the Youngballymun interventions is that they built on and enhanced the work of existing mainstream services in an integrated manner.</p><p> The Department has also participated in a number of education-related initiatives to support Limerick Regeneration.  These have largely been run by the Programme Innovation Development Fund, which is a joint initiative of Government and Atlantic Philanthropies, and Strategic Innovation in Education, a project set up by the University of Limerick to support the education sector in responding to Limerick Regeneration.</p><p> My colleague, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, recently announced a new area-based poverty initiative, which will be jointly funded by her Department and Atlantic Philanthropies, and will seek to implement programmes which have been proven to work in improving outcomes for children and families at risk of disadvantage.  The new initiative reflects the programme for Government commitment to adopt an area-based approach to child poverty in co-operation with philanthropic partners, drawing upon best international practice and existing services, to break the cycle of child poverty where it is most deeply entrenched.</p><p> In the context of the literacy and numeracy strategy, it is particularly important that learning from previous and current literacy initiatives being delivered in schools can be mainstreamed to ensure the widest possible benefit from the considerable investment that has been made.  </p><p> It is important to note that in all cases PEIP literacy initiatives are being implemented locally alongside schools which are part of DEIS, Delivering Equality of Opportunity in Schools, the Government's main policy initiative for tackling educational disadvantage.  This means that they can all avail of the considerable additional resources allocated to DEIS schools in those areas where disadvantage is most concentrated.  Smaller classes and support programmes, one of which is the home-school-community liaison officer, usually a teacher, who makes contact with families that are having difficulty of one kind or another.  The other is the school completion programme, which is an attempt to ensure young people stay in school for as long as possible.</p><p> We believe it is important that we operate an inclusive school system where all children feel welcome.  The Education Act 1998 sets out clearly that schools are required to operate admissions policies that provide for maximum accessibility to the school.  Most schools in Ireland, most of the time, are inclusive and welcoming of all children.  The Education Act, however, is light touch in terms of providing ways and means of ensuring that all schools welcome all children.  Other than appeals under section 29 of that Act, which have become cumbersome and often adversarial both for schools and parents, the Department is of the view, and I share the view, that the current legislation does not include an adequate set of provisions to deal with this matter, which is the reason we will change the system.  I will shortly bring to Government the draft heads of a Bill entitled the education (admission to school) Bill 2013.  In bringing forward legislative proposals, I do not want to unnecessarily intrude into the way schools do their business.  The aim is to ensure that schools decide on applications for enrolment in a structured, fair and transparent manner.  The proposals will be published in draft form along with the statutory instruments to give them effect.  They will be referred to the Oireachtas committee here.  I hope to have a fairly comprehensive debate and then bring back the final proposals.</p><p> Turning to North-South co-operation, specifically on literacy and numeracy, I am pleased to note the ongoing dialogue which takes place here under the auspices of the Good Friday Agreement between the education authorities in both jurisdictions on a range of issues of mutual interest, but particularly in relation to measures to improve educational outcomes in our schools.  In particular, I note that the last meeting of the North-South Literacy and Numeracy Working Group<b></b>discussed the prospect of a joint report by the two inspectorates, focusing on best practice in both literacy and numeracy in post-primary settings.</p><p> Encouraging an appreciation of the value of learning is a key task for all of us who are interested in raising educational standards.  Last year's promotional media campaign in Northern Ireland - Get Involved Because Education Works - emphasised the fact that education does not begin or end at the school gate and that families and the wider community can contribute to and enjoy education.</p><p> A current initiative in this jurisdiction is &quot;The Family Project&quot;, a weekly television programme which showcases the educational tools and techniques available to all families.  It demonstrates how families can work together to improve collective learning.  Since 2000, the National Adult Literacy Agency, NALA, has been using the mass medium of television to highlight literacy issues, outline supports that are available, motivate people to return to education and provide opportunities for learning in the privacy of their own home.  NALA has also developed a website to help parents support their children's education.  Entitled Help My Kid Learn, it is a website where people can see that supporting a child's literacy and numeracy development is a natural, easy and fun activity that can be integrated into any part of their day.</p><p> Although there are a number of marked differences between our education systems, we face similar challenges North and South when it comes to raising standards, particularly in the area of literacy, and I believe that we have much to gain from a sharing of learning and experience in order to develop sound policies for future action in this important area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000003#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  I will now take questions and observations from members.  I call Deputy Kitt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000003#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister for the overview he has given on education.</p> <p>On the proposed four-year primary teacher training course, I have spoken to some students who are looking forward to it.  However, this means there will be a gap in a particular year when no students will emerge from the teacher training colleges.  If I recall correctly, this happened previously when the teacher training course was lengthened from two to three years.  Certain issues arose and teachers who wished to retire were persuaded to stay on for another year.  Has the Minister thought this through in the context of the teacher training courses at Hibernia College and whether there might be more students on such courses?  As I understand it, the Department of Education and Skills is aware of how many primary school teachers emerge from the colleges each year.  Consequently, it is possible to control the numbers, unlike, for example, second level teacher training.  Has the Minister given consideration to what might be done if there is a shortage of teachers?  This certainly happened in the past when we moved from a two to a three year course.  However, my understanding is that students are looking forward to the extended course.</p><p> The Minister has also mentioned the number of teacher training centres which he is talking about reducing.  What is the final figure?  Can he give members further information in that regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00200"><p>The intention is to have six clusters or six coming together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1040" speakername="Michael Kitt" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00300"><p>While I am on the issue of teachers, the practice of appointing or retaining teachers on the basis of enrolment levels in the previous September has been followed for years.  Has the Minister given consideration to it?  As members are discussing North-South bodies today, does this happen in the North or in any other European country?  Obviously, difficulties arise when enrolment increases in a school, but teachers are still being appointed or retained on the basis of old figures which obviously are out of date.  </p><p>  I refer to the panels which I gather are still based on the diocesan system.  There appear to be many issues where people cannot transfer from one diocese to another.  A person could live in one diocese while teaching in another and could find himself or herself, when on a panel, being obliged to travel long distances.  While the panel system is good from the perspective of job security, it is not very good if one is obliged to travel very long distances to the next school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00400"><p>If the Minister does not mind, I will take two speakers at a time.  I acknowledge this involves taking multiple questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1085" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00500"><p>I have two questions for the Minister.  First, on the area-based rural initiative to tackle child poverty, will this be based in DEIS areas or will it be expanded to cater for other areas also?  On the point as to whether an inclusive school system is operated, most schools in Ireland most of the time are inclusive and welcoming of all children.  Obviously, the system has been tested, probably by parents and schools.  Will the Minister outline incidents that give a flavour of where problems actually arise and what precisely does he intend to do about it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00600"><p>The Chairman should try to ensure my answers are short, as I have a tendency to go on a bit.  </p><p>  To answer Deputy Kitt's question, we do not expect that there will be a gap.  Some teacher unions have complained about the number who are qualifying as teachers or applying to undertake a transfer degree course.  For example, someone with an arts degree can apply to take the conversion course to become a qualified and recognised primary school teacher.  It is one profession which is in short supply worldwide.  Irish people are particularly well suited, for example, to teaching in the United Kingdom and the south of England has a massive crisis in the provision of both primary school places and teachers.  Sadly, the same situation does not obtain across the rest of United Kingdom, but there is a shortage of teachers.  Consequently, we cannot stop people from doing these courses.  We can limit the supply in the public sector, but as of now, we do not anticipate, on the basis of what we can foresee, that there will be a crisis in the gap to which the Deputy referred.</p><p>  In respect of the enrolment numbers and the payment of schools, I have just come from a new school that is opening in Swords, where people were complaining about the problem they had experienced.  When the school started, it had 24 pupils, but it now has 224.  However, it is being paid a capitation grant based on last year's enrolment figure - just 100 pupils.  I am told the reason the system was put in place was that when the primary school system was, in population terms, declining, it was a way of providing some stability within the school system.  The White Paper published in the mid-1990s by a previous Minister for Education, Niamh Breathnach, stated the big challenge facing the primary school system was managing decline.  It was then thought we would be losing population in schools.  At the time, there were just under 500,000 pupils, but we now have 520,000 and rising.  There will be 70,000 additional primary and post-primary kids in the system within the next seven or eight years.  It is a cash-flow problem for some schools and as we are in straitened economic circumstances, I do not have much room for manoeuvre.  However, I recognise this is a major challenge for rapidly growing schools and it will become an even greater challenge.</p><p>  On the panel system and the diocesan structure, I share the Deputy's view.  We would like the Catholic authorities to modernise their system of allocating school teachers and resources and some progress has been made in this regard.  The Deputy's family has made a great contribution to the world of education and I am merely telling him things he knows well, but, in effect, we have a public private partnership system of education which, as I stated, dates back to 1831.  In a sense, the State undertook to pay the salaries of teachers, set the curriculum and provide for the examination process, while the partner on the private side, namely, the patron, provided the premises, either completely or partially in the form of a site, as well as providing the board of management and for supervision.  The patron became the employer that ran the school.  That was a 32 county system which, by and large, is still in place and essentially has not changed.  We had a primary school examination at the end of sixth class which I think - Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in should help me - was abolished in 1967.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1018" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00700"><p>It was something like that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000004#C00800"><p>It was a long way back.</p><p>  On Deputy Frank Feighan's question about the area-based initiative, I am not entirely sure and must revert to him to ensure greater clarity.  While there is an application process, I do not have the details to hand, but I will forward them to him.  </p><p>  On the reference to inclusive schools and the reason for the enrolment policy measures I have discussed, we have three kinds of post-primary school, namely, VEC schools, community colleges of one kind or another and the traditional free voluntary schools, as they are known in the jargon and which, by and large, have been run by the religious teaching orders.  The community schools evolved from a situation in which, typically, a town had the brothers at one end, the sisters at the other and a technical school in the middle.  The three schools then came together and are now funded by the State.  However, they are independent of the VECs, although there is an involvement with them and their structures can vary.</p><p>  The National Council for Special Education has recently published a report with a new set of 28 recommendations which I received on 17 May.  Having spoken to parents of children with special needs, the council found they encountered a kind of soft barrier, where schools would decline to enrol such pupils, even though they had space for them.  A school would suggest to the parents that it thought the VEC school down the road would be better equipped to meet the challenges the child would present.  Alternatively, schools would claim they did not necessarily have all the requisite resources or state they would not take in the child in question without an undertaking from the Department of Education and Skills that a full grant would be given.  One must be careful in how one decodes all of this because one is not sure one is getting the code right, but part of it is that schools compete for pupils in parts of the country.  They compete on the basis of their school examination results and it is suggested they may do this if they consider that taking in such a pupil will require more time and will not necessarily enhance the academic performance of the school at junior cycle in the junior certificate examination.</p> <p>We do not have proof positive but we know that the number of appeals under section 29 for non-admission to a school have risen exponentially, are costly and take up a great deal of teachers' time in July and August.  That is the reference to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.260" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Pat Doherty" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00200"><p>I welcome the Minister's submission.</p><p>  I have three broad areas.  I am aware that there is a slight disjoint in terms of the two Departments because in the South, the Minister covers first, second and third and in the North, the Department of Education covers first and second and the Department of Employment and Learning covers third level, although the proposed restructuring of the Assembly and the Executive might well resolve that.  I would be concerned that a joint survey which was ready in January of this year was to be taken at the February meeting of the North-South Ministerial Council, but they did not get round to that.  It is now scheduled to be taken at the October meeting.  I seek reassurance that there would be no further slippage on that report being dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00300"><p>Is this the cross-Border strategy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.262" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Pat Doherty" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00400"><p>The cross-Border survey.</p><p>  Second, I understand that the universities in the South are independent and, therefore, the Minister can have influence but not necessarily control.  The recognition of A level qualifications of the North in the system in the South needs to be resolved so that we have a broad understanding of how it works.  There are some specifics that keep being raised in our constituency offices which we find difficult to deal with.</p><p>  Third, there is a programme of promoting Southern institutions in the schools in the North and we hope to build on that.  I am not aware of any such programme in the South promoting the two universities in the North.</p><p>  Finally, and this may be anecdotal rather than survey based, the education systems on these islands are broadly rated as follows: Scotland is the best, the South is the second best, the North is the third, Wales is the fourth and England is the bottom of the heap.  In his introductory remarks, the Minister spoke of dropping from fifth to seventeenth place and the efforts needed to move both North and South further up that list.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/970" speakername="Brendan Smith" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00500"><p>I have three quick questions for the Minister.  Are there any proposals to advance or develop a common curriculum, North and South, in a particular subject or subjects?</p><p>  With regard to rural schools, in parts of the Six Counties, in particular, in Fermanagh with which I am familiar because I live on the Border, there are considerable concerns about proposed closures, not of really small schools but of schools with substantial enrolment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00600"><p>What numbers would Deputy Smith consider substantial?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/970" speakername="Brendan Smith" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00700"><p>Well in excess of 100 anyway, from what I gather from some of the commentary in local newspapers and from residents.  Has the idea of co-operation on access to schools on both sides of the Border been mooted?  Some travel from North to South and <i>vice versa</i>, but the numbers are small.  If there was a gap in an area, be it South or North of the Border, are there any such proposals?</p><p>  On skills shortages, of which the Minister will be aware in specific areas, have any particular initiatives been undertaken, at further education level or third level, North or South, to address specific skills shortages, be it in language proficiency or science subjects?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00800"><p>I thank the Minister for his presentation.</p><p>  First, following on from what Pat Doherty stated regarding recognition of A levels from the North, I do not accept that is a contributing factor explaining he low entrance rate from the North in third level here.  I think the rate is 0.5% or 0.6%.  It is a mitigating factor in building a harmonious and all-island aspect to our education policies.</p><p>  Getting back to the Twenty-six Counties, I would concur with the Minister who linked child poverty, regeneration and educational disadvantage.  Where there is economic disadvantage, there is educational disadvantage and a lack of early intervention which is vitally necessary.  Is there any cognisance given to the need for an enhanced programme of lowering the pupil-teacher ratio, particularly in the most disadvantaged areas, for a child who is born in economic circumstances outside his or her control?</p><p>  I have one other questions relating to the Six Counties.  I strongly believe in de-sectarianising the institution of education.  The power that various church groups have over education is grotesque.</p><p>  Regarding a forward management plan on education in an all-island capacity, has any progress been made towards moving in that direction?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000005#D00900"><p>I welcome Pat Doherty.  We go back a bit in time.</p><p>  The joint survey to which he refers was an initiative proposed by my Northern counterpart, Mr. John O'Dowd, MLA, and it responds to some of the matters about which Deputy Smith asked.  There was an initial resistance from the Unionist side in Northern Ireland to it but I fully supported it.  We undertook a survey of parents on either side of the Border, at 20 km for post-primary and at 10 km for primary, to see whether there was an interest in doing exactly what Deputy Smith stated, to offer parents, because of the arbitrary nature of the Border, the ability to send their child to a school of their choice on the other side of the Border if that is what they wanted.  Frankly, the results were less than promising.  I would like to offer it and see it happen.</p><p>  I can link that matter to Deputy Smith's second question, which was about the small schools.  It would be a way in which we could sustain the viability of small schools in rural areas, by allowing children from, for example, the reformed church tradition in the South to travel to reformed church schools in the North and vice versa.  Perhaps residents in the North, if there was a gaelscoil south of the Border, would be able to access that.  The principle is removing any barrier that exists and then enabling parents to simply make that choice themselves.</p><p>  As Deputy Ferris referred to it, I will be trying to move this at the October meeting, which will be held in Armagh, to try to advance it.  It is not threatening.  We had to assure people that it was not some kind of hidden agenda and it was only to facilitate parents.  We are doing it pragmatically in the area of health.  Altnagelvin Hospital, for example, regularly accepts patients from across the Border.  I cannot see any difficulty.  If the parents are left in charge and if they want to make the choice to send their child in any direction, then it is a matter that should be facilitated rather than prevented.</p><p>  The question of the A levels is a problem.  The Central Applications Office, CAO, system in the South, which is the college admissions office, is owned and controlled by the seven universities.  It was set up in the late 1980s or early 1990s.  They have offered participation to all of the other educational institutions, including Griffith College which is a private college, so that pupils finishing second-level school fill out their CAO form in the months of January and February.</p> <p>The CAO grades leaving certificate results alphabetically according to the grades A1, A2, etc., and it is according to these grades that points are awarded.  We have referred the matter in question to the CAO already.  It was referred by a North-South enterprise working party because complaints were made in the North about the fact that an A* is not being accorded the value it should get in the CAO form.  I will be raising this with the CAO again.  We are talking about transitions to determine whether there can be an increase in the value.  We are being told by Northern Irish students that the full value of their educational achievement is not being properly recognised by the CAO system in the South.  Hence, there is a very low take-up.  There are many more southerners going to study in the North than there are northerners coming to the South.  It is claimed this is one of the factors responsible.</p><p> Deputy Smith raised the question of a common curriculum.  There are no proposals on this at present and none has been suggested.</p><p> With regard to skills shortages and co-operation, I am publishing today my response to the Higher Education Authority's survey of third level educational institutions' reformation.  There is a reference therein to better co-operation between the North and South in the area of third level provision and access.  The next phase of the overall study will show that we need to achieve better value for money, eliminate duplication and waste within the system and have better co-operation between colleges within the South.  However, I would like to see better co-operation between colleges on an east&ndash;west basis also.  I hope that will happen.</p><p> Deputy Ferris referred to child poverty.  It hardly comes as a surprise that all the studies point to the fact that deprivation in the home contributes significantly to deprivation in educational achievement.  By the time many young people go to primary school, they carry disadvantage into the classroom.  The DEIS programme, which has been in operation for some years, is an attempt to deal with this by giving extra resources to the affected schools and by having a more favourable allocation of teachers per pupil than is the norm.  The schools are inspected in a different way from others.  They must prepare educational programmes.  In many cases, they do achieve good outcomes relative to their starting point.</p><p> At a recent ESRI conference I attended, reference was made to improving the quality of the preschool ECCE year.  I acknowledge we are discussing this in the context of the controversy over a cr&egrave;che.  I hope that, in the context of SOLAS, the body replacing F&Aacute;S in the field of further education, money can be spent on upskilling people who work in preschool year facilities to level 5 on our national framework of qualifications.  The objective is to improve the quality of preschool education.  This is not to be confused with the minding of children for parents at work.  The latter is a different phenomenon.</p><p> I believe I have answered all the questions.  If I have not answered one, I apologise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1018" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000006#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister for attending.  One reason I was looking forward to this conversation was that, in the northern context, we believed this committee could determine how it could be of benefit in the educational sphere.  The Minister has touched on many of the issues already.  When analysing some of the areas we have been to and some of the issues that underpin sectarian tensions in the North with a view to overcoming them, education arose time and again as the great liberator, the one thing that will help youths and others who have experienced conflict to bounce back, regardless of their circumstances.  How can we be of benefit to the institutions in the North?  Can we share experiences, particularly regarding educational disadvantage?  Conflict tends to happen in areas of social and economic deprivation and tends to be something that poorer people engage in.  Particularly in the North, victims have tended to be from a lower socioeconomic status.</p><p>  Will the Minister elaborate on literacy, oral language skills, numeracy and the area-based strategies that the Department of Children and Youth Affairs is trying to roll out in the South?  I wish to ask about the capacity to share experience in respect of areas of the North that are mirrored in the South, and areas where there is deeply entrenched disadvantage.  We must examine the capacity to empower parents.  The problem with schooling is that children do not live in schools.  There is a limit to what a teacher and a school can achieve in giving children basic skills to survive in life.  It is a question of empowering parents also.  The tragedy with the Irish education system, both in the North and South, is that schools are used as an enforcer of identity, not just as educational institutions.  Children are sent to a particular school because it espouses the identity with which their parents feel most comfortable.  Parents feel their child's identity can be enhanced in the school, and this is almost the priority.  We have had an interesting discussion on the motivation of Catholic and Protestant parents in respect of their children.  There is deep suspicion regarding integrated schooling.  I noted this on both sides of the divide in the North.  I found this interesting because, from the outside, integrated schooling might appear to be an obvious move to make.  In the North, it is not as popular.  What capacity have we to share experiences?  What can we learn from what is happening in the schools system and wider community in Northern Ireland?  The Minister referred to the preschool experience.  How can we learn from the Northern Ireland experience?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000006#E00300"><p>This follows on from the debate we had in the Seanad yesterday.  I really welcome the Bill that is to come before the House on admissions policy.  It will assure us of the existence of an open system for including people with special educational needs, those with different ethnic backgrounds and religions, and people who move to another area during the school year.</p><p>  With regard to the extension to the higher diploma for secondary school teachers and the four-year degree for primary school teachers, will there be more teacher training?  Will it be more practical in effect?  I hope it will be more practical rather than just a book-learning and rote-learning experience, which has been the case to date.  I hope additional time will be devoted to concentrating solely on special educational needs such that teachers can be trained to teach pupils with a variety of needs.</p><p>  Coming from Dundalk and being well aware of the problems there, I draw the Minister's attention to the article by Andy Pollak, which I was given some days ago and which is contained in the notes.  It is an excellent study on cross-Border mobility.  Again, we return to the problem of recognition of qualifications, which others have raised.</p> <p>I would ask that institutes of technology, in particular, could be included in the UCAS system and listed in its directory.  We talk about having greater communications but that would be one way of increasing awareness.  The common theme emerging is a lack of communication. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00200"><p>As the Senator said, the precedent has not been set.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/950" speakername="Jack Wall" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00300"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for his presentation.  My question is about the opportunities for people in disadvantaged areas to attend third-level education.  Is the Minister satisfied that a sufficient percentage of people from such areas can attain third-level status?</p><p>  The unemployment figures are unfortunately remaining stubbornly high here, as they are in Northern Ireland.  Is the Minister satisfied that there are sufficient opportunities for such people to return to education?  If so, what can be done to facilitate them in this regard?  There is a common denominator concerning social disadvantage and unemployment.  Following our visits to the North, we are aware that there is a major concern, especially in Protestant areas, about people being unable to obtain third-level education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00400"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for his presentation.  It is very disappointing that since the Good Friday Agreement, the national strategy for higher education - particularly under the aegis of the Higher Education Authority - has not driven collaboration between North and South.  The Minister should push the authority to drive that strategy and get the message out that we are in favour of collaboration.</p><p>  I would like to hear the Minister's opinion on pre-school education.  Would it not be a good idea to attach pre-school education to the national school structure?  I was involved in opening a pre-school in Athlone.  The school principal had a free classroom and gave it to two ex-SNA teachers who had undertaken further education.  It was a very satisfactory situation in that school building.  </p><p>  A new school that was opened a few years ago in County Monaghan has its own privately-run pre-school attached.  The Minister knows the point I am making.  Would it not be ideal if our pre-school education was in the same building and on the same format as the national school?  We would then have an equally high standard of training for pre-school education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00500"><p>I am conscious of the time and the Minister has to attend the House for a vote, so we really have to go.  May I ask the Minister and his officials to formally respond to the three contributors?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00600"><p>What about the pre-school issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00700"><p>Perhaps the Minister could respond specifically to the pre-school question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1035" speakername="Ruairi Quinn" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00800"><p>I agree with the Senator, but the legacy is of junior and senior infant classes at INTO rates of pay.  That is the cost factor, to cut to the chase.  I have just come back from a new school where there was capacity, and there is a not-for-profit pre-school in it.  It is facilitating parents and it works.</p><p>  I would like to see co-operation on the history curriculum.  We should get away from the kind of Celtic-Rangers controversy - where our victories are their defeats and <i>vice versa</i> - to a wider approach using modern media.  The junior cycle reform will give students at that level a better opportunity to explore modules, particularly from Dundalk to Letterkenny where they are living in the reality of a cross-Border zone and know about this.  It is something that I can see evolving.</p><p>  Because we are mainstreaming children with learning difficulties, teachers in training colleges will be introduced to a pedagogy of how different learners learn and particularly those with different kinds of disabilities.  In that way, they will be aware of it. </p><p>  As regards the H.Dip., I personally want to see a break in the umbilical cord system whereby a bright girl or boy goes to college and comes back to do their H.Dip. in a school and stays in that school.  They consequently have no broad experience outside that very narrow path.  It should be made a requirement before somebody can get into the system on a permanent basis, that they would have experience of teaching in two or three different types of school.  </p><p>  As regards the special access programmes, Trinity College in particular has a very good one.  Students who do post-leaving certificate courses and examinations are better equipped to get into university if they come from a disadvantaged area and have not been in that narrow academic stream in the traditional leaving certificate class.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000007#F00900"><p>The division bells have stopped, so we have to go.  I wish to thank the Minister very much.  We will seek a follow-up engagement, but we appreciate him being here this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.280" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.25 a.m. and resumed at 11.40 a.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.281" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000008#H00100">Cross-Border Student Access to Higher Education: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000008#H00200"><p>I welcome Mr. Paul Hannigan, president of the Letterkenny Institute of Technology, Mr. Dennis Cummins, president of the Dundalk Institute of Technology, and Mr. James Brennan, head of life sciences from Sligo Institute of Technology.  Professor Terri Scott, president of Sligo Institute of Technology, is unfortunately unable to join us today.</p><p>  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they are to give this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person or persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p><p>  I invite Mr. Paul Hannigan to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.283" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000008#H00300"><p>I thank the committee for its invitation to present to it today.  Professor Terri Scott could not make it today as she is, coincidentally, speaking at a career guidance conference in Derry.</p><p>  The Good Friday Agreement placed emphasis on matters such as agriculture, transport, tourism and urban and rural development as areas for North-South co-operation and implementation.  Education received only a single mention because of the profound complexity of the issues involved and the many sensitive subtexts in 1998.  Despite the immense challenges that still lie ahead on the path to reconciliation, pluralism and mutual cultural respect, there is today much greater social and political maturity.  Accordingly, the opportunity now exists to address North-South co-operation in higher education.  Much has been achieved since April 1998 upon which we can now build.</p><p>  Higher education has mutually enriching objectives.  It prepares participants for the employment marketplace, contributes to job creation and economic prosperity through research and technology and knowledge transfer and helps to contribute to social stability by imbuing participants with civic values and awareness of the responsibilities of citizenship.  Across the two jurisdictions, there are now many opportunities to give impetus to the aspirations of the Good Friday Agreement and to contribute to economic regeneration and competitiveness by greater co-operation and harmonisation of the higher education systems.  This would help to articulate strand two of the Agreement which aims &ldquo;to develop [areas of] consultation, co-operation and action within the island of Ireland&rdquo;.  Another and no less important legacy of greater occupational and student mobility would be a much higher awareness of what the Agreement refers to as shared &ldquo;cultural identity and heritage&rdquo;.</p><p>  Such mobility and harmonisation can only be achieved by taking practical steps to bring it about.  This paper sets out some of the relevant issues.  There is currently capacity in the institutes of technology sector.  There is under-capacity in Northern Ireland, as it is the only one of the 13 regions in the United Kingdom that has a cap on higher education numbers.  Each year, this forces many thousands of students from Northern Ireland to go to Great Britain with the additional costs to them and their parents, a situation exacerbated by the increase in fees.  Although some go by choice, many are forced to go because of a perceived absence of opportunities North and South.  Equally important, there is evidence that up to three quarters of such students do not return to Northern Ireland or the Republic to contribute their knowledge and skills to economic regeneration and social progress.</p><p>  The national strategy for higher education 2030, currently being implemented in Ireland, proposes to create a dynamic new globally competitive higher education system to the benefit of all participants.  There is a misperception of the institutes of technology sector in Northern Ireland due to the confusion caused by its name.  Many potential participants are unaware that each of the 13 institutes of technology offers a wide programme of internationally recognised degrees and areas of study up to doctoral level.  The Central Applications Office, CAO, entry mechanism needs reform because it disadvantages students coming from the North to the South.  Careers guidance services in the North must also have a greater awareness of opportunities in institutes of technology in helping second level students to make informed choices.</p><p>  Online learning is an integral part of the future of higher education throughout the world.  Not least of its benefits is that it allows access to higher education for many socially disadvantaged but talented students who cannot afford to study in traditional institutions.  There is an urgent need not only to promote and facilitate access to online higher education but to incentivise students to study by virtual means.  Sligo Institute of Technology has led the way in this growing means of provision and has the largest population of online students in the island.  One means of encouraging greater student mobility would be the establishment of several scholarships and bursaries in fields of study of particular importance to developing an island-wide knowledge economy.  This could begin in the Border counties where there exists an established tradition of graduates travelling from one jurisdiction to the other every day to work.</p><p>  The stated longer-term objective of higher education in both the North and the South is to create genuine and inclusive systems of lifelong learning.  IT Sligo commissioned a scoping study to look at some of the issues underlying choice of location and participation in higher education North and South.  To fully understand the opportunities for North-South co-operation and harmonisation, a much wider scoping study would need to be undertaken under the aegis of this committee to examine the factors acting upon student choice and mobility and to make appropriate recommendations.  Its terms of reference must include the impact of demographic changes in the next decade upon capacity and participation in both jurisdictions.</p><p>  The Northern Ireland Assembly&rsquo;s independent review of variable fees and student finance arrangements is also pertinent.  Both sets of findings need to be part of the wider consideration.  The establishment of a joint working group to create greater harmonisation within the two higher education systems North and South and to help break down the boundaries to island-wide higher student mobility would be a significant step forward.  By such an initiative we could ensure existing capacity North and South is optimised and increased and that reciprocity and complementarity would characterise higher education North and South.</p><p>  The most recent work on undergraduate mobility North and South was completed by Andy Pollak and D&rsquo;Arcy Smyth.  The Higher Education Statistics Agency, HESA, in the UK and the Higher Education Authority, HEA, in Ireland collate data and provide analysis.  Pollak identifies some conclusions regarding the obstacles to undergraduate mobility on a cross-Border basis.  The underlying themes emerging from this research are a lack of information and clarity regarding recognition of qualifications and entitlements to financial support.</p><p>  The D&rsquo;Arcy Smyth report concentrates more on the number of students moving between jurisdictions, with a particular focus on the financial barriers impacting upon them.  It concludes with a number of suggestions for education policy with a particular focus on the impact of fee differentials on the movement of undergraduates.  There are suggestions for pupils, parents, and guidance counsellors which are useful.  The report suggests &ldquo;a need for a new and substantial joint North-South initiative to co-operate and co-ordinate the responses of both jurisdictions to the likely changes in cross-Border third level study.&rdquo;</p><p>  Figures provided by Dr. Vivienne Patterson from the HEA identify the flow of students from North to South over the period 2007-2008 and 2011-2012.  The number of undergraduate new entrants to higher education in the Republic of Ireland from Northern Ireland has stubbornly stayed at 0.5 % or below over that period.  The actual number of entrants varied between 113 and 177 with 168 registered in 2011-2012.  However, when the statistics are further investigated from 2007-2008 to 2010-2011, an average of 86% of new entrants went to Irish universities, with institutes of technology averaging 13%.</p> <p>There is a relatively consistent number of students from Northern Ireland going to high-points courses in TCD and UCD, with 82.5% of those attending university going to these two institutions.  However, the year 2011-2012 shows some change, with this percentage dropping to 61%.  In the same year, the combined entrants to Letterkenny IT, IT Sligo and Dundalk IT totalled 21%, almost twice as many as the previous year.</p><p> The number of applications from the UK to Irish institutions decreased from 1,291 in 2012 to 1,159 in 2013, a decrease of 10.2%.  Applications from Northern Ireland applicants showed an increase from 1,139 in 2012 to 1,223, an increase of 84.  Overall, applications from the UK and Northern Ireland make up 3.3% of all applications in 2013, the same percentage as in 2012.  Therefore, given these figures, it is unlikely to show any major change in undergraduate new entrants for 2013.</p><p> While there is an expectation among staff in each of the institutes in which we work that cross-Border mobility of undergraduates should be intuitive, it is obvious from the figures that this is not the case.  Despite various initiatives by single institutions, the level of North-South mobility remains lower than one would expect between neighbouring jurisdictions.  There is a necessity in Border areas to consider an institute's broader hinterland in the context of regional development and this requires strong political support.  I will ask Mr. Cummins to take us through the recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.285" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Cummins" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000009#J00200"><p>The institutes of technology at Dundalk, Letterkenny and Sligo are closest to the Border and have the greatest interest in improving student mobility, particularly from North to South.  The three institutions are working in a co-ordinated way, have a number of recommendations to make and seek the support of this committee.  I will quickly run through them.</p><p>  The three presidents of Dundalk IT, Letterkenny IT and IT Sligo recommend that the committee support the establishment of a North-South higher education joint working group.  The purpose of the group will be to promote student mobility between the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland.  In particular, the group will promote the following: providing improved co-ordination in respect of admission and progression opportunities for students on an all-island basis; increased student recruitment on a cross-Border basis; the establishment of a programme to facilitate cross-Border staff mobility programmes between higher education institutions; the monitoring of cross-Border student mobility programmes; ensuring the CAO system provides equitable treatment to students from Northern Ireland; facilitating better co-operation between careers services in the higher education institutions, particularly to promote job opportunities for graduates on a cross-Border basis; an annual conference targeted at second level guidance services on a cross-Border basis to promote greater awareness of the portfolio of courses available at higher education institutions on either side of the Border; and the establishment of a scholarship fund targeted at promoting cross-Border student mobility for students from low-income backgrounds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000009#J00300"><p>I thank Mr. Cummins.  Does Mr. Brennan wish to speak or will I open it up to the members?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.287" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. James Brennan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000009#J00400"><p>Basically, this is a joint proposal from the three institutions.  The two presidents have outlined what is in the document.  I do not have anything extra to add to it until questions are put.  I will not delay proceedings other than to say that Professor Terry Scott is 100% behind this proposal, as is the institution as a whole.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000009#J00500"><p>I will take questions and observations from members and the witnesses can decide who will respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/970" speakername="Brendan Smith" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000009#J00600"><p>Like the Chairman, I welcome our visitors and very much welcome their presentation, which was good and concise and shows the potential for co-operation on an all-island basis.  I welcome the recommendation for a North-South higher education joint working group.  It is a proposal that we should be willing to vigorously support and pursue with the Higher Education Authority and the Minister for Education and Skills.  I will add one particular bullet point for consideration - a proposal that we optimise existing capacity, to which Mr. Hannigan referred earlier in the presentation, and minimise course provision in the case of courses in niche areas with small numbers of students.  There is no point in having a particular course in both the North and the South when it does not have a critical mass of students pursuing it.  Given the challenging financial circumstances facing administrations North and South, we must optimise existing capacity.</p><p>  One of my bugbears is the fact that we have good infrastructure, such as the different facilities in institutes of higher education and universities, lying idle for substantial parts of the year.  We should be trying to derive benefit from this area on an year-round basis rather than on the basis of the academic year. </p><p>  I warmly welcome the fact that the three institutes of technology in the Border area are working together.  The witnesses mentioned that the Good Friday agreement had only a passing reference to education.  Teagasc, which is an educational research institute authority here, has a close working relationship with its counterpart north of the Border, as have the two Departments.  There is a lot of co-operation that is not specified or prescribed in formal agreements, but the Good Friday agreement was the backdrop to much of the increased co-operation between those institutions.  Obviously, it is an area that needs to built upon.  Representing two of the southern Border counties, we must be more outgoing and stronger advocates for Border regional development.  If we do not utilise and maximise the potential of our third-level sector, we will not maximise the potential of our economies, North or South.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1085" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000009#J00800"><p>I welcome the delegation and very much value its presentation, which was concise and informative.  The aspirations of the Good Friday agreement with regard to education have not been followed through.  I wonder what we were doing for the past ten or 15 years, because it reflected the economy of our island.  We have capacity down here and there is a cap on education in Northern Ireland.  We were just lazy.  The colleges needed to look at a market that effectively was not there, and it has not been successful.  However, we need to move on from there.</p><p>  A total of 82.5% of Northern Ireland students attending colleges in the Republic of Ireland went to Trinity College Dublin and UCD.  I do not think anybody needs to pat themselves on the back over this figure.  If I was a student in Northern Ireland, Trinity College would be the Ivy League college to aim towards, so those figures are very much manipulated.  I would like to know how many of those students attended Trinity College.  I suspect the figure is much higher than that for UCD, although I may be wrong.  </p><p>  We are where we are and I very much welcome this report.  I very much welcome the idea of a higher education joint working group.  This committee must work very closely with the three institutes of technology to promote that working group.  How will the scholarship fund operate?  Who does the delegation hope to target and what areas does it hope to target?  It is very sad that only half of the people from the Unionist tradition in Northern Ireland go on to higher education.  This anomaly is very worrying and people should not be clapping themselves on the back for it.  We should not forget about the Nationalist community but this is one area that could be targeted and focused upon.</p> <p>It could help that community integrate or see what is on this side of the Border.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.292" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Pat Doherty" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000010#K00200"><p>I thank representatives of the three colleges for their presentations.  I have some broad questions, the first of which is very simple.  I support their recommendations but I also suggest that they approach the Committee for Education in the Assembly and the Oireachtas Committee on Education and Social Protection.  I have been a Member of the Legislative Assembly for 14 years and I am well aware of the potential for joint North-South committee meetings on issues of relevance.  If the witnesses were to make presentations to both committees and encouraged them to enter into a joint undertaking they might advance their proposal.</p><p>  They spoke about the misperception about the status of institutes of technology.  That offers a challenge to us as politicians to change these perceptions but the institutes also have a role in addressing the issue by giving politicians the tools to act on their behalf.  I am familiar with Letterkenny Institute of Technology through family members who studied there and other interactions with the college.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.293" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Cummins" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000010#K00300"><p>I will address the questions on scholarships and misperceptions and Mr. Hannigan can address the other questions.  In one sense, a scheme is already in place, namely, the Erasmus programme for student mobility across Europe.  My own institution hosts up to 200 students at any one time from partner universities in France, Germany, Finland and Spain.  I am not aware of a single exchange with Northern Ireland, however.  It may be a case of making better use of the Erasmus programme rather than funding a new scholarship.  I would prefer to target scholarships at low income students and, in the case of Dundalk, I would love to see students coming from the Protestant community in Northern Ireland.  At present we have approximately 50 students out of 5,000, which is a small drop in the ocean.  As far as I know all of them are from Nationalist backgrounds.  This year for the first time in our history a Protestant school visited during our annual open day.  The point was made that Protestants avail of higher education to a much lesser extent than the Nationalist community.  I would like to increase their participation as a way of building mutual understanding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.294" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000010#K00400"><p>There is a degree of overlap with the questions raised and I will attempt to deal with them on that basis.  I am originally from Ballyshannon in County Donegal, which is a Border town.  For ten years I worked with Mr. Cummins in Dundalk Institute of Technology before returning to Letterkenny Institute of Technology, where I have been for the last 15 years.  I have spent my entire life around the Border and I am well aware of the issues that have to be considered.</p><p>  In the context of the overall situation, cross-Border collaboration has undoubtedly gone down the political agenda.  Deputy Smith made reference to the attitudes of people who do not live in Border areas and noted that they do not regard cross-Border educational initiatives as being relevant to them.  We have to fight that battle initially within our own constituencies to persuade people that such initiatives are vital for Border colleges.  We work alongside people from both sides of the Border but few students from Northern Ireland study in our institutions.</p><p>  Deputy Feighan suggested that we were lazy in the context of implementing the agreement and that we should be doing more to develop relationships with Northern Ireland.  However, each of the three institutions have invested considerable amounts of money, effort and time on changing perceptions in Northern Ireland.  It is difficult to identify the obstacles to mobility on both sides of the Border.  The central issue is, as Andy Pollack has noted, the complete confusion that exists about what is on offer in our respective institutes.  We put obstacles in front of people without meaning to do so.  This issue arose in the earlier discussion about entry levels and confusion about A levels.  We recently dealt with the question of how we should set entry level requirements for students with applied A levels.  There is a problem of misinformation but the wider context is that people regard it as solely a matter for Border counties.  I am glad to hear the commitments expressed by members regarding political support for our recommendations.  The proposal to make a presentation to both education committees offers one way of progressing the matter.</p><p>  To put the issues facing Letterkenny Institute of Technology in a context with which Deputy Ferris will be familiar, they are the equivalent of the Institute of Technology Tralee not taking students from any other part of Munster.  A large hinterland would be removed in terms of student participation, with knock-on effects on how the institute operates and serves the region.  We should not lose sight of the spatial strategy in this debate.  Letterkenny is a joint gateway with Derry city.  We need to continue reminding people of the importance of cross-Border co-operation and its impact on the day-to-day operation of the institutions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.295" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Cummins" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000010#K00500"><p>The single biggest obstacle we face is misperception.  Focus groups we have worked with in Northern Ireland simply did not realise the opportunities available in our institutes of technology.  We are confused with further education in Northern Ireland and students are often unaware that we offer degree and post-graduate courses.  Clearly our institutions can do more to address that misperception but political support would help in this regard.</p><p>  The second biggest obstacle is the way in which the CAO system unfairly disadvantages students from Northern Ireland.  The best performing student from Northern Ireland would be capped at 450 points, whereas the best performing student in the Republic of Ireland is capped at 600 points.  We have examples of students who are refused admission to DKIT but get places in Queens University Belfast.  Something is not right in the way the system is working.  Our three institutions are committed to developing direct entry procedures on the basis of a fair apportionment of points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.296" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. James Brennan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000010#K00600"><p>One could argue that we were lazy but we are now moving much further and faster to address the matter.  Significant effort has been invested in developing links with Northern Ireland but the biggest problem is misperception.  When I was recently in King's Hall representing IT Sligo, a group of students came around the corner and, on seeing our sign, said they were not planning to study IT.  I had to explain that we teach all sorts of subjects, including business, science and engineering.  In regard to being mixed up with further education in Northern Ireland, we have sought to link with further education colleges.  We are in a process of mapping how people can come from further education to advanced entry level in courses in science, engineering and business.  The CAO system and the misconception of what we do are major difficulties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1068" speakername="Peter Fitzpatrick" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000011#L00100"><p>I welcome the witnesses.  I am amazed, if not shocked, at the number of people from Northern Ireland who do not avail of the opportunity to attend institutes of technology along the Border.  If the witnesses need any help, there will be no problem whatsoever.  I come from Dundalk and I know Mr. Cummins pretty well.  The Dundalk Institute of Technology, DKIT, is looking to give university level higher education to graduates, and that would be a major plus if it can go ahead with that.  The education opportunities in DKIT are very high.  The entrepreneurship is excellent.  DKIT is doing a lot of cross-Border developments.  Within a 90 minute drive of DKIT is a population catchment of more than 3 million people.  I see no reason we cannot push hard and try to get as many people from Belfast and Derry as possible.</p><p>  Regarding value for money, the cost of going to DKIT or other institutes of technology in the Republic compared with the universities in the North is vastly different.  On the range of courses in the Republic compared with the North, I was talking to Mr. Cummins recently about potential new courses coming up in DKIT.  He mentioned the school of business and humanities and the school of engineering, and these are all bachelor of arts, BA, courses.  He mentioned the school of informatics and creative art and the school of health and science.  He has a fantastic agriculture programme in DKIT and it is growing significantly.  Agriculture is keeping the country going with its exports.</p><p>  The witnesses mentioned equal status.  Could they elaborate on what they mean by that?  They also mentioned the opportunity for cross-Border jobs.  Mr. Cummins already spoke about the scholarship fund.  He mentioned improving admission.  We will do anything we can to help because the education is fantastic.  DKIT has more than 5,000 students and 80% are from the Louth, Monaghan and Cavan area.  Mr. Cummins is trying to advance the colleges all the time.  We have a goldmine here in our area around the Border and it is very important we get out that message not only to Northern Ireland but also to the UK.  More than 400 Chinese students attend DKIT.</p><p>  One of the main reasons companies such as eBay and PayPal come to the area is because of the education we have there.  The infrastructure will be a big help.  Ms Louise Phelan of PayPal has been picking Mr. Cummins's brain and requesting language courses, and I am sure he is bending over backwards to facilitate her.  I have nothing but praise for the work the witnesses are doing and I would love to see the institutes of technology go from strength to strength.  Another major plus is the number of people they employ locally.  I am very enthusiastic about the whole thing and if the committee can give any help, we will be more than happy to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000011#L00200"><p>I welcome the witnesses from Letterkenny, Sligo and Dundalk.  The contribution of the institutes of technology to education is phenomenal.  I sat on the board of DKIT for nine years.  Unfortunately, I had to leave it when I was appointed to the Seanad, but I am aware of the great work that is being done in DKIT.  Are all the witnesses happy with today's report on the future of third level education?  How will it impact on their institutes?  How will it help in the efforts to get students from the North into our institutes of technology?  That is the most pressing issue I have to ask about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000011#L00300"><p>I, too, commend the witnesses on their work.  I apologise for not being here for their briefing but I have a fair idea of what they are proposing and I wholeheartedly pledge my support for it.  Coming from Dundalk, DKIT is the one with which I am most familiar.  I see it growing from strength to strength.  In my area of music I studied my masters course in DKIT, which I would not have been able to take anywhere else were it not for the courses and how it was laid out for people on a part-time basis.</p><p>  The establishment of this North-South higher education forum would be a wonderful initiative to encourage movement.  We have all seen the facts and figures and the lack of students coming North to South.  Earlier this morning I raised better communication and awareness for the Universities and Colleges Admissions Service, UCAS, and the Central Applications Office, CAO, to get on.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn explained what is happening in the CAO system but it gives us scope to work on that and impress on him the importance of ensuring there is better scope and that people have more mobility, North and South.</p><p>  We also spoke about people from low socioeconomic  and low income backgrounds.  The idea of a scholarship fund is great and should be encouraged.  It would be a pledge to show the institutes of technology are progressive in their thinking and are catering for people from lower socioeconomic backgrounds.  The issue of the A levels and the fact that when one transfers them one has only 450 points in the Irish system is ridiculous.  That is the huge barrier we must overcome first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000011#L00400"><p>I raised the matter of the lack of activity and neglect by the Higher Education Authority, HEA, on North-South co-operation with the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn.  He listened.  It is disgraceful.  Many years ago, Charles Haughey appointed me to the HEA so I have an interest and I know what happens there.  It is quite a closed organisation in its own way.  It is a pity the North-South co-operation has lapsed and the HEA does not have it as part of its strategy.</p><p>  The establishment of the joint working group to create greater harmonisation within the two higher education systems, North and South, will help break down the barriers to higher island-wide student mobility and would be a significant step forward.  Business people, such as the management of PayPal in Dundalk, do not see the Border.  If people have experience and qualifications, it does not matter where they come from.  The quicker we get this back on track, the better.</p><p>  I congratulate the two colleges and the Institute of Technology Sligo on the fantastic work they do.  It is a brilliant contribution.  The committee will support them in any way we can.  Formally, under the Good Friday agreement, I raised with the Minister the lack of drive by the HEA in its action plan.  The HEA action plan does not mention co-operation at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000011#L00500"><p>I acknowledge DKIT's contribution, particularly in the past ten years.</p> <p>I congratulate Mr. Cummins on the part he has played in expanding the educational facilities at the college.  I have a personal connection to Letterkenny but I have no connection to Sligo.  Perhaps I will after this meeting.</p><p> What can be done to increase the number of students from Northern Ireland attending DKIT?  Is Mr. Cummins happy with the current enrolment?  There is a large population in the Border region.  Are sufficient numbers attending the institute?  Could the institute capitalise on that?</p><p> I congratulate all the institutes of technology.  Ten years ago, I envisioned Dundalk becoming a university town.  That has not happened but we are well on the way.  The facilities at DKIT are to be commended and Mr. Cummins is to be congratulated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.303" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Cummins" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000012#M00200"><p>I thank everyone for their positive comments about our institutions, which is encouraging.  I will deal with the questions raised by Deputy Fitzpatrick and Senator Brennan, and my colleagues will deal with the others.</p><p>  The future strategy of DKIT is built around a collaboration and alliance with Dublin City University.  We have mentioned the greatest challenge we face in recruiting students from Northern Ireland is the misplaced perception.  The existence of an alliance with DCU will help to deal with that.  The progression path that will be followed by other institutes of technology is towards technological universities.  Mr. Hannigan will comment on that shortly in response to Senator D'Arcy's question about the early publication of the future strategy.</p><p>  Deputy Fitzpatrick mentioned PayPal in Dundalk.  We are working closely with the company to help recruit employees.  Only yesterday we had a meeting involving our careers services, language department and work placement office.  There is great potential both with PayPal and eBay.</p><p>  Deputy Smith mentioned agriculture, and he will be aware of a successful collaboration between DKIT and Ballyhaise College in County Cavan, which we are keen to grow.  There is huge demand for agriculture programmes and we are not able to meet the demand.  One of the difficulties in our system is what while there areas in which we have spare capacity, there are other areas where we cannot cope with demand and it is not easy to move resources between departments.  We provide an honours degree course in sustainable agriculture, which we run successfully with Ballyhaise College.  We have an ambition to introduce an agrifood degree, and there is big demand in our region for that, but we are challenged in doing that because of staffing restrictions.</p><p>  Senator Brennan asked whether we are happy with the number of students recruited from Northern Ireland.  All three institutions would say we are not at all happy about that.  My institute's new strategic plan sets targets to increase recruitment from Northern Ireland.  We referred earlier to the problems and barriers, but it is up to us to break them down.  Some are cultural and political and they are difficult, but others are related to simple logistics such as how students make applications and providing better information.  We have made a proposal for a scholarship targeted at students from Northern Ireland specifically to come south.  Our three institutions have a bigger interest.</p><p>  I refer to Senator White's criticism of the Higher Education Authority.  The authority looks at the overall system for the entire country.  Our institutions, given their location, are particularly interested in Northern Ireland.  I suspect this will not be an issue in Tralee or Cork but better mobility will be key to our future development.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.304" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000012#M00300"><p>I will respond to Senator D'Arcy's question about whether we are happy with the landscape document published by the Minister.  Mr. Cummins and I are at a disadvantage in that the report issued as we were heading here and, therefore, we have not yet had an opportunity to read it.  However, I would like to correct the front page article in <i>The Irish Times</i> this morning, which said three technological universities were approved by Cabinet yesterday and an application from GMIT, Sligo IT and Letterkenny IT was refused.  That is news to me because we did not make an application to be turned down.  That is a major inaccuracy.</p><p>  I will refer to the broader report shortly but there was a major missed opportunity.  Two higher education strategies were developed over the past two years.  The national higher education strategy in the Republic of Ireland was published in January 2011 and, in the middle of last year, the Northern Ireland higher education strategy was published.  Having spoken to those developing the strategy on both sides of the Border, I thought there was a great opportunity at that stage to have a common chapter within both strategies to address cross-Border issues, including student mobility and so on.  That did not happen.  Paragraph 5.7 on page 23 of the Northern Ireland strategy refers to &quot;cross-Border co-operation and student mobility&quot;.  That is the extent of the commitment to cross-Border activity in the strategy.  Our national higher education strategy contained commitments about collaboration between institutes of technology and universities in Northern Ireland.  We were particularly interested in that because, at the time, we were pursuing a close collaboration with the University of Ulster.  Those opportunities remain.  There is a possibility that both strategies could be revisited and there could be an overlap.  A common element could be developed within them because it is crazy that they are both developing with no overlap at all.  Given both were developed at the same time, this does not make sense.  That is where there should have been an engagement by the HEA to ensure that occurred.  From the point of view of colleges in the Border region, we would have been dealing with an entirely different context because we would have had something specifically to work with.</p><p>  We are engaged in rearguard action now where we are trying to redress the strategies that have been published and to examine the issues causing difficulty for student mobility and other elements of collaboration, to retrofit them in the strategies.  That was a missed opportunity to commit to cross-Border collaboration generally and specifically in higher education.  However, it is something the joint working group we propose could revisit and in which it could engage in a more proactive way.  It seemed like the simplest thing in the world from my perspective, but obviously our comments at the time fell on deaf ears.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000012#M00400"><p>Perhaps we could invite Mr. Hannigan back to discuss this issue again.  However,  I asked whether the institutes were happy with today's report and the proposals for clusters.  Will DKIT be given the space and scope to move forward with its link to DCU, in particular?  I thought the report was like a curate's egg.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1085" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000012#M00500"><p>I am shocked by the report from a Northern Ireland perspective with only one paragraph referring to it.  We have had 15 years of cross-Border operation and implementation of the Good Friday Agreement.  The document has denied the inclusion of cross-Border support.  I will not get into where that came from and why, but there were no checks or balances.</p> <p>We talk about the implementation of all the strands of the Good Friday Agreement.  The members of this committee are very involved but I am not sure if it goes through the Assembly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.308" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N00600"><p>I was glad to hear the Minister say earlier this morning that there is some element of cross-Border collaboration mentioned in the document to which Senator Jim D'Arcy referred.  Earlier drafts of that documents did not include a reference to cross-Border collaboration.  This is on both sides of the Border, not just on one side.</p><p>  What I have been saying for a long time, and I have been shot down a number of times, is that because of the economic circumstances on both sides of the Border, from the political perspective this has become of less interest to people.  It is also of little interest to anybody at present.  While our institutions see it as vitally important to the hinterland we serve, we have to get the issue back on the political agenda and ensure that it is an issue worthy of consideration, which it did not get in the past.  When we see a draft document with no element of cross-Border collaboration and highlight the fact, there is no point when it comes back with a paragraph in it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N00700"><p>Was Mr. Hannigan consulted before this document was issued this morning?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.310" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N00800"><p>Yes, there was definitely consultation.  To set out the chronology, last year in 2012, the Minister met with the chairs and the presidents from each of the colleges, institutes of technology and universities.  In that discussion in February 2012, there was an element of North-South collaboration.  He subsequently met us again in November 2012 and there was no mention of cross-Border collaboration.  A document was issued in January 2013, on which we were consulted and again there was only a slight mention, just one sentence on cross-Border co-operation.  From our perspectives we went back with a very strong position on clusters - to which Senator D'Arcy referred - and raised the question of whether we would have a cross-Border regional cluster.  We put it that we should engage from that perspective so that there is direct engagement with higher education institutions in the North.  We try to deal with issues from that perspective.  I am not sure what is in today's document, but I know the Minister said earlier that there was some element of cross-Border collaboration within the document he is publishing today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N00900"><p>Mr. James Brennan has something to add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.312" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. James Brennan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01000"><p>Just in case there may be a perception that IT Sligo is disrespecting the question and not responding to it, I am not a member of the senior executive group, so in spite of the fact the Chairman said I was representing the views of the president, I would hesitate to represent the views of the president on that particular question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01100"><p>I thank the delegates for their contribution.  They have made a suggestion to the committee.  Before we consider the ways we would follow up on it, may I ask the witnesses if they are getting a reciprocal buy-in from their colleagues north of the Border?  Do the representatives from colleges in the North think in the same way as they do?  If they do, should they not be part of the proposal for a North-South higher education working group?  Is there work going on behind the scenes?  I am trying to tease this out as to how we as a committee can develop this proposal with a buy-in from universities north of the Border.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.314" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Cummins" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01200"><p>We have very good working relationships with the University of Ulster and Queens University, particular in the area of enterprise support programmes and INTERREG programmes.  On the issue of student mobility there is less interest in that from our counterparts in Norther Ireland.  Obviously there is an element of competition for students which comes into it as well, so that one can understand that.  We have good collaboration with them at other levels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.315" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01300"><p>There is a lot of collaboration and work and we are pushing on with the University of Ulster specifically in terms of trying to develop a cross-Border higher education region in the north west.  Probably most of the impetus to develop that is coming from ourselves.  I think the University of Ulster is very interested in developing it but once the economic circumstances changed on both sides of the Border, everybody went into retrenchment mode and that had a direct impact in terms of how we try to develop this.  I think there would be an interest in looking at this issue because the demographics in Northern Ireland, as outlined in their strategy, is that there will be a decline in the number of school leavers for the next ten to 15 years in Northern Ireland.  In the South it is the complete opposite.  As a result there must be some synergy in terms of how we follow that through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01400"><p>Is the difference in the level of fees North and South a major problem?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.317" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01500"><p>In 2006, which does not seem that long ago, when they introduced the fee of &pound;3,000 in Northern Ireland, the Institute of Technology in Letterkenny set up a stall in the shopping centre in Derry city which said "3,000 good reasons to come to Letterkenny IT".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01600"><p>That is very good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.319" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01700"><p>I am not sure if it had a major impact at the time but there is no doubt that the fee at that stage was having an impact on preventing people going from South to North.  The fee structure generally has evened out a little because the student contribution in the Republic of Ireland will be &euro;2,500 next year and the fee in Northern Ireland is &pound;3,500.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.320" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01800"><p>I think is &pound;3,300 sterling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.321" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Cummins" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N01900"><p>I think it is set to go to &pound;9,000 in Northern Ireland and one would expect that would make a big difference.  Just like the IT Letterkenny, Dundalk IT had a stall at the Buttercrane shopping centre in Newry but it did not result in a significant flow of students in our direction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.322" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. James Brennan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02000"><p>The Institute of Technology Sligo went to King's Hall in Belfast with the same sort of message.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.323" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02100"><p>I know that plenty of school pupils in County Donegal fill out UCAS forms.  I remember filling out an UCAS form for Jordanstown and perhaps Mr. Pat Doherty will comment on this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.324" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Pat Doherty" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02200"><p>When discussing collaboration North and South, one of the problems in the Northern side is that education is divided into two different departments, Mr. John O'Dowd is the Minister with responsibility for first and second level education.  An Alliance Party Minister has responsibility for third level and that will be resolved because the Department will be split between the Departments of Enterprise and Education but at present it is a separate Department.  There is an added problem of linkages and that report from the Department should not have got passed in the way it did get passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.325" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02300"><p>May I suggest, subject to the agreement of members, that the committee formally brings this proposal to the attention of the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, who was present this morning so he will be interested in the follow up meeting that the delegates are attending?</p><p>  We can ask the Minister to contact both Mr. Stephen Farry and Mr. John O'Dowd in relation to the delegates' proposals.  Let us start the conversation because if one looks at what is happening on a cross-Border basis in regard to health, between Altnagelvin and Letterkenny hospitals and also the Belfast and Dublin hospitals in relation to paediatric and cardiology services, there is an awful lot of pragmatic practical engagement going on at a health level and there is no reason it cannot happen at an education level.  Subject to the agreement of committee members we will write to the Minister for Education and Skills, bringing this issue to his attention and he can communicate directly with both Ministers in Northern Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.326" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02400"><p>Other counties might benefit if they had sent their budding managers to the IT in Tralee just as Donegal has benefited from Mr. Jim McGuinness.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.327" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02500"><p>Tralee is a kind of a border - - - -</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.328" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02600"><p>Should we set a target for delivery on what the committee is trying to achieve and track it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.329" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02700"><p>We are starting the conversation.  I think Mr. Paul Hannigan rightly pointed out there is a HEA and other reports with references to cross-Border provisions.  It is up to us to work on the issues.  This is not set in stone and we can drive it and work on this together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.330" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/970" speakername="Brendan Smith" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02800"><p>What might be relevant is the future projected enrolment at third level North and South.  There has been a significant increase in the level of participation in the South in the past 12 to 15 years.  I do not know, but presume there has been a similar increase in the number north of the Border.  With increasing levels of participation we need to maximise existing infrastructure and co-operation.</p><p>  If we had the projected enrolment figures for third level, it might bolster the case for increased collaboration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.331" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N02900"><p>I have a document that I can leave with the committee from the Department of Education and Skills showing the projected number for the next number of years in the higher education sector in the Republic of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.332" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/970" speakername="Brendan Smith" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N03000"><p>I presume the number is increasing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.333" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Hannigan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N03100"><p>Yes, absolutely.  It is going through the roof.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.334" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N03200"><p>We will circulate that to members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.335" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1085" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000013#N03300"><p>This has been one of the most proactive and aggressive meetings that we have had here.  It will have a practical impact on the ground.</p> <p>I agree with Senator White's proposal to the effect that we should invite our guests to return in six months' time in order that we might discover exactly what progress has been made.  It is very important that the committee should be seen to be driving this matter forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.337" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000014#O00200"><p>I second that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.338" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/GFJ2013053000014#O00300"><p>I thank our guests for attending.  The joint committee will now go into private session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-30a.339" nospeaker="true" time="12:20:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 12.40 p.m. and adjourned at 1.10 p.m. until 12 noon on Thursday, 13 June 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>