<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:35:00" url="">Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:35:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 13:35</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Richard Bruton (Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation), Deputy Seán Kyne, Deputy Dara Calleary, Deputy John Lyons, Deputy Michael Conaghan, Deputy Gerald Nash (Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation). Deputy Damien English (Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation),</p><p>DEPUTY MARCELLA CORCORAN KENNEDY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.4" nospeaker="true" time="13:35:00" ><p>The select committee met in private session until 1.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.6" nospeaker="true" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700003#C00200">Estimates for Public Services 2015<br />Vote 32 - Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation (Revised)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700003#C00300"><p>We are meeting today to consider the Revised Estimate for Vote 32 - Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation for the year ending 31 December 2015, which was referred to the committee by an order of the D&aacute;il on 18 December 2014.  When the committee has considered the Revised Estimate this fact will be reported to the D&aacute;il.</p>  <p>  I welcome the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, the Ministers of State, Deputies Gerald Nash and Damien English, and their officials.  I thank them for the briefing documents they have supplied to the committee.</p>  <p>  As members have seen, the 2015 Revised Estimate was presented to the D&aacute;il in programme-based format.  This means the Revised Estimate as presented contains the following information for each programme: how the money allocated to the programme is proposed to be spent and the previous year's outturn in each case; the number of staff assigned to work connected with the programme and how this compares with the previous year; performance-related information and departmental outputs with corresponding information for the previous year; and performance and impact indicators with the previous year's information also.</p> <p>Administrative expenditure for the Vote as a whole is summarised in more detail than previously.</p> <p> The Revised Estimate gives us an opportunity to review whether the targets set and the distribution of moneys across the Vote are appropriate in all circumstances and demonstrate the best use of resources.  It also gives us an opportunity to explore issues facing the Minister in terms of the 2015 allocation to his Department.</p> <p> A timetable for today's meeting has been circulated and agreed.  It allows for a brief opening statement by the Minister, followed by a discussion on the 2015 Revised Estimate and questions on each programme listed therein.  I invite the Minister to begin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700004#D00200"><p>I thank the committee for facilitating us.  It is an honour to attend.</p>  <p>  As members will see, we are seeking a &euro;790 million allocation for 2015.  We can stand over the value that we are yielding from the budgets the committee is giving us.  The amount is broken down into capital expenditure of &euro;489 million and current expenditure of &euro;301 million.  Our capital expenditure shows a modest improvement and we continue to make savings on the current side.  The one factor that members must watch out for is the 27th pay day in 2015, which may result in a change.  There is also a technical adjustment, in that &euro;39 million is being switched from the current side of the capital side.  Members should bear these factors in mind when assessing the Estimate.</p>  <p>  This is a year in which we can expect solid progress across all of the areas in which we operate.  IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland had a record year.  Significantly, Enterprise Ireland's net employment creation exceeded that of IDA Ireland for the first time in a number of years.  This shows the powerful recovery that is occurring in many Irish-owned, export-oriented enterprises.  I do not know whether the figures are presented in this document, but members will also see that there has been a diversification in Enterprise Ireland companies' export destinations.  Many committee members have been keen to see this, with emerging markets becoming a more significant player.  What economists call Irish companies' export propensity - in other words, the percentage of their output that they export - is steadily increasing.  The committee is seeing a strong fight back by Irish companies finding new markets and using exports as a key driver of recovery.  We are improving in competitiveness rankings.  As the Minister of State, Deputy English, will undoubtedly point out, our ranking in terms of the impact of our innovation spend is also improving.  We are showing good, solid progress.</p>  <p>  We are also continuing to undertake structural reforms within the Department.  This plays an important part in ensuring that we yield-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.10" nospeaker="true" time="13:40:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700004#D00400"><p>That was not my telephone.  The reforms play an important part in ensuring that we yield value for money.  They are reflected in the Estimate.  In April, we dissolved the county enterprise boards, CEBs, and established local enterprise offices, LEOs.  Since then and under the new service-level agreement with Enterprise Ireland, there has been a new dynamic in those offices.  As the CEOs of local authorities, county and city managers are significant new drivers of enterprise.  This alliance is working well and the LEOs are showing a good impact.  They have rolled out new projects successfully, for example, for young entrepreneurs.  They are also showing an impact on micro-finance, where the take-up level has nearly doubled.  They have been key agents.</p>  <p>  We have dissolved Forf&aacute;s.  Deputy Calleary is concerned that, since its functions were brought into the Department, we have blunted Forf&aacute;s, but that is not the case.  It has been key to driving the Action Plan for Jobs and, through the National Competitiveness Council, continues to have an edge in its work.  Shannon Development was formally dissolved.  We merged the Competition Authority and the National Consumer Agency.  The new commission is settling down well.  We passed the Companies Act 2014, which is major legislation.  I thank the Oireachtas for facilitating it.  It was years in process.</p>  <p>  The workplace relations commission, WRC, Bill is nearing the end of its legislative process.</p> <p>It is another major reform undertaken within the Department that is delivering better impacts and quicker hearing of cases.  Members will be aware of the proposal to establish a low pay commission, which initiative will be undertaken by the new Minister of State, Deputy Nash.  Work on this initiative is advancing and the Minister of State, Deputy Nash, will shortly announce the membership of the new board of the commission.  He is also progressing the construction contracts legislation, which members will be aware had been held up.  </p> <p> Looking to the future, we are seeking to identify the areas we need to continue to improve.  There is no doubt that the two main areas in this regard are entrepreneurship, where we can significantly improve our performance, and regional development.  Although every region has experienced overall employment growth, including through Enterprise Ireland and IDA, as measured by the QNHS there is no doubt that we can improve our capacity to exploit the potential of our regions.  This is something I am very keen to do.  We are starting a process this year which I hope will drive that forward in a way that has not been done before.  We are looking forward to a high quality of application for some of the competitive funds we are setting.  Our hope is that not only will this result in a more concerted action by the existing agencies in the regions, with a much more strategic look by those agencies at the regions, but that the process will act as a catalyst for the many other players in the regions in terms of their impact on enterprise growth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700005#E00200"><p>We will now consider the Revised Estimate and, in particular, performance and expenditure proposals for 2015, programme by programme commencing with programme A - jobs and enterprise development.  I ask members to identify the subhead of the programme to which they are referring when asking a question.  We will start with the general position in relation to savings measures that are to be introduced in 2015 and then move on to consider performance and expenditure proposals for 2015.  Programme A deals with jobs, enterprise and development.  Subhead A3 deals with agency legacy payments; A4 with InterTradeIreland; A5 with IDA Ireland; A6 with export credit insurance; A7 with Enterprise Ireland; A8 with local enterprise development; A9 with monitoring of EU programmes; A10 with INTERREG; A11 with NSAI; A12 with the temporary loan guarantee scheme; A13 with subs to international organisations; A14 with commissions, committees and inquiries; and A15 with other services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700005#E00300"><p>On subheads A1, A5, A7 and A8 and the relevant subhead dealing with the credit guarantee scheme-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700005#E00400"><p>We will deal with subhead A1 later.  The Deputy should commence with questions on subhead A3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700005#E00500"><p>I welcome the Minister, the Ministers of State, Deputies English and Nash, and their officials.  I also thank the committee secretariat for the brief provided to members.</p>  <p>  On subhead A5, I take this opportunity to congratulate IDA Ireland and all involved on the successful year they have had.  However, is it a matter of concern to the Minister that while 15,012 jobs were created in 2014, 7,881 jobs were lost in IDA client companies, which equates to 52% of the number of jobs created?  It is a similar story in terms of Enterprise Ireland.  Is any work being done within the Department on identifying the reason for this high proportion of job losses?  Given the level of investment and fantastic effort that went into securing those 15,000 jobs, what work is being done to identify where those jobs are being lost?</p>  <p>  The Minister announced last week that under the IDA building programme for 2015 onwards, it is proposed to construct more advance units.  Perhaps he would update the committee on the three units announced.  I understand the units at Waterford and Letterkenny are almost complete.  What is the position in regard to the Athlone unit?  The Minister might also expand on his commitment in the D&aacute;il last Thursday regarding additional IDA capital expenditure on existing IDA parks.  </p>  <p>  On subhead A7, I congratulate Enterprise Ireland on its success.  However, as in the case of IDA Ireland while it was responsible for the creation of 19,705 jobs, 11,229 EI client jobs were lost, giving a net of 8,476 jobs created, which equates to a 56% of a loss.  Again, this is a matter of concern.</p> <p>With regard to subhead A8, I congratulate the local employment offices, LEOs, which are definitely up and running.  One gets the sense that they have hit the ground running.  As the Minister acknowledged, there is no doubt that they have made an impact on Microfinance Ireland.  I have not seen a figure relating to the number of jobs they, or the old county enterprise boards, CEBs, created in 2014 and how many were lost in CEB enterprise client companies.  If the Minister has that, perhaps he would provide it.</p> <p> I cannot find the subhead for the credit guarantee scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700006#F00200"><p>It is A12.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700006#F00300"><p>A sum of &euro;15 million out of &euro;150 million has been approved.  We had a discussion about this last Thursday during Question Time.  The Minister made a significant announcement about expanding the credit guarantee scheme to companies whose banks are exiting the market and are selling off their loan portfolios.  I cannot stress enough how urgent that is.  It really cannot wait.  A major bank - I will not name it and it is not a pillar bank - is selling off its loan portfolio and these are exactly the companies I suspect the Minister has in mind.  They are running out of time, so when will we see the proposal and the legislation?  Is there any way the Minister can introduce this on a temporary basis for the companies that are running out of time with their banks?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700006#F00400"><p>I invite the Minister to respond on subheads A5, A7, A8 and A12.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700006#F00500"><p>I will take them in order.  The Deputy is correct to alert us to job losses, but that rate of job loss in the context of the IDA's total portfolio is 4%, which is one of the lowest on record.  It is marginally higher than last year, but last year it was at an extraordinarily low level.  We take a very keen interest in companies in difficulty.  The IDA has a substantial transformation programme targeted at identifying companies that need improvement in some area or another.  This year, for the first time, we are introducing a budget in the Action Plan for Jobs focused on lean processes to be applied in those companies and on management development to be available to the IDA.  Some of the EI programmes that were in place and which have established a track record are now being extended into the IDA.  Indeed, some of the lean process is done by EI on behalf of the IDA, so we are expanding the knowledge that was learned in Enterprise Ireland.</p>  <p>  The same can be said of Enterprise Ireland, although I do not have the exact percentages.  Again, last year was higher than the previous year, but it was a very low number in the previous year.  What we saw in 2014 was something of a comeback in the level of job losses in some of the company base.  However, I expect that in the recession years there was a big shake-out and that left something of a dip, but we are well below what would traditionally be a norm for a job loss rate.  Nevertheless, the Deputy is correct and we are very alert to it.  It is key.  Maintaining a job is much easier than creating a new one, certainly in Enterprise Ireland companies.</p>  <p>  With regard to the new units, the midland building is located at the IDA Garrycastle business and technology park.  It is 2,600 sq. m.  I will get the Deputy an update on the exact state of play on that, as I do not have the latest one with me.</p>  <p>  On the LEO job creation, the LEOs are reporting full-time gains of 3,127 and part-time gains of 1,132.  Those are probably gross gains.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700006#F00600"><p>The Minister can refer back to me with the details.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700006#F00700"><p>Actually, these are net numbers.  The net figure is 3,690 full-time equivalents, made up of 3,127 full-time and 1,132 part-time.  It is very satisfactory.</p> <p>The service level agreement is only beginning to have an impact.  The LEOs will develop their first annual plans this year.  That process is ongoing at present and it is a big part of the regional enterprise approach.</p> <p> There are two elements to the loan guarantee, and the Minister of State, Deputy Gerald Nash, is taking responsibility in this area.  We have a legislative area, which is the extension of terms and certain changes.  We are also bringing in a scheme that does not require legislative action, also to be dealt with by Deputy Nash.  The legislation is being worked on.  It is a more complicated piece of legislation than we would have hoped in terms of getting the drafting done.  The matter is being given top priority within the Department and we are working with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00200"><p>I know Deputy Calleary is well aware of the issue of exiting banks and refinancing of loans.  We are going to do two things in terms of adapting this scheme, which is permissible under the existing Act in any event.  I will lay the new scheme before the House over the next few days.  We are making significant progress on the matter.  As we have stated previously, the scheme will allow for refinancing where an SME's bank has exited or is exiting the SME credit market.  It will also allow us to extend the maximum length of the guarantee from three to seven years.  That change is imminent and it will be laid before the Houses shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00300"><p>I ask the Minister of State to give a briefing on the scheme, as the matter is urgent, as he will know himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00400"><p>I will definitely do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00500"><p>Every Member should get a briefing on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00600"><p>It will command broad support.  I will be happy to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00700"><p>The IDA will be developing proposals to improve existing business parks and identifying areas where it needs to make other property investments - land banks, service sites or whatever.  That would be part of its own five-year plan, which it will announce fairly soon.  This will set out its approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00800"><p>I welcome the Minister, the Ministers of State and the officials.</p>  <p>  I wish to ask a couple of question on subheads A5, IDA Ireland, and A7, Enterprise Ireland.  I welcome the success in 2014.  Already this year, 2015, we have had major jobs announcements, including in my own area of Galway.  I welcome the increased allocations in the Estimates for those areas, including allocations for IDA Ireland, Enterprise Ireland and the LEOs.</p>  <p>  With regard to the future, it is grand, as far as I know, to allow Northern Ireland to set its own corporation tax rate.  Can the Ministers let me know the strategies IDA Ireland will adopt to anticipate the move?  </p>  <p>  My next question relates to the debate that is taking place in my other committee, the Oireachtas Joint Committee on European Affairs, on the possible exit of Britain from the EU.  Would this be an opportunity for Ireland?  Have IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland mentioned the development in their negotiations?  Jobs are not created overnight; it is a long-term process.  I would like the delegation to comment on the matter. </p>  <p>  In regard to LEOs, there has been an increase in funding, and one of the outcomes is the implementation of 31 local enterprise development plans.  Is the Minister confident that each LEO is properly funded?  I am not talking about my own county.  Having talked to colleagues whose counties have LEOs, I heard one express the view that the LEO office consisted of two individuals.  Are counties monitored individually to track the staffing level in LEOs and whether they have the resources to complete the work they need to do?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700007#G00900"><p>I thank the Deputy for his acknowledgement of the progress being made.  Some exciting announcements have been made, particularly on the Enterprise Ireland side.  One can genuinely say we have Mittelstand companies, as they would be described in Germany, such as the likes of Combilift and Ribworld.  There are several that are now proving their capacity to be global players and they have the ambition to match.</p>  <p>  I see no problem or threat in Northern Ireland having its own capacity to set corporate tax rates.</p> <p>One is competing daily with other European destinations or Singapore.  The competition for foreign direct investment is fierce.  Anything that is good for the island of Ireland's economy is really good for all of us.  I have no concerns on that front.  We compete all the time and we will continue to compete.  Obviously what might happen in the United Kingdom referendum in 2017 is an issue on which one will comment with a certain level of caution.  Other people are making decisions about their future.  In the natural course of such things, it throws up threats and opportunities.  I think the balance of advantage for Ireland as a country is to see Britain remain in the European Union.  Britain is our main trading partner, but of course we do not control the outcome of the referendum and we have to look at how we minimise the threats and take the opportunities that come as a result of such decisions.  While there is very active assessment of this, we will not try to influence the decisions of the British.  We work with the UK all the time, we have a very close relationship and clearly that relationship will remain.</p> <p> The local enterprise offices, LEOs were established with both the existing complement of staff from the county enterprise boards and an incoming complement of staff from the local authorities.  It was bringing in the local authority business units, so there is no LEO operating with a lower staff complement than it had in the beginning.  We are conducting a review of resources and clearly we will be looking at the adequacy of the support in all cases.  We have specific permission also to have a graduate programme so we will be introducing graduates not to replace the core strength of the existing LEOs but to improve customer delivery and service and so on.  Obviously we are looking at this very closely.  There are four positions for head of enterprise currently being advertised in different areas by the Public Appointments Service.  Some unevenness has been inherited from the existing structure but we are trying to ensure we deliver an even service, and as resources become available, we will strengthen services.  We have specific opportunities to place graduates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700008#H00200"><p>We will now deal with programme B - Innovations.  Does the Minister of State, Deputy English wish to make a brief opening statement?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700008#H00300"><p>I cannot repeat or stress often enough that innovation is at the heart of competitive advantage.  If one looks at the companies that are engaged in innovation and research and development, the case is proven by the increase in exports and the creation of more jobs.  Consecutive governments in the past 15 years have enjoyed success.  Our aim is to continue to build on that.  We invest &euro;730 million annually in research, which is a significant investment.  We constantly monitor it and keep working on it to ensure we get the results from it.</p>  <p>   The Minister, Deputy Bruton, commented on the question of global rankings, but let me add that we are first in the world for the availability of skilled labour, we are 11th in the global innovation index in 2014, and we are 13th in the world for university, industry preparation and research and development.  We are punching above our weight in some categories and that is where we want to be.</p>  <p>  The key highlights for 2014 is the 102 high venture start-ups with a three-year commitment of more than 1,500 jobs.  There have been more than 1,700 collaborations between industry, third level institutions and Science Foundation Ireland researchers supporting the development of close business links between industry and research and the research system.  We are trying to build on that.  The plans for 2015 will be to enhance that relationship and to encourage more SMEs to get involved in the research community.  Five new research centres have been funded by SFI through an investment of &euro;155 million.  We thought it would have been two centres but five is a success story this year.</p> <p>Some 475 students and researchers have been appointed on structured PhD and emerging technology programmes.  This is another example of something we want to encourage.  Since we last met, we have published Ireland's first national directory of research centres of scale.  Some Deputies will have a copy of the directory in front of them.  This important point of contact will flag to people looking in how the system works and where they can make contact.</p> <p> The first national innovation showcase, which was held at the National Convention Centre, was a great success.  It was fully subscribed.  It was probably over-booked.  Over 2,000 entrepreneurs, industry representatives and researchers from around the country were involved that day.  It worked out very well.  Many relationships were developed and many connections were made on the day.  It is something we want to build on.  I am not sure when we will have the next one.  We will learn from this one.  Industry feedback has been very good.  We will be aiming to hold another event, in 2015 if possible.  The aim behind this is to develop our Horizon 2020 applications.  If we are to achieve our targets in this regard, there needs to be much more involvement from the SME sector and from the multinationals.  Our higher education institutions are probably doing their bit in terms of percentages, but we need to get a greater involvement from business as well.</p> <p> I have touched on a few areas.  We are attempting to prioritise the funding that is available for the prioritisation agenda, which covers the 14 main areas.  I suppose our science sectors of excellence will push that agenda as well.  That is just a short summary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  Do Deputies have any questions on programme B?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00300"><p>Can the Minister explain why subhead B5 provides for a reduction in the funding allocated for the programme for research in third level institutions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00400"><p>The programme for research in third level institutions is coming to a natural end.  The funding comes in blocks.  The current block is nearly running out.  Fewer than 18 projects are being finalised.  Expenditure on students and PhDs is now regarded as capital expenditure as a result of a change in the accountancy rules.  The programme in question is winding down naturally.  Investment in this whole area, in terms of maintenance and additional capital requirements, is being looked at in the new strategy that is being considered at the moment.  A study that is ongoing will report into that and feed into our strategy, which we hope to have published in July of this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00500"><p>Okay.  Under subhead B4, which relates to research, there has been an increase of &euro;100,000 in the science and technology development programme.  What are the specific areas at which this will be targeted?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00600"><p>In terms of personnel, the main aim is to get more collaborations.  It will follow the 14 prioritisation areas we have identified.  These are key areas for Ireland to build excellence in.  The aim would be to have another 1,000 collaborations with industry and new industry over the year ahead through the various agencies, including Enterprise Ireland, Science Foundation Ireland and IDA Ireland.  We recognise that if we are going to build on this, we need to push it constantly and get new players in.  That involves attracting new industry as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00700"><p>It has been a suggested in the past couple of years that a referendum will be held in the whole patent area.  I know there is referendum fatigue in the country.  What sort of timescale is in place for that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00800"><p>It would have been nice to have fitted it in this year.  I know this committee has had an active role in pursuing the matter.  I think the Government has made the right decision in this area.  We will have a local division of that as well.  I think that has satisfied most of the concerns that were expressed at this committee over the years.  The referendum has to be passed by the third quarter of 2016.  I would imagine at this stage that we will possibly see a referendum sometime in 2016.  It does not look to be on the agenda for this year because I think people are fatigued in that area.  I think it has to be passed by the autumn of 2016 at the latest.  It is an important one for the country.  This committee will have a role in it because it has been involved from an early stage.  Some of these referendums do not catch the imagination of the public even though they are important.  This referendum will be important because it will make it much easier for Irish inventors, scientists and researchers and other companies to get involved in this market and to get patents.  It will make it much more affordable for new emerging players in this area.  I think it will be important for this one to be passed.  We will engage with the committee on it closer to the time if that is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J00900"><p>Does the Minister of State, Deputy Nash, wish to make an opening statement on programme C?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J01000"><p>I am fine, thanks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700009#J01100"><p>Under programme C, we will consider subhead C3, Workplace Relations Commission; subhead C4, grants for trade unions for advisory and education services; subhead C5, Health and Safety Authority; subhead C6, trade union amalgamations; subhead C7, Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement; subhead C8, Competition and Consumer Protection Commission; subhead C9, Personal Injuries Assessment Board; subhead C10, customer support; subhead C11, Companies Registration Office and Registry of Friendly Societies; subhead C12, Irish Accounting and Auditing Supervisory Authority; subhead C13, Low Pay Commission; subhead C14, subscriptions to international organisations; subhead C15, commissions, committees and inquiries; and subhead C16, legal costs.</p> <p>Are there any questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700010#K00200"><p>On subhead C5 and the Health and Safety Authority, in particular the agricultural side of things, representatives from the authority appeared before the Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine some time ago.  There is an ongoing high number of deaths in this area, in particular of young children.  It was stated that there will be a reduction in the number of inspectors but an increase in the number of discussion groups.  Does the Minister of State have any information on how this will operate or what sort of roll-out or timeframe is envisaged?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700010#K00300"><p>As I understand it, farm safety walks are a relatively new innovation and something the Health and Safety Authority wishes to promote.  The authority takes what might be described as a blended approach to safety issues.  From the point of view of farm safety, the number of farm fatalities in recent months, including those of young children and experienced farm workers and owners, is very concerning.  The view taken by the HSA is that resources need to be directed towards farm safety walks, discussions groups and this type of engagement.  Inspections in isolation do not seem to be bringing down the number of fatalities.  There is a huge job of work to be done by all of us to raise awareness.  We in public office and the representative organisations, including the IFA and the ICMSA, must work closely with the HSA and other relevant organisations to try to create a wider awareness of farm safety.  This is a priority for me.  The Health and Safety Authority and I plan over the next couple of months to hold a series of events throughout the country on what is called Workers' Memorial Day to raise awareness of safety in the workplace.  This will include farms as well.  I am quite positive about the approach being taken in terms of farm safety walks.  People in my community in Louth have engaged in such processes and have found them useful.  This approach will enable the HSA to reach a wider number of farm workers and owners over the next period and to promote the safety message.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700010#K00400"><p>There is an Estimate for the low pay commission, which is welcome.  Will the Minister of State comment on the timeframe?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700010#K00500"><p>This is a new innovation in the public policy landscape.  Today I will be announcing the composition of the low pay commission.  I hope that the chairman designate will have the opportunity to speak to the committee over the next while.  The commission is a priority for Government in terms of our dignity at work agenda and making work pay.  This year there is a budget of &euro;500,000.  We have modelled this very closely on the budget for the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council and the arrangements will be the same.  It will be staffed, in an advisory capacity, by staff from the Department who will work to support the low pay commission.  The Estimate breaks down as &euro;270,000 current pay and &euro;230,000 current non-pay.  There will be significant resources, therefore, to allow it to carry out and commission research where gaps emerge.  For those who have seen the terms of reference, which I distributed to the committee recently, and the heads of the Bill, the data sets that the low pay commission will use to arrive at its annual recommendation for an appropriate national minimum wage are clear.  Where there are gaps, the commission will be enabled to initiate research to fill those gaps to ensure that it can arrive at a rate for the national minimum wage in an evidence-based and robust way.  The work will start very soon.  I expect the first meeting to take place over the next couple of weeks and to have a recommendation from the low pay commission in the summer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700010#K00600"><p>We will move on to programme D, appropriations-in-aid.  Do members have any questions on this programme?</p> <p>If there are no further questions, we will move on to the administration subheads under each programme.  These include subheads A1, A2, B1, B2, C1 and C2.  Do members have any questions?  Everyone is satisfied.  I take it the discussion has concluded, although if anyone wishes to make closing remarks, they would be most welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700011#L00200"><p>I am sorry that I was late.  I was at another meeting and I could not get away.</p>  <p>  The economy has made a successful comeback and people on the streets are now beginning to talk about it.  They see the evidence among their families and communities.  I live in Ballyfermot.  I am close to what people say in terms of unemployment because there are high levels of unemployment there.  It is pleasing to see that people are beginning to have confidence in the recovery.  This is largely the work of the Ministers in this room.  They have taken on a singularly difficult portfolio and have done remarkably well to make the progress that has been made in a short period.  I am keen to emphasise that.  It is gratifying, especially speaking as someone in one of the Government parties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700011#L00300"><p>It makes life easier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700011#L00400"><p>I thank Deputy Conaghan.  The truth is that Irish enterprise and Irish workers have shown remarkable resilience in the face of difficult circumstances.  We have seen them finding new markets, going further afield, applying innovation and applying more lean processes to become globally competitive.  They have been extraordinarily successful in this regard.  We have yet to see the confirmed Enterprise Ireland expert numbers but it appears they have performed exceptionally well in 2014, certainly beyond wildest expectations.  With their backs to the wall, people have shown fantastic ingenuity.</p>  <p>  Another encouraging aspect is that we are beginning to see start-ups on a far wider scale.  It is heartening to see the growth in the numbers of people starting their own business.  Moreover, the indication is that the number of people who would consider starting their own business is even higher or at least showing greater growth.  There seems to be a good climate here.</p>  <p>  The challenge for all of us is to ensure that the policy regimes sustain these changes.  This good growth has not happened by accident.  We have moved mountains across all Departments, not only ours, to consider the skills base, the tax mix as well as the things we do in the areas of health, education, the environment and infrastructure to make it easier.  These policies must be sustained.  We need to be competitive in the long term if we are to achieve sustainable full employment.</p>  <p>  Twice in a generation I have seen a situation where the country has had within its grasp the capability of becoming a full employment economy on a sustainable basis.  However, we lost the run of ourselves and committed to unsustainable policies that simply fell flat on their face.  Significant damage was done.  One of the things we need to learn is that policy matters.  The type of sustained policies we have been trying to put in place are important for the long term for this economy as well as for our capacity to provide employment for people who genuinely want to stay here.  Perhaps this does not apply to everyone.  Some people will want to travel.  However, we need to be able to get back to a position where anyone who wishes it can choose to work in this economy, and we are on the way.  Unemployment and emigration are coming down, but we need to sustain the approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700011#L00500"><p>I wish to add to the comments of Deputy Conaghan.  It seems more jobs are becoming available as well.  There is an issue now in respect of ensuring we have the skills to fill all the jobs being created, now and in the months and years ahead.</p>  <p>  Under the Action Plan for Jobs, one of the indicators of performance is the national talent drive.  This involves making sure we have a good deal of home-grown talent to fill these jobs, but it will make it a little easier to bring in talent from abroad, when necessary, to augment that supply.</p>  <p>  This committee has considered reports over the years which have identified areas like apprenticeships, where we have to change how we do it.  The main aim of this year's Action Plan for Jobs is to have a further engagement between industry and the education system to ensure we are developing the skills and the jobs we need.</p> <p>There may be a role, following on from some of the previous reports, in making that connection.  </p> <p>The new apprenticeship council, which was formed before Christmas, has made a call for proposals from industry, representative bodies and so on for new apprenticeship suggestions.  Various Departments are now out beating the bushes to get people, organisations and industries interested and coming in with their ideas.  We need to do some work to make sure this happens.</p> <p> We need to develop schemes that have on-the-job training, involve employers in identifying courses, needs and so on, and make sure they are involved in training and outputs.  This is important because there is no point in creating jobs in six months' time if we cannot fill them with people who are living in the country.  A lot of work needs to be done and we are focused on it.  It is in the Action Plan for Jobs.  The committee was part of that in recent years and we need to build on it.  </p> <p> There is an awareness issue, and industry has to step up.  There is no point in members of the committee telling people around the country that they could employ 50 or 60 people if they will not get involved in training them to make sure the skills exist.  It is a challenge and a sign of recovery, but we have to build on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700012#M00200"><p>I welcome Deputy Conaghan's remarks.  As a Minister of State with responsibility for SMEs, I have had the opportunity over the past few months to travel around the country and talk to SME owners and managers about their experiences.  We are now in an entirely different space even compared to two years ago.  There is now much more confidence out there.  The local enterprise office approach is working.  I visited quite a number of them over the past few weeks.  That is not to say there are not still challenges.  We need to keep a very close eye on their resources and make sure they are supported in developing over the next period and meeting the challenges that exist.  One of the most significant things Ministers and Ministers of State can do over the next period is to marshal through regional economic strategies.  It is no longer any use to try to create the impression that every region of the country is competing for the same type of foreign direct investment.  We need a balanced regional approach.  </p>  <p>  The regional economic strategies will essentially be an action plan for jobs at a local and regional level.  That is a process initiated by my colleague, the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and Department officials.  It is a strategy that has been proven to work.  We will see a process whereby local agencies such as the IDA or Enterprise Ireland will take responsibility for driving these strategies and showing leadership at a local level - working with local authorities, third level institutes, local enterprise offices and so on - to make sure we get the balanced regional economic activity that we need.  There is very little point in having an economic recovery that is focused on our main cities.  We will spread that right across the country and will have a very involved process in terms of developing regional strategies.</p>  <p>  It is also important that we have harmonious industrial relations and progressive legislation - it is recognised that our legislation is the best in developed economies - which is developed in partnership with employers and trade unions in the way that we seek to address issues around the REA and collective bargaining legislation.  It is important that we do that in collaboration and partnership with employers, trade unions and those who represent working people.  </p>  <p>  With regard to balanced economic development, I do not mean just regional development.  I also mean making work pay and making sure that people are always better off in work rather than ensnared in a social welfare system from which they cannot get out.  The best thing we can do is to provide somebody with the dignity of a job, and that is what we are all committed to doing.  We have seen our economy recover considerably over the recent past.  There is still a lot to do, and we are all very focused on that in terms of regional strategies and all the work we are doing in the Department.  We can be positive and optimistic about the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700012#M00300"><p>I ask the Minister of State to keep a sharper eye on small craft industries which sometimes go unnoticed.  One such industry started in a prefab in a VEC school in Ballyfermot 14 years ago and was the beginning of the modern film animation industry.  It has now been to Hollywood on four occasions for the Oscars.  There are other people in creative categories who may need to put their heads over the water.</p> <p>We must let the people involved in those types of small-scale initiatives know there are supports and funding available to assist them.  I was on the board of that school at the time the project was launched.  Initiatives like that can be multiplied several times, as I am sure is happening throughout the country, but they need recognition and support from the beginning.  We must keep a sharper eye out for those types of creative efforts.  It would be enormously encouraging for those involved if somebody could reach out to them at an early stage in their development and offer a small grant or other types of support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700013#N00200"><p>The local enterprise offices are effectively first-stop shops for all such initiatives, but we are also stepping up the advertising of the more than 80 programmes that are available to small and start-up businesses.  We have a website, <i>actionplanforjobs.ie</i>, which includes a tool that allows users to input information about the profile of their businesses and obtain information on suitable financing options, whether that be microfinance, for example, a tax break for former PAYE workers setting up a company, or something else.  Many of these schemes have take-up way below their capability, and we want to see progress in that regard.<br/><br/>As the Minister of State, Deputy Nash, outlined, the thinking behind the regional enterprise strategy is that there are many opportunities for community enterprise centres to become much more innovative in what they offer their client base.  They might tap into institutes of education, for instance, or tap into a chamber of commerce with accountancy support.  There is scope to have an entrepreneur in residence or available as an advisory resource.  Those little hubs have good potential to step up their performance, and that is what we hope will come out of this regional call.  We want people to consider how they can tap into available resources and make more of what they currently have and are doing.  One idea might be seek the assistance of a local person who is recognised as an entrepreneur made good and get some momentum behind particular initiatives.  There are great ideas out there and there are people doing great things, but we need to tap into them at regional level.  That is what we are hoping will come out of this initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700013#N00300"><p>The Action Plans for Jobs spans several Departments and has a particular relevance to rural affairs, agriculture and the environment, all of which are connected with the Leader programme.  As part of the new rural development plan, that programme might not be approved until the end of year.  In other words, because of the changeover with the Common Agricultural Policy regime and the rural development programme, the programme is effectively in abeyance.  Will the Minister comment on that?</p>  <p>  The Minister of State, Deputy Nash, referred to the provision of rural broadband services.  I acknowledge that the roll-out plan is proceeding and there is European Commission approval for state aid.  However, it is vital that progress be made as quickly as possible.  Is there potential to expedite the tendering process?  Even though good plans have been put forward by Vodafone in co-operation with various groups, they are targeting places that already have adequate broadband.  In fact, there is reference to the 50 largest towns, which includes Dublin, Galway and other urban centres.  I understand there are commercial reasons for that, but the problem is that it is the areas outside these urban centres which are dealing with inadequate service.</p>  <p>  My final point is more of a political one, but it seems okay to raise it as there are only Government Members present.  We are well on our way to achieving the target of creating 100,000 new jobs during the Government's term in office.  I am concerned, however, that the target of 40,000 for this year is a little ambitious.  Of course ambition is good and I hope the target is exceeded.  However, in the event that 35,000 or 38,000 new jobs are created, which would still be a tremendous achievement, my concern is that we will see headlines about the Government failing to meet its jobs target.  There has been great progress in recent years on the job creation front, but the Minister will understand my concern in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700013#N00400"><p>We see the regional enterprise strategy, like the Action Plan for Jobs, as being an annual event.  The Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Alex White, is working on the issue of broadband provision and a tender will be drawn up later in the year, but there is a lot that can be done with our existing resources.  We are very much about looking to see what we can do today that will enhance the performance of a region in the next 12 months.</p> <p>A year from now, we can consider what can be done afresh.  We should not stop what we are doing just because the Leader programme might be postponed.  At the end of March we will be calling on local enterprise offices and community enterprise centres to commence the process of encouraging people to consider how they might enhance the assets they already possess.</p> <p> When we declared our ambition of creating 100,000 new jobs, people said we were overestimating what was possible.  All the critics stated that if various Departments' statistics were taken into account, it was obvious that what we were seeking to do could not happen.  However, it has happened.  I am of the view that there is an opportunity to push on in this regard.  IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland companies are performing strongly and the construction industry, although coming off a very low base, is moving again.  Parts of the retail sector will struggle as a result of the switch to trading online, but other areas of it are showing a strong recovery.  If we can put in place some of the things to which I refer, encourage entrepreneurship and make it easier to start up businesses, then we will deliver on those targets.  I would not be disappointed if, ultimately, we were to hit 95% and fall slightly short.  We have been in the businesses of setting stretched targets all through this process and we can stand over what we are delivering in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700014#O00200"><p>I congratulate the Minister and Ministers of State on the work they have done.  A Government Deputy would almost be expected to say that but I genuinely mean it.<br/><br/>We are in a different place now than was the case four years ago in the context of what is available for SMEs.  When one is driving to work, one regularly hears radio advertisements relating to the Credit Review Office, access to finance, etc.  However, is a person who owns a shop in Phibsborough, which I might pass on my way home, aware of what is available to him or her?  I accept that it is not possible to knock on the door of every SME throughout the country and spend an hour explaining to its owners the massive suite of options that exists and the fact that they may be able to avail of some of those options.  The Minister referred to the <i>actionplanforjobs.ie</i>website and there is also the online tool for SMEs.  These are great but what sort of checks are in place to ensure that the maximum number of people possible are using those tools?  In the computer age in which we live, websites are windows and those windows require to be changed almost daily.  I mean this in the most respectful way but I remain somewhat unconvinced with regard to this matter.  As the Minister and Ministers of State will be aware because they meet them regularly, there are those in the SME sector who perform three jobs, for which they receive a single salary, and who work around the clock.  Sometimes these people, when checking their post each day, might miss some material relating to that which we are discussing.  That material could take the form of a very important document which might, for example, highlight some of the really good things being done by the Government to improve the SME platform in Ireland.<br/><br/>What checks are in place to monitor whether the tools which have been developed, particularly those available online, are being used by sufficient numbers of people to ensure that <i>actionplanforjobs.ie</i>is both reaching its target audience and paying for itself?  Essentially, there is a job to be done in terms of monitoring the advertising of the various schemes to ensure that those schemes are working for us.  I am a member of the Ballymun Civic Alliance, which replaced Ballymun Regeneration.  The local enterprise office is represented on the alliance and one of the other members is an individual who runs a very successful business on Dublin's northside.  People, SMEs and other organisations involved with the Ballymun Civic Alliance and bodies like it are all clued in to what is happening.  I am concerned about those people who are not aware of what is going on because they are not involved in this way.  I am sometimes of the view that I might know more than the owners of SMEs about the various services that are available to them.</p> <p>This is not a criticism but a concern.  We should always strive to ensure we are confident that everything we do trickles down to the person who owns the coffee shop on the corner.  A scheme about which he or she does not know could make the difference with regard to employing somebody else.  It is not a criticism but a question on what systems we use to ensure we have maximum penetration of all of the genuinely good initiatives which have been established since 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00200"><p>We are learning and applying metrics to the exercise we are running at present, including on the impact of our social media campaign.  We have brought in our industry partners, the people who won the young entrepreneur competition and the main business organisations such as Chambers Ireland, the Irish Small and Medium Enterprises Association, ISME, and the Small Firms Association.  Our spend is &euro;250,000.  If we just got 12 people back to work we would justify it.  We use the local enterprise offices as first stop shops.  We will also use the Companies Registration Office as many companies must make returns every year.  We have already used the chambers of commerce to get out the information and we are trying to plug into any network we can.  The reason we are doing this is according to the most recent survey 90% of people felt they were not properly aware of what was out there and 80% wanted more information.  We are responding to this demand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00300"><p>I recognise this is a difficult task.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00400"><p>Few people know of the existence of the seed capital scheme as only 63 claimed it.  This scheme allows a PAYE worker who establishes a business to get a refund of the tax paid in the previous six years to offset against some of the investment being made.  The 63 claimants are a drop in the ocean of the 12,000 businesses which have been established.  The scheme should be more widely available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00500"><p>I want to highlight that I am not making a criticism.  I am only short of knocking on the doors of the 40,000 homes in my area to tell them about some of the services available in other walks of life.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00600"><p>We would encourage the Deputy to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00700"><p>People often say they have never heard of schemes and I know we cannot please everybody.  I just wanted to check that we are constantly ticking away at maximum penetration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00800"><p>At the beginning, the Minister mentioned my concerns about the National Competitiveness Council.  I do not see a budget line for it.  I am trying to find Forf&aacute;s's budget line, whereby its staff has gone into the Department's general administration.  To assuage my concerns, will the Minister consider including a budget line for the National Competitiveness Council so I can see where the money is?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700015#P00900"><p>The National Competitiveness Council is a group of people serviced by the strategic policy unit of the Department.  It is not a spending centre.  It commissions consultancy reports and publishes reports, and is entirely independent.  A new chairman has just been appointed.  I strengthened the council by including industry partners who are actively engaged in key sectors and we have an effective body.  It is not a question of a line in the budget; the real issue is to ensure our strategic policy unit is a real driver of new thinking in the Department, and at present it is working on enterprise 2025.  Traditionally the Department has had strong agencies and a weak Department.  Forf&aacute;s was outsourced and largely run under the auspices of the agencies.  The idea of bringing it in is to give the Department a stronger arm in being able to think afresh, which we are determined to do.  We established a protocol at the very start to ensure Forf&aacute;s would not be sucked into line management and would retain its independence and capacity to produce reports without fear or favour.  It is not so much about Forf&aacute;s being a line in the budget, but about giving it this independence.  Already I can see the benefit for the Department of having an active policy arm.</p> <p>I would like to see more of our officials having a more active interface with our client base.  That is one of the weaknesses.  The agencies have the front-of-house experience.  We need to see that experience filter back into the Department.  That is an area we should be examining in terms of how we can get more exposure to the marketplace for our senior line managers and policy people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700016#Q00200"><p>Regarding subhead C5 covering the Health and Safety Authority, I have considerable sympathy for it because it does a very good job in regard to farm safety but it is a very difficult area.  Is there any financial contribution from the Department Agriculture, Food and the Marine towards its work or has the Minister any idea what that Department invests in health and safety initiatives?  Farm safety is a major problem and it is a difficult one to crack.  The HSA has been trying to do so for many years but last year's figures were horrendous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700016#Q00300"><p>The HSA is an area for which I am responsible.  To the best of my knowledge, there is no direct financial contribution from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine but our Department and that Department, as the Deputy will know, work closely together on initiatives.  The Minister, Deputy Bruton, and the Minister, Deputy Coveney, had some public engagements last year in regard to raising awareness of farm safety.  I intend to co-operate closely with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  As I said to Deputy Kyne while the Deputy had stepped out, the number of farm fatalities are worrying.  The HSA will direct resources into the area of farm safety and walks, and also discussion groups.  They are important to get to the harder-to-reach farmers and I believe that has to come from the community with the support of the HSA.  That would be a progressive way of spending Health and Safety Authority resources.  Obviously inspections are very important but they, of themselves, do not save enough lives.  There is never an acceptable level of fatalities on farms.</p>  <p>  The Irish Farmers' Association, IFA, the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers Association, ICMSA, and other organisations work very well together.  I was very impressed when I visited them at the National Ploughing Championships.  Their level of commitment to this whole space is truly astonishing.  They see the importance of it, as do we and as does the whole system.  We must work hard to make sure we can get those numbers down.  There is never an acceptable level of fatalities but the HSA continues to work co-operatively with the IFA, the ICMSA and others to try to address those issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700016#Q00400"><p>I commend the Minister, Deputy Bruton, the Minister of State, Deputy English, and the Minister of State, Deputy Nash, and all their officials on the great leadership they have shown in this tremendously challenging economic period in which we found ourselves.  It was a huge undertaking to try to stimulate job creation again in our very flagging economy when people's spirits were low, never mind the loss of jobs.  We are beginning to see an energy from the people working in our State agencies and from the people with ideas now that there are supports in place that they can identify.  It is tremendous to meet and engage with them and see their energy and hear of their ideas and innovations.  A key factor is that supports are now in place.<br/><br/>I was lucky enough yesterday to be invited to Offaly Local Development Company's business development programme certificate launch for a number of the people who participated in it.  Word not broken yet about the <i><i>a</i></i><i>ctionplanforjobs.ie</i>launch.  They all spoke of how being able to access one portal to get all the information will be very beneficial.  We all have a responsibility to get that message out.<br/><br/>Another aspect is encouraging young entrepreneurs.  The programme in that respect led by Enterprise Ireland was fantastic and the final of it was held in Google Foundry.  It was fabulous to see all those young dynamic people energised by that experience.  People are waiting with great anticipation for the announcement of the pilot plan for the midlands and also how the regional plans will be rolled out nationally.  It is timely that is happening and it will be very welcome. </p> <p> With regard to the entrepreneurship policy statement before Christmas, we are doing a report on women entrepreneurs so the witnesses can look forward to receiving that from us when we have completed our hearings on it in the coming weeks.  </p> <p> In my area in Offaly the local enterprise office has taken on a new energy in terms of it moving in under the local authority.  It has always been successful but in terms of the challenges being brought to bear on it, there is nothing like a crisis to get people to sit up and take note.  Under the Minister's leadership it has proven to be very successful, and an innovation hub will be opened there very soon.  If we can see all of that being replicated across the country it will be welcome.</p> <p> I very much welcome the acknowledgement that broadband provision is a cross-departmental issue because if we are serious about encouraging community enterprises we must remember that all the young people graduating from wonderful institutions such as the one in Ballyfermot can create a business on their own, almost in their own bedrooms, and all they need is a computer.  However, if they do not have broadband, they cannot do that.  That is critical for certain areas, and particularly those that have enterprise parks.  If we could put particular pressure on that it would be tremendous.</p> <p> I thank all the witnesses for attending today's meeting of the select committee.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.81" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700017#R00200">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015021700017#R00300"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:<blockquote><br /><br />The Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation has completed its consideration of the following Revised Estimate for public services for the year ending 31 December 2015: Vote 32 - Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.83" nospeaker="true" time="15:00:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned at 2.55 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.84" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.85" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Eric Byrne, Senator Aideen Hayden, Deputy Timmy Dooley, Senator Terry Leyden, Deputy John Halligan, Senator Kathryn Reilly. Deputy Derek Keating, Deputy Seán Kyne,</p><p>DEPUTY DOMINIC HANNIGAN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.86" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#B00100">Possible Exit of UK from European Union: (Resumed) Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#B00200"><p>I remind people to turn their phones off.  It is not sufficient to put them on silent mode because they may interfere with broadcasting equipment.</p> <p>  Apologies have been received from Senator Colm Burke.</p> <p>  Today the committee continues its series of meetings considering critical issues for Ireland in the event that our nearest neighbour, the UK, decides to exit from the European Union.  A referendum on this question has been promised by the British Prime Minister, Mr. David Cameron, MP, should his party be returned to power following May's UK general election.</p> <p>  The committee took the decision to examine this issue now in view of the potential impact on this country and the many Irish citizens living in the United Kingdom.  We had two meetings on the topic last week and we will hold another five meetings after today.  Today's meeting will focus on the four freedoms - the freedom to trade in goods, services and capital and the free movement of people - and what would happen to Ireland in the context of these freedoms should the UK exit the European Union.</p> <p>  We have a number of guests today.  We will start with Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh from the Institute of International and European Affairs.  He will be followed by Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally, professor of law and director of the Centre for Criminal Justice and Human Rights; Professor Alan Matthews, professor emeritus of European agricultural policy in the department of economics, Trinity College Dublin; and Mr. Steve Aiken, the former chief executive of the British-Irish Chamber of Commerce.  I welcome all four of our guests to today's meeting.  We look forward to their respective insights on the issue.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Chairman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2239"><img src="../images/info.gif" border="0" alt="Information on Dominic Hannigan"/></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=committees&amp;amp;code=EUJ&amp;amp;memberid=2239&amp;amp;pid=DominicHannigan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=17"><img src="../images/zoom.gif" border="0" alt="Zoom on Dominic Hannigan"/></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Before we begin, I need to remind Members of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official, either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/><br/>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.<br/><br/>We will begin with Mr. Daith&iacute; &Oacute; Ceallaigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.89" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#C00200"><p>I have been asked to talk about the possible implications for trade between Ireland and the UK in the event of a UK withdrawal from the EU.  I will preface my remarks by addressing two issues.  First, I wish to inform the committee that the Institute of International and European Affairs has just finished editing a book on Great Britain and Europe that we expect to publish on the web early in March and as a printed book later in March so it may be of some help to the committee in its studies.</p> <p>  Second, the situation in the UK is very uncertain and entirely unpredictable.  The Prime Minister, David Cameron, has said that he wants to have a referendum in 2017.  We in the institute think that regardless of whether Mr. Cameron is re-elected, a referendum in the UK is likely in the next few years and that, in practice, this referendum will be of an "in-out" nature.  However, we do not know what the British want.  The Prime Minister has said that if he has a successful renegotiation with Europe, he will recommend a "Yes" vote.  The British Government has not made clear what it actually wants in a renegotiation so this is uncertain.  There will be one negotiation between now and whenever there is a referendum but we do not know what it will be and we do not know what the issues are.</p> <p>  When the referendum comes, we do not know whether it will result in a vote to remain within the EU or a vote to withdraw from it.  If it is a vote to withdraw from the EU, there will then be a negotiation period which will probably take the best part of two years.  This negotiation will essentially be led by the European Council but most of the work will be done by the European Commission.  There is a further question regarding what will happen internally in the UK if there is a vote to withdraw.  The Scottish National Party has already said that it does not want Scotland to withdraw unless there is a majority vote in Scotland to do so.  There is great uncertainty and the possibility of two negotiations, all of which would affect Ireland's relations with the UK and Europe.</p> <p>  I will now turn to trade.  By trade, I mean both merchandise and services.  Trade is one of the key economic linkages between Ireland and the UK.  The impact on that trade will depend on what happens in the first negotiation and the second negotiation if this takes place.  At the moment, trade between Ireland and the UK, like trade between Ireland and the rest of the EU, takes place on the basis of the EU Internal Market - the Single Market.  The British appear to be quite happy with the Single Market.  From time to time, one sees commentaries in the British press stating that they would like to remain in the Single Market.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, as I am sure some of my colleagues will mention later, some of the basic freedoms in Europe underpinning that single market are freedoms about which people in Britain are demanding serious changes, such as the free movement of people.</p><p> If there are negotiations following a referendum to withdraw, there is no doubt but that trade between Britain and Ireland would be affected.  That is really what we need to examine.  We also need to know how much trade there is between Britain and Ireland.  In 2012, 43% of merchandise exports from Irish-owned firms went to the United Kingdom.  The proportion of exports from non-Irish-owned firms is much lower, at about 12%.  About 20% of our services exports went from Ireland to the UK.  Therefore, should there be a change in the arrangements about trade, there will obviously be very big implications indeed for Irish exports to the UK.  In the book I mentioned earlier, there is an attempt to quantify the result on this trade, and on Ireland, of a British withdrawal from the EU.  The argument is that the effect on Irish exports, were the UK to withdraw from the EU, could be in the order of a decrease of 3.6%.  I should mention that there are so many ifs and buts in this thing that we need to examine that figure with caution, but that is the way it looks.</p><p> Should the British succeed in a renegotiation of their terms of membership between now and the time of a referendum, and remain in the EU, that in itself could have an effect on our trade.  Should they withdraw, however, the effect is likely to be much greater.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#D00200"><p>Our next contributor is Ms Siobh&aacute;n Mullally, who is a professor of law and director of the Centre for Criminal Justice and Human Rights at UCC.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.92" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#D00300"><p>I am going to talk about the possible implications of a UK withdrawal from the EU with regard to free movement of persons.  The debate concerning the UK's membership of the EU and a possible withdrawal has centred to a considerable extent on the free movement of persons.  Proponents of reform argue that the current EU legal framework does not provide adequate safeguards to ensure the free movement of persons without overburdening member states' public finances.</p> <p>  The free movement of persons is protected in the EU treaties and also in the charter of fundamental rights, where we also see a protection of access to social security benefits and social advantages.  Also of relevance here is the 2004 citizens directive.  Of the proposals to reform current EU free movement law as part of a possible precondition to the UK's remaining within the EU, several of the proposals that have been raised would require a treaty amendment and unanimous approval by each of the 28 member states, followed by enactment into domestic law.  Other proposals do not require such change.</p> <p>  At the outset, it should be noted that one of the key concerns for Ireland will be the continuing functioning of the common travel area.  Movement between Ireland and the UK of EEA and non-EEA nationals is likely to be significantly affected should the British exit proceed.  As recently as December 2011, a joint programme of work was agreed to strengthen the security arrangements of the common travel area and to provide a framework for a more strategic approach for this co-operation.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Given this quite recent initiative and the existence of the common travel area arrangements, albeit relatively informally for a significant period, it seems likely that the UK would wish to treat Irish citizens differently from other EEA nationals should withdrawal proceed.</p><p> If withdrawal were to proceed, there would be a number of possible scenarios, which have been discussed.  There are uncertainties associated with each.  One possibility would be that the United Kingdom would remain as a member state of the EEA and continue to participate in the Single Market with a status similar to that currently enjoyed by Norway, Iceland and Liechtenstein, for example.  This would require little change to free movement rights but is unlikely to be an option given that much of the debate on withdrawal has centred on limiting free movement rights.  Discrimination between EU citizens dependent on their country of origin is likely to be problematic as a matter of EU law.</p><p> A second possible scenario would be bilateral negotiations whereby the United Kingdom would negotiate bilateral arrangements with selected EU member states.  This, however, would lead to significant fragmentation of free movement rights and could create difficulties, particularly for Schengen area states if all Schengen area members were not to be included in such bilateral agreements.  As such, it is likely to be politically difficult for any individual member state to negotiate bilaterally with the United Kingdom.</p><p> A third option would be that domestic UK laws on immigration would apply, in which case we would see a repeal of the exceptions currently provided for EEA citizens.  In such a scenario, EEA citizens and family members already in the United Kingdom may be permitted to remain - as permanent residents, for example.  Those without rights to permanent residence, particularly jobseekers, would be easier to remove given that the current protections provided by free movement law would not apply.  What we would then see would be the introduction of visa requirements for entry for work, study or family reunification.  EEA nationals would effectively be treated as third country nationals are treated at present.  A range of possible restrictions could be introduced, including visa requirements, linked, for example, to minimum income requirements, language skills and the supply of biometric information.  We would see a phenomenon akin to the current five-tier points system that applies in UK immigration law being applied to EEA nationals.  There is concern that this would lead to significant reductions in migrant workers, including highly skilled workers, coming to the United Kingdom.  Any of these scenarios would be likely to have a significant impact on the operation of the common travel area between Ireland and the United Kingdom.</p><p> With regard to the possible reforms that are being mooted as a precondition to the United Kingdom remaining within the EU, a number of touch on free movement.  One covers access to social security payments, including a proposal limiting access to housing benefits, social housing and tax credits for a minimum period, possibly up to four or five years.  With regard to EU citizens who are categorised as workers as defined in EU law, a change in the EU treaties would be required.  Therefore, it would seem unlikely to come into effect.  For those who are jobseekers or do not meet the definition of "worker" or "former worker", this reform would be less problematic.  The European Court of Justice judgment in the Dano case in November 2014 confirmed that limits can be placed on access to non-contributory benefits, including a requirement that the residence conditions of the citizens directive be complied with.</p><p> A related proposal would be that the UK Government would seek to renegotiate the principle of exportability so origin states would remain legally responsible for covering unemployment or non-contributory benefits that would, for example, be required by their own citizens for a minimum period.</p><p> There is some commentary that these changes would not lead to any significant changes in terms of movement of EU or EEA nationals and that they may actually lead to more vulnerable persons falling through the cracks of social protection.  It could have a significant impact on UK nationals living in other EU countries.  This, of course, is of significant concern to a number of countries, including Ireland, Spain, France and Germany, where the costs of providing health care are high and where the number of ageing UK citizens would be significant.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> A second proposed reform would be in the area of rights to family unity and family protection.  The right to private and family life is protected in the EU's Charter of Fundamental Rights and also, of course, under Article 8 of the European Convention on Human Rights.  A proposal to impose restrictions on the entry of non-EU citizen family members in light of the Metock judgment could create difficulties and may be viewed as requiring a treaty amendment, at least with regard to those persons categorised as workers and former workers - those who derive rights from the treaties.  Other proposals - for example, to link family reunion to minimum income requirements and language skills - have already led to some criticism from the European Court of Justice.</p><p> A third proposed area of reform relates to the possibility of limiting rights of entry for job seekers by imposing a requirement that an EU or EEA national seeking entry to the UK be in possession of a genuine job offer.  This could raise practical difficulties, but also legal difficulties.  Currently, an EU citizen can reside for a three-month period with a valid passport and without recourse to social assistance, and thereafter the right to reside is dependent on having sufficient resources and sickness insurance.  Those EU treaty rights to free movement also apply to job seekers, which is particularly relevant here, so long as they have a genuine chance of being engaged in employment.  It is likely that a treaty amendment would be required to effect such a reform, and this would be difficult given the protections of the right to private and family life in European human rights and fundamental rights law.  Linked to that is a proposal that job seekers who do not secure employment within a six-month period could be removed.  This also would lead to difficulties and would come into conflict with decisions already given by the European Court of Justice, notably in the Antonissen case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#F00200"><p>The next speaker is Alan Matthews, professor of European agricultural policy at the Department of Economics at Trinity College.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.96" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Matthews" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#F00300"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to talk to the committee about the implications of a British withdrawal from the European Union for the Irish agrifood sector.  My remarks summarise a somewhat longer submission, which I have made available to the secretariat.<br/><br/>The former ambassador, Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh, referred to the importance of trade between Ireland and the United Kingdom, but the trade links in the agrifood sector are even more important, and more important than for any other EU country.  Approximately 51% of Ireland's total agrifood imports are from the United Kingdom, and the United Kingdom takes approximately 51% - the same percentage - of our total agrifood exports.  Therefore, more than half of imports and exports of agrifood products come from and go to the United Kingdom.  These are also much higher proportions than for Irish manufacturing.  A British exit, or &quot;Brexit&quot;, from the EU could potentially lead to significant disruption of this trade.<br/><br/>As the previous speakers have mentioned, much would depend on the nature of the trade relationship that is put in place between the UK and the EU post-Brexit.  The various alternatives that are on the table include: membership of the European Economic Area, as in the case of Norway; membership of European Free Trade Association, EFTA, combined with literally dozens of bilateral agreements approximating the Single Market, as in the case of Switzerland; a customs union, as in the case of Turkey; a deep and comprehensive free trade agreement, as negotiated with Canada; or trade on most-favoured-nation terms without a trade agreement.  I agree with the other guests that the UK is not likely to leave the EU because it dislikes some Single Market regulations, only to sign up to these again outside the EU.  Therefore, the most likely outcome is a free trade agreement in which the UK is no longer a member of the Single Market, tariffs on most - if not all - trade between the two partners are eliminated and the United Kingdom is free to set its own trade policy, including tariffs with third countries.  In my view, there is a good possibility that in that scenario trade in agrifood products would also remain tariff-free.  I will call that the good outcome, although it is clearly less desirable than the maintenance of the <i>status quo</i>.  In another scenario, tariffs might be reintroduced on some primary agricultural products and the primary element of processed products, which could include important Irish exports such as beef and dairy products.  I will refer to that as the bad outcome.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Professor Alan Matthews:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Even in the good outcome, without the reintroduction of tariffs, there would be additional costs to trading compared to the current situation.  Trade conditions would revert to what they were in the early 1990s prior to the introduction of the Single Market.  Trade costs arising, for example, from the reintroduction of Customs controls, rules of origin checks, import licence requirements as well as the additional costs of complying with two different regulatory regimes where regulatory divergence occurs, would increase.  This would put downward pressure on producer prices in Ireland and upward pressure on consumer prices, an important issue given the close integration of supermarket supply chains between the two countries.</p><p> The United Kingdom, given what we know about its preferences regarding food and farm prices, would be likely to adopt a less protectionist trade policy with respect to third countries.  That means its average tariff on agrifood products would likely be lower than the EU tariff it applies today.  It may also find it easier to enter into free trade agreements with extensive agricultural concessions with partners such as New Zealand, Australia, Mercosur and the United States.  For both reasons, competition on the UK market will intensify for Irish exporters, even in the good scenario.</p><p> Food trade, more than most, is governed by detailed regulations governing plant and animal health and safety, marketing standards, labelling requirements, allowed food ingredients and many other areas.  The greater the degree of regulatory divergence between the UK and the EU, the greater will be the costs for Irish exporters and importers.  As aversion to EU regulations is one of the driving forces behind BrExit, one would expect the UK to adopt different regulations in many areas, although there are countervailing forces such as strong UK consumer, environmental and public health organisations which will seek to maintain high standards, as well as the fact that the EU will remain the UK's largest trading partner in food and agriculture, both of which will give it an incentive to keep its regulations harmonised with the EU, perhaps by continuing to transpose EU regulations into British law.  Nonetheless, examples where different regulatory regimes might emerge include the regulation of plant pesticide products, genetically modified crops and animals, and food labelling.  These are all areas where the UK position is at variance with the EU position at the moment.  Dealing with these different standards will imply higher costs for both exporters and importers.</p><p> If tariffs were to be reintroduced on some elements of agrifood trade between the UK and Ireland, in what I have called the bad outcome, trading costs could be increased by much more and, in some cases, could become prohibitive.  The question of tariffs is also relevant to the introduction of an economic border between North and South of the island.  Land borders between EU and non-EU countries are not unusual and in principle, under the good scenario, would not lead to problems additional to what I have already mentioned.  Even if the UK were to pursue a less protectionist and more consumer friendly farm and food policy after BrExit, the likely change in food prices North and South of the Border would be much smaller than what we observe today as a result of exchange rate fluctuations.  However, if tariffs were reintroduced there would again be incentives to smuggle those agricultural and food products subject to high tariffs.</p><p> There might be a temptation among some in Ireland to welcome Britain's exit from the EU because of its traditionally hostile attitude to the Common Agricultural Policy.  However, in my view the overall impact of UK withdrawal on the future of the CAP would be rather minimal.  Partly, the succession of CAP reforms and the greater flexibility provided to member states under the 2013 reform address many of the UK concerns.  It is true the EU would lose a voice arguing for fewer exemptions and more trade liberalisation in concluding trade agreements with, for example, Mercosur or the US but on the other hand the UK is a massive net contributor to the EU budget, the largest after Germany, and it made a net contribution to that budget amounting to almost &euro;11 billion in 2013.  If the remaining member states want to maintain farm support at currently foreseen levels, they must be prepared to contribute more to the EU budget to ensure this following a BrExit.  In this calculation, some member states that now see themselves as benefiting from high CAP spending could well move to the other side of the ledger.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Professor Alan Matthews:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> In my view, BrExit is an outcome to be avoided if that can be achieved, but if it were to happen, the Irish agrifood sector should pursue a number of objectives in the subsequent negotiations on the UK-EU trade relationship.  These include minimising the disruption to agrifood trade and particularly to avoid the reintroduction of tariffs, but also to seek to minimise the impact of regulatory differences, through continued UK adhesion to Single Market rules, at least as it relates to items such as product standards, veterinary and phytosanitary rules or through mutual recognition agreements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#H00200"><p>Thank you, Professor Matthews.  We will now hear from Mr. Steve Aiken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Steve Aiken" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#H00300"><p>I thank the Chairman for inviting me to address the committee.  The views I would like to express are mine and not those of either the British Irish Chamber of Commerce or Dublin City University - as I go through some of my remarks, members may wonder why I said that.  As I have this opportunity to talk to the members and to have heard what the three previous speakers said, nothing I say will contradict what they have done.  The main point I want to get across is that things have changed significantly and that change is unlikely to be reversed.<br/><br/>I would like to start by quoting both George Osborne and Peter Spencer, the chief economist at Ernst and Young.  George Osborne recently said: <blockquote>My... goal is for Britain to become the most prosperous of any major economy by the 2030s...  <br /><br />It is within the power of my generation to achieve this ...  <br /><br />The ingredients are all here: <br /><br />We now have the most competitive tax rates of any in the G20.<br /><br />We've sharpened work incentives with tax cuts for the low paid, welfare reforms and a higher minimum wage ... <br /><br />[We have also invested significantly in research and development and] We've secured the number one place in the world index for investing in infrastructure.<br /><br />We' re attracting more Chinese inward investment than Germany, France and Italy put together.<br /><br />By 2030 we're set to have the largest economy in Europe.  </blockquote>These remarks have been covered by Peter Spencer, who said: <blockquote>However it's not all good news. The global economy has slowed and prospects for the Eurozone appear to be going from bad to worse. The euro has fallen to an all-time low against the dollar, which will help combat deflation and stimulate Eurozone exports at the expense of UK producers.  [However] Investors face the uncertainty of the UK General Election, followed by the possibility of a referendum on UK membership of the EU. Overall, the prospects have brightened - but remain ... risky.</blockquote>These two statements point to several of the significant factors running through current UK political and economic thinking in the lead up to the election.  These are that the UK economy is doing well, as is our own, and despite a significant debt burden, the UK's growth is outstripping that of Europe but the UK has more flexibility with its finance and economic policy than the eurozone.  That raises a question of the UK's involvement within Europe.<br/><br/>A second issue, as seen from an increasingly sceptical UK audience, is that the problems of the eurozone may not have been arrested and may be getting worse.  In the UK this is coupled with a subtext that the EU's attempts at stabilising and reflating the eurozone may no longer be a benign influence on the UK economy, but may be undermining attempts to achieve further growth in the UK.<br/><br/>There is a growing sense - I stress this is currently a minority opinion - in the city of London and several large corporations that I have had the opportunity to talk to that the comparative advantage for the UK of being part of the EU is being eroded.  Eurosceptisim, which until fairly recently was largely absent from major UK companies but which was getting a significant hearing within the SME community, is getting a much wider audience.  Mr. John Longworth, director of British Chamber of Commerce, at last week's British Chamber of Commerce Conference stated:<blockquote>Chamber members fundamentally support the Prime Minister's objective: Britain in a reformed Europe.  The next government must set out what it will do to protect the United Kingdom against the prospect of being in a club where all the decisions are made by, and for, the Eurozone.<br /><br />More than any repatriation of powers, businesses want to know that the UK has safeguards against being drawn closer to the Eurozone <br /><br />...Economic pragmatism - what's best for Britain, for British business, for our national growth ambitions - must win the day.</blockquote>Before I talk about the impact it is likely to have on us, there are some disruptive factors, as already alluded to by Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; &Oacute; Ceallaigh.  The first of those is with regard to the UK election.  There is an uncertain outcome both in the likely composition of government and in the role of parties such as the SNP, DUP, UKIP and the Greens.  As a subsidiary point, it may be postulated that some form of EU referendum, regardless of the composition of the government, may be on the agenda.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Mr. Steve Aiken:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is also noteworthy that the themes of this referendum will focus not on economic issues but on emotive issues such as sovereignty in certain decision-making processes and, in particular, migration and the free movement of people across the EU.</p><p> The second disruptive factor is the effect the success and stability of the eurozone will have on the EU, sentiment in the UK media and the markets.</p><p> While not an immediate impact, the nature of the UK and its relationships within these islands is changing and will change significantly.  An all-island corporation tax rate of 12.5%, similar arrangements for Scotland, and other regional attempts to gain competitive advantages to counter what is seen as the overwhelming influence of the south east will have an impact on us.  We will be measured against Northern Ireland, Scotland and other regions in the UK.</p><p> A more fundamental point is that, when the UK thinks of Europe, it looks east.  Even though we have a contiguous land border with the UK, in the vast majority of British thinking the EU is 25 miles away across the English Channel.  Ireland is not part of the equation in any significant or fundamental way.  This will have a considerable impact on us when we examine trade issues, particularly with our largest markets.</p><p> In terms of goods, services and trade policy, we must consider where the UK sees itself.  For example, the patent box, research and development investment, reducing corporation tax, investment in infrastructure and investment in education are key in its estimation of how to make itself as competitive as possible.  Given our success levels, we seek to take the same types of measure.  Increasingly, we may be seen to be in competition not just with the UK but also with its individual regions.</p><p> The question of the possible imposition of tariffs and border controls has been raised by many informed debaters in Ireland, including myself and Mr. O'Ceallaigh.  The implications of border controls and their political impact are recognised by those who are listening in the UK, but they are a relatively small group.  When people discuss the EU, they do not think about the wider relationship on this island.  It is not a significant calculation when dealing with the pro- and anti-EU lobbies.</p><p> The Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, is another area of significant impact.  I am surprised that I have not heard it mentioned so far.  For Ireland and the UK, TTIP is one of the most important areas that we would like to see grow and develop.  The relationship with the US is particularly important, as both Britain and Ireland are Atlanticists in their outlook.  Seeking a greater relationship with the US that links the world's two largest trade zones is a key consideration.</p><p> We have already discussed the UK's competitive edge, but it will undoubtedly seek further competitive advantage.  A loosening of EU regulation will form part of that.  However, one of the main points that is constantly mentioned is the UK's access to the Single Market.</p><p> Taking all of this as the backdrop, what will happen to us and what will the difficulties be for us?  I had the opportunity to brief this committee two years ago, when I was asked directly whether I expected to see a "Brexit".  I stated that it would be unlikely, for many reasons; the situation is now uncertain.  For Ireland, it would impact on trade, agriculture, services, energy policy and so on.  In the widest strategic sense as well as an economic and trading sense, a vast variety of activity in Ireland's relationship with the UK is likely to be affected severely.  Regardless of the next UK general election and the referendum that will happen, though, the game has changed.  We are in a new dynamic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#J00200"><p>I thank Mr. Aiken.  He stated that a referendum would happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Steve Aiken" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#J00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#J00400"><p>Will it happen regardless of the election or is he predicting the election's outcome?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.105" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Steve Aiken" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#J00500"><p>Regardless of the result of the election, there will be a referendum.  There is a significant push for the major political parties to hold a referendum.  As we head towards the election, we will hear the rhetoric increase, particularly in the British media, and a referendum will occur at some stage during the next Parliament.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#K00100"><p>I thank the four speakers for their thought-provoking presentations.  It is often difficult to have European matters discussed in this country because much of the time people do not appreciate their relevance or potential impact.  It is very clear from all of the presentations that the public has not really zoned in on this topic, which is why this discussion is timely and helpful for our understanding of it.</p> <p>  Mr. O'Ceallaigh mentioned a period of negotiations, perhaps of two years, after any poll that might take place.  If this is the realistic timeframe in which these negotiations take place, people will be led into a false sense of security that we will get a deal which resolves the major issues between us and the UK, such as the agrifood sector, trade generally, human rights or the movement of people, and that all will be fine.  This might be the case in some areas, but we cannot end up on the other side of an exit of a country whereby that country gets the benefits and all the positives of these agreements.  This cannot be the case.  We must be careful.  The fact we have co-dependence in certain areas should not lull us into a false sense of security that we will reach an amicable agreement.  There is often conflict about issues which prevents the type of deals, arrangements or accommodations we want.  This is why we have the European Union in the first instance, to try to do this in a balanced way.</p> <p>  My concern is that industry and trade generally will believe there is such a level of co-dependence that an exit will not really matter and we will sort it out.  If this is the case, other countries will wonder what is the benefit for them of being restricted or constricted within a European Union and will consider going down the same road.  Then we will be in the proverbial manure business.  We must sell the argument that if one slate comes off the roof, the entire roof is in jeopardy.  Here, and perhaps to a greater extent in Britain, we must try collectively to get the message across that it will not just be a series of bilateral agreements which will get us through.</p> <p>  Mr. O'Ceallaigh spoke about the impact on exports of a 3% or 3.5% reduction.  I believe it would be greater.  For a while the co-dependence would assist in maintaining the level of activity, but then we would start getting into tariffs and these would have an impact on deals with other countries.  We would end up with this spiralling out of control and the consequences would become much greater than anything that might have been anticipated because of the complexity of the various arrangements which exist.  We have a job of work to do to create this level of concern in the minds of the people who will be impacted greatest.  There is a responsibility, particularly on those involved in active trade between the two countries, to spell out Ireland's concerns to their associates, whether customers or suppliers, on the other end to try to feed into it at the earliest possible opportunity.</p> <p>  The presentations were very solid and did not lend themselves to too many questions.  I thank the witnesses for their assistance in our work.</p><p>I have a number of questions on agriculture and North-South economic relations.  With regard to food labelling, a voluntary beef label was agreed in November 2014 under the voluntary label scheme to deal with the issue of nomad cattle.  How do the witnesses think a British exit would affect the market for beef from mixed-origin cattle such as those which are traditionally exported to the North for fattening and slaughter?<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kathryn Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2355"><img src="../images/info.gif" border="0" alt="Information on Senator Kathryn Reilly"/></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=committees&amp;amp;code=EUJ&amp;amp;memberid=2355&amp;amp;pid=KathrynReilly&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=17"><img src="../images/zoom.gif" border="0" alt="Zoom on Senator Kathryn Reilly"/></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This issue was fairly contentious and it has only recently been bedded down, for example, under the voluntary scheme.  What could happen to those farmers who are using "Irish" as a voluntary term in connection with their meat?</p><p> Second, what will happen to farmers whose land in Border areas is split between the North and South?  What consequences will the reimposition of the border between the EU and Britain have?</p><p> Finally, following a possible exit, what will happen in terms of economic and social relations between North and South?  When one considers that many existing areas of North-South co-operation such as trade promotion, agriculture and rural development, environmental issues, health and transport take place within an EU framework, what needs to happen in terms of the political leaders?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#L00200"><p>Following our previous experience with witnesses, I came in here of the view that we were dealing with a complex question with many ifs and buts.  However, I am sorry to say I have been made deeply depressed by the contributions, particularly when our little dream that the referendum may not be held is, according to Mr. Aiken's position, unrealistic, notwithstanding that the election has not yet occurred and the Tories have not yet won, and all the ifs and buts that go with the United Kingdom's internal dynamics in terms of Scotland and, to a lesser extent, Wales.<br/><br/>We were also dealing with the notion that, no matter what happens, there must be a significant amount of negotiations before the fact, even if the Tories win the United Kingdom election.  I do not know how long that might take.  Presumably it would take years, because we would be talking about a considerable process of unravelling.  What will happen with the internal dynamic, for instance, within Northern Ireland, with the Unionists and Sinn F&eacute;in, and with Northern Ireland <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>the majority of Scottish MPs?  There are still a lot of balls in the air.<br/><br/>Frankly, the debate about Europe needed Greece like it needed a hole in the head.  Would they agree that those eurosceptics in Britain and across Europe might be taking solace from what is happening with Greece?  My worry is that there are so many people who are now becoming eurosceptics that they are seeing immigration.  My question on immigration is as follows.  Are UKIP, the Conservatives and the British people more concerned about the free movement of people from within the Union of 28 than what they perceive to be the influx around the Mediterranean from North Africa, of, for instance, Iraqis and Libyans?  There are hundreds of thousands of people trying to get to Europe.  Of course, Britain is conscious of its rail link with France and the horrors of significant numbers of stateless persons all trying to get across, either on ferries or on lorries, to Britain.  Is the worry immigration from outside or from within the Union?  We are in a horrible situation of an unstable world.  There is Russian expansionism in Ukraine, potential Russian expansionism in Latvia, and unstable relations from Moldova to God knows where.  Sadly, there are a considerable amount of people on the move - more than ever there has been.  Of course, Greece has been seen to be the leaky border that facilitates the through flow.  I am rambling.  Italy, Australia and Japan, amongst others, are taking specific steps on controlling immigration and the movement of people.  I note the horrors that would occur if the worst should be realised.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eric Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=142"><img src="../images/info.gif" border="0" alt="Information on Deputy Eric Byrne"/></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=committees&amp;amp;code=EUJ&amp;amp;memberid=142&amp;amp;pid=EricJByrne&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=17"><img src="../images/zoom.gif" border="0" alt="Zoom on Deputy Eric Byrne"/></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I congratulate the Chairman of this committee on engaging in this very theoretical but very serious debate.  How should the Government now engage, and with whom?  Should it start with bilateral talks with our 27 colleagues in Europe?  Should it start engaging immediately with the British Tories, or should it start engaging with the Commission?  How can we now be sufficiently proactive in engaging with the key players so we will not be left guessing the outcome for Ireland if the United Kingdom decides to leave the Union?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1094" speakername="John Halligan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#M00200"><p>I found Mr. Aiken&rsquo;s submission very interesting.  He said there will probably be a referendum.  Consider the consequences beyond the economic effect on Ireland if the United Kingdom leaves the Union.  There was a referendum in the United Kingdom in 1975.  Even with all Mr. Murdoch&rsquo;s media backing the UK Government at the time, the result was still two to one in favour of the United Kingdom staying in the Union, which was very close.  The United Kingdom rejected the single currency in 1999 and also the Maastricht treaty.  One may recall that Mr. John Major&rsquo;s Government almost collapsed in 1993.  It is very interesting that the Institute of Economic Affairs stated recently that the United Kingdom could be better off outside the European Union.  I believe it cites the cases of Switzerland, Iceland and Norway, which lie outside the Union but which are part of the European Free Trade Association.  They, apparently, enjoy all the benefits of the EU Internal Market.  I was listening to Mr. Nigel Farage some weeks ago.  He quotes organisations such as the institute and claims what it has outlined could be the case.  Even within the British Labour Party, some of whose members I know, there is a lot of scepticism that is not coming to the fore regarding the European Union.  It is not just coming from the Conservatives.  I do not believe the view on Mr. David Cameron because many of the businesses in England have railed against leaving the United Kingdom.  However, I believe it is inevitable there will be a referendum and that Mr. Cameron has to call one.</p> <p>  During the last few weeks of the campaign in England, the Labour Party itself will come under fierce pressure internally to call a referendum.  What is the delegates' view on the Institute of Economic Affairs, which appears to be contending the United Kingdom could very well be fine outside the European Union?  What is the delegates' view on Switzerland, Iceland and Norway?  Believe it or not, they indicated in recent months that they would have no interest whatsoever in being part of European Union because of the European Free Trade Association.  They seem to be doing quite well outside the Union.  If a referendum asking the UK electorate to leave the Union were called in the morning, it would be carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#M00300"><p>I apologise for being late.  I missed the contributions as I was at another committee meeting, which started at 1.30 p.m.  I have read through some of the transcripts and other submissions on this matter.  I have a few questions for Mr. Matthews on agriculture.  I am not particularly sure what trade role the Commonwealth has at present.  Would Commonwealth countries benefit or be afforded opportunities if the United Kingdom left the European Union?  What will transpire given the view that Britain, as a food importer, would benefit from the Commonwealth rather than the existing arrangements within the European Union?<br/><br/><b></b>Regarding the vote, I presume Wales and Scotland are more reliant on the Common Agricultural Policy than England.  Would this have an impact?  Was any analysis done regarding direct transfers?  Wales and Scotland have many environmental programmes that are funded through the Common Agricultural Policy, whereas England has a much higher number of larger farmers with larger single payments who would not be as concerned as the Scots or the Welsh.<br/><br/>My next question is for Professor Mullally.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"><img src="../images/info.gif" border="0" alt="Information on Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne"/></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=committees&amp;amp;code=EUJ&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=17"><img src="../images/zoom.gif" border="0" alt="Zoom on Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne"/></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->According to British commentary over a number of years, there seems to have been an inordinate amount of discussion about the radical cleric, Abu Hamza.  It took a number of years to expel him and it seemed to be garnering headlines.  Does Professor Mullally think that incident alone has caused damage to the case for the European Convention on Human Rights?</p><p> I would like to ask Mr. Aiken the old question about Wales.  I have not seen individual polling figures, but is there a possibility that Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland could vote "No", yet if England votes "Yes", the "Yes" side would win?  Has there been any discussion on what would happen if the result was 50.5% "Yes" versus 49.5% "No"?  </p><p> Migration is obviously a big concern.  In January 2014, when the rules changed for Bulgarians and Romanians, the television cameras were waiting at airports expecting this huge influx.  However, one poor creature got off the plane and was that day's headline.  Given that we have a Border with the Six Counties, would there be a concern in Britain that if borders were not reinstated, we would be an easy point of access to the UK for migrants who could come through Ireland?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#N00200"><p>I have a number of observations to make.  Mr. Aiken made an interesting point that we are not that important in this debate from the UK's point of view.  In fact, giving us some of the historic preferential new tariffs, or no tariffs at all, might be against the interests of regional Britain.</p> <p>  In terms of rational expectations, the witnesses all seem to be agreed that there will be some form of referendum in the UK at some point, whether in 2017 or thereabouts.  At what point does it become a self-fulfilling prophecy, one way or the other?  In that sense, businesses will start to anticipate an outcome at some stage, particularly concerning foreign direct investment, inward investment and British firms' decisions to relocate some of their activities outside the UK.  What impact might that have?  </p> <p>  Professor Matthews made an interesting point on standards in the agricultural sector.  He said it would be in Britain's interests to keep its standards uniform with the rest of Europe.  Does that transpose across to other aspects of the economy?  One of the things to fear is that Britain gets all the benefits of leaving with none of the costs other European countries have arising from social or regulatory standards.  To what extent does Professor Matthews think that is possible, or will the balance be more in favour of Britain retaining the standards of the rest of the EU countries?</p> <p>  If the various measures currently being taken in Europe prove to be successful in reflating the European economy - for example, quantitative easing and the Juncker plan - to what extent does Professor Matthews think a European recovery could make a difference to the outcome?  How much of a factor is a European recovery?  There seems to be a view in Britain which says they have done very well outside the eurozone, the strategies they have followed have proven to be the correct ones and they do not need Europe.  If Europe was to start turning the corner, however, would that have an influence on matters?</p> <p>  The UK is the EU's single biggest market.  Professor Matthews might correct me if I am wrong, but I understand that the UK imports more from the entire EU than it exports.  In other words, it is a net importer of all EU goods.  How important is that as a factor in the negotiations for other EU countries in trying to influence the UK's outcome?  As regards the negotiations, how much are other EU countries willing to concede?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#O00100"><p>Before returning to our speakers I wish to comment on the likelihood of a referendum.  My understanding, from speaking to my colleagues in the Labour Party in the UK, is that their leader, Ed Miliband, has faced down calls from within his party for a referendum.  I would have thought it would be unlikely, should the Labour Party get into government, that we would see a referendum.  It is an issue for them and it is not for this committee to decide whether there should be a referendum.  We are more interested in the impact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/976" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#O00200"><p>Try influencing the Prime Minister at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#O00300"><p>Let us look at the speech David Cameron made at the Bloomberg headquarters in January 2013.  On that occasion, he identified a number of issues on which he would like to see reform in Europe, as well as many other things.  I think there were five in all.  These included the implementation of the Single Market, on which he will not find any disagreement here; competitiveness; the issue of the disconnect between citizens and Europe; and the need for national parliaments to use to a greater extent the powers that have become available to them since Lisbon.  All of which we agree with here.<br/><br/>When it came to a concrete list of proposals, the UK Government undertook to carry out a balance of competences review, going through each Department and identifying the type of power that could perhaps be returned to the UK national Parliament.  My understanding is that it was not a huge list of items that came out of that particular review.  From looking at the debate in the UK over the past 12 months, I feel the question is more focused towards freedom of people and workers.  I noticed in today's <i>Financial Times</i>that one of the most senior trade diplomats has said he does not think the programme of negotiation from Mr. Cameron is extremely ambitious.  He thinks there is a very small list of requests from the UK Government.  It is suggested that perhaps, as a result, a negotiation process could be undertaken and resolved quite quickly post-election, in advance of a referendum.<br/><br/>Can our guests tell us their views on what needs to be changed in order to meet a minimum requirement for the UK Government to advocate a stay-in vote if there is a referendum?  Clearly, if the Conservative Government does win, then what we in this country would like to see is for the Government to advocate a &quot;Yes&quot; vote.  What is required from Europe?  What changes do the witnesses think would be the minimum required to convince the UK Government to advocate a &quot;Yes&quot; vote?  A lot of questions have been asked.  Does Senator Hayden wish to contribute?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#O00400"><p>I wish to give my apologies.  I will read the replies in the transcript.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#O00500"><p>I suggest we start off again with Mr. O'Ceallaigh and work our way around.  I ask witnesses to answer as many questions as they can, and if they want to make any concluding remarks at the same time they may do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#O00600"><p>I thank the Chairman.  I shall first address the question of whether there will be a referendum.  It is quite true that the Labour Party leadership is against a referendum.  However, there are two things which could bring about a change.  The first is political pressure, particularly in the run-up to the election.  Rather more importantly, Westminster passed legislation which stated that there would be a referendum were there to be treaty changes in the EU.  There is quite a possibility that there will be treaty changes in the EU within the foreseeable future.  It is my view, for what it is worth, that there will be a referendum in the UK in the foreseeable future, and that no matter what the wording is, in essence it will be a referendum about whether it stays in the Union or pulls out.</p> <p>  On the question of Switzerland, Norway, Iceland, Turkey and so on, none of the arrangements that those countries have with the European Union would suit the United Kingdom.  They all mean that those countries have to accept free movement of people.  Free movement of people is at the heart of the British problem - the question of immigration.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would mean, in effect, that Britain would have to implement all forms of European legislation, without being at the table when that legislation is being negotiated.  I do not believe the British would find any of the solutions that Switzerland, Norway, Turkey and Iceland have found acceptable.  If there is to be a new agreement with Britain outside the EU, it will have to be something specific to Britain.<br/><br/>Let us presume that the UK has a referendum and it decides to withdraw.  I agree that the negotiation will be extremely difficult, as has been said by one or two of the members of the committee.  I cannot imagine a member state wishing to give the United Kingdom a better deal outside the Union than it has inside the Union, particularly given the amount of time that the member states have had to spend up to now, not to mind between now and when the negotiation takes place, trying to assuage the British position.  The fact is that member states are losing patience with the British.  We hear that from all over Europe.  They feel that concessions were made to the UK in the Lisbon treaty which it was believed would settle the question of British membership for a considerable period, but that is not what happened.  Instead, British membership of the European Union is on the table at practically every meeting that takes place in Brussels or Strasbourg.  There is a lack of patience with the British within the Union.<br/><br/>The implications for Britain, should it withdraw, are very deep.  The leader of the Scottish National Party has said that she would like to see a majority one way or the other within Scotland, and that it is not sufficient for an overall majority in the United Kingdom to withdraw if there is a majority in Scotland that wishes to remain in the EU.  If the Scots take that position, it is quite likely that the Welsh will take the same position.  Northern Ireland is even more complex.  If the British take a decision to withdraw, there is a serious possibility that the United Kingdom could break up.  The unitary state with sovereignty in Westminster could break up in one way or another.  The Scottish question has not been settled.  The implications for Northern Ireland are enormous, as are the implications for our relationship with Northern Ireland.  These are matters we really need to ponder.<br/><br/>What should we do?  We should decide whether it is in our interests that the United Kingdom remains in the European Union.  If we decide that way, and the Government has made its position very clear, we should examine what we can do to try to ensure that it does remain in the Union.  There is one area where the British are not involved and, in my view, are very unlikely to be involved, if ever, and that is within the Eurogroup.  As a result of what has happened over the last five to seven years, that Eurogroup is becoming increasingly closer.  We might need to think of a relationship, or try to bring about a relationship, in which the United Kingdom remains within the European Union but with some type of special relationship with the Eurogroup.  As I said earlier, the special arrangements made with Norway or with Switzerland will not meet that situation.<br/><br/>It is correct, as the Chairman said, that in his Bloomberg speech Mr. Cameron indicated some areas of concern.  He also indicated more areas of concern in an article he wrote in the <i>Daily</i><i>Telegraph</i>about a year ago.  Frankly, I am sure solutions can be found in the seven or eight areas of concern he mentioned, but I believe the problem is much deeper.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As mentioned by Mr. Aiken there is a cultural problem here and a historical sense of British exceptionalism.  As stated in our book which will be published shortly, it may be that we have reached the endgame in terms of finding new arrangements which keep the United Kingdom within the European Union without inhibiting the drive within the eurozone to go forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.123" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#Q00200"><p>A number of speakers mentioned that free movement rights have been very much at the heart of the push to consider withdrawal from the European Union.  Many of the proposals for reform that have been put forward as a possible condition to the UK remaining within the EU would require reform of the treaties and of the core fundamental freedom of free movement and so would be difficult to secure, although not impossible.  They raise significant legal challenges and would be politically difficult given that free movement has been very much at the heart of the European project.<br/><br/>There is also concern that some of the proposals I mentioned would have significant implications for UK nationals living in other parts of the EU, including Ireland, Spain, France and Germany.  For example, should the type of reforms being proposed be proceeded with, the cost to other EU members states of providing the type of publicly funded health care provided by Spain to ageing UK nationals living there would be significantly difficult.  The desired approach of some UK parliamentarians is a type of <i>&agrave; la carte</i>approach to free movement, in other words, free movement negotiated with some member states but not all.  This, of course, would be legally problematic, would not fit with EU free movement rules and would be politically very difficult to secure.  The preference would be for bilateral negotiations with selected member states but not including all 28 member states and, most specifically, not including the newer member states that have acceded to the EU.<br/><br/>There is significant misinformation circulating around immigration and free movement.  There is little evidence to suggest that free movement is primarily for the purpose of, for example, securing access to social security rather than work and study opportunities.  Unfortunately, this type of misinformation does take root and hold.  With regard to third country nationals, non-EU and non-EEA nationals, there are already significant restrictions in place in terms of immigration under EU law.  As such, movement is already restricted and regulated.  In the UK context, the points system and five-tier system apply.  While there are already significant restrictions in place, the UK and other EU member states have taken a selective approach in terms of prioritising immigration for highly skilled nationals who meet the requirements of their job markets.<br/><br/>The right to seek asylum, the position of asylum seekers and those seeking protection was raised.  Withdrawal of the UK from the EU would not change the position in that regard in that the right to seek asylum and protection predates the coming into existence of the European Union.  The UK will continue to have obligations under international refugee law, including the 1951 convention relating to refugees to which it is a party, the UN convention against torture to which it is a party and the European Convention on Human Rights which protects against <i>refoulement,</i>namely, return of a person to a country where he or she would face a serious risk of torture, inhumane or degrading treatment.  The debate around the European Convention on Human Rights and the Human Rights Act is a related but separate debate.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Of course, that has also become very problematic in the UK and has significant implications for Ireland, given the requirements of the Good Friday Agreement.</p><p> With regard to the crisis concerning people fleeing from Syria, the burden of that is being borne primarily by Mediterranean states and with very little EU support in terms of meeting the significant responsibilities and burdens that have arisen.</p><p> Regarding the Abu Hamza type of scenario, this is something that arises under the European Convention on Human Rights and the non-refoulement obligations.  It raises a core question as to whether we consider that human rights protections apply to all persons, including those persons we may not like and who may not be considered desirable.  Is the protection from torture and inhuman and degrading treatment to be considered absolute?  It is under European human rights law and, of course, it has been very much valued in Ireland as we saw most recently in the request to the European Court of Human Rights to re-open the Ireland and UK case.  Again, significant misinformation circulates around something like that.  That protection would remain regardless of withdrawal from the EU in that it is provided for under the UN Convention against Torture, the refugee convention and the European Convention on Human Rights, for example.</p><p> With regard to the position of movement between Northern Ireland and the Republic and the safeguarding of the common travel area arrangements, it is likely that there would be an attempt to secure that and that it could be secured in some way.  However, managing that in practice would be very difficult given that there would be a need for strengthened border controls with regard to the movements of non-EEA nationals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#R00200"><p>We are outside Schengen at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.126" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Siobh&aacute;n Mullally" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#R00300"><p>Yes, but we still have a common travel area.  If the UK were to opt out of free movement laws and were to be outside of that, apart from Schengen, other free movement protections would not apply, so we would require significantly more policing than we currently have.  That would be quite difficult in practice as well as legally.</p> <p>  The final point relates to a comment that was made as to whether the benefits of free movement could be retained.  Again, this goes to whether it would be possible to negotiate a series of bilateral agreements or a position such as would be available as a member state of the EEA.  As I mentioned, that is very unlikely given that much of the debate has been around limiting free movement.  Giving that type of concession is unlikely either to meet the needs or desires of those proposing an opt-out for the UK or those seeking to leave the EU entirely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Matthews" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#R00400"><p>I will confine my remarks to the specific trade questions that were raised rather than the broader political issues, as the committee has heard some very helpful comments on that already and Steven Aiken will probably add to that when he speaks.</p> <p>  On the trade issues, I refer to the point made by Deputy Dooley to the effect that there might be a temptation among Irish businesses to think that as we have a special relationship with the UK, we can still manage to come to an accommodation which would ensure that our beef, dairy products and other products avoid any tariffs and so forth even if Britain leaves.  It is important to be clear that the rules regarding trade relationships have become much tighter since the days when we had the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement.  Even though, at least legally, it might be possible to think of the common travel area as a type of bilateral agreement, although as Professor Mullally has highlighted there could be very practical difficulties in introducing it, the idea of a bilateral trade relationship is completely out of the question.  First, the UK will remain a member of the World Trade Organization, WTO, which prohibits discriminatory trade arrangements except in the context of regional trade agreements.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Professor Alan Matthews:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would only be possible for Ireland to have a special relationship if, from a purely theoretical point of view, there was a bilateral relationship.  As we know, external trade policy is now an exclusive competence of the European Union and we are not at liberty to enter into our own trade agreements with a third country.  If we want to protect our interests in a post-Brexit situation we have to do so through the arrangements that the EU as a whole will enter into with the UK, whatever they might be.  It is important to scotch the idea that somehow we can have some sort of bilateral old boys' network arrangement between the UK and Ireland, at least on trade issues.</p><p> Deputy Kyne raised the important issue of the UK's relationship with the Commonwealth and so on.  I referred to the matter in my opening remarks.  Certainly, the UK would, post-Brexit, be entitled to pursue its own trade policy.  That means it could set its own level of tariffs which would apply to other countries, including exports from the EU.  The UK could also enter into its own free trade agreements.  I suggested that it would be highly likely that the UK would find it easier to have a free trade agreement with New Zealand and Australia, because the world has changed since the old days of the Commonwealth, and also with Mercosur, the United States and so on.  The UK would be more willing to give agricultural concessions than perhaps the EU is in negotiations with the same groups of countries.  I agree with the Deputy that this is an obvious path for the UK to pursue in a post-Brexit situation.  That would imply, it seems to me, increased competition in the UK market for Irish exporters, because we would have to compete with cheaper Brazilian beef or New Zealand dairy products than we do at present.</p><p> A third comment which came across from a number of contributions is the idea that if Britain were to withdraw it could negotiate a deal which would give it the benefits of access to Single Market without having to accept the costs.  It is important to be clear on the matter.  Mr. O'Ceallaigh has explained the nature of the agreements with the European Economic Area countries and with Switzerland, which is a little different.  Switzerland has a free trade agreement but it also has a lot of bilateral agreements which link it very closely with the Single Market.  It is important to emphasise, as Mr. O'Ceallaigh did, that these countries, in return for getting access to the Single Market, commit to transposing every single EU directive directly into their domestic legislation without having any possibility of influencing it.  There are some consultation rights and so on, but these are not very meaningful.</p><p> Let us consider the apocalyptic situation in which we are faced with a Brexit and are trying, two years later, to negotiate a common EU arrangement with the United Kingdom.  For example, let us look at the key issue of the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, which is no longer tariffs but has to do with regulatory co-operation.  I would have thought such co-operation would also be a key area in the post-Brexit trade negotiations.  At least in the case of agriculture and food, it may well be the case that the UK would be willing to continue with EU standards and might even be willing to accept, in certain limited areas, that it would simply adopt and transpose EU regulations in these areas.  Due to the importance of its own trade with the EU, the UK might be prepared in some limited areas to accept that loss of sovereignty in return for the access that these Single Market arrangements would give it.  Perhaps I am not as pessimistic, if we have a free trade agreement, about whether it will be possible to integrate some mutual recognition arrangements and so on.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">  Professor Alan Matthews: :</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would imply, I think, that the UK would simply have to agree that in these areas we will follow EU legislation to ensure we keep our access.</p><p> Senator Reilly raised two questions, and she has put me on the spot.  It seems to me that Brexit would not require any change in current arrangements.  She raised the question of a farmer with land on both sides of the Border. I think that farmer would not notice any big difference because as members are aware one's entitlements to direct payments - let us assume the UK keeps that entitlements type system - are not transferable across borders.  If one had a situation where one could transfer one's entitlements across members states in the European Union, then if Britain withdrew, that would affect it.  At present one's entitlements on land in the North and in the South are completely separate.  As I reflect on it, that would not be affected by Brexit.  Similarly, the cattle and the voluntary food labelling is the sort of bilateral agreement that could continue.  Although there could be significant disruption to trade, on both of these issues I do not see Brexit as having a major impact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.130" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Steve Aiken" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#T00200"><p>I will deal with the issues in the order in which they arose.  Senator Reilly raised the issue of beef supplies and Brexit.  When I was in the Chamber one of the things we looked at quite closely was what we called the circularity of trade.  The reality is that the UK, if it went alone could not source enough beef in the UK and would always look to Ireland.  For many of the larger supermarket chains and the fast food companies, British and Irish beef are synonymous with each other.  That would continue.  If we look at the large numbers of companies that are involved in that space, I cannot see that changing.  That would be quite significant.</p> <p>  The one thing that does bother me, as Senator Reilly mentioned, is the issue of the North-South economic relationship and what is likely to happen if there was a Brexit or any sort of change.  I am on the board of the Irish-British Association and one of the things we have been trying to do in the past couple of years is to raise this debate because there does not seem to be any critical thinking at the possible implications on a North-South relationship if we move toward Brexit.  Last October-November we hosted a conference in Queen's University Belfast and Mr. D&aacute;ith&iacute; O'Ceallaigh and others in this room attended.  Quite a few academics were involved in the conversation, but significantly, of the political parties only UKIP turned up, which made it quite an interesting debate.  The reality is that this issue needs serious consideration.  </p> <p>  This leads me on to the answer to Deputy Byrne's question on what should Ireland be doing.  Ireland is in an unique position with the United Kingdom, because it is trusted as a trusted agent.  The United Kingdom views Ireland as a great friend to the United Kingdom, that thinks the same way on many issues.  In fact our views and opinions have a considerable degree of weight.  We might not think they do, but they do.  One of the things we should be doing is helping this advocation process of informing the United Kingdom about the importance of remaining within the EU  and talking to our European compatriots about the importance of keeping the UK in the tent.</p> <p>  That leads to a question about what we should be seeking to ask as well.  What would the UK be like outside the EU?  In the global context it would be much diminished.  It would have less influence on the world.  It would be still a significant economic power and it would be a significant power, whatever it wants to call itself, but it would be diminished.  I sat on several of the EU competency panels both in London and in various other places and one of the things that came through in the discussions and in the study is that it would not be in the UK's interests to be outside the EU.<!--/p--><!--p><span class="speaker_continuing_label">(Speaker Continuing)</span></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Mr. Steve Aiken:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is not the same as saying the debate can be shaped among the British populace, or that it is the same sort of result for which they should be looking.  That would be the answer I would arrive at for that one as well.</p><p> Mr. O'Ceallaigh has already touched on the implications for Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland.  I have had the opportunity to talk to various leaders from the Scottish National Party over a considerable period of time in the past three years.  It is quite clear that a major constitutional issue would arise if Scotland voted to stay in and England voted to go.  I would say there could be similar sorts of arrangements in Wales and in Northern Ireland.  If most of the constituent parts of the UK - by the national composition of the country, rather than by population - wished to remain in the EU but England, with a substantial body of population, particularly in the south east, was potentially looking towards moving out, that would represent a significant crisis point.  It would have major implications.  A steady hand, a reasoned debate and the voice of friendship from Ireland would be of considerable importance in that context.</p><p> I was also asked about the business position and the impact on business if the Brexit were to become a self-fulfilling prophecy.  Some businesses actually have a long-range horizon, whereas others do not.  Those that have a long-range horizon are already beginning to look at these issues as well.  If one listens to the debates within the Confederation of British Industry and the British chambers of commerce, one will be aware that their view is that some form of accommodation will be met.  It is an interesting point when we talk about imports and exports.  The activities of companies like Airbus and BMW motors as part of the prevailing "just enough, just in time" manufacturing process show how integrated the UK is within the European manufacturing chain.  I refer to the large-scale output from certain places as "the Swindon effect" because all of BMW's diesel engines are manufactured in Swindon before being put into vehicles in the US, Germany and Austria.  European countries have a great deal of interest in making sure the UK remains part of the process as well.</p><p> I was asked whether a European recovery would be of benefit to the pro-EU lobby in the UK.  Of course it would.  One of the reasons the euroscepticism debate seems to be gathering momentum relates to what is happening around Greece, its wider implications and what is happening in eastern Europe.  The UK is looking to show greater leadership in sorting out Europe's problems.  If the eurozone were to pull itself out of its current malaise, get the deflation business sorted out and begin to experience real growth again, particularly in key areas, it would be a very positive statement for the UK electorate when it is thinking about whether to remain in the EU.</p><p> I will conclude by setting out what I would advocate to encourage the UK to stay in when it votes on EU membership.  We have already spoken about the implications of the vote for the free movement of people and of ideas.  This is one of the areas we would probably need to look to.  The most significant thing we would probably need to do is to ensure the EU is looking at what is possible.  We need to make sure it is well signalled to the UK that the EU is willing to move at least in some direction to keep the UK within the EU.  Even to mention that the UK would be much better within the EU from the majority of the EU would probably be a very significant push.  I thank the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2015021700002#U00200"><p>On behalf of the committee, I thank all of our guests for attending today's meeting and for giving of their time.  The committee will have further discussions on this issue at its meeting next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-02-17a.133" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 3.40 p.m. until 2 p.m. on Tuesday, 24 February 2015.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>