<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.6" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500003#G00100">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500003#G00200"><p>We are now in public session to scrutinise EU legislative proposals.  COM (2012) 498 deals with establishing a long-term plan for cod stocks and fisheries exploiting those stocks.  Is it agreed to note the responses received from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine dated 17 December 2012 and 23 January 2013?  Agreed.  It is proposed that the proposal does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  COM (2012) 535 is an amendment to COM (2011) 626 final/3, for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing a common organisation of markets in agricultural products.  It is proposed that the proposal does not warrant further scrutiny</p><p>  COM (2012) 552 is an amendment to COM (2011) 625 final/3, for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council establishing rules for direct payments to farmers under support schemes within the framework of the Common Agricultural Policy.  Is it agreed that the proposal does not warrant further scrutiny?  Agreed.</p><p>  COM (2012) 553 is an amendment to COM (2011) 627 final/3, for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on support for rural development by the European Agricultural Fund for Rural Development.  It is proposed that the proposal does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  We will suspend the meeting to allow the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and his officials to take their places.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500003#G00400">Burger Content Investigations: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500003#G00500"><p>I welcome the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney; Professor Alan Reilly, chief executive of the Food Safety Authority of Ireland; Mr. Raymond Ellard, Food Safety Authority of Ireland; Mr. Martin Blake, chief veterinary officer at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine; and Mr. Philip Carroll and Mr. Martin Heraghty, assistant secretaries in the Department.  Other departmental officials present include Ms Paula Barry Walsh, deputy chief veterinary officer, and Mr. David Lynch, senior veterinary inspector.</p><p>  I remind everybody present to turn off their mobile telephones as mobile interference causes difficulties for the transmission people and streaming of the hearing over UPC channels.  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give this committee.  If a witness is directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter but continues to so do, the witness is entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of his or her evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>  I invite the Minister to make his opening statement, followed by Professor Reilly, and I will then open the discussion to members.  The Minister has discretion to ask an official to address the meeting at any point during his contribution.  I hope we can keep that part of the proceedings to 30 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500003#G00600"><p>I am pleased to have this opportunity to report to the committee on the intensive investigation undertaken by my Department and the Food Safety Authority of Ireland into the source of equine DNA disclosed in certain beefburgers.  This meeting was scheduled for last week and would have taken place then if it had not been for the tragic death of Detective Garda Adrian Donohoe.  Indeed, it would have taken place during the previous week had I not been taking questions in two European Parliament committees.  I am glad the meeting is taking place now.  In some ways we have a much clearer picture of what has happened and I can provide more information than I could have last week or the previous week.  I am aware that a number of members have received detailed briefings from the Department in regard to the investigation.  Spokespersons were particularly interested in the briefings.  As the investigation proceeds, members can continue to avail of the opportunity to be briefed by my Department and I will make any member of my team available to provide detailed updates on testing methods and the conclusions that we have drawn.</p><p>  I am joined by officials from my Department, along with Professor Alan Reilly, who is part of the team investigating what happened.  I do not need to remind the committee of the importance of the agrifood industry to our economy in terms of exports and jobs.  The industry's success is based on maintaining the highest standards of food safety and quality.  Our food safety, traceability and quality control systems must be beyond reproach to allow us to provide the assurances necessary to gain and maintain the edge in consumer markets worldwide.  Let us not forget that the vast majority of what we produce on this island is exported to consumers abroad.  The particular food incident under discussion was uncovered as a result of the operation of our multi-layered control systems operated coherently by the Food Safety Authority of Ireland and my Department under service contracts and the use by the Food Safety Authority of advanced testing methods which are not yet routinely used in other jurisdictions.</p><p>  Before I spell out the sequence of events I will briefly outline the control regime that operates in meat plants in Ireland, because there is a degree of confusion in this regard.  Under EU law, primary responsibility for safety of food placed on the market lies with food business operators.  The role of my Department is to verify compliance with the requirement by food business operators.  This is done through a combination of inspection of establishments and audit of the food safety management systems that operators are required to have in place.  These controls are applied at different stages of the food supply chain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.15" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500006#K00200"><p>I thank the Chairman for inviting the Food Safety Authority of Ireland to update the committee on our study investigating the authenticity of meat products on the Irish market.  In making this presentation and addressing the committee's queries I am joined by my colleague, Raymond Ellard, director of the FSAI consumer protection division.  The FSAI has brought to light some very poor practice within the burger manufacturing industry which really is not acceptable, although it remains to be seen whether this is as a result of carelessness, collusion or deliberate fraud.</p><p>  The FSAI was established in 1999 as the national body with responsibility for enforcement of food law in Ireland.  We are a statutory, independent, science-based agency dedicated to protecting public health and consumers' interests in the area of food safety.  We were set up to be independent of the food industry and we operate under the aegis of the Minister for Health.  The FSAI's principal role is to take all reasonable steps to ensure that the food consumed, distributed, marketed and produced in Ireland meets the highest standards of food safety and hygiene.  We were also charged with bringing about the general acceptance that the primary responsibility for the safety of food is borne by the food industry across the whole food chain.  Over the past 14 years the FSAI has worked in partnership with all interested parties to ensure a consistent standard of enforcement of food legislation and to underpin food law with science-based risk assessment.</p><p>  The FSAI oversees an extensive programme of food testing in Ireland to safeguard consumer health in respect of food and to assess compliance by the industry with labelling and other relevant legislation.  Annual monitoring programmes are agreed with official agencies that work under service contract to the FSAI.  Based on a collective risk assessment and the requirements of regulations, these programmes cover a diverse range of micro-organisms and chemical compounds that are tested in a network of official laboratories.  The Minister spoke about some components of these programmes.</p><p>  Each year the FSAI organises additional surveys across a range of foodstuffs.  The survey on the authenticity of meat products was one of these.  Since 2005 we have used DNA testing for similar surveys which have examined the authenticity of chicken fillets and smoked, wild and farmed salmon and compared the authenticity of some of these products.  In 2012 we selected meat products for examination using sophisticated DNA-based analytical techniques to differentiate between animal species present.  This was a routine survey examining the authenticity of beef meal products, salamis and beefburger products.  We tested for pork, beef and horse DNA.  Contrary to some speculation, it was a random survey.  Our ongoing work is guided by a combination of scientific risk assessment and common sense.  The survey was carried out against a background of increasing prices of raw material used in food and feed manufacture and global sourcing of ingredients.  This can lead to a temptation to cut corners and to substitute cheaper raw materials for higher-priced ingredients.  The longer the food supply chain, the higher the risk that something may go wrong, such as the sourcing of ingredients containing horse DNA.  In conducting the survey we uncovered a problem which might otherwise have gone undetected or have been discovered first in our overseas markets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500008#M00200"><p>I thank Professor Alan Reilly and the Minister for their very comprehensive presentations.  It is a great pity that the Minister did not facilitate his officials and Professor Reilly by having them appear before this committee two weeks ago because most of the information given by the Food Safety Authority of Ireland relates to the period prior to 15 January.  It would have been very useful if all the information had been put into the public domain immediately.  This committee is probably the best place to make the information available because members, on behalf of the people who elect us, get an opportunity to ask relevant questions.  The integrity of the beef industry is incredibly important to this country.  As has been said, everything we do here is to ensure that confidence in the industry is maintained.  We must ensure that if there is a problem, we get to the bottom of it and deal with it.  It is important to stress there was no risk to human health.</p><p>  A number of issues arise from the presentations.  At what stage did Professor Reilly realise there was definitely a potentially serious problem?  When he did, did he inform the relevant line Minister, the Minister for Health?  The Food Safety Authority of Ireland was set up purposely under the Ministry for Health so we would not have industry capture.  At what stage were the Minister for Health and his Department informed?  At what stage was the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine informed?  When it was asked for the samples in December, did it know there was a potential problem?  At what level in the Department was the problem flagged?  When the officials became aware of the issue, did they inform the Minister that there was an unproven, but potentially serious, problem that would have to be dealt with?  It is important that there be clarity on that issue.</p><p>  The information going to the Department is so important because the paper trail pertaining to the purchase of ingredients is the key.  I accept that the level of pork contamination could be explained by the killing of the two species in the one factory.  When the Department became aware of the problem, even if the likelihood thereof had been but 10 to 1 because horse DNA was not expected, did it immediately carry out an unannounced visit to the premises to inspect the books to determine the source of all incoming ingredients?  The quicker this information is obtained, the lower the chance of something going wrong.  Perhaps this could be clarified today.  After Professor Alan Reilly became aware that there was a possibility of a problem, however small, was the Department informed and was an inspection carried out in the plants?  Did those running the plants know before they were inspected that some issues had been identified?  Knowing this is crucial.  I accept that although the DNA samples proved positive, the quantity was not known and that this took a while to establish.  Was all the contamination of beef by pork at such a low level as to be attributable to minor cross-contamination?</p><p>  On 16 January, the Minister stated in the D&aacute;il that a number of individual ingredients were imported into the State, specifically from Spain and Holland.  Having heard what Professor Reilly said, it appears it was known at that stage that the traces were very small.  Does the Minister now accept that this was not the source of the problem?  He stated there was no evidence from the investigation conducted at the time to show the manufacturer knowingly bought in equine meat for use in the production of the burgers.  Is this still his position?</p><p>  Will the Minister outline the nature of the Garda investigation and the people and companies being investigated?  Very early in the process, the issue of labelling must have become apparent to the Department.  In other words, the Minister knew at the commencement of the investigation to find the source of the factories' ingredients that those ingredients had been imported.  This must have put up a red flag indicating that there was incorrect labelling, given that the beefburgers were being sold as Irish.</p><p>  Is the Minister absolutely sure that no Irish horsemeat is entering the food chain in this country, either directly or indirectly?  Could we have categoric assurance in regard to this?  Has the Minister raised the issue of standards?  Considering that the Poles are stating they are not licensing horsemeat for ingredients or labelling it, has the Minister raised the issue of EU standards and controls at the meeting of the Council of Ministers and with the EU Commission?  He is President of the Council at present.  What steps have been taken at EU level to ensure other member states are applying the same standards we are applying?  It is important that we recognise the first flaw is that people were mislabelling products by labelling as Irish products into which they were putting foreign ingredients.  This is a European problem of mislabelling.  It is a very great concern because, according to what the Minister stated earlier in the D&aacute;il, purchasers did not realise what they were buying.  Some 29% of the meat in the burgers was horsemeat, according to the professor.  I presume Irish beef was the main ingredient.  Does this mean that the extra, imported ingredients - the trimmings, I believe - were 100% horsemeat?  </p><p>  There are many serious questions to be asked.  We need an independent investigation to get to the bottom of them and determine what is happening in regard to horsemeat in Europe, including Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500008#M00300"><p>I thank the Minister and the officials from the Food Safety Authority of Ireland for their presentations.  I welcome the fact that the Minister and his officials obliged me when I requested a meeting with them.  I thank him for that.  The meeting was very helpful in our examination of this matter.</p><p>  Food processors carry out regular tests themselves.  Is the Department privy to the results of these tests?  Has it been notified of any tests carried out by the processors?  If so, was there any indication of contamination in any of the ingredients?</p> <p>Can the Minister confirm that Silvercrest bought meat ingredients directly from Poland?  Was it a victim of fraud or did it buy the product knowing it was horsemeat?  How confident are the Minister and the Food Safety Authority of Ireland that the contaminated ingredient originated in Poland?  From the report today and the report I got previously, it was traced to a company in Poland.  Is there any connection between the said company and the owners or directors of the processors in this country?  I understand from the Minister's presentation that he is in contact with his counterparts on the other side of our island, across the Border.  Has any evidence come to light of contamination there and on sources of allegations of contamination?  Have there been any dealings between a third party and Silvercrest or any other company in regard to ingredients for fillers for burgers?  </p><p> What is the connection between Rangeland and Silvercrest?  Is there any connection through ownership or is there any connection between senior members of either company?  In his presentation, the Minister was very critical of the way Silvercrest was run by its management and so forth.  Is he satisfied that the management was implementing its own policy in regard to what was happening, or was it getting instructions to that effect?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500009#N00200"><p>I will try to answer some of the questions and maybe Professor Reilly will pick up on some of the technical ones.  I thank Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v for his questions.  Professor Reilly will confirm this, but my understanding is that 29% of the meat in the burger contained equine DNA as opposed to beef.  Sixty-three percent of that burger was meat and the rest was filler.  Effectively, 20% of the burger contained equine DNA - that is, some form of horsemeat.  That is my understanding, but Professor Reilly can clarify that.</p><p>  On whether I raised this with the Commission of the European Union, I have not to date because it is important to get to the bottom of what happened before we do that.  I do not want to go off half-cocked to the Commission in terms of making claims or accusations without knowing what I am talking about and what we are dealing with.  The first thing we need to do is to get to the bottom of what happened - who is responsible for it, who made the decisions, who added horsemeat to consignments of beef product and at what point in the chain did that happen, what regulations were broken, whether there was fraud involved and all of the other questions to which I am confident we will have answers in the not too distant future.  When we have those answers, then let us look at what EU regulations were breached and whether there were control systems that should have picked that up here, in Poland or elsewhere.  At that point, I will happily raise the issue with the Commission if it is appropriate to do so.</p><p>  I was asked whether I am sure there is no Irish horsemeat in the food chain.  I am as sure as I can be that there is not, but what I would say to members or to anybody else in the country who has evidence to the contrary is to let me have it.  We only have two plants in the country slaughtering horses, although there were more until recently.  Our records will show that of all horses slaughtered in Ireland, all of the horsemeat destined for human consumption is exported from Ireland, but as I said, if there is evidence to the contrary, I need to know that.  However, in this particular investigation, none of the product sourced from Irish-supplied ingredients tested positive for equine DNA.  It is important to say that.  That has consistently been the case, and we have tested a lot of ingredients.</p><p>  On the issue of labelling produce as Irish beef, there is a requirement on sellers of pure beef product to have country-of-origin labelling, but if it is a processed product there is no requirement to have country-of-origin labelling.  If somebody chooses to put a label on a product on a voluntary basis, then he or she is obliged to give accurate data on that label.  One will often see country-of-origin labelling on products in supermarkets, which is done on a voluntary basis.  From next year on, we will introduce country-of-origin labelling EU-wide for other meat products in the same way we do for beef.  There is a labelling issue with regard to processed products that have multiple ingredients.  That is important.  The commentary members got from Tesco and Burger King in regard to severing ties with Silvercrest were to do with breach of contract, as the company had given an assurance to its customers that it would supply Irish-only beef in those products, but it did not do so, and the consequences of that were clear.  That is not necessarily illegal.  It is important to highlight the difference between the two.  One can breach a contract with a customer but that does not mean one is breaking the law from a labelling point of view.</p><p>  On the most recent finding with regard to Rangeland, our understanding is that there was not a breach of contract in regard to the labelling of sources of ingredients because the company has told us - the investigation will either confirm or contradict this - that the product it was importing from abroad was going into burgers which were being exported to catering customers outside Ireland and that its product for Irish customers, of which Supermac's is the largest, involved all home-grown or Irish beef.  The head of Supermac's confirmed again today that he is satisfied that this is the case, but we will have to independently verify that through the teams of people investigating.  </p><p>  In regard to the nature of the Garda investigation, Professor Reilly and I spoke to Assistant Garda Commissioner, Derek Byrne, last night.  I asked him if the National Bureau of Criminal Investigation would involve itself in this joint investigation.  He was happy to oblige and as of this morning, the garda&iacute; involved in the investigation have got a detailed briefing and an update on the story so far.  From now on, they will be very much involved in assessing the paperwork, the supply chain and everybody involved in it and, indeed, the processing facilities concerned.</p><p>  I made the statement on 16 January that in my view, given the information we had available to us, nobody in Silvercrest was knowingly importing horsemeat.  Given the information I have in terms of paperwork, orders and so on, that is still the case.  I have no reason to believe anybody was knowingly importing horsemeat into Silvercrest, and it is important to say that.  On 16 January I repeated the press statement Professor Reilly outlined - which was made the day before, on 15 January - that ingredients from Spain and the Netherlands had tested positive for traces of equine DNA, but I also made the point, and have subsequently made it over and over, that despite some commentary over the weekend, I was not pointing the finger at any one country or any one company until I had proof to back it up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500010#O00200"><p>Does Professor Reilly have anything to add?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.24" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500010#O00300"><p>Yes.  The Minister has answered most of the questions, but the one I will address is when we realised we had a problem.  I realised we had a serious problem late in the evening on Friday, 11 January.  We had received the results from IdentiGEN and I went home and had a very uncomfortable weekend thinking about what we would do.  We had started the work of taking samples and so on in the middle of November.  When we had received initial results, I was saying there had to be something wrong; that this could not be happening.  We were finding it difficult to believe we had horsemeat in burgers.  We tested, took more samples, retested, went to another laboratory to confirm the results and so on.  We went at it hammer and tongs with respect to the science because we had to be sure.  If we had come out with a half-cocked story about horsemeat in the meat industry on the market, we would have been crucified.  I would be sitting here today and members would be asking me the reason I had come out with such a half-cocked story, why I had not verified the results and so on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00200"><p>Perhaps I can ask a question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00300"><p>Very quickly, Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00400"><p>If the amount of filler in a beefburger is, say, 30% and the remainder is 70%, excluding onions or whatever else is added, and the burger is found to contain 29% equine DNA, would that, more or less, lead to one to conclude that all of the filler was horsemeat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.29" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00500"><p>The answer to that question is "No".  That particular burger was declared as having 63% meat.  Of that 63%, 29% was equine meat and the remainder was bovine meat.  We are not talking about the filler, the rusk and all the rest of what goes into it - only the meat content.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00600"><p>To be absolutely clear - because the public want to know this - in Professor Reilly's estimate, 29% of the 63% of the burger that was supposed to be beef was horsemeat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.31" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00650"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00700"><p>So that was about 20% of the burger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00800"><p>Yes, but 29% of the meat in the burger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.34" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P00900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01000"><p>In the manufacturing process, was the manufacturer taking so-called beef from various sources to make up the burger?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01100"><p>I can answer that question if the Deputy wants.  "Yes" is the answer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01200"><p>Sorry; I think the scientist who did the experiment and was in charge of the thing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01300"><p>Will Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v please clarify that question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01400"><p>This goes to the nub of the issue.  If we forget about the rest of the burger, 63% of the burger is meat.  Of that 63%, 29% - nearly 30% - is horsemeat.  In making that burger and adding the meat to the burger, was the manufacturer using two sources of meat, from two different suppliers, to make that burger, and were they being mixed?  Is that what was happening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01500"><p>Can the Deputy-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01600"><p>I can be helpful here.  When one looks at the records - this is not a scientific thing - one can establish what goes into burgers by looking at the ingredients records, assuming one has been given accurate information.  That obviously has to be verified.  With any burger - this is an example of a batch of samples with ingredients going into individual burgers, some of which tested positive - one will see different meats going in from different sources.  When the overall product is tested, one can establish the amount of bovine DNA versus equine DNA in terms of the meat content, but different batches have different ingredients-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01700"><p>But the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01800"><p>-----and there are many different suppliers.  Some people think that Silvercrest slaughters.  It does not.  Silvercrest is a processing facility, and all of the 200 million burgers per year that it processes are made up of ingredients that come from lots of different sources, including other factories - meat cuts and low-value meat, in most cases, that are made into burger material and sent frozen into the frozen stores within Silvercrest.  They are then taken out and it is decided to mix a batch.  The appropriate ingredients are put into the mixer and these go through the system to be turned into a burger.  The reason our investigation took some time was that we had to try to match up the ingredients going into individual batches, which change every half hour, and try to correlate ingredients that were testing positive for equine DNA with burgers that were testing positive to try to find a common problem ingredient, which is where the Polish-labelled material came in.  That is how the burgers are made up.</p><p>  With regard to the rest of the industry, it is important to say that it is unusual for a burger to contain only 63% meat.  Most burgers have a much higher meat content.  Of all the burgers we tested this time, 63% was the lowest meat content.  I understand that in contracts between burger manufacturers and their clients, there is a requirement to hit a certain percentage of meat in all burgers and obviously that should be adhered to, but it is not always adhered to.  That is how the system and the process works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P01900"><p>The answer to the question I asked is "Yes".  A mixture of various meats goes into the burger.  If the equine DNA percentage was as high as 29%, can we take it that, in all probability, at least one of the ingredients was pure equine?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.45" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P02000"><p>The Polish product was described as beef trim.  Somebody had mixed in some horse tissue or horsemeat into that beef trim at a fairly high level.  That is the bottom line.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P02100"><p>To be helpful, the tests that were made public yesterday on the held batches at Rangeland Foods Limited and the company in the North showed a horsemeat content of 75%.  That is probably the best indication of the content.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P02300"><p>That is for all intents and purposes pure horsemeat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500011#P02400"><p>That is probably the best indication of the level of equine content in those mixtures.  It may not be 100% but it could be up to 75%, or perhaps 79%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500012#Q00100"><p>The Minister spoke about an ingredient trader who was involved in dealing with the companies that were mentioned.  I assume that trader supplied ingredients to Silvercrest and Rangeland.  Has this individual trader any connection with ABP?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500012#Q00200"><p>Not that I am aware of, apart from the fact that he was supplying product to Silvercrest.  Last Friday, the FSAI, along with a local authority vet, entered that specific trader's premises and office and acquired all of his files and computer disks so he is very much part of the investigation.  I understand he has been named in the media but that is not as a result of anything we have said.  Obviously, we need to establish what he knew and when he knew it.  That is happening this afternoon and I understand he is being very co-operative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500012#Q00300"><p>I thank the Minister and Professor Reilly for coming in today to address the committee.  I have a number of questions, some of which are for Professor Reilly and some for the Minister.  In his contribution, Professor Reilly stated that the survey was carried out against the background of increasing prices of raw materials using food and feed manufacture and the global sourcing of ingredients, which can lead to a temptation to cut corners and substitute cheaper raw materials for higher-priced ingredients.  In the previous paragraph, he said that the decision to test for DNA in the meat products was guided by a combination of scientific risk assessment and common sense.  Did the FSAI have any prior knowledge in advance of initiating the testing programme given the explanation in that paragraph and the scientific risk assessment?  Given the amount of beef, pork and sheepmeat processed in this country, why did the FSAI not test for sheepmeat when it was testing for the DNA and why did it select horsemeat instead of sheepmeat?  I would have thought that if there was cross-contamination, it would be quite possible for it to involve sheep.</p><p>  In respect of lessons to be learned, the final page of Professor Reilly's presentation stated that a key lesson for the food industry is that there should be robust supplier control and verification of supply, that when purchasing raw materials for inclusion in processed meat products, it is necessary to ensure that all ingredients are lawfully declared, and that knowledge of primary and secondary suppliers is essential.  I would have thought this would have been standard in the food processing sector in this country.  I wonder why Professor Reilly felt it necessary to include that as a lesson to be learned given the size of Silvercrest.  One would imagine that it would have had robust procedures in place and would have been required by its customers to have those procedures.  </p><p>  The Minister has been quoted in newspapers on 2 February 2013 talking about the very poor management at the Silvercrest facility and how he was going to work hard to win back the contracts that have been lost.  Is the intention to win back the contracts under Silvercrest, given that its facility is very modern, as the Minister stated?  How could he have faith in ABP to put in place management that would be responsible in that facility?  Is it appropriate for the Minister to work to get contracts for a facility and management that have shown such a breach of trust?  </p><p>  The Minister outlined in his contribution the number of infections that take place.  I previously worked in a meat factory where one would regularly see vets inspecting the product.  There were over 7,000 infections in 2011 in the meat sector.  How robust is the auditing process given that the management at the Silvercrest plant was so poor and deficient?  I understand the vets would look at the ingredient processes and whether ingredients were being sourced and used in the proper way.  Is one of the lessons to come out of this that the auditing process needs to be looked at and revamped?</p><p>  Why does the Minister now feel it necessary to involve the special investigations unit and the Garda?  What has changed in the past few days to make him think he needs to involve them in the investigation?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500012#Q00400"><p>I thank the Minister and Professor Reilly for coming before the committee.  I have questions for both of them.  Has the Minister and his Department knowledge of how long these bulking agents that have affected our precious beef industry been used in these processing plants?  Following on from the Minister's statement and one of his earlier comments, why would Silvercrest buy from Poland through three different channels - a meat trader in Ireland, one in the UK and directly?  Has anybody in the Department measured the commercial gain or margin that would have been gained by the likes of Silvercrest by putting 29% equine material into a beefburger?  If we lived in France, what would be the difference in price per kilo between beef and horsemeat because we need to educate ourselves in this area?</p><p>  Is testing on all our meat processors being stepped up and are any other processes or meat traders under suspicion at present?  I admire the investigation that the Minister is pushing and the fact that he brought in the fraud squad.  The law is the law but if I have a big contract with Burger King, say my product is 100% beef but do not give it to Burger King, I have not broken the law.  I will probably just lose my business.  Once the Minister finishes his investigations, I hope there will be consequences and I want him to ask whether there will be consequences for the companies involved.  They are not just affecting themselves and their own livelihoods; they are affecting the entire Irish beef industry.  </p><p>  We confirmed that Silvercrest does not slaughter its own animals but we must note that it only makes up 4% of the ABP food group.  That is an enormous beef industry.  Previous speakers asked us to make sure there were no connections between any of its other companies in these investigations.  Could the Minister confirm the report in <i>The Irish Times</i> and let us know how things are going with Poland?  According to the report by Derek Scally, who is in Warsaw, there is upset in Poland.  The article stated:<blockquote>&quot;Such accusations not grounded by any sound evidence are inacceptable, regardless of what they pertain to,&quot; Stanislaw Kalemba, Poland's minister for agriculture told The Irish Times.  He noted how many recent food scares ended with the first countries named as culprits later cleared.</blockquote>Could the Minister clear up the situation between himself and Poland?  When will we have exact evidence and when will Poland put up its hands up and say it was responsible?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500012#Q00500"><p>I consistently said as late as last night that I am not condemning all Polish food and putting a question mark over it.  Much of the food imported from Poland into Ireland is of very high quality and comes from certified plant.  We have a very large Polish population in Ireland and many members of it import food.  Other food companies import product from Poland in the same way as they do from other countries in the EU.  That is what a common market is all about and because of that common market, we have a large food industry which is predominantly based on exports.  We should not give out about food that is imported into Ireland when we export nearly 90% of the food we produce.</p><p>  The problem is that all of the ingredient we tested - the only ingredient that has consistently tested positive for significant amounts of equine DNA - is labelled as coming from Poland.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.55" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500013#R00200"><p>On the question of whether the Food Safety Authority of Ireland had any prior knowledge of what we found, we did not have such knowledge.  It is that simple.  In collaboration with our counterparts at the European Food Safety Authority and other food safety agencies around Europe, we look at emerging risk analysis.  We try to do horizon-scanning in an effort to identify what could be the next risks associated with food which will need to be dealt with.  A broad category of risk is associated with substitution and the sourcing of cheap ingredients from different parts of the world.  Some previous food scares have been associated with such ingredients.  We are looking at the opportunities for species substitution - using one species and calling it another.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500014#S00200"><p>Why does the Food Safety Authority of Ireland not test for sheepmeat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500014#S00300"><p>To be quite honest, we were not particularly interested in sheepmeat.  Having looked at some of the results we got back, there were traces of sheepmeat in one or two of the composite products which were supplied from the Netherlands.  Again, one has low traces of these species in these products.  There is no commercial advantage from that type of contamination; it just happens in the processing conditions.  For us, sheepmeat was not an issue.  We chose three species - beef, pork and horse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500014#S00400"><p>When will the contracts lost by the Silvercrest be won back?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500014#S00500"><p>Let me be straight with Deputy Pringle.  I cannot give him the detailed answer he wants because there are ongoing discussions which we hope will be helpful in securing the jobs at Silvercrest.  They are commercially sensitive at this point.  If contracts are to be rebuilt to allow the infrastructure at Silvercrest to be providing large volumes of burgers to clients, something fundamental needs to change to facilitate that.  I have been working with the industry and the clients concerned to find a way to do that.  We have made some progress but I am not in a position to be able to give the Deputy any more detail on it.</p><p>  I can assure the Deputy that we have not forgotten about the 140 or so people working at Silvercrest who are innocent victims in this.  Likewise, it was the same problem last night for people working in Rangeland who had nothing to do with this scandal.  We are working with the industry from an Ireland Inc. point of view.  We want to be supplying large customers like Burger King and Tesco in the UK.  It is my job to facilitate progress to do this.  When I am in a position to give more detail on this, I will do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500014#S00600"><p>I welcome the Minister and Professor Reilly to the committee.  Over the past 20 years much hard work has been done by stakeholders in the meat industry to bring it to be worth &euro;2 billion and much more to the economy.  Farmers, the primary producers, have had to endure on-the-spot inspections which could result in penalties for minor incidents.  There does not seem to be the same level of inspection in the meat processing plants like Silvercrest.  Are the monthly audits unannounced or is prior notice given?  Has any processing plant endured any penalties for failing to comply with standards?</p><p>  Ireland exports 500,000 tonnes of beef every year.  Why do we need to import 45,000 tonnes?  If that amount of beef is available, why should Silvercrest have gone to Poland to import this particular contaminated product?  Is it not available here or is the Irish equivalent too expensive?  We have heard much talk about the middlemen meat traders.  Is there a list of these traders?  Are they registered and licensed?  What regulatory system is in place for them?</p><p>  I welcome the Garda investigation into this matter.  Has it a particular timeframe?  Everyone will agree the sooner this particular issue is taken off the agenda, the better.  From the Minister's perspective, there are many important negotiations going on in Europe which will have consequences for the country's future.  It is important this issue is brought to a conclusion as soon as possible.  While it is important the investigation is detailed so as to get to the bottom of this matter, a definite timescale should be in place.</p><p>  Ireland's reputation is very much at stake in this regard.  The Minister summed it up when he said the management of Silvercrest left a lot to be desired.  How long has this management team been in place?  If it has been such a bad team, how has it survived so long to bring us to the stage of doing serious damage to the industry and bringing the whole industry down around it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/977" speakername="Michael McNamara" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500014#S00700"><p>I thank the Minister and Professor Reilly for their candour.  Professor Reilly stated research is required to determine if there are thresholds below which cross-contamination is unavoidable.  What does this mean to the ordinary consumer?  For example, if I use a knife to cut beef, simply wash it under the tap and use it to cut pork, will that lead to cross-contamination?</p><p>  We are hearing much about beef trimmings used in these burgers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.64" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00200"><p>First, I will deal with the DNA issue and what is an unavoidable level.  We need to establish what is unavoidable.  When one is using mitochondrial DNA one can detect even ten or 100 cells.  That is the level of equine, porcine or beef material one can detect.  We do not wish to introduce a testing regime to put the industry in a straitjacket in which it cannot operate.  There must be some form of tolerance in industry to allow the use of the same premises for processing different species and to allow some form of unavoidable crossover.  We must establish this and get agreement with other trading partners in Europe such that we can all work to a given standard.</p><p>  The most practical way would be to consider the quantification system.  The quantification method used in this test involved nuclear DNA.  There is a good deal less nuclear DNA in a cell than mitochondrial DNA; there is probably 10,000 times more mitochondrial DNA.  Quantification is a less sensitive method.  If we are to use that method with a limit of quantification of 0.1, it could become the standard for crossover contamination and it would be a practical measure.  We must try to get European-wide agreement for that way of thinking.  There is something else the industry could do.  If there is unavoidable contamination with different species a business could label a product in a certain way.  For example, the label could indicate that a given beef burger was manufactured in a premises that also processes pork.  That would give a consumer some indication.</p><p>  It is different when it comes to the strict faith groups.  For example, for Muslims in the case of halal meat there is no limit of crossover.  One must ring-fence halal food in production.  For example, if one is processing halal beef, it must be processed in a premises altogether separate from any other species such as pork and so on.</p><p>  These issues have all been thrown up by the study we carried out.  We need to hold a broader discussion industry-wide with stakeholders to try to reason things out and determine what the industry norm should be.  What our testing system has done will raise the bar for consumer protection.  Tesco has already gone down the road and committed to introducing this form of testing.  There will be greater protection for consumers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/977" speakername="Michael McNamara" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00300"><p>Is it possible to use the kitchen knife analogy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.66" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00400"><p>One could detect traces with a kitchen knife.  If one sliced beef with a knife and then one sliced pork with it, one could possibly detect some cells.  However, we are discussing commercial conditions in which tens of tonnes of meat go down a processing line and people clean out the line afterwards.  However, what degree of cleaning is necessary?  How likely is a person to leave behind traces?  Any system that is eventually adopted will have to have built in this type of testing within each processing facility, probably once or twice per year.  After cleaning down, an operator must consider the traces left behind such that it can give guarantees to its customers that there will be no such crossover contamination.</p><p>  To answer Deputy McNamara's question, if after slicing meat I gave the knife a good clean I would probably get rid of any contamination, but if I only gave it a quick wipe it may be different.  Perhaps under commercial or industrial conditions one might not employ the same strict hygiene that one would have in one's own kitchen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00500"><p>A question was asked about beef trimmings.  Essentially, they are the bits and pieces of the carcass that remain when the prime cuts are removed.  It is basically the cheap meat that does not have a market of itself.  From what I have seen in the cold storage facilities in factories such as the plant in question, beef product is pushed together and then traded as an ice block of product.  One reason we have been able to test samples that go back some time is that the factories have storage facilities that are run at -20&deg; Celsius, or colder in some cases, and this allows them to store such blocks of product that arrive in refrigerated containers.  Then they are used while the production process mixes the various ingredients to make the type of burger that the factory is supplying.</p><p>  I wish to back up what Professor Reilly said.  If a person applies DNA testing of the type applied to a murder scene, which might involve examining under a person's fingernails or testing whether there is DNA on a telephone and so on, one will pick up tiny traces of anything and everything.  We need to figure out how to use this technology to ensure that if people are adding ingredients inappropriately then we can spot it quickly through testing.  At the same time, we have to accept that food is not manufactured or produced in the same type of environment as an operating theatre in a hospital or a laboratory.  That is not how these plant work, even if they are power-hosed, deep-cleaned, sanitised and so on.  There must be some threshold which is not unreasonable and which will not cause a food scandal any time a factory is under that threshold.  However, we must also have a threshold above which the consumer has a right to know.  The industry accepts that this is the direction we are going now and we need to put in place a protocol to make that happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/977" speakername="Michael McNamara" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00600"><p>Does a normal butcher have beef trimmings at his or her disposal?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00700"><p>Yes, some of them probably would.  If a butcher is deboning in his or her butchery, he or she will have leftover meats.  This stuff is not necessarily bad for people.  In the case of soups, sauces, chicken stocks and so on, one is eating material which has been either flavoured by or involves a good deal of the product in question.  It may not look particularly nice or we might not like the idea that we are eating desinewed meat, but it is not necessarily bad for people.  There is no health risk necessarily as long as we do all the tests for food safety.  However, that is different to selling something to a consumer and labelling it as something when, in fact, it is something else.  That is essentially what has happened here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00800"><p>What is the position on Deputy Deering's questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500015#T00900"><p>I am unsure how long the management at Silvercrest Foods has been in place.  I imagine the management system has changed and evolved over time.  Clearly the management in recent times has not been supplying to its customers what it should have been supplying under contract, and that is what I mean by bad practice.  It is not necessarily a breach of the law but it has resulted in Tesco and Burger King moving away from that facility for supply.  It is not simply a horsemeat issue and both companies made that clear in their statements.  I do not wish to get into the issue of bad management.  If there is a breach of the law, then we will get involved.</p><p>  The reputational issues have caused a good deal of damage and that is rather frustrating for someone such as me and for many other people in the food industry who are trying to build a reputation on the back of good practice.</p><p>  Many meat traders are also meat suppliers and have a trading arm as well as a production facility.  There are also middlemen meat traders who buy and sell on meat, somewhat like meat brokers.  They are licensed as businesses but there is no particular licence that our Department gives them to operate.  Perhaps that is something we need to consider.  Let us wait and see the final results of the investigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500016#U00200"><p>Was a timeline set for the Garda investigation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500016#U00300"><p>It will continue for as long as it takes.  For obvious reasons, we have put the team under pressure to get results as quickly as it can, but I am not going to rush it regardless of what people may say.  Similarly, we have not rushed the Silvercrest investigation.  I suspect legal cases and litigation over compensation will be pursued at the end of this process.  Before we establish the facts we need to gather sufficient evidence to develop a credible case, backed up by testing and the interviews that are ongoing.  The sooner we can draw this to a conclusion the better, but I want to be able to stand over the final results.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/968" speakername="Pat Deering" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500016#U00400"><p>Has any factory or processing plant been penalised in the past year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500016#U00500"><p>I do not know whether that has happened in the past year, but I understand plants have been told to suspend production and have lost certification for certain types of production at different times.  I will have to revert to the Deputy regarding the last 12 months because I do not have the figures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500016#U00600"><p>I ask forgiveness if I do not scratch my head about some of what has happened.  I am, however, puzzled as to why the Department was not notified earlier than January.  I appreciate the need to ensure the tests were correct before the Food Safety Authority could announce publicly that a problem had arisen but I do not know why the Department would not at least be informally notified about the unexpected presence of equine DNA.  <i>The Sunday Times</i> reported in May 2012 that it had been following lorry loads of horses to abattoirs in Ireland, Britain and Europe and that it had observed abattoirs being opened up late at night to receive horses for slaughter.  We should not have been surprised that horsemeat was in the system in the wrong way and I am concerned that the Department did not learn about the matter earlier.</p><p>  How old were the boxes of frozen meat which were carefully tested and what state were they in?  Had they been thawed and refrozen?  Was there any evidence of tampering with labels or did the authority not look for that information given that, in fairness, it was on a DNA chase rather than a label-tampering chase?  Surely the boxes were examined by somebody, however.  Are standards in place in the Department for the length of time that frozen meat can be stored?  There have been stories about meat being thawed and refrozen or relabelled.  The announcement by Polish officials that they tested the plants in that country last week but found no trace of equine DNA would not be surprising if these boxes were older than six months.  Perhaps the plants have been cleaned up but there appears to be a discrepancy.</p><p>  I appreciate the description given of beef trim.  Does the market trade in trim to the extent that it can be divided into lean trim and scrag trim or better trim and worse trim?  I understand that is the case but I am open to correction.</p><p>  Is the Minister satisfied with the progress thus far?  I recognise that the process is painful and slow but here we are in February with a number of questions still unanswered.  I am concerned about the length of time this investigation has taken.  I appreciate the Minister's dilemma but I wonder if he has a shortage of manpower.  Was the special investigation unit deployed on foot of the aforementioned report in <i>The Sunday Times</i>?  What sort of expertise does the unit contain in regard to horsemeat and potential imports of meat from Poland?</p><p>  If somebody puts a sticker containing the word &quot;Taoiseach&quot; on my back, it will not make me Taoiseach.  A label can be put on anything.  How knowledgeable is the Minister at this stage in regard to the level of labelling carried out?  His officials will be aware that the capacity to alter labels has existed for many years.  I am not surmising or speaking about cloud cuckoo land.  I know it can be done and that paper trails can be adequately altered.  Is there any evidence of such practices and what are the Minister's views on it?</p><p>  People in the industry have said it is an open secret that Silvercrest was a mess prior to this incident.  I appreciate that departmental officials were not based permanently at the plant because it did not slaughter animals, but the Department certainly maintained a presence.  Silvercrest is not obliged to share certain information due to commercial sensitivities but I am concerned that the matter has come to this.  Did anybody employed by the Department make a complaint of any description about Silvercrest?  Perhaps somebody noted that extra boxes were being delivered, that the stores were open late at night or that people were being paid overtime apparently without need.  The Minister will know exactly what I am speaking about.  Was such behaviour brought to the Department's attention and, if so, was anything done about it?  If nothing was done, why not?</p><p>  The Polish officials have been invited here, but is it a matter of invitation at this stage?  Should they not be on the next flight?  I appreciate the problems of interpreting between English and Polish but I am sure we could find some interpreters to help out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00200"><p>That is right.  The Minister said in his contribution that before he went public with the findings that the source was Polish, he contacted the Polish authorities at three different levels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00300"><p>That is correct and I understand that.  However, the information has come to light that there is a Polish connection to this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00400"><p>With all due respect, we cannot instruct Poland to do anything.  It is a separate country and it makes its own decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00500"><p>I appreciate that.  What I was saying is that I am concerned at the status of the invitation.  Will the Minister clarify whether he thinks they are about to come or whether it was only an invitation to come.  Are they or are they not going to come?  I appreciate the Minister must act according to protocol.</p><p>  I have a number of other questions, but I am aware other people may wish to come in.  I would be happy to finish now and come in again later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00600"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00700"><p>I thank the Minister for his attendance and Professor Alan Reilly for providing all the information.  Coming from a farming background, I am aware of the regular and robust inspections conducted by Bord Bia and the Department and of the penalties imposed where there is a lack of compliance and wonder whether the same thing happens within the food industry.  Is the Minister confident that all of the sources have been identified at this stage?  This has dragged on for some weeks and is he happy all of the sources of the horsemeat DNA have been identified?</p><p>  Is it the case that because supermarket chains and retail outlets are forcing down the cost of food to such an extent, people in the industry must try to get the cheapest inputs possible?  Is that the problem?  This brings us to the importance of country of origin labelling.  It is vital product is clearly labelled as to whether it is fully Irish and if so it should be labelled as such.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500017#V00800"><p>I will take those questions in reverse order.  As regards labelling, if a product is a pure meat product, it must have country of origin labelling wherever it goes and there must be full traceability right back to the farmyard.  Ireland has better traceability than any other country of which I am aware in terms of its systems and how they work.  The problem arises with processed food.  When multiple ingredients are going into the food, there is no requirement for country of origin labelling under current EU labelling rules.  Perhaps that is something that should change.  I would certainly like to see some change there, but that would bring challenges as it is not as simple as it may seem.</p><p>  With regard to the loose comment that this has been dragging on for a number of weeks, it is important to point out that within 11 days of us starting our investigation, we established the source of the problem.  Nobody else had managed to do that.  ABP, Tesco and Burger King could not do it, despite the fact they were all trying.  In a plant of that scale and size and given the testing resources we had available to us and the time needed to test, check and verify the results, it took time to get the facts right so as to ensure we could stand over them.  It is true another week has passed since then, but we are now focused on the supply chain and I hope the Garda and the special investigation unit can be helpful in that regard.  I have explained why I brought them in.</p><p>  With regard to why the Polish side is not here, I must be careful I do not extend my decision making capacity beyond Ireland.  Our job is to try to get to the bottom of what happened here.  We sent as much information as we have available to Poland so that they could see this is not a case of us pointing the finger without significant information to back it up.  We want to work with them to solve this problem and to find out who is responsible, whether those responsible are in Ireland or in Poland or somewhere in between.  We cannot get away from the fact that we have details of containers that came from Poland over a three-day period in one case and over a ten-day period in another.  Those records are now being examined again and are very much a part of the investigation as to how they came here, the transportation company involved, whether the container seals were intact and all of the other standard issues when investigating this type of activity.</p><p>  The comment was made that everybody knew Silvercrest was an open mess.  I did not know that.  Certainly everybody did not know that.  Our inspection team, which has been visiting Silvercrest on a monthly basis for some time, did not know that.  Therefore, it was not commonly known.  We must be careful with our language.  People's livelihoods and jobs are on the line.  I will certainly not stand over or protect practices that are inappropriate and when there is bad management, I am happy to expose it.  My understanding is that Silvercrest operated on a two ten-hour shift basis and people came and went.  Large volumes of burgers were being produced in what is a very modern plant.  I agree there was some bad management and the company must answer for that now.  Horse DNA came in through product that should not have come there and we must now establish whether people knew about that.  I have no evidence now to suggest they did.  I will not cast aspersions on anybody, regardless of who they are, unless I have evidence to back them up.</p><p>  The Department does not have a shortage of manpower to deal with this issue.  Many of the people involved in this investigation are women and there is no shortage of human resources involved.</p><p>  There was a question on whether there is a difference between the types of trimming used.  There is and there is a grading system based on the percentage of visible lean, whether it is 80% or 90%.  The grading system has an impact on the price.  Members can see an example in the document of a product that came in from Poland, which is described as frozen beef trimming 80:20.  This refers to the visible lean reading.  With regard to the age of the frozen beef trimming after which it should not be used, I think the period is 18 months.  All of the products we tested were supplied in 2012, with the exception of one batch from 2011.  Perhaps Professor Reilly can give more detail on that.  I can provide the exact date, if required, later. </p><p>  I have taken a real and personal interest in the issue of the slaughtering of horses.  Since I have come into this Department, the Government has done more for the horse sector, in terms of animal welfare, IDs, the passport system and microchipping, than we have seen done for a long time.  We have changed, enforced and improved the regulations.  There was evidence in the past that horse passports could be purchased far too easily and they were advertised for sale in a way that suggested something was not right.  We have seven certified bodies in Ireland which can issue horse passports.  We removed one of the certified bodies, the Irish Cob Society, last October, because we were not happy there was proper governance there.  Until now, we had a permanent meat inspection presence from the Department in the factories we certified, but none of those is still in operation.  The only two certified equine slaughter houses remaining have, until recently, been supervised under the responsibility of local authorities.  However, I have changed that and we are now taking responsibility for those into the Department.  </p><p>  I have heard it said, particularly by the head of the Ulster Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, that large numbers of horses were being exported out of Ireland, presumably for slaughter. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00200"><p>I also asked whether any of the officials from the Department who worked at Silvercrest had ever reported anything and, if so, whether those reports had been followed up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00300"><p>I am not aware of any such reports.  I am not aware that any breaches of the law, or of food safety standards, were uncovered at Silvercrest.  That is really what we were there to look at.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00400"><p>Had they reported the presence of horsemeat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00500"><p>Obviously, we have sifted through all of the paper and computer records to see if there is any evidence to suggest that horsemeat could have been knowingly imported.  There is no evidence to suggest that.  If such evidence emerges in time, it will be a very serious issue.  There is no evidence to date to suggest that is the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00600"><p>Does Professor Reilly have anything to add?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.92" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00700"><p>I would like to make two points about how long meat can be stored.  The industry norm is that it can be stored at -18&deg; Celsius for approximately six months and at -30&deg; Celsius for approximately two years.  The Senator asked why we did not tell anyone sooner.  I thought I dealt with that in response to Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v's questions.  If we had made this known sooner, in the absence of full knowledge or the full results, I think we would have done immense damage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00800"><p>With respect, I asked why it was not made known informally to the Minister.  I understand completely why it was not made public.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W00900"><p>On 21 December, we asked the Department to take samples of raw materials from the Silvercrest plant.  I asked the officials in question not to mention this to anyone - to keep it to themselves for now - because we did not know what was going on.  We were in the middle of an investigation.  We are living in an era of social media.  If there had been a small hint of what was going on, it would have gone around the world 20 times before I got home that evening that there was a horsemeat problem with Irish products.  One could imagine what would have happened, especially with some of the journalists we have now.  Even within the authority itself, the investigation was limited to a small number of people.  We did not want anything to leak out because of the immense damage it could cause.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W01000"><p>What about the Minister?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.96" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W01100"><p>The Minister's officials were informed that the investigation was ongoing but were told not to do anything because nothing needed to be done.  We could have said we were investigating a problem, but what would have happened if the problem had turned out to be nothing?  One of the things the Food Safety Authority has to do is advise Ministers.  We are not going to go in with a cock-and-bull story that sends a Minister off on a wild goose chase.  We are going to get sound scientific evidence before we lay the information before a Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W01200"><p>I would like to compliment the Minister, Professor Reilly and both bodies.  I do not think this thing could have been rushed.  We had to make sure we had all the facts before we brought them into the public domain.  My sympathies are with the people involved in Ballybay and Castleblayney.  The livelihoods of the workers are being threatened.  Farm families will suffer if this situation has an impact on the beef industry.  Professor Reilly summed it up when he said that trust is the most important thing in any industry and especially in the food industry.  We must bear this in mind, given that we have spent years building our reputation.</p><p>  Most of my questions have been asked.  The Minister said that 7,189 inspections were carried out in 2011.  There is a difference between the type of inspection carried out by the Department and the kind of inspection carried out by the Food Safety Authority of Ireland.  Since 2005, the authority has done DNA testing on chicken fillets, on smoked, wild and farmed salmon and on fish products.  In 2012, it decided to do DNA testing on meat products.  Professor Reilly said:<blockquote>The survey was carried out against a background of increasing prices of raw material used in food and feed manufacture and global sourcing of ingredients.  This can lead to a temptation to cut corners to substitute cheaper raw materials for higher-priced ingredients.</blockquote>Professor Reilly also said that this was a random test.  Was there a high level of suspicion with regard to certain products that were in use in this country?  Was the authority tipped off that other products may have been in use in this country?  Was that why it decided to test certain products from certain plants?  The retailers have a duty here too.  When a retailer tells a plant to source or supply a burger for 9 cent so it can be sold for 20 cent, it should appreciate that it has a duty of care with regard to what goes into the product.  If one tries to drive the price down, one will get a cheaper product.</p><p>  The final question I would like to put to the Minister relates to the Garda inspection.  I welcome the decision to call the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na into this.  We would hope that nobody in Ireland - in the plants or in the meat trade - is tied into the Garda investigation.  If it transpires that this is entirely a Polish problem, what level of co-operation with the Polish police can we expect?  I appreciate that it is early in the process.  If the Garda needs to access records in Poland as part of its investigation, is there any agreement with the police or the ministry in Poland that will enable it to establish certain facts?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500018#W01300"><p>I would like to echo the welcoming comments that have been made.  I thank the Minister and Professor Reilly for their comprehensive statements and replies.  I will pick up on one or two things that have been touched on.  Like Senator O'Neill, I have to say I have not heard any great understanding of the worries of the Silvercrest workers and families in all of this.  The Minister has said on the record that Silvercrest's state-of-the-art plant is currently operating at 50% of its capacity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00200"><p>I will answer Senator O'Neill's questions first.  With regard to whether we will be looking for co-operation from the Polish authorities if there is a police investigation that spans a number of different countries, to be honest, it is too early to give an answer to that.  What I hope will happen is that either we will send a team to Poland to talk through all of our findings, or they will send a team here.  I would like to have more interaction with the Polish authorities in regard to the investigations and testing they are carrying out following what has happened.  We would like to work in partnership to get to the bottom of this.  In the absence of that, for the moment, we are continuing to keep connections open with the Polish authorities on a daily basis but we are also proactively going after this investigation to try to establish the facts.  For all the reasons members have outlined today, we do not want this issue to drag on a day longer than it needs to.</p><p>  With regard to Silvercrest, although I am not sure if Senator Mooney was present, I said earlier that I had been working with the broader industry and with the companies that were supplied with product from Silvercrest, particularly the larger ones, to try to ensure we can keep that business in Ireland.  I do not want to give any more detail on that because there are some sensitive discussions going on at the moment which I do not want to damage.  We are trying to make progress on that and I assure the Senator that the staff at Silvercrest are very much part of our plans in terms of trying to find an answer that can allow that plant to stay open and producing from what is probably the best piece of infrastructure of its type in Europe and arguably in the world.  We are working on that.  As soon as I can be more open about it, I will happily say that.  I am confident we will find a solution but I do not want to over-promise and not deliver.  None the less, it would be wrong to say we are not doing anything.  In fact, we are doing a lot.</p><p>  With regard to pressure from the multiples, there is an idea that the buying power and tight margins of the retail multiples, which are driving down prices, have somehow caused this.  That is no excuse for what has happened here.  Whether one is producing a very cheap product or a fillet steak, the same food safety standards should apply and the same traceability standards should apply if it is appropriate for that product.  We have regulations in this regard.  What is happening here is that different products are being produced with different ingredients at different values.  For example, burgers that are being made for Burger King are actually very high-end product and cost significantly more to produce, and, as a result, the producer is paid significantly more for them.  Companies such as Burger King want to source beef in Ireland because of the quality of our beef and the guarantees around it in terms of sustainability and all the other things we have built up in our sector.  There is also a market for low-cost burgers.  There are people who go to supermarkets who cannot afford to buy the high-end products.  There is no food safety risk in buying cheaper product.  Yes, it is lower value meat, and it is probably a bit tougher and contains off-cuts and trimmings, but it is perfectly safe.  People are in the market for that because it is all they can afford to buy or it is all they want to spend on that type of product.  It is these low-cost frozen burgers which are under the microscope here.</p><p>  It is important to repeat the point that this is not an issue of investigation across the broader beef industry in Ireland.  This is a specific product - frozen beefburgers that are cheaply produced and sold for very low margins at high volume-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00300"><p>Is the Minister completely dismissing price pressure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00400"><p>No, I am not.  I am just saying that, in this investigation, it is no excuse for what happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00500"><p>I am not suggesting that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00600"><p>We are here to talk about the investigation.  On the broader issue, there has been a growing problem in the past ten years.  If one looks at what food producers get from the end price in the supermarket of product sold at retail level, ten years ago they would have got more than 30% of that price, whereas they now get less than 20%.  That is not a trend that is sustainable into the future.  However, we need to address that with broader policies at EU and national level.  One will see, for example, the Government introducing in the next few weeks new legislation with regard to mandatory codes of practice between food suppliers and large multiples.  That, in some ways, is a separate issue to the issues we have here.  A company as large as Silvercrest should be able to produce burgers at the very highest of standards regardless of what it is being paid for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00700"><p>We are talking about six burgers for &euro;2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00800"><p>They should not be supplying them if they cannot provide them with the guarantees that are needed from a safety and contractual point of view.  That is the marketplace; that is how it works.  I am not comfortable with the fact that producers are under pressure - at times, huge pressure - to supply product at very tight margins but we cannot use that as an excuse for what has happened here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X00900"><p>Professor Reilly was to deal with my question on DNA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.108" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500019#X01000"><p>We did not have a tip-off for this study.  We initially went out and took burgers from nine different manufacturers.  When the burgers came back, we focused on those companies where we found burgers to be positive for equine DNA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/949" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500020#Y00200"><p>I will not repeat questions that have been already asked.  I acknowledge the extensive testing carried out by the FSAI and the role of Department officials in this process.  It is a very complex area, as the reports have outlined to us.  It is important for us to bear in mind that DNA testing is what brought this to light.  This was not brought to State organisations and highlighted by an outside body; it was a State organisation that highlighted it through the testing process.  It is important to note this from a consumer confidence perspective.</p><p>  Farmers, as primary producers, have built a reputation on traceability.  There is a significant cost to farmers, who also put in time in respect of paperwork and keeping records in addition to the significant level of examination that happens through cross-compliance and other on-farm measures.  How does that level of on-farm inspection compare with the level of investigation of food processors?  Does the same level of scrutiny exist further down the line?  We talk about traceability from farm to fork and I am happy that from farm to farm gate, our primary producers are pretty impeccable.  It is then very frustrating for farmers to see that the actions of processors can damage the reputation of an industry key to their livelihoods.  I say this while accepting that this material was not for the Irish market and that DNA testing found minute traces in most instances.  </p><p>  Is the system of risk assessment for secondary processors the industry norm for other countries?  Is risk assessment the form of investigation used?  I know we have an open market but I would not be overly happy that as the largest exporter of beef in Europe and the fourth largest exporter of beef in the world, processors here are going to Poland to access this material.  Is that because it is cheaper or due to quantity?  Retailers are putting on the pressure in respect of lower prices in this market but I accept the Minister's point about the forthcoming consumer and competition Bill and welcome the mandatory code of conduct that will be introduced because it will be a key component.  It is probably not directly associated with this issue but it is in the mix as well.  </p><p>  The Minister said he raised the matter with meat processors.  What kind of interaction has he had with them and what has been their response?  Bord Bia initially said it was happy that the market reaction to this was fairly negligible across Europe and anecdotally with consumers in Ireland.  Has that changed as the story has developed or is there any sense that there has been an impact here in terms of market reaction?  </p><p>  What struck me about Rangeland and the product coming from Poland was the fact that it was frozen.  I know it was in a large block and I heard it said earlier that the testing mechanism involved drilling into that block.  Does that product have to be defrosted before it is used to make a burger?  Is it then refrozen, and are there issues around that?  Could the Minister clarify how that process works?  </p><p>  One thing that struck me when the Silvercrest story broke and we heard about the discovery of 29% horse DNA in one of the burgers was that the specific burger had a meat content of 63%, which is very worrying.  I accept the Minister's earlier point that this would not be the norm.  He said that many contracts require a minimum meat content.  Is that purely a matter for contracts or is it one for law?  Is it something we need to look at?  If one goes into one's local butcher, the home-made steak burgers one will get at the higher end are probably 97% or 98% beef, with the exception of a bit of parsley and onion or something to make up the difference.  At what point does a burger stop being a burger if one is getting down to very low meat content levels?  Do we have a threshold below which producers cannot go?  </p><p>  The Minister said last night on television that the Rangeland story was not a huge surprise considering what he found out along the way.  Does he expect us to get to the bottom of this fairly soon, so that we can draw a line under it?  I accept completely that time has to be taken, this has to be done properly and that we must dot the i's and cross the t's, but the drip, drip effect of news is damaging.  We must strike a balance between making sure everything in the investigation is right and making sure it does not drag on any longer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500020#Y00300"><p>Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill is next.  Does he wish to let Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v add something quickly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500020#Y00400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500020#Y00500"><p>I have some very specific questions.  Was there a worry about the possibility of horsemeat contamination that prompted the specific testing for equine material?  The Minister mentioned that specific testing for equine material was carried out.  If the FSAI thought such contamination was the most unlikely thing in the world it probably would not have done so.  Was there a worry that prompted that?</p><p>  Does he accept that if we took a very small random sample from all factories producing beefburgers, one of which is producing 200 million burgers a year, one would have a better chance of winning the national lottery or the EuroMillions than of getting a positive result if this was not a pervasive and continuous practice?  Therefore, we must extrapolate that the likelihood is that this was quite continuous and pervasive.</p><p>  The next question is technical.  Is it possible by DNA matching to determine the origin of the horsemeat?  My understanding is that it is sometimes possible to say that DNA comes from a certain breed in a certain area and in that way, one could find the source of the horsemeat independent of labelling.  Would it be possible, by taking DNA samples from horses in Ireland or Poland, to eliminate any rumours that are circulating?</p><p>  The Minister did not tell me when the Department of Health, as the parent Department, was informed.  Things have changed in the past few years.  When I was a Minister, if there was anything that might have become a problem, one was informed about it on a confidential basis and one kept it to one's self.  I was told many things that might have been problems but turned out not to be and that was the end of it.  I was a bit surprised the Minister was not told earlier about it.  It is a change of practice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500020#Y00600"><p>All of Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v's comments were directed at Professor Reilly so I will let him get his thoughts together and I will deal with Deputy Heydon's questions.  We are all very familiar with the inspection system and the system of traceability for farmers.  In respect of how that compares with the risk assessment and inspections we have in factories, the truth is that there are many more inspections in factories than there are of farmers.  This is how it should be, because of the volumes of food going through.  We are required under regulation to inspect up to 4% of farms that draw down the single farm payment.  Otherwise, we lose the single farm payment in what are called disallowances, so we are required to do that.  There are other inspections on farms and it is because of those inspections that we can stand over the food produced on Irish farms, command higher prices for it and carve out new markets all over the world.</p><p>  In respect of inspections in factories, we have a permanent presence in slaughterhouses.  We do a risk assessment of all other processing facilities and depending on the results of those assessments, as is consistent with EU regulations, we put in place an inspection system that meets that risk and goes way beyond what is required of us in terms of the number of inspections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.116" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500021#Z00200"><p>Risk assessment is required under European regulations and under domestic laws relating to food.  The food control system should be based upon risk assessment.  It is part and parcel of what we do in the context of categorising food premises according to risk.  This is used in determining the number of occasions on which they are inspected and so on.  That is all required under EU legislation.</p><p>  On the question of whether we were worried, I can state that we were considering the matter.  In hindsight and as matters progressed, we became more concerned with regard to equine DNA in burger samples.  With regard to the sample whose meat content comprised 29% equine DNA, we were looking at a plant which produces 200 million burgers each year, and we found one burger containing that level of equine DNA at the plant.  The Deputy is correct in stating that in light of the probabilities involved, this was the equivalent of winning the EuroMillions.  Our discovery of a burger containing 29% equine DNA was really the basis of the statement we issued.  The trace amounts of pork and equine DNA were explainable in terms of crossover, etc., but the burger to which I refer alerted us to the fact that a problem existed that we would be obliged to address.  In light of how matters have developed, I am of the view that we made the correct decision.</p><p>  The Deputy inquired when the Department of Health was notified.  We informed our colleagues in the food unit of the Department of Health at a meeting on 7 December last.  We told them that an investigation was being carried out but that there was no action required.  We asked them to keep the matter confidential for the time being.  Essentially, that was the message.</p><p>  The Deputy also asked whether DNA matching could be used in order to focus on where the horsemeat came from.  There are research techniques that can be used in this regard.  I refer, for example, to using stable isotopes in order to discover the provenance of different food materials.  This might work with equine material and we are looking into the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500021#Z00300"><p>Under normal practice, I am supposed to allow the actual members of the committee to conclude first.  Deputies Martin Ferris and &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v wish to ask some supplementary questions.  However, I will conclude this part of the meeting with Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill and Deputy Conlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500021#Z00400"><p>I do not wish to rehearse matters with which the committee has already dealt.  However, there are one or two issues on which I wish to focus.  The Department and the FSAI employed DNA testing for the first time in 2012.  I presume this was not done on a whim but was rather based on the assumption that there may have been an issue.  If one considers the official figures for horses that are being slaughtered legally for their meat in this country - albeit for the export market - one can see that they increased sixfold from approximately 2,000 in 2008 to around 12,000 in 2011.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500021#Z00500"><p>The figures are actually much higher than that.  I can supply them to the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500021#Z00600"><p>There is a very respected organisation in the North of Ireland, namely, the Ulster Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, which estimates that 70,000 horses have disappeared from the island of Ireland during the past 18 months and that they either ended up in the UK food chain or were at least slaughtered in that jurisdiction.  Will the Minister comment on this matter?  In light of the information I have just provided, will he indicate whether there is a need to carry out further investigations or engage in further co-operation with his counterparts in the Six Counties, England, Scotland and Wales in respect of this issue?</p><p>  I wish to focus on the percentage of horsemeat in burgers and the sample which contained 29% equine DNA.  How many burgers containing that level of equine DNA were produced by Silvercrest?  Is there any estimate or indication in that regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500022#AA00200"><p>I call Deputy Conlan because he has waited a while to comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/972" speakername="Se&aacute;n Conlan" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500022#AA00300"><p>I compliment the food safety authority on its investigation and carrying out the initial DNA tests.  I also compliment the Minister.  I have had discussions with people who work in the industry.  I live beside the Silvercrest plant and a few miles from the Rangeland plant so I am greatly concerned about protecting the jobs and local economy.  Obviously I want to also protect farmers, their beef products and the Irish food processing industry.  The Minister and the FSAI have been proactive and responsible in carrying out tests.</p><p>  If we do not get co-operation from the Polish authorities will the Minister go to the Commission and the Council of Ministers to seek the introduction of DNA testing as the industry norm across Europe?  I have heard many people talk in irresponsible terms.  I heard one member mention the term continuous and pervasive industry practice but we have no evidence of that.  It is irresponsible to lay that at the door of Silvercrest.  An issue arose and the product was tested.  I understand that a solution has been found by the Department in terms of rigorous testing in the facility on a weekly basis, a deep cleaning of the facility, a change of management structure, and ensuring that only Irish and British beef is used at the facility.  The Silvercrest plant is now the safest plant in the world, it is certainly the safest plant in Europe.</p><p>  People have talked about the safety of eating horsemeat but eating horsemeat is a cultural norm across Europe and it is not unsafe.  The FSAI tests on 19 December found that there was no evidence of bute or any chemical in the horsemeat.  Therefore, it is not a food safety issue.  It is a food labelling issue.  We need to ensure that food safety is of paramount importance.  </p><p>  In terms of the Rangeland product, the company approached the Department to ensure that tests were carried out.  We must be responsible when debating the issue because livelihoods are at risk if we cannot ensure that contracts will be maintained.  I compliment the Minister on what he has done so far in terms of talking to the multiples and the farmers concerned.  I want him to make sure that whatever has to be done will be done at departmental level to ensure that there is consumer confidence in the products produced by these facilities.  The multiples must also have confidence in the product and a scenario like this can never happen again.</p><p>  If the Polish authorities do not co-operate then I ask the Minister to seek to introduce DNA testing as the norm across Europe.  I do not blame the authorities in Ireland because regularly testing DNA is not standard anywhere in Europe.  That is my understanding.  DNA testing is a new test that was introduced in Ireland because we are proactive when it comes to ensuring that food is safe and traceable.  To ensure that there is accurate food labelling we need to insist that DNA testing is introduced as the norm, thus assuring consumers that when they buy a product which states that it is 100% Irish or British beef then that is what they get.  Consumers need to be reassured that burger content is not a safety issue.  There was no evidence of bute or any other chemicals found in any of the burgers tested.  There has been a lot of scaremongering about the food safety of the product.  It is not a safety issue but a labelling one and we must continue to stress that.  </p><p>  A number of measures have been put in place to deal with the issue.  Can the Minister inform us what else can be done to get the multiples back on board in order to retain jobs and protect the local economy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500022#AA00400"><p>I shall allow two more members to contribute after the Minister replies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500023#BB00100"><p>Stephen Philpott, who heads up the Ulster Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, USPCA, has expressed serious concerns about the trade in horsemeat.  I recently heard him speaking about this on radio.  The following morning I got someone from the Department to telephone him directly.  There have been two, if not more, meetings since then between him, someone from my office and the special investigations unit to follow up on his concerns and get evidence upon which we can act.  As well as that, we have engaged with the authorities in Northern Ireland and in the UK on the movement of horses.  We will continue to do this.  There will be no one more eager and proactive than me in exposing wrongdoing, if it is there.  I need to act on evidence rather than rumour, however.  After I read an article on this matter in <i>The Sunday Times</i>, I asked for a note to be put together on what we have done to reassure people on the horse movement issue.  I will e-mail it to all committee members.  If they want briefings on it, they can come back to me.</p><p>  We have gone from 4,347 horses slaughtered in 2009 to nearly 24,000 last year.  This is because people can no longer afford to keep horses.  There is a significant problem with the abandonment of horses which is why there is a strong section on abandonment in the new animal welfare Bill.  Local authorities have been given resources, along with new regulations, to deal with this problem.  We are taking the accusations seriously but we have to build a case around it.</p><p>  On the question of how many burgers that contained 29% of equine DNA were produced by Silvercrest, processors are required to keep library samples of batches that go through their systems.  They keep them in cold storage for some time, so if there is a consumer problem there will be a sample to access.  We tested the library samples from the same time as the 29% equine burger was produced.  We tested a sample burger produced half an hour afterwards which actually tested 20% equine DNA.  We also tested a burger produced half an hour before but there was not even trace element of equine DNA.  What we suspect is that the ingredient product essentially had chunks of horsemeat in it which led to high levels of equine DNA in the burgers but in a sporadic way.  It is a bit like crumpling up a packet of biscuits.  Most of the biscuits are in small pieces but there are larger chunks.  In the same ice block one will get trace elements of equine DNA and then suddenly a 75% spike.  This suggests horsemeat is being added in an inconsistent way which is not good.</p><p>  DNA testing will be part of our regulatory system.  We need to work with the Food Safety Authority of Ireland, FSAI, the industry, retailers and consumer groups to put in place a practical and implementable system that will establish what is in food products and one that gives real value.  This discussion began yesterday morning in the Department.</p><p>  So far, from the data I have seen, all of the companies that have supplied product into the system that have tested positive for equine DNA are EU-certified companies.  Accordingly, they should be subject to the same regulations as our companies are.  We need to be in a position to trust systems in all European countries because we have an open market.  The open market is a significant advantage to Ireland to sell its products.  From what I know, the Polish authorities are implementing the regulations.  However, one cannot regulate for a fraudster.  If someone is deliberately putting horsemeat into the mix for profit, then the regulations cannot solve the problem.  It is an enforcement issue.</p><p>  It is important to note our systems uncovered this fraud.  Much of the product was going to the UK yet it was the Irish systems that uncovered this from front-testing products from retail outlets in a targeted way.  This is proof - partial proof anyway - that our systems are robust and working in uncovering fraud.  We need to go through the ugliness of the trail to get to the bottom of this and see who was involved.  This has resulted in newspaper headlines that are not good for the Irish food sector.  So be it but we need to get to the bottom of it and move on afterwards.</p><p>  I appeal to members not to claim this investigation as having already taken four months.  As we established today, this investigation began on 15 January 2013 and we are now at the start of February.  This was after the FSAI established there was a problem which it did in a professional and thorough manner.  Once that was established, then the investigation began.  The accusation that this has been going on for four months does not stand up to scrutiny.</p><p>  I understand Deputy Se&aacute;n Conlan's concerns about the jobs at Silvercrest.  As the local Deputy, he is under pressure from families associated with the firm who want to know what the future holds for them.  However, we have to be uncompromising in getting to the bottom of this for the sake of the entire food industry which employs over 200,000 people and has the potential to be a key driver for growth in the economy.  In the meantime, I am also focusing on finding a way we can create a future for Silvercrest and its workers, as well as winning back contracts that have been lost as a result of this contamination.  That is all I can say on the matter for the moment.  There are industry players who are actively participating in trying to facilitate this.  Hopefully, we will have positive news on that in the coming days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="17:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500023#BB00200"><p>Has the Polish company that supplied the contaminated trimmings had any connection with horsemeat produce?  How long has this company supplied Silvercrest or any other Irish meat processing company?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC00200"><p>Senators Susan O'Keeffe and Mary Ann O'Brien are next to contribute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC00300"><p>I know that the figures for Rangeland Foods only came out yesterday and appreciate the Minister may be unable to indicate the position.  However, the company has stated the meat it imports is only used for exports.  Had Silvercrest been asked six months ago, it would have stated it used Irish beef only.  I wonder how much store we can put in such statements.  What will the Minister put in place to establish that such a claim is, in fact, true?  That is a serious concern.</p><p>  I raised another query previously.  I realise the Minister has stated he was not entirely clear on the labels used.  However, I asked whether there was any evidence of meat having been frozen, thawed and re-frozen when it was being examined.  I do not believe my related question was answered, but many questions were put.</p><p>  What is the position in the United Kingdom plant which was also involved in the equine DNA case?  What is the position of the Food Standards Agency in the United Kingdom?  The Minister, kindly, showed us an 80:20 trim.  Will he clarify exactly what this means, as the explanation passed me by?</p><p>  What other meats should the Food Safety Authority of Ireland test for now?  It is not a very nice question, but in the circumstances we ought to ask it.  There has been no mention of mechanically recovered meat and its role in the burger meat case.  I am unclear on whether this is because it has not been tested for or because it was simply not part of the conversation.  What are the observations of the delegations on the tests available, if any, for mechanically recovered meat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC00400"><p>I wish to comment passionately on how proud we are of our food safety standards, the Food Harvest 2020 strategy and everything to do with our food production.  It is something positive to take away from this discussion because it is tough going.  However, we were the ones to spot the problem.</p><p>  Senator Paschal Mooney raised some interesting points.  I implore the Minister to think futuristically about the price of food and consider engaging in dialogue with all of the multiples which have got into a bind.</p><p>  Let us consider the produce in question.  The number of burgers involved was eight and I happen to know the price in sterling - eight burgers for &pound;1.  I have attempted to work out the margin and estimate that Silvercrest was probably selling at 7p per burger or &pound;1.38 per kilo.  However, it is difficult to know, as I am unsure of the tonnage or per kilo price throughout Europe for beef trimmings.  I realise the make-up of cheaper patties does not include the meat used in quarter pounders and so on.</p><p>  I have discussed the issue with friends of mine involved in the meat industry who make ready meals.  They have nothing to do with Silvercrest.  They maintain that Asda is selling two portions of lasagne for &pound;1, or 50p each.  That must stop somewhere.  We would all welcome dialogue with the multiples, which is necessary on behalf of the consumer.  A price of &pound;1.38 per kilo does not stack up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC00700"><p>Senator Mary Ann O'Brien commented on the price of food.  My understanding is that the price of the eight burgers was &euro;1.59, but I will stand corrected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC00800"><p>It was &pound;1 sterling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC00900"><p>Either way, it is a ridiculously cheap product.  That is why the product used is primarily beef trimmings, the type of product that does not have a home anywhere else.  It is very much at the bottom of the market.  However, as I stated, that is no excuse for not having standards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC01000"><p>Dog food has a higher price per kilo, which is frightening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500024#CC01100"><p>That may be the case.  We are considering a code of good trading practice at EU level.  The conversation is taking place at EU level among Ministers and there is a good deal of pressure from farmers, primary producers and small food companies producing good quality products.  Such players are feeling the squeeze by large multiples which have significant buying power and can drive down prices, especially in the horticulture sector, among others.  This is something to which we need to find a solution, but it must be an EU-wide solution.  If we come up with an Irish solution, retailers will simply source product from outside Ireland elsewhere in Europe.  We must address this issue collectively.  It is an ongoing debate in the context of the Common Agricultural Policy reform process and we are looking to support producer organisations to collectively bargain on price in order that there can be economies of scale and they can bargain with retail outlets and so on.  </p><p>  I understand Senator Susan O'Keeffe has good knowledge of this area and why she is sceptical about some of the practices engaged in, given the research she has conducted.  On the 80:20 trim, it refers to 80% visible lean meat and 20% fat.  Professor Reilly or one of the veterinary specialists will correct me if I am wrong, but that is my understanding.  The higher the visible lean meat content, the less fat in the product.</p><p>  Undoubtedly, there will be a significant role for DNA testing in the future to provide reassurance for the consumer and our larger clients also.  Tesco has stated it will insist on DNA testing.  I have already offered to other companies which will potentially source from Silvercrest that we will introduce DNA testing at the plant, on a daily basis if necessary, to reassure them.  We will introduce it in a more systematic way than what we have in place, but either way, it needs some thought and work.  Perhaps we might come back to the committee to get the input of members.</p><p>  The straight answer to the question of whether there was evidence of frozen meat thawing and then being re-frozen is no, but I cannot definitely say it was not happening.  However, we did not see any evidence which suggested it was happening.</p><p>  There was a question about mechanically recovered meat.  There were ingredients containing mechanically recovered meat from a different EU country on which there was a spotlight earlier in the investigation, but there was only small trace elements of equine DNA in the sample.  We quickly came to the conclusion that it was not the problem product and we reported the findings to the appropriate authorities.</p><p>  Another question was related to a specific test to check for mechanically recovered or de-sinewed meat, as I term it.  I will outline the process for those not familiar with it.  When all of the main cuts are taken from a carcass, there is some meat stuck between the bones.  The meat content is removed from the carcass or bone using a pressurised system.  As I understand it, this is regarded as de-sinewed or mechanically recovered meat.  There is nothing wrong with it in terms of food safety issues, but I realise people do not especially like the thought of that process being used.</p><p>  Senator Susan O'Keeffe asked me a question about Rangeland, but I am unsure what it was because I only have the word "Rangeland" written down.  To be honest, we do not yet have detailed files from Rangeland, as we have only just gone in.  I do not have reports back on auditing and so on, but we will have them soon.  Therefore, I will be cautious in what I say about Rangeland to be fair to the company and ensure I am accurate in what I say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00200"><p>Do the retained samples give any indication of how long the problem has been ongoing?  Have the burgers been seized by the Department or do they remain in the ownership of the company?  A lot of people are asking that question.  From a food safety point of view, why did DNA testing of processed meats only begin in 2012?  Was the November sampling the first occasion on which this test was used?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00300"><p>That was asked earlier.  Does Professor Reilly wish to respond?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00400"><p>It is simple: we did not test previously.  We have focused on other categories of food, such as farmed fish and wild Atlantic salmon, cod and other fish products in batter, and honey.  This was the first time we investigated the species going into meat products.  My colleagues from the Department can answer the question about the length of time these practices might have been ongoing but the results from the UK indicate that 17.1% equine DNA was found in a burger produced for the Co-op in April 2011.  The Department may have data going back further than that.</p><p>  I share members' concerns about consumer protection.  Our job in the Food Safety Authority is to protect consumers' health and interests.  In protecting consumers' interests, we must ensure foods that are on the market are labelled correctly.  That was the rationale for investigating this area.  We do not at present plan to investigate other meats.  Our focus should be on putting systems in place to ensure this does not happen again.</p><p>  With respect to the UK, we are in daily contact with our colleagues from the Food Standards Agency in both London and Northern Ireland to share intelligence.  They are carrying out a similar study to ours and we shared our methods with them.  They will be investigating similar types of product for sale in UK markets.  Members will have read newspaper reports over the weekend regarding halal pies supplied to UK prisons.  That is part of their work.  Essentially they are taking a lead from us in doing similar work.  Some of the larger supermarkets and companies are conducting similar testing processes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00500"><p>Has anything emerged from the investigation into Dalepak that might be different or would add to our sum of knowledge?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Alan Reilly" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00600"><p>Nothing has emerged from that investigation.  The company used some of the Dutch product that we identified as containing low or trace levels of equine DNA.  That was the reason for the findings in regard to it.  The Food Standards Agency is more concerned about pork in products that are specifically marketed to religious groups in the UK.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00700"><p>As I did not answer Deputy Ferris's questions earlier, I will answer them now and then comment on Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill's questions. Rangeland's three samples indicate the involvement of two different companies based in Poland.  Certainly the labels suggest these companies delivered product through a meat trader arrangement.  Both of these companies also delivered to Silvercrest.  One of the companies is a deboning plant which brings in material from four or five different slaughtering houses.  All of those plants are EU-certified.  I understand the Polish authorities are currently testing product from these plants.</p><p>  I wish to correct a comment I made earlier.  Use of the term "mechanically recovered meat" is inappropriate because it is illegal to mechanically recover meat.  The proper term is "desinewed meat".  It is important that we do not discuss something that is illegal if it is not happening, although I think we can be forgiven as amateurs in this game.</p><p>  Product from these companies has been coming to Ireland for a couple of years in respect of Silvercrest.  We do not know whether the problem existed six, ten or 18 months ago.  Our investigation is focused on the burgers produced in January, which confirmed the existence of a problem in the system and explained how the finding of 29% equine DNA in a burger could have occurred.  We have some library samples from the batch but we still do not have any of the ingredients that went into that burger.  Our focus has been on the burgers produced in January because we have the ingredients that went into them.  It is likely to be the same, for obvious reasons.</p><p>  The burgers are being moved out of the plant today, under supervision.  I understand they are going for rendering, if that is the correct terminology.  We are trying to allow Silvercrest to move on from this affair.  Jobs, families and livelihoods are seriously affected and any new customer who sources from Silvercrest will want to start from scratch with a plant that has been sanitised and deep-cleaned and is operated according to an entirely new structure.  We are proceeding on this basis for the reasons I outlined earlier.  As we still have 140 different samples of burgers and ingredients, I not sure we will gain anything by keeping large volumes of this product in cold storage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2013020500025#DD00800"><p>After four hours and 50 minutes, we are burgered out.  I thank the Minister, Professor Reilly and their colleagues for their full and frank engagement.  We agreed before the meeting started to proceed along a line of questioning that would try to establish the facts rather than be political or provoke a negative impression of the Irish industry.  We are collectively concerned with moving on from this incident at the earliest opportunity.  I commend members on engaging in that spirit.  It is clear that the process needs to be concluded as quickly as possible and must be evidence-based.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.146" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.147" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:30</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.150" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500003#G00100">Reform of National Micro and Small Business Support Structures: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500003#G00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, and his officials, Ms Clare Dunne, assistant secretary general, Mr. Dermot Sheridan, principal officer, Ms &Aacute;ine de Bairtis&eacute;il, assistant principal officer, and Ms Claire Madigan, assistant principal officer.  The purpose of the meeting is to discuss the reform of national micro and small business support structures and what emerges will feed into the debate within the committee on this matter, which is being led by Deputy &Aacute;ine Collins.</p><p>  Before we begin, I remind members of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500003#G00300"><p>I provided a submission for the joint committee which, I presume, has been circulated to members.  I will not read it, rather I will deal with the broad issues involved.  Perhaps members might then raise whatever concerns they harbour.</p><p>  The programme for Government contains a commitment to reforming the system of supports for small and micro businesses.  This is also a central plank of the Action Plan for Jobs 2012.  Our ambition is to make small business a more central part of the national enterprise strategy.  To a degree, small business has been operating on the fringes.  The steps we are taking will bring it to the centre of enterprise strategy and help us in developing a much stronger local service.  There are six key elements to delivering this change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00200"><p>Deputy Dara Calleary apologised for having to leave before the Minister's presentation.  I call Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00300"><p>Go raibh m&iacute;le maith ag an Aire mar gheall ar a chur i l&aacute;thair.  I wish to mention briefly the issue of upward-only rent reviews.  I spoke to the owner of a small business over the weekend who has three outlets.  Two of them are under upward only rents and he is having major difficulty getting a reduction in them.  There is the threatened closure of B&amp;Q in Waterford and Athlone and the other outlets are also under major pressure.  Upward-only rent reviews are costing hundreds of jobs each month in this State.  The advice from the Attorney General, which none of us has seen, is that we cannot do anything about it without a constitutional amendment.  Will there be a constitutional amendment to make that change?  Last week, when the Minister of State, Deputy John Perry, was asked about upward-only rents he said that they were not an issue in the closure of businesses in Ireland.  I considered that a shocking thing for a senior Government Minister to say.  Does the Minister agree with the Minister of State that upward-only rents do not have an effect on the closure of businesses and does he have confidence in the Minister of State, Deputy Perry's, ability to do the job, given that so many businesses have closed due to upward-only rents?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00400"><p>Will the Deputy try to keep to today's discussion, which is about small business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00500"><p>It is an issue for small businesses as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00600"><p>I accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00700"><p>With regard to the LEOs, I agree the county enterprise boards have been in a no-man's land for a number of years, including before this Government took office, and they must be reformed.  Could the Minister furnish the committee with the number of jobs that each of the county enterprise boards created in the last number of years, so we can get an understanding of what the objectives of the new LEOs should be in the forthcoming year?  We could then measure the output of the LEOs and the cost per job as well.</p><p>  The Minister has been getting input from private business with regard to the LEOs.  Some of that input came after the decision was made.  Perhaps we could get some of that input and an understanding of it.</p><p>  My other question is about credit for small business.  Niall O'Donnellan, who is the liaison between Enterprise Ireland and AIB, Bank of Ireland and Ulster Bank, told the Committee of Public Accounts last week that the Irish banking system is not fit for purpose for lending to the SME and exporting sector.  This is still a major issue for small business.  I met a small business owner in Trim yesterday whose business is ready to go.  He has a grant from a development organisation but the banks will not give him the money for a long enough period to spend it and then draw down the grant to cover it.  The system is still hampering small businesses in a major way.  Does the Minister agree with Enterprise Ireland's representative?  What can he do with the banking system by using the public interest shareholders?</p><p>  If the Chairman will permit me to raise another issue, Tara Mines in my constituency has threatened temporary closure of the mine.  Many small businesses deliver to Tara Mines and the industry is very important in the local economy.  Will the Minister try to persuade the management in Tara Mines to stick with the wage agreements it agreed less than nine months ago-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00800"><p>You have raised the issue.  It is not fair to the other members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500005#J00900"><p>First, I have absolute confidence in Deputy John Perry.  Not only is he totally committed to the small business sector, he also knows a great deal about what is happening in that sector.  For a long number of years he has been pointing to the vulnerability of some elements of the small business sector, particularly the retail area and the over-shopping that was allowed to be developed during the boom years.  He has an acute understanding and if people had listened more to his warnings about the hazards of what was happening during the boom years, we would be in a stronger position now.</p><p>  Clearly, upward-only rent is a major concern.  Everybody went into this in good faith, hoping a solution could be found.  There has not been a possibility of a solution other than the State, through the taxpayer, compensating individuals for any loss incurred in the revision of an upward-only rent.  That option is not open to us in the current financial climate in the State.  To be fair, the National Asset Management Agency, NAMA, which is a big property owner on behalf of the State, has applied changes in its rules.  I believe the penny has dropped with landlords to some degree as to the true state of businesses and many rents are being negotiated down.  That is not to say it does not remain an issue, because it does.  Certainly, it was an issue in the B&amp;Q case.  There is no doubt that there are individual areas where very high rents are a problem.</p><p>  On the overall data on job creation, I have the provisional 2012 figures.  The number of jobs created was 6,905 gross and under 1,000 net.  There were job losses in the sector as well as gains.  Roughly speaking, the cost per job sustained is approximately &euro;6,000.  Clearly, we take into account that it has to be assessed over a number of years to see the overall impact.  In total, nearly 1,000 projects were assisted and there were many participants in soft support, as it were.  I can get the breakdown by county for the Deputy as it is available.  As regards the type of comment received, Claire Madigan has been going through them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500006#K00200"><p>Will the Minister consider holding a referendum on upward-only rent reviews, given that the Constitution as it stands will not allow for change in this area?  While I agree there has been good work done on reducing rents associated with NAMA, there are hundreds of rents payable to Departments, including the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, that are subject to upward-only reviews.  These Departments, as landlords, charge upward-only rents.  Will the Minister commit to change in this area such that the rents will reflect market rates?  How often does the Minister meet representatives of the banks?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500006#K00300"><p>If I allow questions that are not part of the main discussion, every member will ask three or four additional ones.  We will continue with the conversation on LEOs, if that is acceptable, and then ask the Minister to give answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500006#K00400"><p>Some of my questions were not new.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500006#K00500"><p>If we open up a discussion on every issue, we will not conclude the main topic.  We are supposed to be considering the proposed changes regarding the LEOs.  Deputy Collins is working on a report and I want to address that.  If there is time remaining at the end, we will return to the other issues.  Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n will be on top of the list.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/988" speakername="&Aacute;ine Collins" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500006#K00600"><p>I thank the Minister and his colleagues, who are very welcome to the committee.  I am quite happy that LEOs will be part of local government on foot of the realignment of the local partnerships.  People on the ground are often very confused about where to go to get help.  Having a one-stop shop will be of great benefit to the client.  Supporting the client is paramount.  I am delighted that the centre of excellence, which will be in charge of the training of the staff in the LEOs, will be managed by Enterprise Ireland.  It has a good record and service in this regard.</p><p>  I am glad the Minister mentioned mentoring.  Since he brought it up, I will ask a question on it.  Does he envisage that mentoring will still be provided in the current system?  Will there be a stand-alone network of mentors feeding into the various agencies and sectors?  Will people who are not part of the LEOs be able to gain access to mentoring under a State system?  If so, how will the process work?</p><p>  What I am really trying to figure out is what will be different for the client in this experience.  When the client seeks a service, will it be a question of funding or the delivery of training?  What kind of training will be delivered?  Will it continue according to the current model?  What will be different in terms of supporting the client?</p><p>  While I appreciate that resources may not be available, will it be possible to have a relationship-management approach whereby we could bring the people in the local enterprise offices into the field to meet clients and businesses to determine their needs and help them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500006#K00700"><p>I thank the Deputy for her comments.  We are not moving immediately to a stand-alone mentoring system outside the service.  We provide for mentoring within a network overseen by Enterprise Ireland's centre of excellence.  There will also be Enterprise Ireland's own mentoring service.</p><p>  I envisage a natural evolution of an improved service in the development of the mentoring service over time.  It will not be different tomorrow, but we will move to make it different over time.  We have already expanded the role in that CEBs are providing the first point of contact with micro-finance, which is entirely outside the traditional area of manufacturing and internationally traded services.  I refer to those in the domestic economy to whom a service is being provided.  We will seek to develop instruments to support innovative businesses, even those that do not fall into the traditional categories.  This represents a natural evolution.</p><p>  From my experience of banks turning down credit applications and my work with the CRO, it is clear to me that the quality of business plans and the mentoring support is not up to scratch.  The way small business presents its face to banks is not good enough.  It needs to be improved and we need to work on it.  It will be important to extend a network from the LEO into the wider business community, be it through chambers of commerce or others working in this field, to improve in this area.  It is an area in which we need to learn and develop rather than one we need to enter with a proposal for a stand-alone operation.</p><p>  Relationship management, as mentioned by the Deputy, already exists to some extent.  We will improve all the time the quality and range of mentoring support.  This will represent a central gain.</p><p>  Let us consider what will be different.  Obviously, there will be a difference in respect of micro-finance.  There will be a financial instrument to support businesses outside the traditional sectors.  There will also be central training, and central standards will be set.  Enterprise Ireland, through its network, will be helping to develop the skills and the reach of the enterprise office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500007#L00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and the senior staff from his Department.  I wish to raise two general issues.  With the standing down of the 35 city and county enterprise boards - I know their performances were mixed - was there any general assessment of how they fared?  Obviously, some did well while others did not.  I think people would like to have access to that kind of knowledge, in particular in terms of passing on the good learning to the new structures.</p><p>  The issue of funding has been raised already.  Funding is the lifeblood of small and medium-sized enterprises.  The criticisms of the banks are like a refrain from an old ballad in that they just go on and on.  Presumably much of this criticism is valid but where would the Minister say it is not valid?  If it is valid, as most people instinctively feel it is, when will it end?  We have been promised action and that the next initiative would be the one.  Where are we in regard to the demand for the lifeblood of small and medium-sized enterprises?  When will we reach a point when the demand is matched by the supply so that this vital sector gets a chance to perform to its potential in terms of job creation and so on?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500007#L00300"><p>I welcome the Minister and his officials.  When Enterprise Ireland was with us in November going through its view of the LEOs, I had a concern that the small local company, which was not interested in exporting and which would never be an exporter but which still could be an employment creator and provide a viable service - I am not into displacement; we do not want to encourage that - would be lost in the LEO structure, in particular in an Enterprise Ireland structure.  In his presentation, the Minister acknowledged some improvements there.  He might just reflect on that and that the LEOs should be good for all companies.</p><p>  The Minister for Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, proposes to bring all the Leader funding - the Leader enterprise strand - into local authorities.  Will the LEOs deal with Leader funding or will that be a separate wing of the local authority?  If it is to be a separate wing, does that not undermine the whole one-stop-shop approach because certainly in Leader areas, Leader enterprise funding is essential?  It will be under the local authority but will it be under a separate part of the local authority?  Do we have EU approval for the enterprise side of things?</p><p>  The Minister mentioned that the LEOs will be the one-stop-shop and that he wanted to start to increase the services.  As he is redesigning the industrial relations machinery, will the LEOs have a role in being a one-stop shop at that end as well in terms of maybe providing NERA advice, or being an agent for NERA on the ground in terms of providing advice as opposed to enforcement?  </p><p>  The Minister referred to local authorities in his report and I have concerns about bringing an enterprise function into local authorities and I am still not convinced.  He rightly mentioned that many local authorities have initiatives supporting enterprises but many of those are at town council level.  Many of the really good initiatives at local authority level have come from town councils which will be abolished.  In the larger local authorities envisaged by the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, how will the Minister protect that spirit of enterprise and creativity?  Will he give us an update on where we are with the industrial relations issues?  </p><p>  It is a bit of a bugbear but the 35 county enterprise boards all have 35 different brands and logos.  One would not realise that the county enterprise board is actually a nationwide model.  The Minister mentioned in his report that he has appointed a company to design a new logo.  Will it be one brand and one logo for the entire country rather than many different ones?  Did an SME get the gig?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500007#L00400"><p>We did a study of county enterprise boards before we embarked on this change, which was broadly positive but made recommendations for change.  We are taking on board the sort of recommendations it made and are integrating them into the new proposal.  Some of them are on the sorts of themes Deputy Calleary raised, that is, to ensure innovative companies, which might not be immediately looking to export, do not fall between the crevasses.  We recognise that and microfinance is the first instrument which recognised that and expands the range of instruments to support them.  We are trying to make it easier to export so we established a firsttime exporters' division and Enterprise Ireland is targeting approximately 2,000 companies which it believes have the potential to export.  Obviously, in a very depressed domestic market, exporting is a very important element.  To a degree, the LEOs will be the feeder stock to that initiative.  We are trying to pick it up on both sides.  There will be a broader mandate for the LEOs than now exists.</p><p>  Deputy Conaghan raised the whole issue of banking which goes back to what Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n raised.  Clearly, the refusal rates here are too high but correspondingly, during the boom, the acceptance rates were too high.  The pendulum swung from accepting every loan application without scrutiny to a miserly attitude to risk.  We need to build the expertise within the banks back up to a point where they can make a quality assessment of bankable projects.  We are not interested in them backing projects which are not bankable but we need to get them back into the space of fair assessment of bankable projects.  We have a considerable way to go but I see improvements and I think those are reflected in falling refusal rates, which have been reported.  Anecdotally, there is more effort in this field but there is a long way to go.  </p><p>  There is also a recognition across Europe that reliance on banks to provide the full response to enterprise needs will not work and that one needs new sources of stronger non-bank finance coming into the field.  Over the past 12 months, there has been nearly &euro;2.5 billion in non-bank finance instruments.  The National Pensions Reserve Fund now has an equity fund, a restructuring fund and credit fund.  Our Department has a development capital fund, the loan guarantee scheme, the microfinance scheme and the innovation fund.  We will launch a new tranche of the seed and venture funds.  Banks need to get better at doing their business but there is also part of the spectrum which needs to be filled out.  We have launched these new instruments but it will be important to monitor them to see if they are fit-for-purpose and are filling the gap.  There will be a continuing gap even when the banks are fully functioning.  There has been a change and we need to have new financial instruments to support it.  It is not just as simple as getting demand and supply back on track.  Both sides of the market have changed and we must respond to that.  </p><p>  In regard to Deputy Calleary's other point, Leader companies are separate, are funded by the EU and are working to a different mandate.  We will have protocols to ensure there is not duplication and so on.  The LEO is a first stop shop rather than a one-stop shop so we are not saying it will deliver Leader supports to Leader or deliver seed capital from Revenue.  Someone who goes to a LEO will get easy turnkey access to the delivery of whatever he or she seeks, whether it is a credit review, seed capital tax relief or otherwise.  That is the ambition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00200"><p>For the advice side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00300"><p>Exactly.  It would apply equally to health and safety.  As the Deputy knows, the HSA has done a lot, such as developing the well-received BeSMART initiative.  I do not see the decision on town councils impinging on reform because it is an enterprise initiative.</p><p>  I agree with the Deputy about logos.  We will have a single logo spanning the network and Designworks won the contract.  It has 12 to 15 employees, which fits into the definition of an SME and is just larger than a micro-company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00400"><p>I hope it does not need a loan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00500"><p>I am conscious that Senator Mary White must leave shortly, so I call on Deputy Lawlor, Senator Quinn and Senator Mary White, in that order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00600"><p>I thank the Minister for attending.  Last week we had a fruitful meeting with his Department's Secretary General, and I welcome today's meeting.  I assume the Minister will return shortly to update us on the jobs initiative and An Action Plan for Jobs.  Perhaps he will allow the committee to make an input into the 2013 action plan for jobs.</p><p>  A lot of high-quality people from the county enterprise boards, CEBs, will move to the local enterprise boards, LEOs.  The Department might not take the good part of the CEBs.  Some of the CEBs are useless while others are excellent.  The Minister should target and identify the CEBs that have proven to be successful and use them as a model for LEOs.  Resources have been a problem for CEBs in my county of Kildare and they will be a problem for LEOs.  So many people will apply for and seek loans  that the LEOs will not be able to meet demand.  Some CEBs did not fulfil their role by not utilising the funds that were allocated to them.  Instead of reinventing the wheel, the Minister should examine the successful CEBs and use them as a template for LEOs.</p><p>  I hark on about two issues.  First, the LEOs will be the first stop for the microenterprise fund.  Second, although a large number of young people are unemployed, we have a high entrepreneurial base among them, the highest in Europe.  I do not like quoting the Minister but he referred to young people gaining access to the microfinance fund.  Perhaps he will direct LEOs to place an increased emphasis on assisting young people with ideas when they apply for microfinance.  Many schools have participated in CEB schemes and there is a lot of competition among them.  A lot of good ideas have emanated from schools but they have found it difficult to secure microfinance.  They should not be handicapped simply because of their youth.  I hope LEOs will play a role in identifying young entrepreneurs and, as the Minister said earlier, they should be given bonus points when it comes to the allocation of funding.  I have met a couple of people who have found it difficult to secure microfinance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00700"><p>I allowed Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n to raise an issue on banks and I allowed Deputy Michael Conaghan to make a contribution ahead of me.  I will allow more comments on banking in a few minutes.  I remind members that Senator Mary White is in a hurry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00800"><p>All right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M00900"><p>I must leave shortly because I have a meeting with the T&aacute;naiste.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M01000"><p>I welcome the Minister.  The concept of incorporating the local enterprise boards into local authorities is sensible.  I have been struck by the number of main streets in towns that have been devastated.  The shops and businesses are empty because shopping centres have been built on the edges of towns.  Yesterday Sir Terry Leahy commented on the issue and said it was a shame but that the move was driven by consumer demand.  A local enterprise board incorporated into local authorities has a much better chance of solving the problem.  The solution will not be easy and it is a difficult question to answer.</p><p>  During consultations, many organisations represented small and medium-sized enterprises such as ISME, SFA, RGDATA, Retail Excellence Ireland and Retail Ireland.  How was it possible to consult so many organisations?  Was it done jointly or independently?  How did the Department manage to get around the problem?</p><p>  The third objective is to reduce the number of licences before encouraging new people to open a business.  One objective is to dramatically reduce the length of time it takes to open a new business here.  That time has been reduced considerably.  Can the Minister touch on the steps that his Department can take to improve the matter?  </p><p>  Being paid on time is a great challenge for small enterprises.  What has happened with timely payments, particularly State payments?  Are we getting anywhere near solving the problem?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500008#M01100"><p>I welcome the Minister and his team.  I am concerned about what will happen to LEOs but I accept,  as a <i>fait accompli</i>, that they will be established.  As I have said on numerous occasions here, the quality of the county and city enterprise boards has been inconsistent, which brought them into disrepute, and I blame the Department.  I was told by people on different county and city enterprise boards that some of its people were not up to the job and that boards did not have a strategy.  Many of the boards were left to lie fallow without adequate funding and, therefore, I am critical of bureaucracy.</p><p>  The Minister has put his heart and soul into his job and the Minister of State, Deputy John Perry, is also committed to small and micro-industries and knows the important role they play in creating employment.  All of the paperwork and actions plans have left me worried about the projects.  As much as 95% of the success of any project in any country is a direct result of the people at its helm, the drivers of the project.  On numerous occasions here I have asked how we can ensure bureaucrats will not be transferred from local authorities to enterprise boards.  We need people who are passionate about entrepreneurship and creating employment.  We need people with a mission, not bureaucrats.  I am sceptical about the initiative and I shall continue to be.  I support the Minister's aims.  However, we must closely monitor the initiative for the boards in order to ensure that the bureaucrats do not take over from the Department or a local authority.  How will the boards be funded?  Funding was a problem for the city and county enterprise boards.  Some of them had loads of people but no money.  What is their budget?  There are good schemes and I know the Minister is doing his best.  I would be happy if I could be convinced that the people joining the county and city enterprise boards were passionate about creating jobs, but with my experience of them I will be hard to convince.</p> <p>Who will be the watchdog?  Reference was made to Enterprise Ireland but I am concerned because bureaucrats do not create jobs, regardless of all the good reports and so on.</p><p> In terms of my experience, I differ from some of the people on this committee.  The point about mentoring is exaggerated.  I do not go with the idea that people will not have the stomach to develop a business and bring it to the market without being mentored by somebody.  </p><p> Where will the funding come from?  How will the Minister make sure, with all his passion for this area, that good people are employed by these enterprise boards who will be understanding of the people who come with the projects to create employment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00200"><p>A number of questions have been put, but could we deal with the local enterprise offices aspect first?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00300"><p>Yes.  To answer Deputy Lawlor, we are approaching the completion of the 2013 action plan for jobs.  It has to be signed off and we hope to publish this month.  We are at a very late stage in that regard.  I have had some individual submissions on this from members but the Deputy is right that there is best in class and then there are others.  Part of the role of having a centre of excellence is that it will promote best-in-class practices.  We will reinforce that by having competitive funds to ensure that, based on the quality of what people are doing, they will be able to draw down additional funding.  There will be a competitive element in the funding as well as an allocation.</p><p>  Deputy Lawlor has talked previously about the importance of young entrepreneurs, and we have many programmes that are equally available to young and more established microfinance competitive starts.  There may be a case for examining a tranche.  Last year we had a very successful tranche aimed at women entrepreneurs.  It started at &euro;250,000 and was so over-subscribed that we increased it to &euro;750,000 within months.  That worked as a way of having a particular brand and looking for entrepreneurs in a particular class.  It is worth considering whether we can do something in that sphere.</p><p>  To be fair, there is a great deal happening in this space also.  I launched UStart in the universities.  The Young Scientist exhibition does something around entrepreneurship.  There are a number of elements to this.  The Department is working on an entrepreneurship strategy and we will be looking at this entire area.  We will definitely consider the Deputy's interest in young entrepreneurs and their potential.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00400"><p>I thank the Minister for that.  I will make a presentation to him that was given to me last week on a youth entrepreneurial fund.  It came from a group of young people in Celbridge and it contains good proposals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00500"><p>I thank the Deputy for that.</p><p>  Senator Feargal Quinn raised the issue of high street decay.  Many practices have changed, and I have seen that myself.  Increasingly, pubs and bookies are in the centres of towns and much of the traditional shopping is migrating out.  Ultimately, it is down to the customers, but some local authorities have had initiatives to try to revive streets or particular areas, with some success.  There is scope in that regard and it is right to bring the local authorities into the fold because they are important determinants of the way towns develop and the other elements, such as parking, that change the environment.  It is good to have them inside the enterprise tent.</p><p>  We consulted electronically, but obviously we went to all the small business units.  We created a consultation document, which we published.  There has been a very good response rate.</p><p>  We will have an initiative in 2013 to try to simplify licensing, starting with the retail sector.  Forf&aacute;s did a study of 159 licences during the course of last year which found an element of duplication and showed how the process could be streamlined and simplified.  We will have an initiative in that sphere and if it works in retail we will move beyond that.</p><p>  Regarding on-time payment, I signed that order for the European directive, which I believe comes into force around the Ides of March.  It creates a new obligation on companies to have certain practices from which they can opt out, but the default mode is paying on time.  Some people would like to see it being made compulsory, but that is another day's work.  The State is already monitoring this, and it has been extended to different tranches of State activity, but all central Departments have been paying within 30 days.  This has now dropped to 15 days and they are meeting that target.  We are trying to widen the circle to make sure the State is paying on time and bringing in extra players.  Undoubtedly, in this climate it is an area in which businesses can help one another by having responsible practices.  It is important that the bigger suppliers recognise the pressure on smaller suppliers that is caused by not paying on time.</p><p>  I do not dispute what Senator White said.  Most members acknowledged that not all county enterprise boards were of equal quality.  That does not lie at the door of our Department; local authorities had their own boards.  We are now seeking to address that by having a centre of excellence that will provide technical support to lift the standards of those who are weaker.  As I said to Deputy Lawlor, we will also have a competitive element and therefore the better will do better in the allocation of funds.  That also helps people to improve.  There will be benchmarks under the service level agreements.  The way in which different enterprise offices are performing will be more transparent.  That is the new professionalism in the public service.  People want to work to high standards and we will assess standards.  The Department has a strategy.  It is one I am behind and we intend to push ahead and deliver that strategy.  Until we see the change, Senator White is entitled to be sceptical, but we are convinced we will deliver it.  The criticism is that it is all paperwork.  It could be said that our action plan for jobs is all paperwork, but in terms of the public service saying it will be accountable quarter by quarter on the delivery of a broad strategy, I have never seen that in my lifetime, and I am a long time in politics.  We have seen many strategies but we have rarely seen a public service-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00600"><p>The Minister's target for jobs that he set-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00700"><p>That is a challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00800"><p>-----is not making much progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N00900"><p>We are making progress.  When we came into office there was a rate of job attrition of 90,000 per year from the private sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01000"><p>The Minister is telling me that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01100"><p>The figure is now plus 12,000.  It is a dramatic turnaround.  It is not where we need to be but it is progress and we have to continue to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01200"><p>Where will the Minister get 88,000 jobs before 2016?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01300"><p>I am dealing with the Senator's questions.  The Senator is aware that we have to build new sectors that will employ people.  Recent years saw excessive growth of domestic banking, property, construction and retail that was unsustainable.  We now have to build a stronger enterprise base that will be founded on innovation, exporting and enterprise, and that does not happen overnight.  Someone like the Senator who has been in business would know that.  The Government cannot wave a magic wand so that enterprises are suddenly taking on people by the hundred thousand.  We have to re-engineer the structure, try to fix the banks, reform elements of our own activity such as licensing, wage setting or whatever, and create a better environment, but that is what we are about.  It will not happen overnight.  It is naive to think it is about clicking one's fingers.  It will not work that way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01400"><p>I disagree with the Minister.  Can I-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01500"><p>No.  Senator, to be fair-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500009#N01600"><p>It is important.  The comment the Minister made about the boards is disingenuous.  That is a good departmental response to what I said.  The boards were shackled by the lack of vision of the people in the Department.  I know that from my discussions with the groups.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00100"><p>The budgets are fully protected.  There will be a competitive element to reward innovation and excellence in the way the service is delivered.  Mentoring is an area that has potential.  The Senator is correct that there is no substitute for an entrepreneur.  Many people do not have expertise across the full range of their business and if they want to break into, say, an export market there are as many failures as successes.  Sometimes the failures are the result of basic mistakes.  For example, someone may choose the wrong person to partner with at the start or may not explore the market.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00200"><p>They did not have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00300"><p>We need to raise the ambition of our enterprises if we want to create new jobs and we all need to support them in the direction in which their ambition takes them.  It is the same for any of us.  We do not all start off knowing the intricacies of moving into the French or German market.  That has to be supported and that is the reason we have enterprise agencies with representatives in 28 countries - to make it easier for people to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00400"><p>I accept the Minister is doing his best.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00500"><p>Senator White, in fairness to other colleagues, Senator David Cullinane is waiting to contribute on LEOs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00600"><p>I thank the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00700"><p>There are three Deputies who are to come back in with other questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00800"><p>We are here to discuss supports we can give to the small and micro-business sector.  An issue that has arisen frequently is that of prompt payments.  The Minister will be aware of the EU directive on the matter, about which the organisations representing business - ISME and the Small Firms Association - are unhappy.  They see it as a sticking-plaster solution.  They carried out a survey this year which found that the average payment period in Ireland for SMEs is 71 days, an increase of two days on the previous quarter; that 40% of businesses are experiencing delays of three months or more; and that 14% are waiting for more than 120 days.  Some of these are State contracts, and money is awaited from the State.  Prompt payment is one of the many issues that affect business, and it needs to be dealt with.  I would appreciate the Minister's views on the EU directive and what legislation can be introduced in the State, as the support organisations are calling for payment within 30 days to be enshrined in legislation.  That would be their preference.  They were very much opposed to the preference for 60-day payment contained in the directive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O00900"><p>That issue is not part of today's discussion.  There are a few other questions as well.  The Minister may answer whatever questions he can and if he does not have the information he can forward it at a later stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O01000"><p>I will be brief.  It has been mentioned that a referendum on patents will be taking place in the State this year.  That could be an ideal time for a referendum on upward-only rent reviews also.  Some 50,000 jobs have been lost in the retail sector in recent years and 30,000 more are in danger.  This is a key competitive problem.  The Departments are landlords with upward-only rent reviews.  I do not have the most up-to-date figures but halfway through last year there were hundreds of contracts with tenants.  I am aware of one firm in Donegal which lost its business with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine as a result of the upward-only rent policy.</p><p>  In regard to Tara Mines, my request is that the Minister go to the management in an effort to ensure that the business does not go down the route of using an aggressive threat against the workers to seek a reduction in their wages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O01100"><p>Upward-only rent reviews is one issue.  There are big companies that can afford the examinership process, but most people cannot afford that process.  There is still a problem in provincial towns where landlords who are locked into mortgages are not dealing with tenants.  As Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n has said, the State is also a player in this regard.  As a landlord itself, it is enforcing upward-only rent clauses.  Whatever about private companies, the State can lead on this issue.</p><p>  The Secretary General appeared before the committee last week and has provided figures today in respect of the credit guarantee scheme and the microfinance scheme.  Under the credit guarantee scheme only ten approved credit guarantees had been issued up to 22 January, representing about &euro;1.117 million.  This seems low; is the Minister happy with the scheme?  The Minister may not have the information with him, but how many requests were turned down?  An issue we raised with the Secretary General last week and one we are hearing from companies is the interest rate on Microfinance Ireland.  He gave a very good and robust explanation of it in relation to risk factors.  There is a 5% margin on the product for Microfinance Ireland, which is a high margin in the current climate.  Many companies would be pleased to have a 5% margin.</p><p>  A serious problem is unfolding in Monaghan with regard to employment at Silvercrest and at the other company whose name emerged this morning.  Has the Department consulted with the enterprise board, the local authority, IDA Ireland or Enterprise Ireland on the issue?  Can the Minister give the committee any information on the Department's or the agencies' response to what is a potentially serious issue? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O01200"><p>I wish to raise the response from banks.  A number of people have been in contact with me in regard to the delay in getting a response back from banks, as a result of which they cannot apply to Microfinance Ireland for funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O01300"><p>I am conscious that many of these questions are not for today's discussion.  The Minister is welcome to come back to the committee with the replies if he does not have the answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500010#O01400"><p>Just before Deputy Cullinane came in, Senator Quinn had raised this issue.   The Senator is correct in saying that the EU directive is coming in.  The only legislation in this field is the legislation I introduced in 1996 in respect of the State's obligation to pay its bills on time.  That Act is effective but it does not apply to every State agency.  The Senator is correct in saying we need to get the full gamut of State agencies paying on time.  We have been trying to get a voluntary code in this area as well as the EU directive.  The EU directive provides a framework within which businesses should operate whereby they must pay on time and if not they must pay interest, including penalty interest and so on.  Given the need for a culture of compliance, we are working with the business organisations.  It is largely business-to-business.  Where one business seeks a longer period before making its payments, it means another person is left without.  It is important to get businesses working in this field.  It is not an area in which one can easily pile in with legislation because one does not know the pressures under which an individual business is operating.  There is a need to develop codes of practice and we are working on that issue.</p><p>  It is not the Government's intention to have a referendum on upward-only rent reviews.  We will have a patents referendum but that is a different issue and has to do with the patents court.  </p><p>  I do not know the full details of Tara Mines situation, but the LRC is available to support both sides in any situation.  We have an experienced service that will lend support.</p><p>  Deputy Calleary said that examinership is prohibitive for some companies.  One issue that is being provided for in the companies legislation that will come before the House in the near future is that we are bringing examinership to the Circuit Court, which will significantly reduce the cost.  That should make it more accessible to people.  The Deputy is correct in saying the credit guarantee scheme is only in its infancy.  We will be monitoring it to ascertain why there is not a greater uptake.  We are conscious that the uptake is low.  The Deputy raised the issue of microfinance.  The rate available is keener than what was available from similar players in the field.  I am confident that under the chairman the administration will be kept to the minimum.  It is a very tight ship and there will be no excess.  The board reduced the original rate, which was mentioned.  If we can reduce it we will certainly do so.  It is taking on an area of credit that is high-risk.  As it is going to be a loss-making area, we are trying to achieve a balance, making sure that people get access to funds and that there is reasonable cover for the taxpayer in taking the risk.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2013020500011#P00200"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for attending.  We dealt with more issues than were listed on the agenda, which is typical.  I also thank members for their contributions.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.218" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00" url="">Committee on Health and Children: Select Sub-Committee on Health</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.219" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 17:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.221" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500002#A00100">Public Health (Tobacco) (Amendment) Bill 2013: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500002#A00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly and his officials.  I have received apologies from Deputies Denis Naughten and Billy Kelleher.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500002#A00400"><p>I understand no amendments have been proposed to the Bill.  Therefore, I take the opportunity to thank all of the Deputies who have supported and contributed to the debate on the Bill.  While there is an obligation placed on Ireland to change its laws on the minimum pricing of tobacco, I am pleased Deputies have supported my initiatives as set out in the Bill in tackling some of the sales promotion strategies of the tobacco industry.  Smoking is one of those issues which always generates lively debate, rightly so.  Whether it be as smokers, ex-smokers, anti-smokers, relatives or friends of smokers, the issue touches so many of us during our lives and there are many views on how we should deal with it.</p><p>  I am pleased that in a recent report on tobacco undertaken by the European Commission Irish citizens were in the top rankings in their support of initiatives.  For example, we had the highest ranking among EU countries in our support of the banning of advertising from the point of sale in shops, a ban which has been introduced in Ireland.  Also we were ranked top in our support of banning the sale of tobacco on the Internet and also of the banning of colours, logos and promotion elements from cigarette packs.  Some 90% of Irish people surveyed support the placing of graphic warnings on cigarette packs, which I am happy to say were introduced last Friday.  This is important evidence of support and I am heartened that the people have a real appetite to tackle the problem of smoking.  It is very clear that the graphic displays have had a very positive effect in other jurisdictions, particularly in Canada, where, after the introduction of this measure, smokers stated they were four times more likely to attempt to give up cigarettes.</p><p>  I know of no smoker who wishes his or her child to become a smoker.  I have made it clear that in a survey conducted by my Department and the Office of Tobacco Control 78% of smokers said they had started smoking when they were minors, under the age of 18 years.  We have a duty to protect our children from this industry which seeks to promote the consumption of tobacco.  If nearly 80% started smoking when they were children, clearly, there is a major focus on children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/969" speakername="Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500003#B00200"><p>I note what the Minister has said and record my support for the passage of the Bill.  As I indicated on Second Stage, I would welcome any further restriction of the promotion of tobacco products.  I wholeheartedly endorse the Minister's efforts in that regard.  I also expressed my disappointment and concern at the EU directive on the right of the State to impose a pricing regime, which was deemed to be not permissible.  We have been directed to pull back from that position, which is most unfortunate.  The idea behind the directive allegedly was to facilitate greater competition.  If this is applicable across the board in the case of all tobacco products, with what are they competing?  My clear understanding is that the consequence of the directive was to remove a critical element of State intervention in setting the price of tobacco products for consumers, which is an integral part of the dissuasion in which we should be proactively involved.  I again note that this does not preclude address through financial measures such as taxation, but that is another day's work.  I had hoped to be able to table an amendment, but as I have indicated, unfortunately, an amendment proposed by a mere Opposition Deputy will not carry the day, given that an EU directive is in situ.  Much as I would like to have it overturned, I have had to concede on the matter and there are no permissible amendments to discuss as a consequence.  I wish the Minister a fair wind in dealing with the remaining Stages of this welcome legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/960" speakername="S&eacute;amus Healy" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500003#B00300"><p>I welcome the Minister's comments on the Bill which I support.  Will he comment on the need to continue to charge a high price for these products?  Will he comment specifically on the possibility of having an environment levy, as proposed by a number of agencies?  On the question of smuggling, will he comment on the penalties for being caught in the act of smuggling tobacco products and the proposals aimed at the control of such smuggling?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1011" speakername="Robert Dowds" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500003#B00400"><p>I, too, support the Bill.  I have two questions, one of which relates to Deputy Seamus Healy's remarks.  First, is there an organisation which is supported by the tobacco industry lobbying on behalf of small retailers and newsagents?  I cannot recall the name of the organisation, but somebody representing it met me last week and I subsequently saw an article in <i>The Guardian</i> newspaper alleging that this organisation was supporting small newsagents.  If that is the case, will it be covered by the measures contained in the Bill?</p><p>  I also echo Deputy Seamus Healy's remarks on smuggling.  Sometimes one hears the argument that there should be no further taxes on cigarettes because it would encourage illegal smuggling.  While this may not be the Minister's responsibility, I understand there are two very expensive machines to detect the smuggling of cigarettes through ports that cost about &euro;1 million each.  Given the level of smuggling, would it be worthwhile acquiring additional machines in order that such checks could be made more frequently?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1068" speakername="Peter Fitzpatrick" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500003#B00500"><p>It was very important for the Minister to retain power to introduce regulation of sales promotion devices introduced by manufacturers, for example, happy hour promotions or offers such as three packets of cigarettes for the price of two.  I am glad these provisions do not come within minimum pricing regulations and delighted the Minister has included such measures in the Bill</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500003#B00600"><p>I, too, join other members in commending the Minister's initiative.  It is important to draw attention to the major concern of members about the illicit trade in tobacco.  Last June I attended a meeting in Cork of Retailers Against Smuggling in Cork, at which they highlighted a number of issues, including the loss of revenue to the State but, more importantly, the damage the composition of cigarettes could cause.  I met the CEO of the Convenience Stores and Newsagents Association who raised the issue of promotions.  I hope that as a consequence of the Bill there will be no further promotional activities.  It is important that, together with the Minister, we advocate for the promotion of health measures.  In fact, as part of our work programme, representatives of the Irish Lung Health Alliance will come before us next Thursday.  I hope we can work in tandem with the Minister and his Department in combating not only the harmful effects of smoking but also in tackling the issue of the illegal trade in cigarettes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500003#B00700"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for their contributions.  I appreciate the support of Deputy Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in who I know, like me, is not anti-smoker but anti-smoking and anti-tobacco.  We will do everything we can to help smokers to quit the habit.  As I said elsewhere, the industry seeks to replace the small number who give up smoking and the very large number who, sadly, will die.  There is no question but that price, as Deputy Seamus Healy said, has an impact.  A sudden hike in price would be much more effective than the gradual hikes we have witnessed to date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1004" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500004#C00600"><p>I thank the Minister for being strong on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500004#C00700"><p>I thank the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, and his officials Dr. John Devlin and Mr. Leo O'Brien.  I thank the members for their co-operation and patience.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.240" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500004#C00800">Message to Dil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-02-05a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/989" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/HE12013020500004#C00900"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:<blockquote><br />The Select Sub-Committee on Health has completed its consideration of the Public Health (Tobacco) (Amendment) Bill 2013 and has made no amendments thereto.</blockquote></p></speech>
</publicwhip>