<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Martin Ferris, Senator Michael Comiskey, Deputy Martin Heydon, Senator Denis Landy, Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív, Senator Paschal Mooney, Deputy Willie Penrose, Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, Deputy Thomas Pringle, Senator Pat O'Neill.</p><p>In attendance: Deputies Lucinda Creighton, Seán Kyne and Anthony Lawlor and Senator Paul Bradford.</p><p>DEPUTY ANDREW DOYLE IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#G00150">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#G00200"><p>We will begin with a consideration of EU proposals before us.  It is proposed that the proposal listed in Schedule B, COM(2015)280 does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  Schedule A, COM(2015)212.1 is a proposal for a Council Regulation amending Regulation (EU) No. 2015/104 as regards certain fishing opportunities.  It is proposed that this proposal does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.30 p.m. and resumed at 2.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#H00050">Horse Industry in Ireland: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#H00300"><p>I wish to remind members, witnesses and those in the Visitors Gallery to turn off their mobile telephones.  I welcome the representatives of Horse Sport Ireland: Professor Patrick Wall, chairman; Mr. Damian McDonald, CEO; Mr. James Kennedy, chairman of the finance committee; and Mr. Mark Bolger, finance director.  I also welcome the representatives of the Irish Bookmakers' Association: Ms Sharon Byrne, chairperson and Mr. Paul Tully, director of Tully&rsquo;s Bookmakers.  I thank the witnesses for appearing before the joint committee today.</p> <p>  The committee appreciates that as one of the leading producers of thoroughbred and non-thoroughbred horses, the horse industry has a very positive impact on the economy of rural Ireland.  We have taken part in the pre-legislative scrutiny process on the Horse Racing Ireland (Amendment) Bill.  As part of that process we undertook to examine the wider horse industry in Ireland whereby a policy can be optimised to develop the sector in future.  </p> <p>  This is our first meeting in that regard.  Next week we will be meeting the Irish Thoroughbred Breeders Association, the Irish Horse Welfare Trust, local authority representatives and the ISPCA.</p><p>I advise witnesses that they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  If they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given.  They are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person or persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing ruling of the Chair to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or any official by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p> I propose to take opening statements from Horse Sport Ireland followed by Ms Byrne from the Irish Bookmakers Association.  Professor Wall will introduce his colleagues and then hand over to Mr. McDonald to make the opening statement. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.11" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Patrick Wall" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#J00200"><p>I thank the Chairman, Deputies and Senators for giving us the opportunity to say a few words.  Horse Sport Ireland governs non-racing sport horses.  I have been the non-executive chairperson for the past two years.  Mr. James Kennedy is the non-executive chairman of our finance committee and a former managing director of Bausch and Lomb.  He has 20 years' experience in American multinational companies so we are lucky to have him.  Mr. Mark Bolger is our financial controller on the executive staff and Mr. Damian McDonald is our CEO.</p> <p>  Horse Sport Ireland is different from many sporting federations in that it has 28 affiliates under its umbrella and covers a wide range of equestrian activities, from showjumping to mounted games, from polo to harness racing.  In addition to the sporting element, we have maintained two stud books.  We are responsible for horse registrations and we have a breeding programme to try to develop the sector.  We also engage in the marketing of horses and ponies and we market Ireland as a venue for tourism and spectating.  There are many opportunities in the field and we have just completed a strategy with two key stakeholders, the RDS and Teagasc.  We worked on a document for 12 months, which was launched in March, and it is timely that the document is out now.  The key areas we looked at included improving the herd quality, because we have the potential to produce fantastic horses on the island, and improving training and education.  We focused on marketing and sales, equine tourism and recreationally focused initiatives as well as high performance issues.  We worked on improving the experience of participants and developing enhanced structures to improve the health and welfare of horses by means of institutional capacity.  A lot of the groundwork is done but funding all these recommendations is a big challenge for us.  If we can deliver on what we have in our strategy, this sector will definitely realise its potential.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.12" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#J00300"><p>I will give a quick overview of the value of the sport horse industry to Ireland.  Figures from a UCD report of 2012 show that there were 124,000 sport horses on the island and that the sector was worth &euro;708 million to the economy each year, supporting the equivalent of 12,500 full-time jobs.  A number of people in the sector have other income but 29,000 people depend on the sector for part or all of their income, and there are 47,000 regular participants, defined as a breeder or other participant on a fortnightly basis.</p> <p>  Horse Sport Ireland is a relatively new body and became the national governing body for equestrian sport in 2008 as recognised by the international governing body, the FEI, the Irish Sports Council and the Olympic Council of Ireland.  In 2010, we were formally recognised by Sport NI as the governing body for equestrian sport on a 32-county basis.  All our equestrian teams compete on a 32-county basis.  There are some issues to be tied up as regards structures but, by and large, we operate on a 32-county basis.</p> <p>  We brought together equestrian sport, which was previously run by the Equestrian Federation of Ireland, and sport horse breeding which was carried out by the Irish Horse Board.</p><p>We were formally allocated responsibility for maintaining the Irish horse register which incorporates the Irish sport horse and Irish draught horse stud books in July 2008.  When we started out on this journey, we inherited 16 affiliates from the Equestrian Federation of Ireland but we now have 28 affiliate bodies, including the Northern Ireland Horse Board.  We do all the registrations under an agreement with the Northern Ireland Horse Board for all the horses in the Irish sport horse and Irish draught horse stud books North and South, whereas previously they were done in Naas and at a location in Northern Ireland.</p><p> I have given a brief summary of our income in the form of unaltered figures for 2014.  We received &euro;1.7 million from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, &euro;1.7 million from our own sources, &euro;1.5 million from the Irish Sports Council and Sport Northern Ireland, and last year we got a sports capital allocation of &euro;30,000, bringing our 2014 income to just over &euro;5 million.  We were in receipt of a significant uplift from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine last year, which I will deal with later and which will be included in our 2015 income.  We do not count the income earned by affiliates, which would probably be between &euro;4 million and &euro;5 million.  Such companies include Showjumping Ireland, Eventing Ireland, the Irish Pony Club and the riding clubs.</p><p> As a body we interface with Government, we act as national governing body, we maintain the Irish horse register and we issue identity documents for horses, as well as stud book documents.  This is an important point which I would like to stress.   Our policy, which is enshrined in the new strategic plan, is for all sport horses on the island to be registered and recorded with a pedigree verified by DNA testing.  One can obtain a passport for the purposes of identification for a horse but it does not record any pedigree.  This scheme was put in place for a very good reason, namely, to mop up a backlog of horses in the country which were not registered, but there are some foals still being registered without a recorded pedigree.  That is a huge loss to the sector if the animal goes on to be successful, because the added value for its dam line and its sire is lost.  It is something we need to address and there are a number of suggestions in the strategic plan, both for the industry itself and in terms of what help we could get with legislation.</p><p> We promote the Irish equestrian industry worldwide and run high performance programmes.  We now run the national equine anti-doping programme and, since 2009, all the affiliates have handed over responsibility for dope testing of horses to Horse Sport Ireland.  The results come to us, we manage them and carry out all the hearings.  It is an issue on which we have made a lot of progress and, touch wood, no horse ridden by an Irish rider in international competition has tested positive for any substance since 2008.  It had been a huge problem up to that point and we can never be complacent about it but the maintenance of a reputation on the international stage is something on which we place a very high priority.</p><p> We run the national equestrian coaching development programme and operate an online pedigree and performance database for all the horses registered on the Irish horse register.  Again, Showjumping Ireland, Eventing Ireland, the Association of Irish Riding Clubs and the international governing body provide us with a link to results in their databases, which is important in helping us give breeders and producers better information about horses.</p><p> At the London Olympic Games, equestrian sport was the only sport where Ireland won medals in the Olympic and the Paralympic Games.  Cian O&rsquo;Connor won a bronze medal in showjumping, our para-equestrian team won a team bronze medal and Helen Kearney won two individual medals.  This is a sport at which we excel and in which we have huge potential.  With further investment, we believe we can make even more progress.</p><p> Since 2008, we have introduced new high performance programmes to bring proper structures and training to our teams.  The graph shows the under-age medals won by Irish equestrian teams in FEI competitions since 2006.</p><p>As the committee can see, we have had unprecedented success in 2011, 2012, 2013 and 2014.  A lot of that success is down to the funding that we received from the Irish Sports Council which we appreciate.  We would always like more funding, of course.  The funding has allowed us to put proper structures in place.  All of our teams are now run by professional managers who select the teams.  We do not have voluntary selection committees and the selection process is managed.  The senior team is managed by Robert Splaine and the team manager for the senior eventing team is Nick Turner.  By bringing in those structures and involving proper professionals we have achieved a huge number of improvements.  </p><p> We are fortunate that the Irish senior eventing team has achieved Olympic qualification for Rio.  We have one last chance to qualify in show jumping at the European Championships which will be held in Aachen from 19 to 23 August.  We missed qualifying by less than three penalties at the World Championships so Olympic qualification is a crucial goal for us this year.  One of the Irish riders is called Bertram Allen.  He is 19-years old and is ranked 7th in the world.  He won the Longines Global Champions Tour competition at the weekend in Paris.  He came up through the under age system and a lot of the medals won at the event were won by him.  He is already a global phenomenon.  There is huge potential in terms of the glory that this one rider has brought to Ireland.  At the moment he is the most talked about rider in world show jumping.  He is a great credit to our sport and we will hear a lot more about him.  </p><p> Two years ago we opened the National Horse Sport Arena on the national sports campus.  The National Sports Campus Development Authority has developed an Olympic standard arena and it has the same surface as that found in London.  All high performance training for the Irish teams takes place at the venue.  We work very closely with the national sports campus to utilise the facility.  It is wonderful that Irish athletes can now train in a world class facility.  The venue has been a big help to us.  We could further develop the arena.  The facilities have  developed since the arena was built.  The venue now has stables but there is potential for an indoor arena and more facilities which would turn it into a world class centre of excellence.</p><p> In terms of the spread of the sport, we have 28 affiliates but for the purposes of these statistics we picked out the three Olympic disciplines.  Show jumping is the biggest discipline in the country.  Our statistics show there were 129,540 entries in show jumping last year.   The figure refers to the rounds of show jumping.  The discipline has a phenomenal reach.  In every village, parish and country in Ireland there are people involved in show jumping in an amateur and professional capacity.  The statistics also show that more than 6,000 horses are registered to compete; in eventing there were 8,000 entries and in dressage there were 5,468 entries.  The figures do not include activities carried out by the Irish Pony Club, riding clubs, hunts and several other organisations.  We have mentioned trotting and polo.  All of these categories are part of our organisation and they all have huge participation levels.  Show jumping is a sport that people can participate in from the age of five to 85.  It is also the only sport in the Olympic charter where men and women can compete on an equal basis.  That is another aspect that is unique about our sport.  There is very good participation in our sport by males and females.</p><p> On the international stage we have 548 FEI registered riders who represent Ireland in international competitions.  In 2014, they represented Ireland in 27 countries.  The phrase that we often use to describe our riders is that they are ambassadors first and sportspeople second.  The level of exposure and media coverage they bring to Ireland is phenomenal.  In fact, they probably get more media coverage abroad than they do in Ireland.  We believe there is great potential to exploit such media coverage in terms of selling and marketing Ireland abroad.</p><p> I will next discuss the breeding side.  Members should be able to see on their screens the Irish horse register's foal registration figures.  The key message to take from the data is that the number of foals produced in Ireland peaked in 2008 and the number has dropped from a peak of circa 10,000 foals down to under 6,000 foals.  The number has held reasonably well in the past four years but there was a substantial reduction from 2008 to 2011.  There was an oversupply problem in the sport horse sector in Ireland and in the thoroughbred sector as well.</p><p>There has been a significant reduction in the supply of horses.  That will help to address some of the problems, including some of the welfare problems that have presented the Irish horse sector in a bad light.  There have been some improvements but more improvements must be made.  With the reduction in the supply of foals that should be a help in terms of increasing the value of animals, so that we do not end up in a situation where we have a great many animals with no value, a recipe for problems.</p><p> We have issues with our rankings on the breeding side.  The red line tracks the event horses.  We have been top of the world every year since 2004 to 2014, with the exception of two years in that period.  That is a significant selling point for Ireland.  We are the foremost producer of three day event horses in the world, despite the fact that we are a small country relative to some of the other countries that are trying to produce horses.</p><p> However, the picture is not as positive for show jumping and there are issues which we have been addressing in our new strategy.  There are further recommendations in the new strategy on how we address this problem.  The Irish sport horse stud book shows that we are in the 12th rank for producing show jumping horses.  That must be addressed.  There have been some very positive signs in terms of the performances of our young horses at the world championships in recent years.  That measures the six top horses from the studbook each year.  They tend to be aged between 12 years and 15 years.  Our hope is that the next generation of five, six, seven and eight year old horses will be better.  If we implement this strategy we would hope the next generation again, will be better again if we can improve our breeding strategies for show jumping horses.  </p><p> The chairman has mentioned the industry's strategic plan - Reaching New Heights.  We may have circulated a copy to the members but I can recirculate a full copy of the document after the meeting.  The document was launched earlier in March of this year.  Professor Pat Wall has already touched on the main themes, improving herd quality, which is to improve the breeding of our horses, improved education and training structures, marketing and sales capacity, increasing participation, improving horse health and welfare and improving institutional capacity.  As the chairman said it took about a year to develop this strategy, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney took a particular interest in it and attended a number of the regional meetings.  He increased the allocation to Horse Sport Ireland in 2015 by &euro;600,000.  We have utilised that funding in three key ways - first, as prize money, which we have distributed to an innovation fund for innovative classes around the country, for young horse classes, for mare classes and for foal classes.  We have a new foal championship which will commence in the coming weeks and will take place in five regions.  The Northern Ireland Horse Board has funded a regional qualifier event in Northern Ireland.  One of the challenges we have as a sector is that while on the sports side there is funding coming from Northern Ireland, on the breeding side, there is no funding from the Northern Ireland Government.  While we operate on a Thirty-two county basis, the funding is all provided by the Government in the Republic.  That is a point the Minister, Deputy Coveney has been making, to try to draw in some additional funding from Northern Ireland for the breeding side.  As of yet, that has not been successful.  That is a key issue that needs to be addressed.  I know there are similar issues on the racing side.</p><p> We have set up a new international marketing division within Horse Sport Ireland and we ran a new series called Jumping in the City,  under which we brought show jumping to greyhound stadiums.  We had one event in Cork, one in Limerick with the final one in Shelbourne Park.  The goal of that initiative was to try to increase the profile of our sport and by bringing show jumping to the city to try to get new people to come and look at it.  Our new international marketing director, Ms Elaine Hatton, joins us from Irish Thoroughbred Marketing and has been in situ for approximately one month.  That is an exciting development for us.  Irish Thoroughbred Marketing has been very successful in marketing the Irish Thoroughbred on the international stage and basically we are trying to replicate that by having a sport horse marketing operation within Horse Sport Ireland, which Ms Hatton is heading up.</p><p>When she is settled in, I sure she will be happy to come and give an update on how we are doing in international markets and outline what her strategies will be.  She is developing a programme in that regard.</p><p> The Jumping in the City series was one of the initiatives we funded from the extra resources received from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  It was very successful in that there were huge crowds in each of the stadiums.  Obviously, there are lessons to be learned from it for next year.  On 21 July we will make a presentation to the board on the outcome of the series to see how we can proceed.  It involved good collaboration with the Irish Greyhound Board and it has great potential to continue with it.  We hope we have demonstrated, as an organisation and an industry, that we have delivered real value for the extra &euro;600,000 provided.  The sector is still dependent on voluntary effort, but we can leverage a good deal.  Even for an event such as Jumping in the City a huge amount of the work that goes into it is done by people on a voluntary basis.  The same applies to shows all around the country.  There are 159 shows run all around Ireland, largely and almost exclusively through voluntary effort.  </p><p> We can give good value for money with an increased investment in the sector.  We are aware that the thoroughbred sector receives in excess of &euro;45 million each year; the greyhound sector, circa &euro;12 million, while we receive &euro;3 million.  Our argument is that in our sector we have more horses and more people and that we make a major contribution to social capital all around the country.  With further investment the sector could deliver much more.  We have many more initiatives, some of which are outlined in the strategy, that we would like to implement.  For many reasons, for a long period the sector was not as well organised and we fell behind in the funding stakes.  That there is no betting is a fair point, but given the amount of money contributed by the Government, even excluding betting tax revenue, a case can be made for an increased allocation.  </p><p> We are delighted to have an opportunity to outline what the sector does and to take whatever questions committee members may have.  I have covered the sector briefly.  If anybody wants to receive more detailed information, we will be happy to provide it.  I again thank the committee for giving us the opportunity to make this presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#N00200"><p>I invite Ms Byrne to make her presentation, following which we will have questions which will be grouped.  Perhaps questioners might concentrate on one subject first, to be followed by a second.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.18" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Sharon Byrne" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#N00300"><p>I thank the Chairman and members for giving me the opportunity to appear before the joint committee.  We are delighted to participate in its review of the horse industry in Ireland.  Before commencing, I commend Horse Sport Ireland, the presentation of which was excellent.  It is an untold success story and should be highly commended.  It is a sector in which there are massive levels of employment, of which I was unaware.  I support any proposal it brings forward.</p> <p>  I am chairperson of the Irish Bookmakers Association which represents all betting shops.  I am accompanied by Mr. Paul Tully, a director of Tully Bookmakers which has more than 20 shops across Ireland.  It is also represented at race tracks and has been one of the few bookmakers left standing at the track throughout the recession.  Mr. Tully and I hope to highlight the important contribution betting shops have made in funding Horse Racing in Ireland for a long time.  We also hope to highlight the severe difficulties facing betting operators and the thousands of jobs being lost.  </p> <p>  There are 958 betting shops in Ireland, down from 1,365 in 2008, in which approximately 8,000 people are employed.  A further breakdown is given on page 6  of our submission.  The Indecon report published in 2012 stated there were almost 20,000 people working in the horse racing industry in Ireland, but this figure included those working in betting shops - 8,000.  The importance of the employment we provide should be noted.  More than 400 betting shops have closed in the past six years, with the loss of 3,000 jobs approximately.  Most of the closures are of small independent operators in rural parts of Ireland.  Turnover in the sector dropped from &euro;3.5 billion in 2008 to &euro;2.6 billion in 2014.</p><p>There is a further breakdown on page 5 of our submission.  This decline continues and jobs in betting shops are being lost weekly.  Retail operators are competing with online and mobile operators which can easily target our customers while inside shops.  This has been a huge contributing factor to the decline in our industry.  Until this year, these operators were able to trade free of betting tax.</p><p> Tax increases for our industry are frequently touted but it must be outlined how steeply the retail industry is currently taxed and how turnover is so intrinsically linked to taxation that any changes would have a severe impact on our sector.  An average betting shop pays &euro;66,500 a year in taxes.  With every shop that closes, in addition to that &euro;66,500, it would cost the Exchequer a further &euro;95,000 in unemployment payments for the five or six staff the shop had employed.  It should also be noted that the betting sector is VAT exempt.  This means we cannot reclaim VAT.  We pay all the other taxes every business pays as well as rates.  We also pay, in addition to those taxes, a turnover tax of 1% on our entire turnover regardless of profit or loss.  The rate may sound small but, when applied to a high turnover-low margin business, it is substantial.  It is penal to smaller operators who struggle for turnover and margin to afford this levy.  </p><p> As those present are aware, our members are the main contributors to the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund and sponsor many meetings across the country.  We pay for access to pictures and data for Irish meetings on top of the betting tax and this money is paid directly to the racetracks themselves.  Many of the tracks would not be able to run many of their meetings if they were not getting these direct payments for pictures.  On top of the betting duty we are paying, we are also paying approximately &euro;30 million for the pictures.  Payments for our pictures and data have risen dramatically over the past few years and the costs per shop have increased by 33.5% since 2006.  Page 8 of our submission outlines how much we are paying.  Each betting shop currently pays &euro;42,000 a year for pictures for racing.  That is &euro;42,000 per shop and approximately &euro;3,000 of that sum goes on Irish racing pictures and the rest goes on UK racing, German racing, virtual content greyhounds and data.  That figure is up from &euro;31,000 in 2006.  The bulk of the increase went to racing in both the UK and Ireland.</p><p> Another factor which seriously affects the cost of the racing content is the exchange rate.  We pay most of our costs via UK suppliers, particularly those for our racing pictures, which go to Horse Racing Ireland.  Apart from the 30% premium on the sterling exchange rate, which has been there for quite some time now, we pay VAT at 23% on top of that, which we cannot claim back.  This makes the price of racing and data very expensive.</p><p> The most important point I wish to make is on page 13 of our submission.  For those who may not have a copy of it, the entire retail betting sector in 2014, which includes every betting shop in Ireland, after all taxes and expenses are paid, made a profit of &euro;12 million to &euro;14 million.  This is not just me blowing hot air, these are published figures available online.  PaddyPower, in its Irish retail sector, made &euro;50 million according to its published plc accounts.  We estimate the value of the retail estate of Boylesports is somewhere between &euro;3 million and &euro;5 million.  That is an estimate and I cannot back up the figure categorically.  Ladbrokes lost &euro;5 million in 2014.  That figure was published by the examiner and I am sure everyone here has seen the figure in the media.  Independent retailers lost somewhere between &euro;3 million and &euro;5 million in 2014.  When one combines all of those sums, the profit made for the entire 950 shops in Ireland last year was between &euro;10 million and &euro;12 million.  That is what was made but we pay Irish racing &euro;26 million.</p><p>Not alone does it get the &euro;26 million from Irish shops but it also gets a further payment from UK shops.  If one combines what it is getting from 9,500 shops in the United Kingdom with what it is getting from 1,000 shops in Ireland, plus picture payments and sponsorship, it gets &euro;53 million on top of the Exchequer funding the Government pays to it each year.</p><p> Some will say the online operators are all creaming it and not paying anything.  If anyone were to check our submissions over the past eight years, he or she would see we have been pressing for the online sector to be taxed for betting duty because there has been a completely unlevel playing field.  The Government is introducing an arrangement in this regard this year.  From 1 August, online operators must pay the same tax the betting shops are paying in respect of Irish people betting.  We estimate that will bring in between &euro;15 million and &euro;20 million in additional betting tax, but it is not true to say that the online sector has not been contributing.  It has been paying for pictures via streaming and has been paying for the data.  It is already paying towards the horse racing, and the extra betting tax that is being introduced and which will go to the Exchequer should be spent by the Government as it sees fit.</p><p> In our shops, approximately 50% of our revenue in retail is from horse racing but that includes UK racing, German racing, Latin American racing and French racing.  Irish racing accounts for 12% of our total turnover in our shops.  With regard to the &euro;12 million profit we made last year, 12% was from Irish racing.  Therefore, we made &euro;1.2 million in Irish betting shops from Irish horse racing last year, and we paid &euro;26 million for it.</p><p> The retail betting sector is fully licensed and regulated.  We operate our business in a socially responsible manner.  We fund a charity based in Northern Ireland that provides advice and treatment for people affected by problem gambling.  That centre is called the Dunlewey Centre.  It is a well-recognised and highly experienced addiction service centre that provides a freephone service that is operational seven days per week.  It also provides free face-to-face counselling sessions all over Ireland.  The service is fully funded by most bookmakers in Ireland.  The reason I included this in the submission is that at every committee meeting I have attended, problem gambling always seems to arise and people are not aware of the services that are offered.  I have included information in this regard for anybody who is interested.</p><p> I appreciate the opportunity to make my points today.  We will answer any questions that arise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#P00200"><p>I am pleased we had the two submissions.  They were very useful.  Before we ask specific questions, we must stand back and say we are in a country that has a reputation for horses.  We have the land, climate and, perhaps more important, the reputation and human capital in general to make a success of this industry.  It is all very intelligent to talk about attracting foreign direct investment and multinationals, as we often do, but it is equally important to consider all the natural industries we could have, or already have that could be a lot bigger and ask how we could develop and exploit them.</p> <p>  How does one develop the horse racing industry, from the very top to the very bottom without distinction, exploiting each sector for its potential?  Rather than seeing the various elements as rivals, they should be regarded as complementary products and as part of a totality.  In other words, one should sell this island as being the horse island and one of the premier places in the world for horses, be they sport horses, thoroughbred horses or horses of any other kind.</p> <p>  I have a technical question before I ask more generally about where we go from here.</p><p>The Irish Sports Council and Sport Northern Ireland give Horse Sport Ireland &euro;1,531,005.  How much of that comes from our brethren in the northern part of the country?  Could its Department of Culture, Arts and Leisure be persuaded to come up to the plate a little bit better than it has?  There seem to be many rows about UK Exchequer funding up there.</p><p> If the strategic plan were implemented fully, what would the country benefit economically from it?  What annual investment is needed to implement the strategic plan?  I accept the points about the social return, such as volunteerism and the enjoyment gained from equestrian sports, but it is the economic return on which we want to focus.  How many jobs will be created by developing a much better domestic and international equestrian product?  We need to know how important this industry could be to the country.  How much do horse-related activities contribute to tourism?  How many people come to Ireland to pursue horse-related tourism activities?  How important are special and indigenous breeds, such as Connemara ponies and the Irish Draught, to highlighting the Irish horse as a unique product and how does this contribute to the industry?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#Q00200"><p>I welcome both delegations.  While there is much tidying up still to be done in the industry, I commend Horse Sport Ireland on the excellent work it has done so far.</p> <p>  Why has Ireland dipped in international show-jumping rankings over the past ten years?  Horse Sport Ireland stated in its report that it was addressing this.  What does this entail?  In recent years, we have seen some fantastic under age talent emerge in show-jumping.</p><p>I am lucky to know some of them.  We need to address how we can support young talented riders and to harness, no pun intended, their talent.</p><p> I am aware of the difficulties that our young rising talented riders face.  Somebody riding a horse worth &euro;100,000 may be competing against a rider on a horse worth &euro;10,000.  The person riding the &euro;10,000 horse might be better than the other competitor but he or she does not have the same quality animal.  Sometimes that talent is lost to the industry when he or she is frustrated by the effort to get to the top.</p><p> I acknowledge there are some bursaries but I would like to see more money being invested in bursaries and support for young talent.</p><p> I welcome the efforts that Horse Sport Ireland is making on registering horses.  Will the witnesses provide more detailed information on DNA?  Is it the aim of Horse Sport Ireland that the DNA of every horse will be traceable?  When will that happen?</p><p> Chairman, are we putting questions to the Irish Bookmakers Association at this stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#R00200"><p>We will come back to that later</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#R00300"><p>I thank the board of Horse Sport Ireland for their excellent presentation.  Based on what has been achieved by Horse Sport Ireland I too, like Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, would invest in it.  Horse Sport Ireland has a website with a vast reach, and has brought its affiliates under one roof.  As a potential investor in the company I would love to hear Horse Sport Ireland outline its vision for the future and what it could do with funding.</p> <p>  What worries me is the stud book and I would like to hear more about it.  I attended some of the excellent evening events hosted by Horse Sport Ireland around the country.  I have spoken a few times to the chairman who is very learned on the subject of the stud book.  How does one get the rankings up to the level of the horses in the eventing world?</p> <p>  I know that Rory McIlroy has to live in America, but why does Bertram Allen have to live in Germany?  Why is Cian O'Connor the only rider who can live in Ireland?  Do our young riders have to live in Europe in order to compete and be in the centre of things?   </p> <p>  Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v asked how we become the centre of excellence for breeding horses.  Do we need something similar to the National Stud to buy in the best stallions?  How can we get back to being the go-to island in the world for excellence whether for show jumpers or the eventers?</p> <p>  Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v mentioned the Connemara ponies which are unique to us.  The French invested in good horses for their riders at the junior European showjumping Championship.  I made representations to this committee last year for funding for that championship but the allocation was so small it was mortifying.  Yet the whole of Europe was coming to participate in it.  We did very well, but the French showed us up, as they had been investing copious amounts of money for years in their horses, many of which were Irish-bred Connemara ponies.  I wonder if Horse Sport Ireland has the vision and the plans to do something similar.  It is a long-term project and not a quick win.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1186" speakername="Lucinda Creighton" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#R00400"><p>I welcome the representatives from the Irish Bookmakers Association and Horse Sport Ireland.  I am particularly pleased to welcome them because my father was a bookmaker for about 40 years.  He had a small retail office and I worked with him at greyhound tracks and at pony racing around the country.  It is an issue close to my heart.  I have been involved in showjumping since I was four years old.</p> <p>  I congratulate Horse Sport Ireland.  I think Jumping in the City was a fantastic success and I was delighted to attend the final in Shelbourne Park.  This was an excellent collaboration with Bord na gCon.  To give credit, where credit is due, it was a real success which I hope will be replicated in the future.  I have no doubt that it will.</p> <p>  There has been a lot to celebrate in equestrian sports in the past few years.  Bertram Allen, the name keeps coming up, is literally a 19 year old whippersnapper from Wexford who is ranked seventh place in the world.</p><p>He is largely ignored by the domestic media, which is a real shame.  Bertram Allen is a role model; his work ethic and professionalism are a credit to his family.  He is a credit to the work of Horse Sport Ireland and Showjumping Ireland.  It is worth noting that Horse Sport Ireland's social media work is excellent because many organisations get it badly wrong.  I follow its Twitter and Facebook accounts which are constantly updated.</p><p> I would like to concentrate on the owners of top level showjumping horses.  The real problem is that the availability of such horses is unpredictable.  We know that one of the top Irish riders who competed at the World Equestrian Games last summer had his entire string of horses pulled from him earlier this year, with just 24 hours notice.  We are relying on foreign overseas investors in showjumping horses that we are expecting to bring us to the World Equestrian Games, the Olympic Games and so on.  I would love to see a plan being put forward to incentivise people to invest in Irish horses on behalf of our riders.  It would not be rocket science to put in place tax incentives to encourage the diaspora in London and the United States to invest in horses.  Frankly, I do not care whether they are Irish bred or otherwise because the first priority is to have our riders winning on the world stage.  Horse Sport Ireland should be promoting and fighting to secure the best horses and this should be included in its budget submission.  This would be a win-win strategy and potentially attract investment by the Irish abroad.  It is something we need to do urgently. </p><p> I welcome the Investec sponsorship deal, which represents fantastic news, about which I  would love to hear more.  As I understand it, the sponsorship package will cover the team competing at the RDS and the FEI European Championships in Aachen in Germany this summer, both qualifier events for the Olympic Games.  Is there an expiry date on this sponsorship deal?  Is Horse Sport Ireland looking at other potential sponsors?  This sponsorship deal represents really good news and I am delighted to hear about it.  The Holy Grail is the Olympic Games and success breeds success.  That Cian O'Connor won a bronze medal in 2012 was a huge cause for celebration and he was very unlucky not to quality last summer.  I am confident, however, that the showjumpting team will qualify this year and congratulate the eventers who have already qualified for the Olympic Games.  That brings me back to the questions of finding quality horses and those who own them; we cannot separate the two.</p><p> The work being done to improve the breeding programme is welcome.  I know that this is an issue close to the heart of Professor Patrick Wall.  I hope he will be more successful at it than he was at the Jumping in the City event, but I will not go there, as I do not wish to embarrass him before the committee.  I would, however, like to hear about the timeframe for the breeding programme.  This ties in with some of the questions asked by Senator Mary Ann O'Brien and Deputy &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v on the five and ten year benchmark.  Is there room for the Army Equitation School which has no money to buy or retain good quality Irish horses?  I hope that as we improve the quality of Irish bred horses, there will be a role for the school.  </p><p> These are just a few of the issues I wish to raise that are very important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1063" speakername="Willie Penrose" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#S00200"><p>I always remember my late mother saying one never saw a poor bookmaker.  However, the Irish Bookmakers Association has cried poverty.  We did not realise we had so many bookmakers.  Certainly, rural bookmakers who provide employment are suffering.</p> <p>  Tremendous progress has been made by Horse Sport Ireland.  Reaching New Heights, the title of the strategy it sent us last April, was excellent.  Of course, much of it is aspirational, unless it is underpinned by funding.  Let us be clear on the need for funding.  Very often when money is invested in an industry such as that overseen by Horse Sport Ireland, there is a negative reaction, as people think it is a waste, particularly when other bodies are competing for very scarce resources.  Money invested in this sector was subject to significant criticism, but I am glad that everybody is on board, as we did try to provide some money in the past five years to ensure the industry would continue.  I am delighted to see progress being made in the high performance sector.</p><p>Professor Wall may look young, but he and I clashed in the mid-1970s in the Ags <i>v</i>. Vets Duke football cup final which was not for the faint-hearted.  I am delighted to see another Gaelic football man making tremendous progress in the eventing programme, Mr. Joseph Murphy, who is from my neck of the woods and comes from a great Gaelic football family.  He has come within a hair's breadth of securing a medal in a very demanding area, which shows what can be done.<br/><br/>I take the point made by Deputy Lucinda Creighton about owners.  However, while progress at the top level is important, I am more worried about owners at the lower level, as they are the ones who produce the horses.  They are at the farm gate in their area, but they are not getting a look-in because at that level it is not a very lucrative or profitable enterprise.  The question is how do we intervene at the non-thoroughbred level to make sure they will continue.  I make a plea on their behalf in the same way Deputy &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, rightly, makes a plea on the distinctiveness of Connemara.<br/><br/>We have all lauded the achievement in qualifying for the Olympic Games in Rio de Janeiro, as it gives us a great sense of national pride to see our own making such progress.  However, I still worry.  At one time, the racing industry was a poor man's trade, but that is no longer the case and small owners are going out of business.  We cannot forget the people with one, two or three horses.  They have produced some magnificent winners and if we were to go back through their pedigrees, we would see that was where part of the nucleus of the industry originated.  However, despite our rush to acclaim the boys at the top - the big boys - everybody cannot be a Coolmore because that level of funding is not available for ordinary people.  Horse Sport Ireland has to implement a strategy that will show a preference.  Let us be clear about this: the people who are able to do it will do it, but we are losing out when it comes to people who have the potential but not the financial wherewithal to do it.  There is a huge gap, some of which can be explained by the figures included in Horse Sport Ireland's presentation, for which I compliment the delegates.  There is a lot of waffle, but Horse Sport Ireland has got down to brass tacks.  Senator Denis Landy has noted that we have dropped in the rankings.  Part of the problem in that regard is the industry is no longer profitable for some.<br/><br/>On the policy of having all sports horses registered and recorded, with their pedigree identified and DNA traced, that is the bedrock on which the industry will progress.  What percentage of foals are being lost in the recording system in the sense that their pedigree is not recorded?  Is it a significant or small number?<br/><br/>Horse Sport Ireland has used the additional money allocated well.  I am glad that it has not all been put into one area; rather than having all its eggs in one basket, it has opted to invest in three or four areas.  That is important because we must have an inclusive rather than an exclusive industry.  For a while it looked as if it was moving that way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#T00200"><p>On the issue of identity documents, reference was made to DNA.  Does it include microchipping also?  I know that under animal health and welfare regulations, all horses have to be microchipped once they are presented.  Are all new foals microchipped automatically?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.32" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Patrick Wall" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#T00300"><p>I will deal with some of the questions asked and then hand over to Mr. McDonald.  </p> <p>  Our objective is aligned with that of Deputy &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v.  We want to make Ireland the land of the horse and the go-to place for riders of all levels.  Horse riding is a sport for high net worth individuals everywhere.</p><p>Just as we cannot drink all the milk or eat all the beef we produce in Ireland, we cannot ride all the horses we produce.  The minor game is Ireland; the senior game is outside Ireland.  Therefore, our strategy is export-led growth.  We want to connect with all those people across the globe because we have special animals to offer.  Some of our competitor stud books can produce elite showjumpers but they cannot do what we can do.  We have an animal for all levels of riders, both horses and ponies.</p><p> The Connemara pony is an iconic brand that is known all over the world.  The Connemara stud book has 18 daughter stud books which all meet every year at the Clifden show, which has phenomenal international participation and thousands of spectators.  It is like the United Nations for Connemara.  I think we undersell it.  When we have Chinese visitors and the like here, we should give them a Connemara pony as a gift when they are going home.  It is a brand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#U00200"><p>There is a precedent in that one was given to Jackie Kennedy in 1963.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.35" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Patrick Wall" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#U00300"><p>That is correct.  Senator Landy asked why we have dropped to 12th in the showjumping rankings.  The sport of showjumping has changed and our animals have not adapted accordingly.  Traditionally, we used to sell the best and breed from the rest, which was a recipe for going downhill.  As Deputy Penrose said, the emphasis has to be on developing the breeders.  They have to focus on the performance of the dam.  The psychology that a mare was not much good of a performer but will be a great mare to breed from is what has us where we are.  We have to focus on dams that have performers in their pedigree, that have performed themselves or that are breeding performers.  We can do that but it is a huge educational issue.  Mr. McDonald highlighted that better.  Younger horses are coming along so I anticipate we will move up from that 12th position.</p> <p>  Senator Landy made the point about investment in young people.  Any investment in the young is an investment in the future.</p> <p>  In response to Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, I agree Bertram Allen is a star.  It is amazing he is not a household name with the non-horsey population because what he has achieved is unbelievable.</p> <p>  We could field an Irish team with the Irish-based riders who are based on three different continents.  We can definitely breed the riders so the whole challenge is to get the breeders to breed better horses.  If we had all these top riders riding Irish horses, they would be a phenomenal advertisement for the country.</p> <p>  The point about the National Stud was raised in the discussions around the country.  The National Stud is in Kildare and is focused purely on the thoroughbreds.  It is nearly 800 acres and the idea that there would be one yard devoted to sport horses is not a bad idea, given it is owned by the taxpayers.  Such a yard could focus on high genetic merit.  There is much we could do with sport horses that we cannot do with the thoroughbreds, such as using artificial insemination and embryo transfer to make rapid genetic gain.</p> <p>  Deputy Creighton referred to Jumping in the City, which was an attempt to attract new audiences.  We are in the entertainment business as well competing, and spectators, media coverage and sponsorship are inextricably linked.  We complain if we do not get the coverage but, at many events, there are only participants.  We got more than 3,500 people in Shelbourne Park to watch just 38 horses, which demonstrates the enthusiasm that exists.  They were all Irish but if one thinks of the RDS and the number of international tourists, we can see the phenomenon we have.  In addition, many new people came along.  If we want to get new sponsors or new owners, we have to introduce them to the sport.</p> <p>  The tax incentives are a great idea and it would be great if we could progress that.  With regard to the Army Equitation School, everyone loves to see the Army and they can relate to the Army as its members are here all the time and can go to the local shows.  Unfortunately, the big money and the big competitions are abroad so, while the public know the Army people, they do not know our riders who are based abroad.</p> <p>  Deputy Penrose hit the nail on the head when he said that some of the strategy, which is a good strategy with good ideas, is almost like a wishlist.  As the Deputy said, it is aspirational if we do not underpin it with the funding to implement it.  We are not realising our full potential.  We have the capacity to do far better with the sector on the breeding side, on the competition side and on the tourism side, but more seed capital is needed.</p><p> I will invite Mr. James Kennedy, our financial controller, to respond.  We had some money in the innovation fund, only &euro;100,000, to try to stimulate ideas but it was completely oversubscribed. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. James Kennedy" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00200"><p>Yes, it was.  We were absolutely amazed.  We got &euro;700,000 worth of inquiries or ideas.  We could have funded each one of them and have had a return on it.  Unfortunately, we were able to give out only &euro;70,000 of the funding.  Some of those events, shows and competitions, were super events throughout the country at different levels.  It gave us an enthusiasm.  This is not a begging bowl.  It is an investment in the future and we believe we can get a return on what we are doing.  A very good question from Deputy &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v is how much money we want and what would be the return.  We have a lot of work to do before we can give a proper answer to that question.  We have the strategy.  I think we have had four months of a short trial but we see we can do things with new ideas.  Our plan would be to work on that strategy for the rest of the year and come forward with a phased investment and, equally, a return.  The one thing I can say from all my years in business is that it is a very exciting organisation in which to be involved and it has a huge future if we manage it correctly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00300"><p>As a committee we are looking at the horse industry as a potentially rich resource but the industry will not invest unless it gets a return.  Can the representatives come back in due course and tell the committee that if a certain amount is invested, some return will be made directly and some indirectly?  At the end of the day that is how it will have to be measured because money is scarce.  I understand all the social issues and so on but let us park those for a while.  If there were a straight investment, what would we get in return?  With people queueing up with ideas for Government, should the industry be in that queue and can it justify the investment?  Intrinsically, one would imagine it would because there are a number of natural advantages.  One thing I see all the time is that the success of native industries can be attributed to a natural resource or, more important, human capital - a particular expertise or knowledge that people bring to it where there can be an international advantage.  Obviously, if one could get both going together, it is likely that one could turn out a very successful industry.  However, we need quantification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. James Kennedy" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00400"><p>We would be very happy to come back on that issue.  Tied to that we are very excited about the appointment of our new executive marketing director because export has to be the way to proceed with the business.  As the Chairman said we have to breed right.  Through our online project, Gateway, we have already seen, with virtually no investment, that people are buying online and we can promote that concept.  We have a number of ambassadors.  We meet every single group that goes overseas from Horse Sport Ireland and explain the significance of what those ambassadors are doing.  They are not just representing Ireland, they are helping to sell our horses.  We will come back on that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.40" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00500"><p>The first question was on how much of that comes from Sport NI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.41" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Mark Bolger" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00600"><p>It is &euro;150,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.42" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00700"><p>It is &euro;150,000 of the &euro;1.5 million.  We were very happy to get it.  It took a lot of work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00800"><p>If it were to pay <i>pro rata</i>for its population, it would be a lot more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.44" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V00900"><p>We did the <i>pro rata</i>sums and it is an argument.  It is 18.26%.  It is a work in progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V01000"><p>If all the funding from the Irish Sports Council, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Exchequer is taken into account, there is a massive difference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.46" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Professor Patrick Wall" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V01100"><p>That would make a difference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V01200"><p>There is no question about it.  It would be a huge help.  All the competitions, bar one or two, would be open to participants from Northern Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#V01500"><p>I attended a great horse show in the Odyssey Arena as Minister.  I am not big into horses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#W00100"><p>That was before our time.  It was very successful for a few years but they needed further investment.  While it was invested in by the authorities in the North for a while, that dropped off, but I am not sure of the reasons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.50" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#W00200"><p>That is why.  It was funded by the Ulster Scots and the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Damian McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#W00300"><p>It was a very successful show.  Just to cover the other points that, perhaps, the chairman has not covered.  On the DNA  side, about 15% of the foals we register do not have a defined pedigree but 85% have.  The figures for older horses are the opposite.  There are many more older horses registered without pedigree than there are with pedigree.  Part of that is mopping up of a historical situation.  All of the animals are microchipped, even those that do not have a recorded pedigree.  One of the competitive advantages our stud book has since 1999 is that we have verified the parentage of all the animals in the stud book using DNA, thanks to funding from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  That is the way we have to go.  Many of the competitions and initiatives we organise here would be restricted to animals with fully recorded pedigree.  We need to get that message out to people that one has to record a pedigree.  We need people to give us that information to build our stud book and build our breeds, otherwise we will go nowhere.</p> <p>  On a related point in regard to ponies, recently we got a licence from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to open a sport pony stud-book.  Again, the problem with non-recorded pedigree would be even greater in ponies.  The Senator made a good point when she said our ponies are still very sought after.  However, many of them are leaving the country with no papers.  That is an issue we have to address.  We have a newly established sport pony stud book that we hope to populate in the coming years.  </p> <p>  The issue about owners is a key point.  Most of our senior show-jumping team are fuelled by foreign owners.  We have appointed Tamso Doyle formerly of Horse Sport Ireland, to work with our owners.  We have an owners' programme in place to better acknowledge the contribution those owners, many of whom are foreign, have made to us.  The Deputy's point about looking at tax incentives to get more Irish people to invest in top horses is a good one and one that we should follow up on.  </p> <p>  We were fortunate this year that a donor made a significant contribution towards funding our eventing team for the Olympics.  That will be a big help.  The Deputy mentioned the sponsorship deal from Investec announced this morning.  We are delighted that a company of the standing of Investec has got involved in the Irish show-jumping team.  It is a limited arrangement.  It runs up until the end of this year's European championships.  It is for the  Dublin horse show and the European championships.  We hope that this would be an introduction and that we would have a long-term relationship with Investec.  The results will be crucial and hopefully we can deliver at the European championships.</p> <p>  Earlier there was much talk about qualifying for the Olympics.  Qualifying in show-jumping for the Olympics is quite difficult because even though we are very good on the world stage, there are only three places exclusively kept for European teams.  Some of the European teams won places at the world championships, which opens up a few more places.  The Olympic movement operates on the principle of universality.  It has places reserved for all the other continents as well.  The reality is that the best teams do not necessarily get to go to the Olympics because of the regional spread.  We are in Europe.  It is a very competitive pool to get out of but, touch wood, if things go well on the day, we should be able to pull off a result to do it.  </p> <p>  I think I have dealt with most of the issues.  If there is anything I have left out, please prompt me and I will be happy to follow up on it afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#W00400"><p>I thank everybody for their contributions.  I will go around again if there are any further questions.  I think a couple have been indicated to the Irish Bookmakers Association.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Deputy Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#W00500"><p>I thank the Irish Bookmakers Association for its presentation.  The headline figure for turnover was &euro;2.6 billion.  The first thing that strikes me is that for every adult in the State that represents &euro;800 in betting.  There are many people like me who do not bet.  For a country that people are always saying is bust, some people are betting quite an amount of money.  Some of these statistics are always interesting.</p><p>Have the witnesses any figures on how much betting now takes place online as compared to through bookmakers?  It is a crucial figure because there is currently a natural move to all sorts of things being done online.  Nothing can be had from the Department of Agriculture these days without filling in a form online.</p><p> The witnesses talk about a decline.  There was always going to be a decline from the peak, because the economy declined.  It is discretionary spending and the first thing to be taken off the agenda is betting.  Let us be honest.  On average, the bookmaker has to win, otherwise there would be no bookmakers.  That includes all the online betting operations.  A friend of mine says the house always wins in the end.  That is the nature of the business.  Only a real expert could make a living out of betting against the shop.</p><p> I would be interested in the witnesses' views on how much of the decline, and the rise to the &euro;3.2 billion, is due to the economy - a fair bit of it must be - and to what extent it is just a natural change.  Whether people are banking, filling in forms, taxing their car or doing a million other things, there has been a move away from physically having to go somewhere to do a thing, towards to being able to do it anywhere, particularly because of these gadgets that allow people do all sorts of things where they are sitting.  No matter what financial regime we had in place, some of this change was going to happen anyway.</p><p> Although bookmakers cannot claim back VAT, they are also not paying VAT.  Most people who can claim back VAT wind up paying more on the sales than they do getting VAT deductions on the purchases.  That is the way VAT works.  If the Government brought in a 5%, 10% or 15% VAT rate, the bookmakers would wind up paying more than they would save in all the reclaims.  I am not sure that argument stands up but I would be interested in the witnesses' take on it.</p><p> When we consider the history of betting duty, it was at 10% and went down to 5% in 1999.  In 2002, it went down to 2% and was cut to 1% in 2006.  I was there for the last two reductions although I was not in Cabinet for the first one.  We brought the rate down because the market was totally distorted between online betting and the bookmakers' betting.  The fear was that we were accelerating the migration to online betting and I think we had a fair point, as there was a fair amount of employment in the bookmakers' shops.  Can we turn it around in the other direction?  If online betting is now the favourite, would it be a good idea to have a higher online betting duty than bookmakers' duty, say, if we had 3% online and 1% in the shops?  What is to say we could not reverse it in this way?  What would the witnesses think of that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#X00200"><p>I think that is a rhetorical question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#X00300"><p>We have to look at all the possibilities because the Government has to look for sources of funding.</p> <p>  The witnesses seemed to emphasise the question of why betting duties should go to horse racing, given that so little of the betting is actually on Irish horse racing.  That is a good question and there is an argument in favour of a "hypothecation" as they call it, that is, that a particular tax is given over to a particular purpose.  The Department of Finance hates hypothecation.  The Department would get the money in the form of a lump sum and then decide how it is going to distribute it but it wants to have all the money to play around with at the beginning of the year.  There is only an advantage in hypothecation if more money is going to be raised.  It is fair to say that the public does not tend to see investing in horses as a good industry investment.  It is actually much happier for us to invest in multinational high-tech and software companies.  For some reason I cannot understand the public is not so keen on investing in thoroughbred horses, although they are huge earners for the country and we have a natural advantage in this area.</p><p>If that is a problem, it makes sense to look at hypothecation, even though there is no direct relationship.  Does the objection come from the bookmakers?</p><p> The bottom line of the submission is a plea for no further taxes.  Is that because of the competition with the online service or is it because it is believed the turnover on betting would drop?  Of course, we cannot know the answer to that unless we get the figures for the online betting and learn whether they have grown as betting with bookmaker shops has dropped and then factor in the drop in the economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#Y00200"><p>I thank the witnesses for their submission.  Bookmakers are a little like politicians - nobody believes them, no matter what they say.  I was born and reared across from a bookmaker's shop and when The Hook was in action - Deputy Creighton will remember that - I was hooked at the time.  I grew up with backing horses but I have seen huge change in the industry.  I have also seen huge change in the little town I come from, Carrick-on-Suir, because retail shops are closing and business is going on line.</p> <p>  I feel sympathy for the smaller bookmakers but the multiples are getting as much online as the real online companies.  I have accounts with a number of bookmakers and it is a lot easier to sit down on a wet Saturday evening and go online and watch whatever is on than to go to town and find parking.  The little advantage Irish bookmaker shops had and seemed to use for a while was customer service.  Biscuits were provided in some of them at one stage, but the biscuits have been withdrawn now and all that is provided is tea.  This might seem funny but the point is that unless bookmakers provide an extra service people will use the online service.</p> <p>  I do not think there is anything in the point made about how much money bookmakers make from Irish horseracing.  There is probably three times more racing going on in England every day than in Ireland.  Certainly there is on an annual basis.  People cannot expect the Irish horse industry to put on racing when it does not have the racing days.  I have a certain amount of sympathy for bookmakers, but as Deputy Penrose said before he left, we never see a bookie on a bicycle.  They must make their case here but to be honest, they will not get too much sympathy from punters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/949" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#Y00300"><p>I apologise for missing the early part of the presentation, due to a prior commitment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#Z00100"><p>Sorry to interrupt, but a vote has been called.  After Deputy Heydon makes his contribution, Senator O'Brien and Deputy Creighton have still to contribute.  Ms Byrne and Mr. Tully must also be given an opportunity to respond.  Rather than let Deputy Heydon get into his contribution, we will suspend the meeting until after the vote.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  Rather than keep the representatives from Horse Sport Ireland, I thank them for their contribution.  If they wish to withdraw and leave during the suspension, that is fine.  They are welcome to remain but the vote process could take ten or 15 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.61" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4 p.m. and resumed at 4.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#CC00100"><p>Deputy Heydon was about to commence his contribution so I will revert to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/949" speakername="Martin Heydon" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#CC00200"><p>I thank the representatives from the Irish Bookmakers Association for appearing before us.  I wish to focus on the online element of its business.  Is it fair to say that there are members of the association that have an online presence?  Could the representatives outline how the new online betting tax is bedding down?  Are there difficulties in its administration or do they find it more straightforward?  It is probably difficult for the Irish Bookmakers Association because in some ways, the retail bookmaker is almost in competition with the online element, a competition they have been losing in recent times.  We have many discussions here about urban regeneration and about how our regional towns are struggling.</p><p>Only this morning I was talking to a couple of local businesses who sell menswear.  They told me that the online market is killing business for them because people now have more confidence in going online and are better able to do so.  That is no different in the case of the bookmaking business.  This is a trend that will not be stopped easily and it is a challenge for businesses and their employees.</p><p> I ask Ms Byrne to outline how the online tax element is setting in for the association's members.  There is a need for a symbiotic relationship between the horse racing and betting industries in both their interests.  I acknowledge the very significant cost of media rights which is crucial for the ongoing operation of the racecourses.  When bookmaking firms sponsor some of the bigger races they bring an added dimension to the promotion of those events.  The industry at times finds it easy to bash the bookmaking sector but it would be in both their interests if they were to work closer together. It is in the interests of horse racing if the bookmaking industry continues to sponsor events and it is in the interest of the bookmakers if Irish racing remains the top brand.  I ask Ms Byrne to outline her experience of the online element.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#DD00200"><p>Another vote has been called in the D&aacute;il.  We have six minutes before we suspend for the vote and we may be able to conclude the meeting.  Deputy Creighton and Senator O'Brien have not returned and they had indicated they wished to contribute.</p> <p>  I have a question for Ms Byrne.  Is it fair to say with regard to the net profits that the independents who lost &euro;3 million to &euro;5 million would, by and large, be the core smaller independent retailer who is less likely to have a big online activity which would seem to be the more profitable option even with taxation?  I ask Ms Byrne to clarify.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.66" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Sharon Byrne" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#DD00300"><p>I will begin with Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v's questions.  He asked about the turnover as between the online and retail businesses.  It is difficult to know because online companies, apart from PLCs, have been so secretive about their business.  I will extrapolate Paddy Power's published figures and its market share as an estimation.  We are expecting a 1% tax collected on Irish business of &euro;15 million to &euro;20 million.  That means &euro;1.5 billion to &euro;2 billion from Irish customers on sports betting online.  The figures from our shops are &euro;2.4 billion to &euro;2.5 billion.  They are almost on par and that figure is growing rapidly.</p> <p>  On the reason for the decline in our business, we currently have the lowest number of shops on record for the company that beams us our pictures.  It was 850 shops 15 years ago.  I received figures this week from the Department of Finance on the betting tax paid for the past 25 years in comparison to the rates.  The number of shops we have in Ireland today is almost equal to what we had nearly 20 years ago.  The recession accounts for some of it but the online element is a big factor.  However, it is not all doom and gloom.  The retail side could certainly compete a lot better if legislation allowed it.  We are now operating in a computerised world.  We have customers in our shops betting on their telephones or at home.  If we had computers in our shops offering the new types of betting we could compete but the legislation dates back to 1931 and it prevents us from competing.</p> <p>  I have commended Deputy Martin Heydon.  In fairness, this Government has introduced the evening opening all year round.  We have been screaming for that for years.  We are now allowed to open after 6.30 p.m. from September to April, whereas historically we have had to close.  This is the first year and it is very welcome.  About three years ago we were also able to get Dundalk to start racing throughout the winter and this has been a huge boost.</p><p>However, preventing us from competing with online operators and not allowing computer products into the shops makes it very difficult.</p><p> The reason I mentioned VAT is not that I think we should not be paying VAT, rather it was to highlight that the cost of racing with the addition of VAT is a real cost to us.  Most businesses get VAT back although I do not think farmers do so.  We cannot and so it is a real cost.  The cost of racing at &euro;3,000 to Horse Racing Ireland per shop plus VAT, is a real cost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#EE00200"><p>My point is that VAT is only repaid if it is taken off the final customer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Sharon Byrne" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#EE00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#EE00400"><p>The VAT on sales always exceeds unless one is losing money-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Sharon Byrne" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#EE00500"><p>It should.  However, we do not have that return.  We pay VAT on everything flat and we have no way of reclaiming it.  I was highlighting the cost of racing.</p> <p>  On the question of whether there should be a higher charge for online betting, I represent the retail sector.  In my view the online sector has got away without paying tax for a very long time.  We have been employing thousands of people.  We are in every little town and community in the country.  We are paying newspapers in our local shops, we are sponsoring local football teams, we have bums on seats around the country.  Should they be taxed the same as us?  It would not be my view that they should be.  There should be a differentiation but I also disagree with the taxation model that is being imposed on exchanges, which is 15% on commission.  A lot of customers on exchanges pay no commission because they are just providing liquidity.  That system is flawed.  I know the Department of Finance is looking at that.</p> <p>  Deputy Landy said there was no sympathy from punters.  We were not looking for sympathy; we are here to try to explain how much money we pay towards racing versus what the profits are.  Deputy Heydon asked how is online tax bedding in.  The collection of that tax does not start until 1 August but we had some concerns with regard to the legislation.  We were concerned about the personal fitness companies from all over the world who can pay a small licence fee to have a betting licence in Ireland while the Department of Justice and Equality has to verify their personal fitness credentials.  They might have to go to the Caribbean to check out this company that no one has ever heard of and which is applying for an Irish online licence.  The Department will have two weeks to verify their fitness credentials.  We have concerns about this provision and also a concern about the identification of the country of residence of the customer placing the bet.  We explained our concerns to the Department and it worked with the industry to find a solution.  The only other concern we have is that it remains to be seen whether it will be collected from all countries.</p> <p>  Mr. Paul Tully wants to make a comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.72" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paul Tully" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#EE00600"><p>It is important that the Irish racing industry is a healthy industry even for the Irish bookmakers.  At the moment we pay a 1% tax on our turnover.  As Ms Byrne has shown with the figures, we cannot afford to pay any more.  Deputy Penrose raised the issue of Horse Sports Ireland and the small owner.  That is a key aspect that needs to be brought back into Irish horse racing.  At the moment, Irish horse racing is dominated by the big owners and the small owner is playing around for small money on bad racing in the back end of the country.  He is not able to compete with the big owner.  Irish racing was built on small owners, not the big owners.  If there were an incentive for small people to have a horse and run it this would make it more competitive and more people would be brought back into racing, and to the racecourses.  This would increase betting and would bring interest into the industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/AGJ2015070700002#EE00700"><p>That goes for both industries.  As part of the pre-legislative scrutiny on horse racing we decided to look at the wider industry.  We will be hearing from the local authorities who have to deal with straying and problem horses and from the ISPCA.  Reputation is everything.  The players and stakeholders in the industry can work and yet the image can be that of animals being neglected in poor conditions.  Then all that effort in good public relations is then diminished.</p><p>As such, the industry has a role in it which we wanted to emphasise so that we can contribute, hopefully, to the development of a model, whether through taxation or incentives to support smaller producers and owners.  It is to ensure it is approached the same way.  Ms Byrne said it herself when she referred to looking after addiction.  That is very important.</p><p> I thank the witnesses for attending and for their forbearance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.75" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 4.30 p.m. until 6.30 p.m on Wednesday, 8 July 2015.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.76" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.77" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Dara Calleary, Senator David Cullinane, Deputy Seán Kyne, Senator Michael Mullins, Deputy Anthony Lawlor, Senator Feargal Quinn, Deputy John Lyons, Senator Mary M. White. Deputy Peadar Tóibín,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Peter Fitzpatrick.</p><p>DEPUTY MARCELLA CORCORAN KENNEDY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.78" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 2.05 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.79" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#H00100">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#H00200"><p>The committee will now engage in the scrutiny of EU proposals.  There is one schedule A proposal and seven schedule B proposals for decision.  Schedule A, COM (2015) 38 is a proposal for a Council regulation on the suspension of customs duties applicable to imports of certain heavy oils and other similar products.  It is proposed that this proposal does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  It is proposed that the proposals listed in schedule B do not warrant further scrutiny: COM (2015) 154; COM (2015) 155; COM (2015) 157; COM (2015) 172; COM (2015) 201; COM (2015) 202 and; COM (2015) 220.  It is proposed that those proposals do not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.81" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#H00300">All-Island Economy: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#H00400"><p>The meeting will now be suspended for a few minutes to allow our guests to take their seats.  When we resume, we will resume in public session.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.83" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.10 p.m. and resumed at 2.11 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#J00100"><p>I remind members and those in the Visitors Gallery to please ensure that the mobile telephones are switched off for the duration of the meeting as they interfere with the broadcasting equipment, even when in silent mode.</p><p>I welcome Mr. Paddy Malone, public relations officer, PRO, of Dundalk Chamber of Commerce, Mr. Jim Boylan, president of Warrenpoint Chamber of Commerce; Mr. Denis Brady, committee member of Warrenpoint Chamber of Commerce, and Mr. Ian Talbot, chief executive officer, CEO, of Chambers Ireland, to the meeting to discuss the all-island economy with a view to generating recommendations on how to enhance economic co-operation and alignment across the island of Ireland.</p><p>I draw the witnesses attention to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p><p>I remind our guests that their presentation should be no more than five minutes duration.  The version of the presentation submitted has already been circulated to members.  I invite Mr. Malone to make the presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#J00200"><p>I thank members for this opportunity to address the committee.  The representatives from Newry Chamber of Commerce send their apologies.  A planning application is going through at present and, as a result, they were not in a position to attend.</p> <p>  I have been involved with cross-Border matters since 1979.  The chambers and the local authorities, Newry, Mourne and Down District Council and Louth County Council, have been working together in various ways in recent years.  The Border has created a divided area, with no regard for physical or cultural references, and it has had a devastatingly negative impact since 1920.  Newry Chamber of Commerce specifically asked me to raise its concerns that the situation would be exacerbated if the referendum in the UK results in the UK leaving the EU.  Two currencies, two bodies of law and two structures have inhibited growth and encouraged the black economy.  The McArdle report, commissioned by the two local authorities and the two chambers, Newry and Dundalk, showed that Dundalk is the poorest of the southern Border towns and that Newry is the third worst off in the North.  The gateway hubs report, which was published by the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government in May 2013 - a copy of which I have with me - places Dundalk last on the list of gateway towns.</p> <p>  Government actions, be they taken in Dublin, Stormont or Whitehall, have had little regard for the area in the context of the consideration of fiscal or regional matters.  The setting of VAT or excise rates is done independently, with no thought as to the consequences.</p><p>It is probably true to say currency movement plays a greater part but nonetheless where policy makers can have an influence they should.  Retail is a major employer in the area and is an economic engine that cannot plan long term in either jurisdiction because it does not know what way the rates will move.  In competition between Newry, Warrenpoint and Dundalk, the rates and other retail costs are significantly higher in the South.  An example of this lack of planning is that Ireland's Ancient East was launched a month ago, on the same day that Louth Chamber of Commerce held a conference on battlefield tourism.  The F&aacute;ilte Ireland advertisement stated this starts in Drogheda and ends in Cork, ignoring the land of C&uacute; Chulainn, Fionn MacCool and the T&aacute;in trail.  It is incredible that it could ignore such a large area.</p><p> Dundalk&rsquo;s unemployment rate is above the national average and has remained so consistently, it is normally approximately 25%.  The loss of our four pillars, engineering, shoes, tobacco and brewing in the 1950s and 1960s has not been made up.  The proposed reduction in corporation tax in the North will leave Dundalk at a further disadvantage if foreign direct investment, FDI, businesses want to move into the area.  We have shown that we can produce world leaders in Naughton, McCann, Goodman and Haughey, who is probably not well known to the committee but he set up Norbrook in Newry.  While all four are from Dundalk, two are established businesses in the North.</p><p> There have been various studies on this area which have concluded that the sum of the area is less than the whole.  In other words, the area has significant potential for growth in the area but it has not been developed.  The Bradley report, Queen's University Belfast, 2012, indicated three aspects to develop a cross-Border area: the deprivation should create a need; the population of the area should be significantly large to sustain a gateway and the infrastructure, physical and administrative, needs to be in place.  Only the Dundalk area along the Border meets those three criteria.  Its other advantages are that the education facilities are in place and the tourist potential is enormous, anyone who has ever visited Cooley will understand that.  This area can act as a gateway from and counterweight to the growing Dublin-Belfast sprawl.</p><p> The chamber has made numerous efforts.  I will not go through individual items.  When Louth, Newry and Mourne signed their memorandum of understanding it was hailed in Europe as an example of how two local authorities in different jurisdictions should work and the chambers have signed up to it as well.  The local authorities have been given enhanced economic responsibilities, North and South, in the past 12 months.  It makes sense that closer collaboration in this area be developed.  Dundalk is the sixth largest urban centre in the country and should be included in the Living City initiative, for the reasons I have mentioned.</p><p> The area needs to be marketed as a whole.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland and the Northern Ireland Tourist Board neglect the area, the land of Carlingford Lough and all that surrounds it.  It could be linked to the Boyne Valley to the South and the Titanic Quarter in the North.  Dundalk and the Carlingford region, including Newry and Warrenpoint, is less than 90km from the major population centres.  We have a reach of 2.5 million people on the island within a 60 minute drive.  No other part of the island comes remotely close to that figure because we include all of Dublin and all of Belfast. </p><p> In conclusion, we recommend an economic zone, which would give enhanced capital allowances; that is a timing issue only, not a loss to the State.  Dundalk should be included in the Living City initiative.  The Gullion-Cooley area should be marketed properly.  There should be recognition in each other's jurisdiction of the business expansion scheme, BES, and other incentives.  At the moment Southerners cannot invest in Northern companies or Northerners in Southern companies.  The specific industries I have outlined should be targeted, including hospitality and geo-finance and in particular, pharmaceuticals.  The Industrial Development Authority, IDA has a major site, at Mullagharlin, which has been lying vacant for over ten years.  These are specific measures we want within a certain time.  We do not want it openended.  We want it for long enough that planners and businesses can get to it.  We want further co-operation with United Kingdom, UK, employment initiatives, and encouragement of cross-Border movement of capital and employment.  There are still problems in that area, although they mainly arise on the Northern side.  Policies should be designed to avoid displacement.  We are not looking for a pharmaceutical plant to move from Cork.  We want new business coming in, not a displacement from elsewhere on the island of Ireland.  The Louth-Newry-Mourne memorandum of understanding should be extended in so far as that can be done.  Facilities and supports such as hospitals should be shared.</p><p>Daisy Hill Hospital in Newry is crying out for an enhanced upgrade, while Louth County Hospital in Dundalk is being downgraded.  Improved access to the greater Down area where there are major problems with road infrastructure is also recommended.  I will not specify particular roads because my colleagues in Newry and Warrenpoint might disagree with me.  When they speak later, they can explain the position.  This unique area has the capacity to grow significantly, but it needs a kickstart.  Once it is kickstarted, it has the potential to stand on its own two feet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#L00200"><p>I welcome the delegation.  Are we to have an input from Warrenpoint or is its shopping list different?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#L00300"><p>I have only one person listed to make a presentation, but if there is another-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.90" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Boylan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#L00400"><p>Our shopping list is the same as that of Dundalk and Newry.  We have formed a good alliance and have a good working relationship.  We would like to emphasise how bad the position is in north County Louth and the Carlingford Lough area.  Money needs to be invested in this hidden gem of a place which could be Ireland's leading tourism attraction if the proper infrastructure was put in place, but this would need the co-operation of the Governments on both sides of the Border.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.91" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Talbot" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#L00500"><p>I would like to add a general view from other chambers on both sides of the Border but particularly the north west.  </p> <p>  Infrastructure is a key need.  Mr. Malone has mentioned roads, without naming particular ones.  For people travelling to the north west, the A5-N2 is a nightmare.  This is impeding growth in the area.  It is important to keep developing infrastructure.</p> <p>  Another piece of infrastructure is the electricity grid.  Work on the North-South interconnector is under way, but we need to ensure it will happen as a priority.  A safe, reliable and secure power supply is vital for economic growth in the area.  </p> <p>  Another point I should mention concerns the potential of the regional action plan for jobs that is being rolled out.  The jobs to be rolled out in Border areas could inform debate on both sides of the Border.  We should try to develop the clusters about which we talked, rather than our side of the equation only.  We must also tackle the black economy.  We continue to hear, particularly in the case of alcohol, that with increasing duties and taxes, alcohol smuggling is on the increase.  This represents a significant loss to the Exchequer and has other implications for the economy.  </p> <p>  My final point concerns the implications of a Brexit.  We know that the Government is taking a proactive view and that a sub-group has been established in the Department of the Taoiseach.  The Brexit conversations will create a degree of uncertainty.  It is an important issue for us and we hope it is addressed in a reasonably discreet fashion from a time perspective.  We can deal with it, but it will have an impact in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#L00600"><p>The delegates live in a special and beautiful part of the country, but were there negotiations or consultations with them on Ireland's Ancient East?  Dundalk Institute of Technology is a strong institution, particularly in the area of renewables.  It was pushing the boat out long before anybody started to talk about them.  No reference is made to this issue in the presentation.  How many graduate from the institute each year and how many of them are retained within the Dundalk catchment area?  Would it be worth looking at putting a support programme in place to encourage the retention of some of the graduates who are engaged in cutting edge work?  Would it be worth putting a package in place to support them to stay in the area and establish businesses?</p> <p>  How much is the black economy costing the chambers' members on both sides of the Border every year?  The general trend in presentations is to say the enforcement measures are very weak and not what they should be.  What is the business community doing to highlight the impact of the black economy and the danger it poses in the produce people are buying?</p><p>We need to highlight the fact that people in the community may be promoting this as a way of doing business.</p><p> I wish to raise two points in regard to the Living City initiative.  Could Mr. Malone clarify if the Living City initiative is a Dundalk initiative?  Mr. Ian Talbot mentioned that consultations are underway on the action plan for jobs.  Is Mr. Malone aware whether Warrenpoint or Newry were consulted, whether they offered a position on the action plan for jobs or got involved in the consultations that are under way?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#M00200"><p>I apologise for going back on this, but let me clarify that this is taken from the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government report of May 2013.  The average rating is 5, so that if one reaches 5 one is on average score for the gateways.  If one is rated below 5 one is in trouble.  Our score is the lowest of all.  The score is arrived at by adding up the eight and dividing by eight, which means that weighting is not given to any one aspect over another.  The only heading under which we scored significantly higher than anything else is under the heading "natural-physical".  I do not wish to be crude but the reason we scored highly under this heading is that Diageo built a sewerage treatment plant in Dundalk.  Members can see we have scored highly only in this area, and otherwise we are not doing well.</p> <p>  Deputy Calleary made a good point in regard to graduates.  One of the action plans of the Louth Economic Forum, which Senator White's husband chairs and of which I am a member, is on clustering.  Kingspan Glen Dimplex and other companies in the region within the Louth Economic Forum are actively working on that area.  Two of the biggest players in the world are collaborating and working on it.</p> <p>  There would not be a week or a month without somebody referring to buying booze overseas or the Dundalk Chamber of Commerce making a statement on it.  All we can do is to keep sending out the same message.  We encourage the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to keep up security.  However it is difficult to police the area, in particular because of the motorway.  Senator Quinn will remember travelling from Warrenpoint to Dundalk and going through three or four checkpoints.  Now with the motorway, one does not stop.  </p> <p>  Diesel and fuel were the major black economy commodities.  I was critical of the Government when it said that a new dye would solve all the problems.  I told the Minister than the ingenuity of those in south Armagh had yet to be beaten.  My understanding is that they have been beaten at present and they have not been able to crack it.  That is very positive.  I would agree with Mr. Talbot that we still have a serious problem with alcohol.  As a parent I have witnessed on more than one occasion the prevalence of cheap booze.</p> <p>  We have the pharmaceutical and other industries in mind for Dundalk.  The reason we target the pharma industry is because of the significant amount of money that has been spent already on a huge IDA site.  This imposing site, which is on the left hand side as one drives out of Dundalk, has light posts sticking out of the ground in the middle of fields, but unfortunately that represents something that did not happen.</p> <p>  We met EirGrid recently to discuss the need for the North-South interconnector and the development of the electricity supply.  I mentioned the pharma plant to it but it did not know that the IDA's next pharma plant would be located in the region.  They would not answer the question on whether there would be enough energy for it but from the messages that I got, there was a question mark over it.  The IDA has spent a fortune building a site, which has been derelict for nearly ten years.  Now we find out that we do not have the power to meet its requirements.</p> <p>  Have I addressed everything?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#M00300"><p>The action plan for jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.96" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#M00400"><p>The chambers along the Border met the Minister on various occasions but as far as I know we did not involve the Northern chambers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#M00500"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  I am delighted that the witnesses are present.  I am the rapporteur for the very important report on the all-Ireland economy.  It is very interesting to hear the information from the witnesses.</p><p>The background to this issue, which people do not necessarily realise, is the level of economic deprivation, displacement and emigration that exists in rural and urban communities along the Border and the effect the Border has on the creation of those difficulties.  It is one of those big problems which is within our grasp, as elected representatives, to resolve.  The majority of people who have come before this committee to speak on this issue have articulated the same views as the witnesses.  I hope I do not get it wrong but to paraphrase it, the necessary attention to resolve this particular problem has not existed.  Indeed, Professor Bradley stated that what currently passes for cross-Border co-operation in this country is an absolute joke.  It has slipped massively down the radar of priorities of the Government and that is a challenge for us.</p><p> Would the witnesses say the equalisation of things such as taxes and excises would play a stronger role than other measures in ensuring the incentive for the black economy starts to reduce?  My second question concerns Retail Excellence Ireland and the Northern Ireland Independent Retail Trade Association, NIIRTA, the Northern counterpart, which recently carried out a great report on the all-Ireland economy.  One of the specific points mentioned in the report concerned tourism shopping.  It said there was a potential &euro;750 million opportunity, North and South, if there was a focus on the issue.  They suggested the establishment of an all-Ireland retail forum to work together on it.  Do the witnesses share this view?  The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation currently sees no reason for such an approach.</p><p> The memorandum of understanding is fantastic and the fact it has been pioneered by the witnesses is brilliant.  I am amazed it has not been replicated across other areas of the Border although Monaghan is looking at it at the moment.  Can we get more detail on the memorandum of understanding?  Are employed individuals joint employees or seconded individuals, North and South?  Is funding made available to work it?  Is there closer planning or is planning carried out together?  I would appreciate a better understanding of how that should work.</p><p> It strikes me that there is a major traffic problem when travelling from Dundalk to Sligo.  Mr. Malone has spoken on this issue before and has said a person would be better off travelling down to Kells and onto the M3 to get there.  We have major difficulties in getting to two significant Irish towns as well as across that area in general.</p><p> The issue of a Border economic zone has been coming up in discussions.  Some people favour proceeding with it along the whole length of the Border.  Others favour a small geographic region clustered around, as stated by the witnesses, an institute of technology, perhaps, and different infrastructural strengths.  What would be the inputs into it and what type of environment would exist within it?</p><p> If looking to invest in a Northern business or a Northern business is looking to invest down South, what is capital mobility like?  What is the current situation with labour mobility?  What is the experience with banks and telecommunications?  Given the Border is currently stuffed economically and we are in the EU together, would Brexit add a serious economic challenge?  Would it create poverty along the Border?  What is the likelihood for the struggling economy in that area if Brexit were to happen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.99" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#N00200"><p>What is Brexit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#N00300"><p>It is the British exit from the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.101" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#N00400"><p>My apologies.  That is another new term for me.  I will deal with the Brexit issue first.  I am old enough to remember when a person's tyres were marked when crossing the Border so that he or she did not buy new tyres in the North, where they were cheaper.  On occasion customs would dip a person's petrol tank to check how much petrol was in the vehicle, take an odometer reading and work out whether petrol had been bought when across the Border.  There were long queues of traffic waiting to get clearance before entering Northern Ireland.</p><p>It was such that it came back into Dundalk, three miles away, and it took between two and two and a half hours to cross.  It would cut out using Larne for a considerable number of exporting businesses in the region, including Baileys' suppliers in Kingscourt, County Cavan.  Instead of sending goods through Larne or Warrenpoint, they would have to be sent through Dublin Port which is already overcrowded.  That is the business side of the issue.  <br/><br/>Problems would also arise in exchange controls and the movement of capital, which could become an absolute nightmare.  Nothing works when it is broken in half.  In 1920 Dundalk was booming and probably the only industrial town in the South, with the exception of Dublin and Cork.However, it went into decline because it was separated from its natural hinterland.  If this were to happen again, it would cause crippling damage not only in Dundalk but also in Newry, as a considerable number of businesses in Newry rely on Dundalk sub-suppliers and <i>vice versa</i>.  Anything that impedes business or the mobility of capital constitutes a serious blow.<br/><br/>The question of taxes is also relevant to business.  Standardisation of VAT rates would bring huge benefits, while the standardisation of our currencies would be even more beneficial.  Currency fluctuations can cause greater differences than changes in VAT rates.  Changes in VAT rates are perceived as dramatic because people see a movement of 1% or 2% and the newspapers give the subject huge publicity.  However, a movement of 5% between sterling and the euro is hardly noticed.  Stability is the most important consideration.  If one travels around Jonesborough and Cullavillle, or through south Armagh into Newry and Down, one will see a succession of filling stations built which were in the past 15 years but are now derelict.  On the southern side one will see brand new filling stations with busy delis.  All we need is a change of Government in the United Kingdom and the situation would be reversed.  This boom and bust cycle will not generate growth in the long term, but we will be fine if we can achieve stability in taxes and everything else.<br/><br/>The N53 is the road between Dublin and Castleblaney, while the N54 crosses the Border.  If I drive from Dundalk to Sligo or Roscommon, as I recently did to attend the BMW assembly, I have to travel south to Kells before turning north again because the drive through Kingscourt and Cavan is a nightmare I would not contemplate in any circumstance.  The infrastructure around Dundalk is adequate if one is travelling north or south, but one is in trouble if one is travelling west.  Our colleagues from Warrenpoint had to contend with a train that was delayed train and a bus that was full.  They were in a sweat when they arrived here, which is why they are so quiet.  While the infrastructure has improved significantly, Warrenpoint should only be a 50-minute drive from Dublin.<br/><br/>On the memorandum of understanding signed by the two councils, credit is due to the former Louth county manager, Mr. Conn Murray, who had the foresight to encourage all of the institutions which might be relevant to sign up to the memorandum, including the chambers of commerce, IDA Ireland and various businesses.  We have become very conscious of including the North in our planning.  Deputy Dara Calleary referred to Dundalk Institute of Technology, DKIT, which faces a serious problem in enrolling graduates from Northern Ireland because the CAO does not give sufficient recognition to A level students.  A student with A1 grades is considered to have achieved a remarkable result, but it translates into 450 points for the CAO which is not even sufficient to gain entry to an accountancy course in UCD.  Something is radically wrong if that is the case.  Three years ago DKIT indicated to the CAO that it planned to introduce its own streaming mechanism in recruiting students.</p><p>However, the CAO indicated that if it did so, the CAO would remove it from the application process.  Ministers have been made aware of it.  Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n's party leader has spoken about it.  I have heard it being spoken about on numerous occasions; I have not seen anything done about it.</p><p> The MOU was created by them.  It is primarily on co-operation between the two organisations in terms of emergency planning and in other areas, including environmental controls.  It has encouraged further development.  For example the LEO in Dundalk and the equivalent training authority in the North are working on a programme for arts graduates who cannot get jobs, to retrain them or enhance their knowledge by giving them some technical skills by using the DkIT and the Southern Education and Library Board.  When I am talking about Newry I find it very difficult to think of the Southern Education and Library Board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.104" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Boylan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#P00200"><p>That is going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.105" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#P00300"><p>There has been collaboration between them involving third level institutions.  That is a very good example of the Louth economic forum and the councils using the memorandum of understanding to deliver.  However, I have not seen any step-up on that in the past 12 months since the election of the new councils in the South and the creation of the new super-councils in the North.  With the exception of that one issue I have not seen an economic driver coming up.  If I were to be critical, I would say it has been a great first start, but we need further action on it and we need to drive it further forward.</p> <p>  In terms of structures, there is an office in the Newry and Mourne District Council which is for the co-ordinator, who happens to be from Dundalk.  He spends two days a week working in his office in Dundalk, another two days in Newry and his location on the fifth day depends on what is required.  There is backing up at assistant director level within the councils.  There was a change in personnel last year - there were many retirements, a new county manager and the new chief executive in the North.  Those changes will take time to bed down.  It would be harsh of me to say it has not moved in the past four or five months.  I hope it will be of more significance in the next five months and we will have all signed up to it.</p> <p>  When we see the LEOs talking about the North and the Northern guys down here, we realise this is beginning to work hand in glove.  When Chambers Ireland responded to Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n's invitation and I came to meet him, my first reaction was to ring my colleagues in Newry and Warrenpoint.  Five years ago that would not have happened.  We got on well with each other and we would have had social outings together, but we would not actually have met.  Five years ago the only social outing we had was when we used to hire a tall ship - I believe Senator White has been on it.  We would have had social functions sailing tall ships down Carlingford Lough, which was fine but that was all we did.  We are beginning to think in terms of an area and we are beginning to develop the area, which is important.</p> <p>  On the definition of the area, it does not have to be a physical area.  It could be a specific area, but I would regard it as being anywhere within the catchment area of the two local authority areas of Dundalk North and Dundalk South, and the equivalents in Newry and Armagh.  We must not forget that Armagh is a separate one.</p> <p>  Within those areas it would be possible to decide that specific businesses or industries would get the reliefs.  It should be specific and targeted and not a general one.  I am not talking about something like Shannon.  We need to target the industries because we need to get value for money and crucially because we do not want to have displacement.  If there is displacement, it does not serve anybody's purpose.  If I am robbing one area to put it into Dundalk, that will not work for all-Ireland purposes and I would not expect the committee to support it or allow it to happen.  We are specifically talking about new places.</p> <p>  We would target using the IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland skills base and using the Northern Ireland equivalent to identify the industries that could be attracted.  It could be pharmaceuticals in the South and financial services in Newry and Warrenpoint where there has been huge success in that area.</p><p>It could be in the area of transport, particularly as Warrenpoint Port is one of the finest ports on the east coast.  My friends from Warrenpoint are always telling me that it is the best port on the east coast.  It is, therefore, possible to target specific things.  On one occasion I used an expression which someone told me was inappropriate when speaking about the Border.  However, I will repeat it now - I want to take a rifle to the problem, not a shotgun.  In other words, I want to hit the specific target I want to hit and nothing else.<br/><br/>I have argued in favour of mobility for some time.  I am an accountant by profession.  I run my own practice in Dundalk and I have clients on both sides of the Border.  On a couple of occasions they have been approached by people who want to invest in a particular business expansion scheme, BES.  I still use the old jargon.  My response has been to state that I know somebody in, for example, Newry who understands the business in question and whose involvement - if it could be encouraged - would be a plus.  The people to whom I refer cannot invest in such schemes - they can but they will not receive any tax relief if they do.  When we were establishing BES schemes, we copied the UK legislation almost word for word.  Hence, there is no reason a person in Dundalk could not invest in a company in Newry or <i>vice versa</i>.  If one wants mobility of capital, such investment is what one should encourage.  One cannot put constraints in place.  If there are incentives to invest in one direction only, that represents an impediment in terms of the overall definition as far as I am concerned.<br/><br/>On employment taxes, etc., I compliment the Irish revenue authorities in respect of the way they have approached the Belfast Agreement.  They implemented it, although not completely.  There are some kinks in the resulting structure but it is not bad.  However, the Northern Ireland authorities have not shown any great sign of a willingness to implement an equivalent.  Consequently, a southerner working in the North will find matters to be okay but a northerner working in the South will be heavily taxed.  For that reason, the number of northerners coming to work in the South is significantly lower than the number of southerners going in the opposite direction.  The only reason people are not flooding into the North to work is that, even allowing for the different tax rates, wage rates there are significantly lower.  People's take-home pay in the South is better than that of their counterparts in the North.  That is one of the other reasons I am highlighting the issue of the corporation tax rate.  It is interesting that at a meeting in Coleraine some ten years ago, Mr. Owen Paterson, MP, of the Conservative Party proposed setting the rate for Northern Ireland at 12.5%.  I was in attendance at that meeting and I congratulated him afterward on uniting the DUP, the UUP, the SDLP, the ICTU and the Confederation of British Industry.  All of those bodies said &quot;No&quot; to the proposal he put forward that day.  They, and many others, are all in favour of changing the rate now.  Many who live in my area are concerned in this regard because the 12.5% rate is our trump card.  If we do not have that as a unique selling point, we will be obliged to consider what else we have to offer.  If our other cost bases in the South are out of alignment with Newry and Warrenpoint, we will have a problem because displacement will occur.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#Q00200"><p>This is an extremely interesting discussion and it brings me back to the days when I started out in business in Dundalk way back in 1960.  My father came from Newry and my grandfather was from Atticall, which is outside Newcastle, so I know the area well.  One of the quick - I will not say easy - solutions to developing business is tourism.  Would it be possible to choose a name for the entire area and, if so, one that would make it better known that it is at present?  Perhaps our guests will indicate what went wrong with the project to put the bridge in place.  The concept behind the bridge was certainly one which brought together those on both sides.  My father's business was a holiday camp in Skerries and the guests who came to visit used to travel up to Warrenpoint.  They would go to Omeath and then travel across to Warrenpoint on the boat.  There is so much potential for tourism in the area.  The great thing when it comes to tourism is that there are immediate benefits.  I have a friend who visited Tayto Park near Ashbourne at the weekend and she could not get over the number of Irish people and tourists who were in the place.  Tayto Park has proven to be successful in a short time but I accept that some additional developments have occurred there in recent times.</p><p>If we are going to make sure that area succeeds, from Warrenpoint, through Rostrevor to Newcastle, and tie it up with Omeath and Carlingford, where there are so many attractions, what can be done and what are the hindrances to getting together to ensure that area works as one unit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Jim Boylan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#R00200"><p>The Senator is saying what we want to hear because that whole area is a hidden gem waiting for tourism.  Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n spoke about poverty and there is poverty along that Carlingford Lough area because the infrastructure is not in place.  We know there is a hotel earmarked for Omeath and one for Warrenpoint which will open if that road link is made.  That link is needed because we need tourism and other business on an all-island model.  It is more than 20 years since the Good Friday Agreement and it is not happening.  Carlingford Lough is being left behind.  That is where the infrastructure needs to go in.  We in Warrenpoint, Newry and Dundalk meet regularly to come up with a new idea.  The Senator is right that there needs to be a brand name for the whole area, like the Wild Atlantic Way.<br/><br/>To reply to the last question about the memorandum of understanding, I signed it, with Mr. Malone, on behalf of Warrenpoint.  It is doing a lot of good work.  It is unique in the European context but we do not have its physical manifestation, a link at Narrow Water or elsewhere, that would give the impetus to kick-start the tourism industry.  That is badly needed.  One change I would like to see in the memorandum of understanding is that it seems to be led by the two local authorities.  It would be better, if it was possible, to set up a committee that was not just made up of politicians but of business people from both areas and people from the health sector.  That is probably the impetus that is needed.<br/><br/>Britain&rsquo;s exit from Europe would be a major step back.  We would be almost stepping back into the Stone Age.  I cannot see it happening.  There is poverty there.  We feel that the region of Louth, south Armagh and Down is being left behind.  As Mr. Malone says, that is why there needs to be a major development in the whole area, industry, tourism, schools and health.  In Warrenpoint we have ideal access to emergency services that could go the whole way down to Carlingford and <i>vice versa</i>.  It does not make sense to keep a Border mindset.  We have to step above that.  We are two jurisdictions, governed differently but that can still happen if our mindset is an all-island mindset.  That needs to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#R00300"><p>I am delighted with the way Mr. Boylan spoke about Brexit.  It is a concern for all of us, not just in the Border area but nationally.</p><p>We can see how serious it is when we have people in the Department working to ensure we do what we can, from the point of view of the Irish diaspora in the United Kingdom, to ensure something like this does not happen because of the negative impact it would have.</p><p> Many of those in the Border area would love to keep the Border in place and one of the reasons for that is the smuggling.  Irrespective of what some people might say, smuggling is still going on.  Mention was made of smuggling of cigarettes, alcohol and diesel to some extent.  There are people along the Border whose criminal activities are politically motivated.  That remains the case and they would like to retain the Border.  </p><p> In regard to tourism, the only time I have visited that neck of the woods was to visit Newgrange.  Are there any historical perspectives that can be linked to tourism in the area?  Recently, in Dublin I saw what looks like a camouflaged Army bus going around covering the 1916 trail.  Perhaps something like that could be done for the Boyne area.  In America, they have a Civil War trail.  Highlighting historical areas like this is one way to increase tourism.  We are changing our attitudes so perhaps we could look at doing something like this.  Our green, white and orange flag is based around the two cultures, the Nationalist and the Orange, with the white colour representing peace between them.  Perhaps we could develop something that would link the two cultures because what we are dealing with now arose from the situation between them.</p><p> I am disappointed that the witnesses did not mention a particular factor.  When I became a Deputy, I saw people from my area, Naas and the surrounding area drive up the motorway to shop in Newry.  Now I see the reverse happening.  I was in a hotel in Naas a couple of weeks ago and heard that it has changed its marketing strategy to go after people in the North.  The currency is the driving factor in this regard.  This is the most significant factor in regard to why people travel from one side of the Border to the other and why the trade moves from one side to the other.  If the pound was worth 91 or 95 cent, as it was when I was elected, traders in the North would be jumping with joy because people would be crossing the Border to shop in Newry.   Now that the situation is reversed, there is more trade coming south.  This is a significant issue.</p><p> Can anything be done in this regard?  We are not going to get the United Kingdom to join the euro and we will not go back to the pound, but could something be done to provide a comfort zone for each side, particularly for the retail sector, that this will not be a significant issue for it in the future?  I expect traders on the north side of the Border are up in arms now because the currency difference operates against them currently in comparison with what is happening here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.112" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Brady" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#S00200"><p>The Deputy has made a very good point.  The currency factor has always been a reason as to why there has been a North-South agenda in regard to where people shop.  Newry is suffering dreadfully, as are we in Warrenpoint.  We see ourselves as more of a tourist area, but we do not have the tourism.  Both Mr. Boylan and I are from the Warrenpoint chamber, the smallest chamber.  The Newry chamber members were not able to attend today.  We felt badly let down when we did not get the Narrow Water bridge, mentioned by Senator Quinn.  That was a huge disappointment to us in Warrenpoint.</p> <p>  From the tourism point of view, the whole Carlingford region, North and South, is huge.  When people who have not visited our area see the region, they say, "My goodness, look what you have got here".  However, what have we been able to do about it?  We have not done enough because we have not tried to.  The North-South tourism agenda is what we want to drive forward as an initiative.  Let us forget about the fiscal problems because they will always be there.  As Mr. Malone said, if corporation tax is reduced, that will be a big issue that may not help us all go forward.</p><p>Again, it is a bit like the shopping.  The gem is tourism.  We do not have the beds to accommodate tourists at present but we could have them.  In Omeath, a man from Newry has a hotel with approval for 40 plus beds.  In Warrenpoint we have a small hotelier who has approval for additional beds but we need something structurally sensible from the North-South viewpoint.  That is hard to achieve but with the co-operation of the chambers in Newry, Warrenpoint and Dundalk on this new initiative we are determined to flag everything that is good and go forward with a much more positive attitude.  It does not help to think about the weak euro against the strong sterling but if one goes to Kilbroney Park in Rostrevor, County Down on a Saturday or Sunday or any day of the week, one will see cars from the South and not just from the Border areas.  Many people are coming to the North but we do not have the beds in our area.  Tourism in Northern Ireland is from the north coast, the Fermanagh lakes and the <i>Titanic</i>centre.  They take them up from Dublin to the <i>Titanic</i>centre and they drive through Newry and bypass us all the time.  We need to get that highlighted, which is what this new initiative is all about, and we have to drive it very hard.  Following the failure to deliver the narrow water bridge for &euro;26 million, that project is off the agenda now.  It is much more about an infrastructure that embraces not just a bridge and a link but a great deal more.  We are determined to flag that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#T00200"><p>County Kildare has the two major motorways but the tourists go through the county to go somewhere else.  We are working hard to suck them in by a variety of initiatives, whether around racing, the national stud or other attractions.  We do not have the battlefield sites although the battle of 1798 did start in the village of Johnston.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#T00300"><p>Through the Chair, the fen in County Kildare is a significant feature and I do not know why the people of Kildare do not make more of it.  I would like to know what Deputy Lawlor has to say about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#T00400"><p>We also have to look at alternative ways to drag people in.  I have always believed there are people going by on your doorstep and if one cannot pull them in there is something wrong.  That is my view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#T00500"><p>I welcome the witnesses from both sides of the Border.  I was born in Dundalk and had to leave it when I was about seven or eight.  I never recovered from leaving it.  I attended the conference on geotourism in Carlingford two weeks ago.  It was fascinating.</p> <p>  There was a gentleman at the conference who had set up a housing village on the northern side and he was looking forward to getting the big cruisers that go into Belfast to come down to Warrenpoint and bring the tourists down into the Mourne, Cooley, Slieve Gullion area.  I would like to hear more about the geotourism.  It is not dissimilar to the point I made to Deputy Lawlor.  The young people have an interest in the geology and archeology of the area.  I remember when we moved from Dundalk to Newbridge County Kildare there was very little known about why the Curragh had short grass or why they do not make more of the fen which is unique.</p> <p>  I ask Mr. Malone to tell us more about the potential for tourism.  To me the potential of tourism is related to the geology.  When I was young, my grandmother used to bring me to visit people in the county home on a Saturday and to do voluntary work.  Ms Carroll, who was in the Legion of Mary with my Granny used to bring us for a drive to the long woman's grave and to the Cooley mountains.  I will never forget it.  As a child, I found it very exciting.  I felt a terrible loss when we moved to Newbridge, County Kildare.</p><p>Will Mr. Malone and Mr. Brady talk about geotourism, that is, the geoloogy and archaeology of a region?  How do they propose to attract tourists to Warrenpoint?</p><p> I am totally supportive of the initiative because there is no place as beautiful as it.  Every time I face north I am in good humour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Brady" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#U00400"><p>It is nice to hear the Senator say that.  She raised a very good point in referring to eotourism.  It is one of the strong points of the region.  Last year Tourism Ireland, which comprises F&aacute;ilte Ireland and Tourism Northern Ireland, was instrumental in running the Geotourism Expo which was hosted in the Canal Court Hotel in Newry.  It was a two-day conference which I attended.  The lead speaker was the chief executive from Kerry where the figure for tourism was up 17% in 2013.  We know that there has been another significant increase this year.  He spoke about what we could do as part of a joint North-South initiative.  It was a very good conference and I was networking on behalf of our chamber.  As a photographer, I am involved a lot in landscape photography.  I was seriously disappointed by the all-Ireland tourist board's roadshows held in Derry and Belfast.  The wonderful initiative on the Mountains of Mourne was only given a three-second slot, which really disappointed me.  That is the problem we face.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#U00500"><p>What is the problem?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Denis Brady" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#U00600"><p>The problem is that our area is not receiving its fair share of exposure in tourism promotion.  That is why we believe we have to shout louder.  The new initiative with Dundalk, Newry and Warrenpoint will try to address the issue.  If we cannot have our area promoted as a tourism destination because we are not doing enough in that regard, we have only ourselves to blame.  The money allocated for the Narrow Water bridge project was part of the tourism offering, but it has now been withdrawn.  In the next round of European funding tourism will be off the agenda and funds will be allocated for roads and infrastructural projects.  We lost out badly in that regard.  It is very important that tourism is promoted properly.  Newry and Mourne hosted the conference, yet the Northern Ireland Tourist Board gave the Mountains of Mourne initiative a three-second slot in its roadshow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#U00700"><p>Disgraceful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1068" speakername="Peter Fitzpatrick" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#U00800"><p>As a Deputy from Dundalk, I appreciate the good work done by the chamber of commerce.  Before I was elected, I did not really appreciate its work.  I attended seminars organised by Dundalk, Newry and Warrenpoint which I found both educational and rewarding.  Dundalk is located close to the Border and despite the different currencies and tax systems, it is good that people on both sides of the Border work closely together.  The infrastructure in place in Dundalk is impressive.  Some 80% of the 5,000 students who attend Dundalk Institute of Technology are local, which is very good for local businesses because the college works closely with the local community.  We have also been very fortunate to attract foreign direct investment.  Among other manufacturing companies, Horsewear Ireland is based in Dundalk, as are a number of IT companies.</p> <p>  The chamber of commerce plays an important role on both sides of the Border.  It holds clinics and arranges presentations for business.  Recently, there was a talk on the draft Louth county development plan 2015 to 2021.  The chamber also advertises job vacancies, which is excellent.  It also organised a cross-Border employment and advice fair.  It hosts business breakfast events, both North and South.</p><p>The Giro d'Italia was fantastic for both North and South and the two sides of the Border worked closely together on it.  It is great to have different parades.  The St. Patrick's Day parade in Dundalk is organised by the chamber of commerce and it is excellent.  The chamber has also developed a shop local voucher scheme which provided a significant boost for the town.  There is no reason similar initiatives cannot be pursued in Newry and Warrenpoint.  It is important we look after our own.</p><p> There is a clear willingness between the North and the South to work together.  Coming as I do from the area, I remember the bad times along the Border, including the RUC and Garda operations.  There was an awful sense of fear.  There is great potential if we work together to develop tourism and business in the region.  As a small island, we must work together.  It was a big disappointment that we were unable to get sufficient European funding to start work on the Narrow Water bridge.  That would have brought a massive boost to tourism and business in the area.  Life is full of knocks but we have to pick ourselves up.</p><p> I welcome the progress that has been made since the Good Friday Agreement and the peace process.  I remember the bad days but it is fantastic to think my children and grandchildren will have a better experience.  As the Taoiseach has said, this is the best small country in the world and we should be proud of it.  The Irish flag is flown in Australia, Canada and America.  My hope is that the economy will pick up on both sides of the Border in the coming years.  It would be fantastic if our families could start returning from all those distant countries.  We probably have the best education system in the world, as well as the best doctors and nurses in the world.  It would be fantastic to see them coming home.  Perhaps Senator Quinn will open a few more supermarkets to bring them back.  There is too much bad feeling at present.  It is important we be positive as a country.  Thirty years ago people never thought there would be this level of cross-Border co-operation.  I welcome that we can all sit in the same big room and share the goal of ensuring both parts of Ireland do well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.125" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#V00200"><p>Senator Quinn's marketing genius is well known.  I could not agree more that we need a name for the region because calling it some combination of Mournes, Gullion and Cooley does not even give us three initials that make sense or rhyme with something else.  We would love to get the name right.</p> <p>  The geo-tourism project to which Senator White referred lasted three years and is now finished.  The project aimed to map the entire area and identify its potential.  In the 1960s, prior to the Troubles, Oxford University brought its students to Slieve Gullion because it is an extinct volcano.  Slieve Gullion and Crossmaglen have developed a different reputation since then but there is no reason why we cannot return to our earlier history.  I agree that the geo-potential for the area is enormous.  Cooley is 20 million years older than the Mournes.  There are three different geological sites in the one area, with a deep water lough in the middle.  There is no other lough on the east coast and Killary Harbour the only comparison on the west coast.</p> <p>  A ferry service is being developed between Greenore and Greencastle.  This project is one of the slowest moving things I have ever seen.  I hope the ferry does not move as slowly.  The former ferry between Warrenpoint and Omeath, to which Senator Quinn referred, had some value.  The ferry would benefit the Greenore and Greencastle area by opening up the Mournes in particular.  The southerners believe it will bring greater benefit to the North by opening up the Mournes and Silent Valley but the northern side seems to be more resistant to the project.  This is one of the problems that arise when one straddles two jurisdictions.  We have to convince people it is a win-win situation.</p><p>This is a collaboration between two jurisdictions that will remain separate jurisdictions until, as the Constitution stipulates, the majority vote to change it.  We need to get that message through constantly and we need to show the hand of friendship.  I have been to conferences run in Warrenpoint and Newry and because representatives of certain political parties were present, I was asked not to speak, which, as Deputy Fitzpatrick will know, for me is almost impossible.</p><p> I refer to the shopping side of things.  Our submission indicated the staccato nature of shopping in the area - it is stop-go, stop-go.  At the moment we are slightly go - not as much as it went the other way.  I remember talking to people in Newry about it in 2009 and 2010.  The unpredictability of it means we cannot have long-term planning, which results in both sides having too many shops.  The Dundalk area has too many shopping centres and Newry has too many as is.  The reason Newry is not represented here today is that another one is being planned, which is madness.  This lack of co-ordination between North and South is destroying both areas and is not making life easy for us.</p><p> We made reference earlier to the DkIT and the Northern side.  Deputy Fitzpatrick mentioned 5,000 students.  It is 3,000 full-time students and nearly 3,000 part-time students.  It fluctuates between 5,000 and 6,000.  Last year I believe there were only 40 from the North even though Newry is only eight miles away.  I have spoken to Mr. Boylan and Ms Orla Jackson, the chief executive of Newry Chamber, about it.  Most students in the North are not aware that the DkIT is a university because they do not see it as such.  They see it as something similar to a VEC.  They do not see it as an alternative to Queen's University, which is a problem.  By contrast, the DkIT attracts 200 Chinese people meaning that the DkIT has five times as many students from mainland China as it has from eight miles up the road.  Something must be wrong with a system that gives that result.</p><p> Deputy Lawlor made reference to Newgrange and the Boyne Valley.  I hope that area will be advertised better than it has been.  It needs co-operation between Louth County Council and Meath County Council, and I think that will happen.  In the same way, we would hope that in the northern end of the county, Louth County Council will co-operate with the authorities in Counties Armagh and Down in spreading that message.</p><p> We have talked about Newgrange and everybody knows about the Battle of the Boyne and all the rest of it.  In three years the Louth area will have a significant anniversary.  The last High King of Ireland was King Edward the Bruce, brother of Robert the Bruce, King of Scots.  He was the last recognised High King of Ireland and was crowned as such in Dundalk.  He ruled Ireland for three years.  The strength of his organisation spread as far south as Limerick.  So it was not just a local clan claiming he was something he was not.  He had all of Ulster, because Ulster was the most Gaelic of all the provinces in Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#W00200"><p>We are watching the clock.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.128" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Malone" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#W00300"><p>We want to use the opportunity of that anniversary to market the area.  We have already spoken to Scottish universities.  There is great interest in looking at the Bruce Irish connection.  There are also other Irish connections.  The sister of Robert Burns is from the area, which is why Carroll's named the brand of cigarettes Sweet Afton.  We want to establish a tourism product.  I will not go into the details, but those are the sorts of niches we want to establish.  Today we have given an overall view, but we have detailed plans to support it.  I just wanted to pick up on the references that were made to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015070700002#X00100"><p>I thank everybody for coming to engage with the committee.  The contributions have been really interesting and the delegates have done a great sales job for their area.  It sounds to me as if putting a strategy together and making a plan to engage with other stakeholders to help them to deliver on it is the way forward.  It would certainly help to inform our report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.130" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 3.20 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 14 July 2015.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.131" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.132" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 16:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Noel Coonan,check Senator Cáit Keane, Deputy Helen McEntee, Senator Denis Landy, Deputy Robert Dowds, Senator Labhrás Ó Murchú. Deputy Tony McLoughlin, Deputy Brian Stanley,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Michael McNamara and Senator Sean D. Barrett.</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL MCCARTHY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.133" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#A00100">Business of Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#D00100"><p>As we have a quorum, I declare the meeting to have started.  We will now go into public session.  I remind members and witnesses to turn off their mobile telephones as they interfere with the technology.</p><p>We have received apologies from Deputy Catherine Murphy and Senator Fiach Mac Conghail.  This meeting has been convened for the purpose of the consideration by the committee of matters pertaining to the consultation paper on the establishment of an electoral commission in Ireland.  The committee will now discuss this matter.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.<br/><br/>It is proposed that this part of our meeting will conclude at 5.30 p.m. unless previously concluded.  At the conclusion of public business, we will go into private session to discuss some EU matters.  We will then go back into public session to formally decide the EU matters.  We will then go back into private session for the remainder of private business.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.<br/><br/>I apologise to the witnesses for our late start.  We had two votes which delayed us.  I thank the witnesses for their patience and understanding.  I welcome Ms Anne O'Donnell, head of citizen participation at the Department of Children and Youth Affairs, Mr. Ian Power, president of the National Youth Council of Ireland, Mr. James Doorley, deputy director of the National Youth Council of Ireland, Mr. Brian Killoran, chief executive officer of the Immigrant Council of Ireland, and Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne, president of Trinity College Dublin students union.<br/><br/>I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and they are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against any person, persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.<br/><br/>It is proposed that all opening statements and any other documents the witnesses and others have submitted to the committee may be published on the committee website after the meeting.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.<br/><br/>This is the fifth of six planned meetings that the committee is holding on the question of an electoral commission for Ireland.  We heard from the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, followed by academics, officeholders, political scientists, local and national agencies and various experts.  Today's meeting will deal specifically with the concerns of young people, immigrants and students as the joint committee continues its examination of the issues surrounding the establishment of an independent electoral commission.  We look forward to engaging with the witnesses and assure them that their deliberations will assist us in producing a report which will go to the Department and to the Minister.<br/><br/>I suggest that witnesses limit their contributions to five or six minutes.  If they wish to submit further materials to the committee they are welcome to do so and we can circulate them.<br/><br/>I call Ms O'Donnell to make her opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.136" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Anne O'Donnell" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#E00200"><p>I thank the committee for inviting me here today.  As other witnesses will speak about older young people, I will confine my comments to children and young people under the age of 18 and the importance of their capacity to engage in decision-making on issues that affect their lives.</p> <p>  I hope committee members are aware that two weeks ago, we launched the national strategy on children and young people's participation in decision-making.  We are the first country in Europe and, very likely, the first in the world to have developed such a strategy.  It is very heavily influenced by the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, the EU convention and other conventions.  The purpose of the strategy is to ensure children have an opportunity in their individual and collective lives to have a say in everything that affects them.  No country knows better than ours what happened in bygone and not-so-bygone days when children were not listened to.  All the major abuse scandals in Ireland have one thing in common, which is that no one listened to children.  It is a very important step that the Government recognises the need to leave that past behind and to listen to and act on the voices of children and young people.</p> <p>  Empowering children is as important as protecting them.  That is one of the most important aspects of Article 12 of the UN convention, which is about the rights of the child.  Children have a right to be heard, to be listened to, and to have a say in decisions that affect their lives.  There is virtually nothing in Irish society that does not affect the lives of children.  I challenge the committee members to think of any policy or decision that would not do so in some way.  In the Department's citizen participation unit, we oversee structures like Comhairle na n&Oacute;g, local child and youth councils and D&aacute;il na n&Oacute;g.  We do vast numbers of consultations with children and young people and engage in all forms of dialogue.  We have a support team that ensures we spread this work as far as we can.</p> <p>  I wish to highlight a number of issues of relevance to children's voices and their eventual participation in civic engagement and in voting.  In page 7 of the document I have given to members, they will see evidence from research all over the world which suggests that enabling children to have a voice in decision-making supports their active citizenship from an early age.  That is critical to our discussion today.  It makes absolutely no sense to think that a young person is going to wake up on his or her 18th birthday and suddenly feel like civically engaging.  If young people have not been engaged before that age and do not feel that having a voice in some way makes them an active citizen with some kind of influence in their everyday lives, why would they want to bother engaging with society?  There is no light bulb moment at 18.  There is ample evidence on this matter, with which Mr. Doorley will be very familiar, particularly from Maurice Devlin, who has stated, "citizenship practice is learned through the lived experience of belonging and participating, of listening and speaking, of being valued and included".  That is backed up by any amount of research on the matter.</p> <p>  In preparing for the national strategy, the Department commissioned a number of pieces of research, one of which measured the impact of participation and decision-making among children and young people who had taken part in projects such as Comhairle na n&Oacute;g and different consultations on mental health and on topical issues such as alcohol.  The findings indicate that even though young people often feel disconnected from political debate, they are interested in playing a part in decision-making and in society.  Just because they are not interested in voting does not mean they are not interested in taking part in decision-making.  The two things are not necessarily the same.  It is important for a commission such as this one to take that into account.  If more young people are to be encouraged to vote, people need to listen to them and hear why they are not voting.</p> <p>  Another important issue is the self-realisation of children and young people.  In order that children and young people feel engaged and part of society when they are young, we need to stop seeing them as the adults of tomorrow and start seeing them as the citizens of today.  We need to stop focusing on what they will be like when they are adults and starting looking at what their lives are like and how they can participate today.  Children have a huge amount to contribute and need to feel that what they contribute today is valued.  There are many good examples of that.</p> <p>  Research from Martin Geoghegan in UCC interestingly showed that although many of the current participants in Comhairle na n&Oacute;g said they did not have much interest in politics or voting, 86% of past participants - young people now aged about 20 or 21 - rated being involved in decision-making when they were younger as having a positive impact on their understanding of the political system, while 81% said they felt their experience would have a positive impact on them voting.  That is very good news for building a stronger civic society.  These findings concur with research conducted in the UK, where there was a very low participation rate among young voters.  The UK research indicated that involving young people in decision-making makes them much more likely to feel they might eventually vote.</p><p> Another issue that arises a lot in our consultations with young people is the fact that they feel stereotyped by the adult world.  The adult world frequently comments that young people are disengaged and have no interest in being engaged.  The evidence is not there to back that up, however.  Young people themselves are interested in engaging.  If one looks at social media, they are actively engaging all the time in campaigns and expressing their views.  The recent referendum is a strong example whereby young people, both under 18 and over, were very engaged in campaigning.  The vote itself proved how, when young people get involved, they do make a difference to the eventual outcome.</p><p> In a consultation we conducted for a youth structure dialogue, another key theme was that young people commented on the fact that they feel stereotyped by adults.  They also said that they do not feel they are listened to by Deputies and councillors.  They do not feel that politicians are interested in listening to their views.  It is important, therefore, for the political system to recognise that.  Politicians are the spokespeople for the political system.  Young people are telling us they need to feel they are listened to by politicians.  That will help them to feel they are valued and that it is worth their while taking part in decision making.  </p><p> Our experience of working actively with young people and children on a regular basis is that they are interested in topics and issues of social concern.  They are particularly interested in a fairer society, so I would urge the political system and the commission to take heed of that.  They should try to find ways of linking into what it is that makes children and young people engage in their own worlds as a way of making them more interested in engaging in civic society when they reach voting age.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.138" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#F00200"><p>On behalf of the National Youth Council of Ireland, NYCI, I want to thank the committee for the invitation to discuss the establishment of an electoral commission.  We have addressed a number of issues in our submission but given the time constraints I will focus primarily on our priority areas, namely, the role of an electoral commission in managing voter registration and promoting turnout, especially among young people.</p> <p>  The NYCI has and will continue to promote active citizenship among young people and to empower our peers to participate in our democracy.  Many of our member organisations have, over time, consistently organised campaigns to encourage and support young people to have their voices heard and to turn out in elections and referendums. </p> <p>  We particularly welcome the fact voter turnout among people aged 18-25 years has increased significantly since 2002.  In 2002, turnout among this cohort was around 50%, while in 2011 it was 62%.  Given the obstacles that young people face in registering and in travelling home from places of learning to vote, it is remarkable that this cohort&rsquo;s participation rate is only 8% below the national average for all age groups.  When one considers that, it is clear that young people are engaging in politics, although that is sometimes lost sight of in discussing young people.</p> <p>  Similarly, we warmly welcome the participation of young people in the recent marriage equality referendum.  One of the many positive aspects to emerge from that was the engagement of young people not only in the discussions and campaigns beforehand, but also on polling day.  Given the number of young people registering on the supplementary register and voting on the day, it is certainly the case that young people do want to take part.  We would particularly like to pay tribute to Laura Harmon, the former president of USI for her efforts, and that of USI, for getting out that vote during the campaign. </p> <p>  The NYCI supports the establishment of an electoral commission.  As outlined in our submission, we believe many aspects of the electoral system currently function well.  Most importantly, they have the confidence and trust of the people.  However, we are concerned about the current voter registration system.  We are of the view that it is not fit for purpose, as it is under-resourced, inconsistent and inaccurate.  Reforming the process will be an urgent priority for the new body.  It was designed at a time when the vast majority of the population were born, raised and lived all their lives in the one area.  That does not speak to the current population of young people, who are highly mobile.</p> <p>  Our analysis suggests that the means by which the register is currently compiled is leading to the exclusion of greater numbers of young people.  In autumn 2014, we commissioned Red C to conduct a poll of young people relating to electoral matters, and particularly voter registration.  The poll found that 30% of young people aged 18-25 years were not registered at that time, which is more than double the 14% rate recorded by a similar poll commissioned by the NYCI in 1999.  From our perspective, democracy is diminished and undermined when so many young citizens are excluded. </p> <p>  As referenced in a report by the Oireachtas Library and Research Service, entitled Electoral Commission: Overview of the Policy Rationale, evidence from the US suggests that eliminating registration barriers can raise voter participation rates by between 7% and 10%.  It also suggests that barriers to young people moving around decreases their participation rate by 17%.  It is therefore a major issue for young people.  The current annual cycle whereby the revised register is revised and closed annually, requires those seeking to be added to the register during this period to go through a cumbersome process of applying to the supplementary register.  </p> <p>  The establishment of an electoral commission would also facilitate the development of a centralised system for online voter registration.  While it is currently possible to check if one is registered online, many young people cannot understand why it is not possible to register online.  This would not only assist those seeking to register for the first time but would also allow those voters who wish to change the address to which their vote is registered.  An online process would reduce the administrative burden on the electoral commission and local authorities. </p> <p>  The establishment of an electoral commission will not solve all these problems unless it is properly resourced.  We note from the Department&rsquo;s consultation document that just over &euro;4.84 million was allocated to local authorities to maintain the electoral register in 2014.  We contacted the Electoral Commission in New Zealand to find out how much it invests in its voter registration system as New Zealand has a similar number of electors at 3.1 million, compared to our figure of 3.3 million.  Their annual spend on the electoral register is NZ$20.5 million or the equivalent of &euro;12.5 million, which is two and a half times what we spend on maintaining our electoral register.  If we want an accurate, complete and user-friendly voter registration system we need to invest in it by employing innovative strategies to maintain it.</p> <p>  We also believe an electoral commission has the potential to play a leading role in research on voter registration and mobilisation.  Based on our experience to date, we are of the view that an electoral commission should be empowered to fund campaigns by non-governmental and non-partisan bodies, which are solely concerned with promoting voter participation.</p> <p>  While any reform of the electoral system should, as we outlined in our submission, be progressed in a careful and considered fashion, we ultimately need action.  An electoral commission was first promised in 2007 and, as stated by the Government, will not be in place for the upcoming general election.  We would like to see a commitment that an electoral commission will be established by 2017 and that such a body is given the powers, resources and time to oversee the next local and European elections in 2019.</p> <p>  I again thank the joint committee for the invitation to attend this meeting.  We look forward to having a discussion with the committee members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.139" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Brian Killoran" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#F00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach and other members of the joint committee for the opportunity to speak on the important issue of an electoral commission in Ireland.  I am the chief executive of the Immigrant Council of Ireland, which is an NGO and law centre that has worked in the area of immigration and integration for a number of years.</p> <p>  In all our work over the years, and particularly in our integration work, we have always sought to link people from a migrant background in Ireland to the political process and we see voting and promoting their enfranchisement as a crucial and necessary step to ensure the continuation of a healthy democracy here.  We must be mindful that the Ireland of 2015 has changed significantly to include a wide and diverse array of new communities, many of whom can vote in local and European elections.  Many of them are now citizens of the State and will be able to vote in general elections and referendums for the first time.  </p> <p>  People from migrant backgrounds are often viewed as not being listened to in the political process.  I am struck by the crossover between how young people and migrants are sometimes regarded as not being interested in the political process.  We find the opposite to be true.  Migrants themselves comprise a diverse group and have diverse issues and interests, but our interest is in political enfranchisement which is an essential part of what should be done by an electoral commission when it is established.  </p> <p>  I will focus my comments on the migrant community today.  Starting in a general sense, we in the Immigrant Council of Ireland support the establishment of an electoral commission.</p><p>The Immigrant Council of Ireland supports the establishment of an electoral commission and believes it will play an important co-ordinating role in future voting and electoral processes.  A number of advantages exist to the establishment of such a body, most prominent among them increased transparency and efficiency.  However, in looking at determining how the functions of the commission will work and to draw upon the elements we believe are of particular relevance to people from a migrant background, we feel that the co-ordinating, compiling and maintaining of the electoral register will provide welcome oversight and reform to the process, not just in administrative terms but also in promoting the registration process to migrant communities.  The promotion of education and awareness functions is a key and needed role in the functions of the commission.  We realise that there will be cost implications but the long-term implications of the failure to inform and enfranchise migrant communities as to their voting rights will have a greater cost, in societal as well as financial terms.</p><p> The commission needs to play a role in the oversight of polling stations and in training and guidelines for local staff involved in administering voting at stations.  This is of particular relevance to migrant voters as, at every election or voting opportunity, small numbers of isolated incidents arise where people of a migrant background are subject to inappropriate comments at polling stations and insinuations as to their ability to vote and whether they have citizenship.  These comments are sometimes based on skin colour and, while they are isolated incidents, they show the need for clearer training and guidelines at polling stations.    </p><p> The commission should also play an important role, either in its own capacity or in partnership with bodies such as the ESRI, the CSO, NGOs working in the area or academic institutions, in researching trends in voter registration and voting generally.  This should include information relating to migrants as there is a dearth of information and data in that area.  It exists in other areas and is crucial information to have.  </p><p> Other countries and electoral commissions have taken on similar tasks.  In Australia, the commission is explicitly responsible for promoting public awareness and for conducting education and information sessions.  It participates in community and multicultural events and even goes so far as to provide language support and classes.  Between 2009 and 2011, of 152 community events 98 were targeted towards migrant communities, which shows a strong reach out to migrant communities.  The additional efforts in Australia have resulted in a huge increase in migrant voter registrations, numbering into the hundreds of thousands.  In the UK the electoral commission regularly monitors trends in voter registration and carries out surveys and research within the UK's black and ethnic minority communities, something we also believe is crucial.</p><p> A comprehensive plan and central management function is needed, not just for voting processes for migrant communities but overall.  The commission must take on this role not only in an administrative or oversight capacity but in education, training, promotion and research.  Ample opportunity exists in such aspects as the positive spectacle of citizenship ceremonies, which at the moment include information about voter registration but have the potential to go much further.  In our experience, information is one thing but reaching out to communities to explain things to them face to face, offering translation services and assisting people in filling out forms are the crucial extra step to get people to register and cross the line into political participation.  We will provide any further assistance we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.141" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#G00200"><p>Until last week I was president of Trinity College Dublin students union and, over the course of the last year, I acquired more experience of the voter registration process in Ireland than I ever thought I would.  I echo the recommendations of previous speakers to set up an electoral commission and make a significant improvement in the way we register people to vote in this country.  I will speed through my paper, which I wrote last week and which sets out most of what I think on the matter.  I am speaking in a personal capacity as someone who is interested in the democratic process but also as a young person and student.</p> <p>  This year was an exceptionally positive year for students and young people and for many it was the first time they had engaged in the democratic process.  I have read a number of articles about how to transfer this energy and I fear that may not happen unless we capitalise on it and not let it dissipate.  I see two reasons why this level of civic engagement might not necessarily transfer into the future and to future elections.  First, young people are very mobile.  The USI has registered 27,000 people to vote this year but most of those 27,000 will have moved house before the next election as a lot of students move house every single year.  Second, the marriage equality referendum was a binary civil rights issue which easily resonated with people whereas the same, unfortunately, cannot be said of general elections.  We need to spur ourselves on in this area.</p> <p>  I am interested in voter registration although if an electoral commission were to be set up it would have many other responsibilities.  I will talk through seven problems which I believe exist with voter registration.  The first is that the system is entirely decentralised and there are gaping differences between the system on paper and the system on the ground.  In theory a decentralised, devolved system has advantages in giving people with local expertise the responsibility to pick the polling stations and go door to door but in reality it does not happen.  In theory, a decentralised system prevents double voting and stops someone from casting a vote in Dublin then getting a bus home to Bray, where I live, and casting another but unless a council happens to telephone Wicklow County Council to ask if a Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne is on its register there is no way to prevent double voting.  In this respect the decentralised nature of the system seriously encourages rather than averts manipulation.</p> <p>  The second problem is that the available information is confusing and contradictory on many different resources and it deters non-traditional voters, by which I mean the people represented on this committee today.  I telephoned a person on a county council and was left with the impression that a poorly literate person, a homeless person, somebody too busy with financial or personal pressures or just not interested in reading the dense prose that one currently has to traverse to go through the guidelines would be excluded from the process.  Ideally, information available on how to register would have the user in mind.  Just before this session I went halfway through the process of registering to vote in the UK using my telephone.  I was asked what I would like to do, whether I wanted to register to vote or to read about something, etc.  The information available is very inward facing. </p> <p>  The third problem is that the primary RFA form, which people use to register, pertains to households and not individuals.  This is a serious problem.  As the previous speaker said, the current system was designed when the vast majority of people in this country lived in the same place for their whole lives and there was an assumed family structure.  This does not apply to students.  Last October, at the start of the year, we did some door-to door registration at Trinity Hall in Dartry in Rathmines.  Some 42 people lived in one address, namely, Cunningham House in Trinity Hall, Dartry.</p><p>There are six spaces on the RFA form and one person asked me how they would all fit on the form.  The answer was they would not.  Thinking in terms of households instead of individuals does not work and does not reflect the change that has happened in recent decades.<br/><br/>Bizarre problems can arise with the RFA form.  Let us say John and Mary live in the same house.  John is going to vote &quot;Yes&quot; and Mary is going to vote &quot;No&quot;.  John could print off an RFA form, give his address as John Murphy, 1 Main Street and send it off.  Mary could then print off the same form and write &quot;Mary Murphy, 1 Main Street&quot;, omitting John's name.  If the current system is applied strictly the council will receive that form in the post and conclude that John has moved out and Mary has moved in.  In theory, then, somebody who knows they are going to vote a different way from somebody who lives with them could manipulate the system in that way.<br/><br/>The fourth problem is that <i>www.checktheregister.ie</i>does not work.  If a person is cursed with a fada, a hyphen or a double-barrelled name, all of which I am cursed with, it does not work and unless one inputs one's details precisely as the person in the county council inputted them, one will not come up on the register.  This year people came to me every day, vaguely remembering that we had registered them, to check if they were on the register and I advised them not to use <i>www.checktheregister.ie</i>because more often than not it is misleading.  The only way to get a definitive answer is to go to one's local library or ring the franchise section of the council.  The overall problem with the website, apart from the local annoyances, is that it is nobody's express responsibility to maintain a decent online modality.<br/><br/>The next problem is that there is no clarity regarding the dates of referendums.  All the student registration efforts this year were predicated on two assumptions, namely, that the two referendums would happen on a weekday and that they would happen before the end of the academic year.  One of those assumptions was correct as it happened on a Friday.  Unfortunately, by 22 May this year the vast majority of students had already gone home to Donegal or wherever so, having been registered to vote in Dublin, they had to change their details, which is a cumbersome process, or get a bus down to Dublin.  Despite the high turnout, many people did not do this.  Somebody suggested a constitution day, a specific date on which referendums would happen.  The fact there is no clarity regarding the dates of referendums is a problem that often goes unnoticed.<br/><br/>The second last problem is that the postal vote system in Ireland is obsolete.  The process is so cumbersome that I would love to have the figures for how many successful postal votes were processed this year in Ireland.  Seven students managed to get almost all the way through the process because we helped them but, as far as I am aware, not one Trinity College student actually managed to register successfully for a postal vote.  The home to vote trend on Twitter, with the images of people flying home from Australia, China and other places to vote, was inspiring but surely it was also totally unnecessary and inefficient and the fact that there is no outlet for citizens abroad to vote is bizarre, particularly in the context of the emigration of the past decade.<br/><br/>The final and overarching problem with the current voter registration system is that it is no one body's express responsibility.  On several occasions when I asked questions about how to register someone, and what the right form was, it was asserted to me that registering people to vote is not the students union's responsibility.  I would ask whose responsibility it is.  In Scotland, for the referendum, there was a turnout of 85% and there was 98% voter registration.  If every single Irish citizen who is not registered simultaneously became civically engaged tomorrow and sent off a registration form, the current system does not have the capacity to handle it.  It is a serious problem and we do not invest as much as we should in these things.<br/><br/>I have not included any reference to votes at 16 years of age or the difficulties in finding out one's polling station within a constituency, but I have broadly outlined the problems.  I thank members again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#H00200"><p>I thank the panel for sharing their views with us on this important matter.  I brought forward a Bill in the D&aacute;il to reduce the voting age to 16 because Sinn F&eacute;in believes young people should be included.  We looked very carefully at what happened in Scotland recently, which has not been extended to general elections in Britain but it is hoped it will be.</p> <p>  Can Ms O'Donnell speak about how the Department intends to engage young people?  She made a very good point when she said one does not wake up on one's 18th birthday and decide to engage civically.  At any rate I do not remember waking up in that way on my 18th birthday.  One of the difficulties is that at second level there is a superficial attempt to engage young people with civil and political education, but my own children and others in second level education have told me how people from other political parties came into school to talk to them about engaging in the political process and about politics generally, yet I have never been asked nor have many of my colleagues, despite the fact I have been a public representative for 16 years.  I am not saying we should be any different from the others but we are not actually asked and that is the difference.  I find it curious and wonder if the panel has any views on that.  It seems that parties of the centre or centre right are asked in, but it would encourage young people to engage if they heard different views such as those of ourselves, a left of centre party.  Does the panel think that would help?  Should schools invite a broader range of political opinion to address young people?  When I inquired about that I did not get a straight answer.  I heard on the grapevine that it depended on the political allegiance of the principal or the class teacher.  To get young people to think about politics, it has to happen before they are 16 and there has to be a discussion about the relevance of politics and how politics affect young people's lives.  The starting point is local government.</p> <p>  Mr. Power spoke about the number of young people who registered in the recent referendum, which was brilliant.  The level of engagement and the turnout were fantastic, regardless of whichever way they voted.  What can be done to sustain that?  He mentioned some of the problems, such as the fact the referendum was on one issue and that people will very soon vote on the 158 people to attend the D&aacute;il and deal with a range of issues which are equally important.  They will make decisions on behalf of the electorate and it is a bit more convoluted than the referendum.  The referendum was direct democracy and a question of whether one voted for or against gay marriage, whereas in a general election, the voters elect someone to make decisions on their behalf or to represent their views.</p><p>How might we carry that over into the general election and, indeed, future city and county council elections?</p><p> I read Mr. Ian Power's interesting paper earlier which said that New Zealand spent two and half or three times more on an electoral commission than we spend here on the electoral process.  How should it be spent?  There are probably a range of things, but does one specific aspect stand out which requires expenditure? </p><p> The vexed question of household registration was dealt with at length by Mr. McGlacken-Byrne.  I came across a house where there were seven people registered but only two people were living there.  There are many stories like that around the country.  It is not confined to any one area; it happens in a number of places.  We should all have an interest in trying to stamp that out, but what system should we replace it with?  We have discussed this matter many times before in the Chamber and outside it with the previous Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Commissioner Phil Hogan.  The PPS number was suggested by our party.  The system in the North involves a rolling registration process, which does not close like it does here.  Would that suffice in place of the current system without going to individual registration? </p><p> One of the problems highlighted to me is that some 6.5 million PPS numbers have been issued.  That can be explained by people in the graveyard, those returning to Poland, or Irish people in New Zealand, Canada, Australia or elsewhere.</p><p> There have been recommendations concerning citizens in the Six Counties being allowed to vote in presidential or Seanad elections.  There have been some suggestions of having a separate panel of people from the North, whereby people in the North could have some voice.  We have had such Senators in the past, including S&eacute;amus Mallon and Gordon Wilson.  There were various people from the North who had useful and important things to say.  What are the panel's views on that question concerning that section of our citizenry, given the fact that constitutionally, they are Irish citizens?</p><p> The Constitutional Convention made recommendations about Northern voters being able to vote for Uachtar&aacute;in na h&Eacute;ireann.  Mary McAleese was a very good President, as is President Michael D. Higgins.  The fact that Mrs. McAleese's family could not vote for her shows how skewed things are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00200"><p>That was nearly eight minutes and a couple of issues were raised there.  I will ask Mr. Power to comment first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00300"><p>As regards how the money in New Zealand is spent, the New Zealand Electoral Commission has 25 permanent staff and the majority of the budget is related to enrolment services.  It outsources updating of the electoral register to the postal service in New Zealand.  The 25 permanent staff make up one-third of its budget, which is around NZ$6 million.</p> <p>  From our perspective, we would see the electoral commission investing a sizeable proportion of its budget in information technology, seeking to streamline the registration process online.  For a start, that might include uploading scanned documents online so that people can get the form, fill it out and upload it.  That is what the New Zealand Electoral Commission does for its citizens abroad.  That is one of the innovations available.</p> <p>  In New Zealand, they also have something called "real me" whereby a person can verify their identity online for a range of public services.  We currently do not have that but it has to start somewhere.  Through the electoral commission, we could potentially start that process of being able to verify one's identity online for use in a variety of ways for public services.</p> <p>  A huge spend would be needed on engaging with marginalised or target groups, particularly young people and those from migrant communities.  As my colleague from TCD students' union, Mr. McGlacken-Byrne, said, it is hard to assess the effect of the youth vote on sustaining the marriage equality referendum, given that the referendum was about an issue which people could connect to in their lives.  That potentially differentiated it from previous referendums which were about Oireachtas inquiries and judges' pay, matters that are not particularly interesting for, or relevant to, young people.  From a politician's perspective the challenge will be to relate to young people, speak to their issues, address their concerns, and ensure that election promises are kept.  That is very important to young people.</p> <p>  The National Youth Council of Ireland has done a lot of work on supporting votes at 16 years of age.  We support the idea that young people should get involved in the civic process earlier.  We view CSP as quite a superficial treatment of civic education.  There is no argument against 16-year-olds engaging in the civic process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00400"><p>Does Mr. McGlacken-Byrne wish to respond to those issues before we move on?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.148" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00500"><p>Yes.  As regards the question on households, due to time constraints on my opening remarks, I cited problems but no solutions.  There are a few solutions.  First, the ideal one is the most obvious, which is automatic registration.  I have never heard a good reason why a person should not automatically be added to an electoral register when they turn 16 or 18.  I was told at the start of the year that voting is important, which implied that one has to jump through a few hoops to merit a vote.  Paying taxes is important as well, however, and I did not have to sign up to do that.  I have never heard a reason why automatic registration would not work.</p> <p>  Second, if for some reason that is not viable, online voter registration would make a lot of sense.  It would remove the problem of deceased people, or those who are no longer resident at an address, being registered.  As I said before, I registered to vote in the UK through online registration, which took about five minutes.</p> <p>  The third absolute baseline solution would be to have an individual-centric system, rather than being based on where one lives or who one lives with.  An online, centralised register makes so much sense that I cannot believe it does not already exist.  If everyone at every polling station had access to the same online database it would prevent double voting.</p> <p>  Surprisingly, it also alludes to the question about spending. People will not jump at anything that requires money but so many changes could be made to improve the efficiency of the process and remove or reduce the number of man-hours required.  For example, this year a number of local councils have not accepted forms in bulk, although some do.  That means there must be one form in one envelope.</p> <p>  Dublin City Council does not accept forms in bulk, which means I had to enlist ten student union colleagues to spend a full day packing 1,500 envelopes and send them off in the post.  Presumably, Dublin City Council staff had to spend a full day opening them.  Replacing that rigid and laborious system would reduce the need for the financial resources required at the moment.</p> <p>  There are certainly many solutions to the household problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00600"><p>May I comment, Chairman?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00700"><p>Yes.  The Deputy might conclude on this please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00800"><p>Does the panel consider it is important that young people are exposed to various political views - left, right and centre?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#J00900"><p>I ask Mr. McGlacken-Byrne to conclude on this please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.153" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00100"><p>That goes back to the question of how we transfer the energy from this referendum to future issues.  This was very direct and tangible.  People do not connect in the same way with political parties.  A basic step would be the provision of some explanation in schooling and education, and on websites, of the parties&rsquo; stances on particular issues and the political meaning of left, right and centre.  Many vote the way their parents vote or for the nicest looking poster.  I would not be an ignoramus but only this year did I get a real comprehension of the stances, for example, what left and centre left mean.  An impartial resource could be provided listing political beliefs and the parties that match them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1082" speakername="Tony McLoughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00200"><p>It was interesting to hear the comments because over the past few weeks we have been listening to some of the experts speaking about the electoral commission.  Mr. McGlacken-Byrne is quite right about the recent marriage equality referendum.  I met with the Union of Students in Ireland recently and it informed me that 28,000 students voted in the referendum.  It was an issue that resonated with many people who may not vote in the next local or general elections.  We need to get more young people involved and to vote and be interested.  Only recently I met with a group of young people in Sligo, the Youth Caf&eacute;, which has sent a submission to the committee.  They would not be prepared to vote at 15 years of age but we also talked about reducing the voting age to 16.  Some of them felt that young people do not have the maturity to vote or the interest in voting.  How do we overcome this?  There are many organisations such as Comhairle na n&Oacute;g, D&aacute;il na n&Oacute;g and others, that are informed on what is happening.</p> <p>  It is very hard to engage and involve people in politics.  The most frustrating thing for us as politicians is that, come election time, people are not registered.  The consensus over the past few weeks was that the personal public service, PPS, number could be used as a starting point.  What are the witnesses' views on that because that concerns every politician?  When we go to a house where a person is not registered, we must get the person to fill out the form, which a garda must sign, before it goes to the local authority and the name goes on a draft register for the next election.  It is a very slow and cumbersome way of registering people to vote.  As the witnesses said, young people who are at college during the week head home on a Friday for one commitment or another, which makes it difficult for them.  In other EU countries and worldwide, elections are held on weekend days, for example, Sunday.  What is the witnesses&rsquo; view of that? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00300"><p>Who is the Deputy addressing?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1082" speakername="Tony McLoughlin" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00400"><p>Mr. Power and Mr. McGlacken-Byrne and Ms O&rsquo;Donnell on the young voters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00500"><p>I will endeavour to bring the other witnesses in on the next round of questioning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.158" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00600"><p>The main issue in respect of the Deputy's frustration at people not being registered is the fact that it is not owned by anybody.  Every year, more than 50,000 people turn 18 and it is nobody&rsquo;s job to ensure they are registered.  It is their job but they are not necessarily made aware of the necessity or the process of registering.  Similarly, because the register closes at a particular point every year, it does not allow young people who turn 18 in the intervening period to register easily, particularly if there is an election or referendum called and they must get a garda&rsquo;s signature.  That is quite a cumbersome and potentially intimidating process for a young person to have to go through in order to register to vote.  Online registration will have a huge impact on the registration of young people because it will make it simple for a generation which is digitally native and for whom doing things online is the norm.  The marriage equality referendum was their first engagement with the system and anecdotally they could not believe they could not register online.</p> <p>  If a vote is to take place during term time, a Saturday is the ideal day for young people, particularly students who may need to travel back to wherever they live or their vote is assigned.  If we had online registration making it easy to change their address they could change it to somewhere close to their place of learning.  Simplification of the process will address the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.159" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Brian Killoran" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00700"><p>I want to add a caveat in respect of automatic registration.  It should not make the assumption that everybody is a citizen.  One does not have to be a citizen to vote in local and European elections or to get a PPS number.  Automatic registration or a similar model would need to be backed up by a very fluid way of amending the information so that a person can opt in to stating nationality or citizenship and learning what voting rights attach to that.  That can change if somebody becomes a citizen.  A more fluid way of registering is absolutely needed but it needs to take into account that not everybody voting is a citizen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.160" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00800"><p>The first question was how to transmit the energy generated this year.  Having an online modality is very obvious and urgent and I echo the comment that there was absolute bafflement that it could not be done online.  That makes very little sense for someone who is digitally native.  The Electoral Act was passed before I was born, before the advent of the Internet and before third level education levels ballooned as they have over the past two decades.  We need to update our system to reflect the times.</p> <p>  In response to the question about the date of a referendum, there are pros and cons to having it on a Friday or Saturday, for example, many people go home on a Saturday, if they study in Trinity.  I go home every weekend to work but I live in Wicklow.  The key is consistency and telling people the referendum will be on a Friday and they should be where they need to be.</p> <p>  As a throwaway remark, if there was an online centralised register, people could vote anywhere.  There would be problems to tease out but it is strange that a person cannot walk into a polling station with a passport, state his or her name and citizenship and ask to vote there.  The mass exodus of people going home reminded me of Herod&rsquo;s census in the Bible. Surely there is a more efficient way than having thousands of people moving around the country on referendum day.  Maybe that is not feasible but the key issue is a consistent date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#K00900"><p>I apologise for being late and missing the presentation.  While I welcome all our guests who came to brief us this afternoon, I welcome in particular my neighbour and fellow Roscrea, Tipperaryman, Mr. Killoran.  I wish him well in the post he recently took up and wish him every success in it.  I know he is very committed and able and will no doubt make a success of the post.</p> <p>  We are talking about the establishment of a proposed electoral commission.  We have heard many good suggestions this afternoon.  One of the most important aspects of the electoral system is the public&rsquo;s confidence.</p><p>As has been articulated here today, there are numerous faults and failings with the system we have at the moment.  When we tamper with it, we need to make sure we maintain or strengthen the confidence of the general public in it.  Do the witnesses think the proposed electoral commission will solve many of the issues that have been raised here?  Does it represent the way forward?  Mr. McGlacken-Byrne spoke about someone turning up at a polling station with his or her passport.  It is important that voters know the candidates they are voting for and are familiar with the problems and the issues in the constituency.  A person who walks into a polling station in Roscrea from Timbuktu and says, "I have a passport here and I wish to vote here", will not know what effect that will have on the local people, the people of the county and the people of that area.  It is not quite as simple as it might seem.</p><p> Some of the issues that arose when previous presentations were made at this committee have arisen again today.  I refer to the education of the electorate, for example.  Somebody said at the last meeting that there were 20,000 spoiled votes in the last election.  The opposite point that can be made, on the basis of an average turnout of approximately 70,000, is that it would make a significant difference in a constituency if the 30,000 people who do not turn out to vote were to do so.  Would an electoral commission be in a position to inspire confidence among the public that it would solve all of these matters?  Do the witnesses think we should have compulsory voting?  Do they think everybody should have to vote?  What impact would that have?  The point I am making, and I would like the witnesses to address, is that confidence in the electoral system, which is fairly high at the moment, needs to be maintained.  We need to be credible in what we do.  The other general point I would like them to address is the question of whether the proposed electoral commission represents the proper way forward.</p><p> I would like to raise one more issue.  It might be of particular interest to Mr. Killoran because he deals with it.  How can the diaspora be registered to vote?  Should they be entitled to vote?  I spoke originally about the effect it might have on a constituency if people living away from it were allowed to vote.  Would they be aware of what is happening?  Would they know what impact their decisions would have on the general public?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00200"><p>I apologise for not being in attendance earlier when I was in the Seanad.  I have a question on this paper.  Reference was made to research that was conducted among young people in which participants were asked how important certain issues are for them.  They obviously said that careers and education is their top priority.  When they were asked about voting and having an active involvement in politics, they gave mainly neutral or negative responses.  As I am only reading this now, I do not know whether any follow-up was done to ascertain why that might be the case.  I can guess why because I have read extensively on this issue, including in the report under discussion.  It is obvious that young people are turned off by politics.</p> <p>  I was a member of South Dublin County Council when the very first Comhairle na n&Oacute;g and D&aacute;il na n&Oacute;g were set up.  I think the names might have come from a proposal I made at South Dublin County Council.  D&aacute;il na n&Oacute;g was first and it was followed by Comhairle na n&Oacute;g.  South Dublin County Council was very active in this area.  It developed a toolkit to get the youth of the area involved.  There is no point in putting people's names on the register if they do not actually vote.  That is where adults should be ashamed of themselves.  Young people could teach adults in this regard.  According to the last survey I looked at, when young people register to vote, 53% of them turn out and do so.</p> <p>  I would like to speak about the issue of automatic registration.  I am aware that Hillary Clinton made a proposal in this regard last month.  One state in America - Oregon - already automatically registers people to vote when they reach the age of 18, if the people in question have driving licences.  I do not know why the driving licence requirement was included.  Lots of people cannot drive, but they should be eligible to vote.  That is the way they did it.</p> <p>  As we know from the debate about RSI numbers, identification is an issue in this country.  Until we have a system that actually talks to the computers and links to everybody, like the "who are you" facility that is used in New Zealand, we will not be able to identify people.  The last time this matter was discussed at this forum, a Senator spoke about a person being registered to vote and voting 12 times in an election.  We need to safeguard against that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1087" speakername="Noel Coonan" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00300"><p>Vote early, vote often.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00400"><p>We know how IT hackers are-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00500"><p>Senator Keane, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00600"><p>Yes.  I would like to speak about the possibility of automatically changing from household registration of voting to individualised registration of voting.  It was found in a survey in the UK that 78% of voters could be transferred over automatically with the touch of a button.  I am sure it would be the same if a survey were done here, but I do not think that has been done.  The only people who would lose out under an automatic household transfer system would be young people who are renting and frequently change their addresses.  Obviously, a way has to be found because I think this is how we should proceed.  Most of the participants we have listened to here over the past four weeks while we have been discussing the possible establishment of a commission have recommended individualisation rather than household registration.</p> <p>  I would like to ask a question about the participation subgroups.  Reference has been made to the importance of local participation and local authorities in getting voting done.  As I have said previously, there is no point in throwing out the baby with the bath water.  We should not centralise everything because local authorities are the best places to do certain things.  A person from South Dublin County Council called to my house in Templeogue last night for the purposes of registration.  The person in question asked me how many people at my address are on the register.  Someone suggested that the local authorities are not involved in this kind of activity, but they are.  Obviously, they do not maintain this presence all the time.  They might not get the co-operation they need, which means their work might not always be very accurate.  Bulk forms are accepted in many councils.  Some councils ask people to come in with a councillor or someone like that in order to identify themselves.  This is another issue that has to be examined.  We need to make it easy for people who want to register to do so.</p> <p>  We will not be at the races until we have a good-quality data matching system.  I absolutely think this should be done online.  Everybody is going online for everything.  I said here the last day that we trust online banking, but someone else said, "No, we do not".  Maybe those involved in banking are the last people we should trust.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00700"><p>&euro;64 billion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00800"><p>The online voting system is a bit like the kidney donor system - it should be a question of opting out rather than opting in.  That should be a way to look at and focus on our system of voting.  Mol an &oacute;ige agus tiocfaidh s&iacute;.  Sin &eacute; an m&eacute;id at&aacute; le r&aacute; agam.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.170" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Anne O'Donnell" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L00900"><p>We were asked about the research.  We pulled out just one page of data from that very big study, which is available on the website of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs.  I am present here to comment on the establishment of an electoral commission.  If such a body is established, it needs to play a part in this national strategy and it needs to listen to and get the views of children and young people under the age of 18, even though they are not yet of voting age.  If children and young people are not actively engaged in decision making, they will not feel a sense of engagement when they become adults.  It is clear from the evidence - both the research and what children and young people say - that they want to be involved in making decisions.  They want to be engaged.  They want to be asked what they think.  That can be facilitated at all ages in many ways, obviously appropriate to the age level of the child or young person in question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.171" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#L01000"><p>We would totally agree with Deputy Coonan's point about people having trust in the electoral system at present, with the exception of the electoral register.  We would have a perception that people have trust in polling day and in the result, but not necessarily in the electoral register process.  We would not be in favour of compulsory voting.  I would respond to his point about the number of people spoiling their ballots by suggesting that many of the people in question believe they are sending a message to the political system.  The message in question is to be digested in whatever way one desires.  People use ballot-spoiling as a means of engaging with the system without necessarily expressing a preference.</p> <p>  We would support any proposal to allow the diaspora to vote in Presidential elections.  We understand there are constitutional complexities and practicalities in relation to the Constitution and how that is done.  It is certainly something we would support.</p> <p>  Senator Keane spoke about voter turn-out among young people, which was 62% at the last general election as compared to an average of 70% across all age cohorts.</p><p>With regard to validating identity online, <i>lotto.ie</i>can validate people's identities using submissions of passports and passport scans.  If a body such as that is able to verify people's identification for that purpose-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00200"><p>By using a passport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.174" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00300"><p>-----then we should be able to develop a process too.  We need to start the process somewhere, which is something that is often put off.  It is thought that compiling databases and so on is too big a job.  We need to start engaging with that job, and it is something that the Electoral Commission can definitely do.</p> <p>  Household surveys were mentioned.  At the moment, that is the only way we can maintain the electoral register, but it is hugely costly and not cost-efficient.  New Zealand spends two thirds of its budget doing such work.  An online system, which would allow us to maintain our records ourselves and whereby it is up to the individual to update his or her own record, would be much more cost-effective for the new body.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.175" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00400"><p>A good few issues have been raised.  In terms of the first issue of confidence in the electoral system, I very much echo what has just been said. People believe the results are very robust, but I personally have had a lot of experience of it and I have a very low level of confidence in how we put the register together.  When one uses the word "tampering" online, in a sentence to do with voting, people think of e-voting and immediately say, "Oh no."  Online voting is very different from including the online option in the process leading up to voting.  Multiple voting hurts confidence in the system as well.</p> <p>  Compulsory voting was mentioned.  Call me radical, but I think it is a great idea.  In Australia a person can be fined $20 for not voting and one can choose to spoil it if one wants, but perhaps that is a discussion for a different day.  Compulsory voting is a cracking idea.  If nothing else, voter registration as an opt-out makes infinite sense.  In 2008, the Geary Institute compiled a report on this issue which circled the drain and eventually came back to the need for an ID number.  There are issues with using PPS numbers and there are issues with using driver licences, obviously.  The institute wondered whether an ID number would impinge on people's privacy and whether we were ready for that step, which I think is a bit silly.  Taxes and lots of things impinge on one's privacy.  A centralised ID number is, unfortunately, something that must be considered very seriously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1180" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00500"><p>I thank our guests for their contributions.  I do not have too many questions, because a lot has been said, many questions have been answered and we are here to have a general discussion.  We have had quite a few interesting weeks and heard interesting comments.</p> <p>  I congratulate Ms O'Donnell and her Department on the strategy that it has launched.  The strategy is fantastic and is something that I wholeheartedly agree with.  I have been surprised, and even more so since being elected, at the amount of engagement.  I have learned that when one engages with young people that they, in turn, engage.  I am talking not just about young people in secondary schools but about those in primary schools as well, whether they are here in D&aacute;il with a Member or in their schools.  Therefore, it is very important to engage with them at a younger age, and this aspect raises the question of whether it is necessary to lower the voting age.  I wonder whether we need to start engaging at a younger age while leaving the voting age at 18 years.  Mr. Power has already addressed this matter.  I would like to know the views of the remaining witnesses on lowering the voting age.  Do they think it needs to be examined?  Do they think we need to engage more with younger people? </p> <p>  I agree with a lot of what has been said today and shall touch on something my colleague has said.  I noted that Mr. McGlacken-Byrne said in his submission:  "I would hope that the democratically positive experience of the high turnout seen in the May referendums would not act as a disincentive to enact much needed change."  If anything, I think the turnout has done the opposite.  A Carlow-Kilkenny by-election took place at the same time as the referendum and the number of spoiled votes was between 3% and 4% higher than the normal rate for a local or general election.  There are problems with registrations.  People made an effort to register, travel home and go into a voting booth, but many chose to vote in the referendum and not in the by-election.  That shows that a more serious question needs to be answered.  Why did people who went to the trouble of coming home to vote in the referendum choose not to vote in the by-election?  That highlights the need for education and engagement in terms of voting.  How do the witnesses view this matter?  We touched on the subject last week when we spoke to one of our guests, Dr. Liam Weeks, who replied that education was key, but I feel that if young people are saying that politicians do not engage with them, we are the ones who need to be educated.  Perhaps we should start engaging with people more.  I would like to hear the views of the witnesses on these matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.177" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00600"><p>The council believes we should lower the voting age to 16.  Voting is something of a gateway drug.  By that I mean that once a person votes, he or she tends to vote every time afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1180" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00700"><p>Not always.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.179" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ian Power" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00800"><p>Voting tends to be a process on which one follows through for the rest of one's life.  It is not something that people tend to stop doing after the first time if they are engaged by the system while young.</p> <p>  There is EUROSTAT research which found that there are a couple of reasons young people do not vote.  First, it may be because they are not registered, which is a matter we have discussed at length.  Second, they do not feel that politicians engage with them and their issues.  As rightly pointed out by the Deputy, when young people are engaged with, they return that engagement.  Therefore, it is up to us as adults and politicians to engage with young people and try to bring them into the political process.  Education is key, but we all know that experiential learning is much more effective than anything else.  Certainly, it would be better if politicians were seen to speak about the issues that are relevant to young people, follow up on them and act upon them.  Young people can definitely see through hollow statements and gestures.  At the weekend, the council held a consultation, and one speaker spoke in a condescending manner on a particular issue.  It was quite clear that he or she had attended for validation purposes and not for anything else.  Young people can see through such activity straight away.  Therefore, politicians must have a meaningful engagement with young people.</p> <p>  In terms of education, we believe that the Electoral Commission will be unable to do such work.  It will need to set up funds for organisations that work with young people in order for them to do that type of education piece.  It will need to be able to put together strategies that will engage people with the electoral and political systems.  We need organisations that already operate on the ground and engage with young people to come up with strategies and deliver on them.  Such an initiative make most sense.  It will be the most effective and best way to spend taxpayer's money in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.180" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Domhnall McGlacken-Byrne" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M00900"><p>Deputy McEntee mentioned part of my document.  I said, in that section, that the high turnout and fantastic images need to act as an incentive.</p> <p>  The Deputy asked why people spoil their votes.  As I have already said, the questions on the ballot paper for the marriage referendum were binary and simple.  The question was: Do you want gay people to be able to marry or not?  If a greater effort or resource was established whereby, as in the Carlow-Kilkenny by-election, one could vote for a person based on his or her stance on a certain issue, then there would be a greater and clearer cause-and-effect relationship when one votes for one party or another.  As Deputy Stanley said before he left, it would be useful to make a resource available that would clarify what voting for one person versus voting for another person actually entails.  All of this information would go some way to generating the same clear relationship that was established in the marriage referendum, which I think led to the brilliant turnout.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1180" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M01000"><p>I wish to make a point about education.  As Ms O'Donnell pointed out earlier, in terms of every single decision made, there is not any piece of legislation that does not affect a young person.  How does one educate young people to ensure they know that the person they elect will make decisions that will affect them?  Young people might not think that is the case but those decisions will have an effect.  We must close the gap in understanding, join the dots and prove that to young people, but all of that comes about through engagement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M01100"><p>And debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.183" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Brian Killoran" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#M01200"><p>There is an important crossover, to a certain extent, with people from a migrant background in terms of what is relevant.  There is a perception that people from a migrant background only vote or are only interested in issues that are relevant to them, but that is not the case.  Everybody who lives in Ireland has kids in school, they are involved in local communities and, therefore, they are involved in all of those issues.</p> <p>  Confidence in the voting system and how to make it more relevant have been mentioned.</p><p>It is about reaching out and if we talk to people and engage with them, they will tell us what they are interested in.  There is often a broad unanimity of interests.  The same applies in our work with migrant communities.  It is not just that migrants have particular interests, they are interested in everything and have diverse views across the political spectrum on every issue.  That is an important point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#N00200"><p>I thank the witnesses for their attendance.  As I said at the beginning of the meeting, this is the fifth of six hearings on this very important topic and the committee's deliberations with the witnesses today will inform its report to the Minister.  We will now allow the witnesses to withdraw and will then go into private session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.186" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 6.05 p.m. and resumed in public session at 6.10 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.187" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#O00100">Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015070700002#O00200"><p>We will continue our consideration of COM (2015) 186, which is the proposal for a Council decision on the position to be adopted, on behalf of the European Union, in the EEA joint committee concerning an amendment to Annex II (Technical regulations, standards, testing and certification) to the EEA Agreement (Batteries and Accumulators).  It is proposed that this proposal does not warrant further scrutiny.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  On the "green card" for food waste, it is proposed that the committee agrees to lend its support to a draft House of Lords proposal to be submitted to the European Commission regarding food waste policy.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>  I propose that we now go into private session.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-07-07a.189" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 6.10 p.m. and adjourned at 6.15 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 14 July 2015.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>